<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: shelters | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shelters/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-26T18:16:04+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-18T14:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>That I like single wall shelters in all seasons isn’t a secret. And that I like pyramid shelters neither. So as <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=462005&amp;pw=73183">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> said they’re going to send me an UltaMid 2, I was very much looking forward to trying this very spacious cuben pyramid shelter here in the north.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html" title="HMG UltaMid"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7324/9708360775_3eec0c98f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG UltaMid" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Attention!</strong> All photos in this post are from an early Proto-type and the final design has changed a few details from this one. I will highlight these in the article where appropriate.</p>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The HMG UltaMid 2 arrived in May and has been used on <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/guided-trips/">packrafting and backpacking tours</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/climbing-at-havukallio.html">climbing weekends</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">hiking in Lapland</a>. All in all I have slept over 15 nights under it, in the rain, wind and also during calm nights.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9253493494/" title="HMG UltaMid 2 at Havukallio"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/9253493494_bde30147bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG UltaMid 2 at Havukallio" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>As with other shelters, its function is to protect you and your gear from the elements. While on sunny, calm summer nights and days that’s not really needed, add in wind or the need for privacy and a shelter is useful to have along. Add in rain or snow and a dry place for sleeping, eating, and lounging looks very inviting indeed.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9519459009/" title="Ultralight camping by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3793/9519459009_f7441f5148_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ultralight camping" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>It’s HUGE. It has a very large footprint - about 270 cm long and 210 cm wide in my prototype - so should even offer tall people a very good amount of space to lay down without bumping into the walls. Add in the recommended pitching height of about 160 cm and you can already imagine that this is a shelter which offers a very large amount of space. If it’s good weather you can even pitch it a bit higher for lots of height and the possibility to dance around the pole.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9771035091/" title="Space by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7341/9771035091_35395339f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Space" /></a></p>

<p>The production model comes with all the bells and whistles you could wish for: Line Locs for easy adjustment of the guylines, a Zipper Garage at the top and a Zipper Strain Relief buckle at the bottom. My prototype doesn’t have these, but I don’t miss them either. The zipper itself is of the waterproof-kind and is two-way and is easy going. It is placed on the short side, in the middle, which is a unique place as zippers often are placed on the long sides.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797345306/" title="Side buckles to stow away the door"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7445/9797345306_304db878d1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Side buckles to stow away the door" /></a></p>

<p>The top has two vents with no-see-um mesh to keep insects out, and they can be closed, too - useful in vertical rain situations where the wind could drive the rain inside. Or snow. The door can be opened completely and stored away neatly with the buckles, which is perfect for calm evenings where you want to enjoy the views with some wind protection.</p>

<p>Watch the video to get an idea how large it is, and how easy to set up:</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/74750776?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Making such a large, durable shelter from cuben is an innovation, I’d say.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797318235/" title="HMG!"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7363/9797318235_d6d8aef94b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>By now you hopefully know that HMG not only stands for ultralight, high quality gear, but that their kit is also durable. My prototype was used by others before me, and has been put through the paces by me and friends since. Except cosmetic looks - the cuben isn’t as white anymore as it was when new - it’s still in great shape and doesn’t show any signs of weakness. The zipper still runs smoothly and all seams and tie-out points are still strong.</p>

<p>Speaking of the seams, they are a mix of bonded and sewn: The large panels are sewn and taped, while critical seams like at the top and at the tie-out points are reinforced for extra durability. The top itself is made of Dyneema, and HMG says it is <em>special</em> as it will not deform. As I only have used poles and paddles and not skis I can’t comment on that, but it’s a sturdy design. It even has a loop on the top from where you could hang it from a tree, for 100% pole-free space inside!</p>

<p>It’s made from CF8 – ct2k08 cuben, which offers good durability and still is very lightweight. The material is 100% waterproof, doesn’t absorb water and small rips are easy to fix in the backcountry - I fixed other cuben kit with just a patch of Duct tape.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797395273/" title="Top"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7443/9797395273_abbde85d28_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Top" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Prototype UltaMid 2 weighs in at exactly 499 g including guylines. That’s 100 g more than my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review.html">LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil</a> but the UltaMid offers a lot more space. I imagine if switching to less burly guylines some additional weight could be saved. The packsack it comes in weighs 15 gram.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797304215/" title="Easy to spot in the summer by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/9797304215_aecb3c1f35_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Easy to spot in the summer" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Cuben is a very expensive material, so you can be sure the HMG plans very carefully how to cut the material up for mids, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/hmg-echo-i-review.html">Tarps</a>, stuff sacks et al. to minimize scraps.</p>

<p><em>More in the future.</em></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>As the UltaMid 2 arrived, I first thought HMG sent me the wrong Mid (they make a 4 Person Version). The shelter was so large that I was sure that there must have been a mistake. As I took it out to make a test pitch, I realized that HMG did indeed send me the right UltaMid, but that the 2 Person version is MASSIVE. I can fit an inflated packraft in there and lay down on it, or on the other side. Or spread out all my trad climbing gear on one side, while my sleep system is on the other side. Obviously thus that two people and their gear will fit in there just fine, and won’t feel that they’re too close as it could be in other shelters.</p>

<p>As with all pyramid shelters, preparation is key for a good pitch. Staking the UltaMid well out, in a good square, will make it go up perfectly. If the long sides are not aligned, or straight, it will be askew - easiest to then take the pole out again, align the sides correctly, and insert the pole again. Then you can go and stake out the mid tie-out points, and adjust the corners if needed.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797392493/" title="Preparation is key"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7368/9797392493_e80346a244_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Preparation is key" /></a></p>

<p>Speaking of poles, I have been using the fantastic <a href="http://www.rutalocura.com/trekking_poles.html">Ruta Locura Yana poles</a> and my <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Paddle/Sawyer-Packraft-Paddle::130.html">Sawyer paddle</a> to pitch the UltaMid. Three sections of the paddle do the trick, you then can adjust the length of the paddle for the height you want. Same goes for the Yana pole, I use three sections and with it I can pitch the mid very low or very high. If you use trekking poles and want to get the UltaMid, get the Yana Poles!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797324484/" title="Can be pitched with a paddle"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5324/9797324484_e2b54bc554_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Can be pitched with a paddle" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797268566/" title="Top with closed vents"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/9797268566_bd53c2634c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Top with closed vents" /></a></p>

<p>If it comes to packing, folding is the way to go. I have just stuffed the UltaMid into is supplied cuben stuff sack, but it is difficult. Somehow the top hat makes the packing for me not easy, but if the whole shelter is nicely folded it goes in with plenty of room to spare. That said, you can stuff it in there, but then the package will be more bulky.</p>

<p>I really liked the placement of the zipper, and how wide you could open up the doors. As the zipper is placed on the short side, you enter the shelter from the “front” or “back” depending on in which direction you sleep. It makes getting in your bivy or inner very easy in my experience, and makes it easier to keep the shelter organized - one side for sleeping, the other for gear. In shelters where the door is on the long side, you often have the gear before or behind your sleep system, this works but the UltaMid certainly feels more organized.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9801226353/" title="Packed size"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5498/9801226353_1b4219791f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="662" alt="Packed size" /></a></p>

<p>I’m a bit torn about the guylines on the UltaMid. On the one hand they work very well - they’re long enough to use them with rocks or for high pitches, but on the other hand they’re pretty heavy. I wonder if using thinner lines would mean a sacrifice in usability? Something to try in the future. Saving some weight will be nice, too!</p>

<p>Hanging a bivy inside is also a bit odd. There’s two D-Rings on the side, but none at the front and back - where I usually lay with my head. For me a D-Ring or similar there would make hanging a bivy or mosquito net a lot easier, now it always involves a bit of fiddling around. If you’re the kind of person who likes to sleep in an inner tent, then you’ll probably want to ask Sean at <a href="http://oookworks.com/">OookWorks</a> if he can make one for you until HMG comes around with their own.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9771259926/" title="Corner tie-out"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3800/9771259926_58d6689938_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Corner tie-out" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There are many pyramid shelters on the market: The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review.html">LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil</a> which I like a lot, then there’s the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=47&amp;products_id=105">MLD DuoMid</a> &amp; <a href="http://shop.bivysack.com/category.sc?categoryId=4">Oware Alphamid</a>, the <a href="http://bit.ly/18ypYuZ">Black Diamond Mega Light Tent</a>, the <a href="http://www.bearpawwd.com/tents_tarps/pyraTent.html">Bear Paw Wilderness PyraTent</a>, the <a href="http://seekoutside.com/products/ultralight-tipis/little-bug-out-shelter/">Lil’ Bug Out Shelter</a> from Seek Outside and even the <a href="http://bit.ly/1eQ9Jmp">GoLite Shangri-La</a> is Pyramid-shaped.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9771258736/" title="Wet"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7320/9771258736_e7396efed6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Wet" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>There’s much too like about the HMG UltaMid 2: It’s light, offers a fantastic amount of space, is very stable in high winds and is easy &amp; fast to pitch. Did I mention that it offers a lot of space? No? OK, the main selling point for the UltaMid 2 will be the massive amount of space it offers. If you hike in wet weather and want to sit in comfort in your shelter in the evening, then the UltaMid offers so much space that you can invite your friends over to your shelter for drinks. And all the very tall hikers will also like this shelter, because finally they can sit inside a shelter without having their head bump into the walls. Now I’m not one of those very tall hikers, but I still enjoyed sleeping in the UltaMid, as did taller friends I loaned it to.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797271184/" title="View"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/9797271184_0079dbd7ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="View" /></a></p>

<p>Sure, there’s some knick-knacks: The packing can be fiddly, and you’ll want to take a pole that can extend in comfort to 160 cm or more. Sure, a pole jack as you could make yourself or buy can help with shorter poles, but it’s not a 100% good solution in high winds in my opinion. Packrafters will just use their paddles, skiers can use their skis in a an inverted V shape, or if you hike in the forest you’ll just look for a place where you can hang it via the top loop. Also the price of $650 is not for small budgets, but then this is truly a four season shelter which will have you covered in all environments. For me it’s really a superb shelter that I love to take along. On <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/guided-trips/">guided trips</a> it’s excellent to show my clients that there are sub-500 gram ultralight shelters which are durable, stable in the wind, easy to pitch and offer plenty of space. If that sounds like you’d enjoy it, get one!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157634403205347/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-ultamid-2">Where to buy the UltaMid 2</h2>

<p>You can get the UltaMid 2 directly at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=462005&amp;pw=73183">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> and I imagine the various <a href="http://trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/index.php?refID=hif">ultralight webshops</a> will offer it soon, too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797250395/" title="Vent on the outside"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7383/9797250395_337673a32a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Vent on the outside" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>

<ul>
  <li>How does it perform in the winter &amp; snow?</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: I’m a proud <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/ambassadors">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Ambassador</a> and got the UltaMid 2 Prototype free of charge for testing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review.html"/>
    <updated>2013-02-26T21:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pyramid shelters are the third wonder of the ultralight backpacking world. Fast to pitch, spacious, and very windproof these are versatile shelters which work in a multitude of locations and seasons. If you’re a true minimalist then a shelter like the <a href="http://locusgear.com/products/shelter/khufu-sil">LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil</a> might be all that you ever need. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7807717428/" title="Wo ein Wille ist... by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8438/7807717428_1981b650ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Wo ein Wille ist..." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>
<p>I have been using the <a href="http://locusgear.com/products/shelter/khufu-sil">LOCUS GEAR Khufu</a> in Silnylon for over one and half years, in winter, spring, summer, autumn and winter again. There were starry nights, windy nights, snowy nights, rainy nights and sunny mornings spent in this shelter, on overnighters, week long trips and weekenders.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6962619602/" title="LOCUS GEAR by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7140/6962619602_71de147a94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="LOCUS GEAR" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>
<p>A shelters function is to protect you from the weather, this often means rain, snow and wind. It gives you a place to get under if there’s no starry night, and to hold out during crap weather. You also might want to cook under it, and generally spend time in it if the weather just isn’t great. </p>

<p>Depending on your priorities - do you walk a lot and only pitch your shelter once it’s time to hit the hay or do you spend a lot of time at camp - you will have different expectations from your shelter. The person who hikes for 12 hours each day likely is looking for a lightweight, compact shelter which still gives her good protection during a thunderstorm at night, while the camper might prefer a very spacious shelter. I think the Khufu fits both groups very well, though the hiker probably will value the shelter more because of its light weight and stormproofness.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7783259222/" title="Open Doors by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8307/7783259222_fbc46ab400_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Open Doors" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<p>It packs in a small package and hence fits well even in smaller volume backpacks. Those who have mesh pockets on their backpacks will find that it fits in a side pocket without problem, and takes also little space in the front pouch.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8511326150/" title="Size by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8100/8511326150_0821a05e75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="739" alt="Size" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8510214893/" title="Packed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8247/8510214893_51788ff235_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Packed" /></a></p>

<p>The top has a mesh air vent, and while it works good I think it would benefit from being bigger. In conditions where there is a lot of condensation you will get condensation either way, but if there would be only a bigger air vent that might make the different between a wet inner or a dry inner (provided there’s a good breeze). The air vent has a wire in it so that it stays open, and while it can not be closed you can pull it close to the door with a guyline &amp; line-lock to hinder spindrift snow come inside. You can circumvent the condensation by pitching one or two sides a bit higher to get more airflow, this would help in situations where this only little condensation, though.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8511330404/" title="Condensation by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8512/8511330404_193824f569_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Condensation" /></a></p>

<p>The doors can both be opened and rolled to the side, giving you fine views from under a roof. Of course you also can only open one door - roll them up and use the toggle and loop to keep it out of the way. </p>

<p>The reflective guylines used are light, thin, and work very well. They could be a bit longer - especially if you use the shelter in winter but I have coped with the stock ones until now. The line locks are the small ones, and make it easy &amp; convenient to re-adjust the tension of the shelter, especially in winter.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6812306790/" title="LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7069/6812306790_d0e579808e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil" /></a></p>

<p>Size matters in inclement conditions. The Khufu is 130 cm high (if pitched with one pole; I have used them with my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekkingstoecke-bf/">Black Diamond Ultra Distance Z-Pole Trekking Poles</a> in 130 cm length), 160 cm wide and 265 cm long. The usable length I’d put around 200 cm and 140 to 160 cm in width. I’m 175 cm tall and for me there’s plenty of space for sleeping and gear in the shelter, but people who are 195 cm and taller might find that they touch the shelter with their feet or head when sleeping. There’s plenty of usable space to store gear along the perimeter of the shelter, and two short persons should fit in the Khufu without problem, even without using the <a href="http://locusgear.com/products/accessories/dpte">DPTE</a>, the Dual Pole Tip Extender which allows you to pitch the shelter with two trekking poles. The long side goes very steep upwards so the width inside is almost all completely usable, whereas the narrow ends have a more gradual angle and hence there is less usable space inside along them.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8510210313/" title="Khufu Sil by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8365/8510210313_ac59202087_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Khufu Sil" /></a></p>

<p>I usually use the Dual Pole Tip Extender in winter, as that way I get more interior space and I imagine also in heavy snowfall the snow might glide down the side more easier (the latter I haven’t been able to confirm yet). It allows you to pitch the shelter in an A-Frame instead of one pole in the middle, so if you’re with two people and want to be close to each other this is an essential tool. It’s 112 g heavy and consists of two aluminium pipes which are connected via a piece of fabric, and for the handles you have two baskets made of fabric which wrap around the handles and connect via a string, that way you get the right distance for the poles for the A-Frame. The Khufu has velcro straps on the inside which allow you to attach the shelter to the poles. It takes a bit more work to get a good pitch when using it, but it’s vert stable in the wind then.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8511322488/" title="DCTP by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8507/8511322488_662dff260d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DCTP" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8511315596/" title="DCTP by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8085/8511315596_c2dc7db467_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DCTP" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8510237709/" title="DCTP in the top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8387/8510237709_1905ea90e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DCTP in the top" /></a></p>

<p>The top of the shelter, as well as the corner and mid tie-out points, have Dyneema reinforcements to not put too much stress on the silnylon. At the mid tie-out points there are elastic loops to connect extra guylines to.</p>

<p>The beauty of the Khufu is that it sheds wind from all directions very well, of course it is best if you pitch the narrow side into the wind, but I have spent nights in the Khufu where the long side was in the wind, and there were no problems either.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8511342460/" title="Mid tie-out point by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8381/8511342460_0b643d051d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mid tie-out point" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>
<p>The Pyramid design has been around a bit. Black Diamond, GoLite, Oware, and Mountain Laurel Designs have been making Pyramid shelters for a number of years, and before them probably also others. </p>

<p>What makes the LOCUS GEAR Khufu special is that you can get it in a number of materials: <a href="http://locusgear.com/products/shelter/khufu-sil">Silnylon</a>, highly breathable <a href="http://locusgear.com/products/shelter/khufu-event_ii">eVent II</a>, ultralight <a href="http://locusgear.com/products/shelter/khufu-cuben">cuben</a>, <a href="http://locusgear.com/products/shelter/khufu-tyvek">tyvek</a> and also a <a href="http://locusgear.com/products/shelter/mesh-shelter">mesh inner</a> is available. This allows you to pick the one Khufu (or two) you need for your conditions, which is a smart move, in my opinion. Add in the DPTE and you really can make this the one shelter to suit every need you might have.</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>
<p>The workmanship of the Khufu is superb. There’s something about Japanese craftsmanship that just makes me awe. Like a well made  刀 or katana the gear I have seen from Jotaro is of the highest quality, and attention is paid to every detail. Be it the materials, seams, guylines and line-locks, everything that goes into making this shelter is like a high quality, fresh ingredient, used by a Michelin Star Chef to create a perfect meal - or in this case, a superb shelter.</p>

<p>Even after a year of use in each season the shelter shows no signs of durability issues. The silnylon still is waterproof and the zipper runs as smooth as on the first day. No thread has come lose either, and overall I have been very happy about the durability of this shelter.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>
<p>My Silnylon Khufu weighs 399 gram including guylines. The stuff sack adds another 12 g. The new Khufus (from 2012 onwards, Aspen Gold &amp; Alpine Green) are a bit heavier, about 60 g, as LOCUS GEAR is using a new Silynlon which is even higher quality than the one in mine.</p>

<p>Products that occupy the same niche are the Mountain Laurel Designs DuoMid (481 g), Black Diamond Mega Light (1050 gram, 4 Persons), Black Diamond Beta Light Tent (535 g, 2 Persons), Oware Alphamid (524 g), so just going by the listed weights it seems the Khufu Sil is the lightest Pyramid Shelter available at the moment (in Silnylon).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7783326010/" title="Locus Gear Khufu at night by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8438/7783326010_c600a7c3cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Locus Gear Khufu at night" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>
<p>LOCUS GEAR pyramid shelters like the Khufu and Khafra are perfectly planned to use the whole fabric in the maximum width so that there are as little leftovers as possible. Even if there are remnants these will be used for accessories, e.g. stakes sacks and stuff sacks.</p>

<p><em>More in the future.</em></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>
<p>The MLD DuoMid &amp; Oware Alphamid are a rather similar design, then there’s the Black Diamond Beta Light Tent, and the GoLite Shangri-La who all are Pyramid-shaped to some extent. There’s probably more, but I’m not aware of them - if you know others, let me know in the comments.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7783323780/" title="The Pyramid Wonder by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7259/7783323780_d91b388b70_b.jpg" width="624" height="1024" alt="The Pyramid Wonder" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>
<p><a href="http://ryanjordan.com/">Ryan Jordan</a> likes his cuben Khufu. <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">Benjamin</a> has taken his Khufu Sil out many times in Germany and Switzerland, and <a href="http://infiniteoutdoors.blogspot.fi/">Marius</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.barefootjake.com/">Jake</a> just got one each in Aspen Yellow. </p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>
<p>I like the LOCUS GEAR Khufu so much that I decided to get a second one in eVent II (which will be reviewed in due time). If I go out on a pleasure trip where research and testing gear isn’t a priority, I grab the Khufu Sil and know that I have a shelter with me that can withstand anything I could encounter - strong winds, snow, rain or a mix thereof. If I want privacy on a camping place I close the doors and have ample space inside. If I want views I open both doors but still am protected from wind and weather. I can sit straight up in it and can get easily dressed/ undressed. </p>

<p>It is a superb shelter which I can recommend to anyone who wants a lightweight shelter which works in all seasons and environments. It is versatile, comes in great colours (I love that green!) and is extremely well made.</p>

<p><em>Two things that could be improved:</em><br />
- Longer standard guylines - even 10 cm more would do it.<br />
- Attachment loops/ tie-out points inside at the head/ food end for easier bivy guyline attachment.</p>

<p>These are personal things I’d like improved, and at least #1 I could easily fix myself (and likely will at some point).</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/37892708?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=c9ff23" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>
<p>The LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil can be bought exclusively at <a href="http://locusgear.com/">LOCUS GEAR</a>. An English website is coming soon, which should make ordering easier, though buying it is as simple as choosing the shelter you want, hit the PayPal Checkout button and follow the instructions on the following pages (and <a href="https://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/browser/">Google Chrome</a> has the nifty translate page function in case you can’t read 日本語). If you have questions, Email Jotaro who is always quick to answer and willing to help you.</p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>
<ul>
  <li>A few more photos</li>
  <li>More on Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</li>
</ul>

<p><em>In some of the photos you see the red/ grey Khufu eVent II. Both shelters are the same design, just different materials.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6812295618/" title="LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7182/6812295618_e28a6bcd6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="LOCUS GEAR Khufu Sil" /></a></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this and found it useful, feel free to <a href="https://holvi.com/shop/hikinginfinland/product/dd006c907dfc0805441be88068460867/">buy me a coffee or two</a> =)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HMG ECHO I Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/hmg-echo-i-review.html"/>
    <updated>2010-10-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/hmg-echo-i-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
Time to start the in-depth reviews of some of the gear used in &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/from-russia-with-love.html"target="_blank"&gt;Russia. I had the &lt;a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/products/echo-i-ultralight-system.html"target="_blank"&gt;Hyperlite Mountain Gear ECHO I Shelter System since a couple of months, doing a few overnighters in it and then of course putting it up and down for eight nights in a row in Russia. Enough nights spent under it to make a objective review, and to let you know if it is worth the money.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/fvnXRe9v6EPxc6FkPpLWiwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TLAcnnAfacI/AAAAAAAADYY/EN8eSX4m_tE/s800/IWG_Russia_0319.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br /><br />Lets start with the basic details, the weights as they were when I got my shelter system:<br /><br />Tarp: 228 g incl. guylines (HMG site: 226 g)<br />Beak: 112 g incl. guylines (HMG site: 116 g)<br />Inner: 305 g (HMG site: 325 g)<br />Stuff sack: 15 g (HMG site: 15 g)<br /><span style="font-weight:bold;">Total: 660 g</span> (HMG site: 682 g)<br /><br />Additional: <br />Nine Titanium pegs: 72 g<br />GG LT4 Trekking Poles: 198 g<br /><span style="font-weight:bold;">Total: 270 g</span><br /><br />The weights on the HMG site are without guylines attached, (I took the HMG weights with guylines as stated by Dan on the BPL forum in &lt;a href="http://www.backpackinglight.com/cgi-bin/backpackinglight/forums/thread_display.html?forum_thread_id=37100"target="_blank"&gt;this thread); also, I got a pre production sample so the to-be-expected weights are what's stated on the HMG site, which are not far off as you can see.<br /><br />In case you're still asking yourself, what is it made of, then the answer is cuben fibre. It is my first cuben shelter, and the weight saving in comparison to my &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/gossamer-gear-spinntwinn-review-video.html"Target="_blank"&gt;Gossamer Gear Spinntwinn is 52 g. The advantage with cuben versus spinnaker is that cuben is 100% waterproof and even more tear resistant, and well, super strong and lighter. As a UL backpacker, lighter (usually) equals better. <br /><br />Now that we got the important bits out of the way, lets get to the tasty chunks. As a starter, I serve today this HD video of how to set up the complete shelter.<br /><br /><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/14928877?title=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0"></iframe><br /> &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TQ75e8R68Ck"target="_blank"&gt;Click here to see the Youtube version.<br /><br />There were some questions about the speed of my pitch, and if it does take so long or if it is difficult to set up the ECHO I. The short answer is "No". The more detailed answer is, in the video I try to do it more slowly to be able to show and explain things, and not just hurry through it as I would in a downpour when on a mountain. I'm also a perfectionist when it comes to setting up my shelter, so I make an effort to get it pitched flawless. Hence the "slow" speed, for a normal, flawless pitch I need around three to five minutes, which probably seems like an eternity to people sleeping in a Tarptent Moment. Anyhow. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/b4BHklVuEkVGgvfUMHQNRwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUPekXRebI/AAAAAAAADbw/7NjoKpjm570/s800/IWG_Russia_0959.JPG" height="800" width="600" /></a><br />Bird's view. <br /><br />I have used the tarp mostly, as there aren't much bugs around anymore which would make me take the inner. I am thinking about if I might take the inner in winter, but am not sure yet. The beak was used on the days that I got extra gear (as a Daily Guide you get to carry a Satphone, GPS and two massive First Aid kits) so the extra space came in handy. Also if it is raining or very windy, the beak will come in handy. And of course one could use the beak as a Mini tarp just for the head when bivying. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Bxv9Vph0jeclAOhbAr6NvAaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUPkqNTyAI/AAAAAAAADb0/V7rxx47tFbs/s800/IWG_Russia_0928.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />When good stake-out points are rare, attach it to a tree!<br /><br />The tarp is one person + plenty of gear size, though you could squeeze with two and gear under it if you really like each other. I found it perfect for my needs, the smaller size also means I need less space for pitching it, which is great - so often in Russia I pitched in places where there was no a lot of good spots, so having a small tarp definitely put me at an advantage - my SpinnTwinn would not have fit some of the spots where I pitched, as it is so much wider than the ECHO I. So if you tarp a lot in areas where space for a good, perfect pitch, is at a premium, you will, like me, value the good size of the ECHO I. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ATn64QoKuDILq-BAmREZ3QaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TLAWz-cj3kI/AAAAAAAADT4/P2lJI_aDzwk/s800/IWG_Russia_0747.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/fEnGLe6m4Rh1wm0AOUYp7QaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TLAgB2o0oaI/AAAAAAAADZ4/4H4lhp4HDAc/s800/IWG_Russia_0745.JPG" height="800" width="600" /></a><br />Extra rain and wind protection with the beak.<br /><br />Speaking of size, the ECHO I tarp is 262 cm long, 213 cm wide in the front and 152 cm wide in the back. I can fit all my gear underneath the tarp, often at the foot end while only keeping the essentials - puukko, headlamp, water, camera - with me in the front, but I also can spread them out, for example while packing. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/UbvB3WUYKWoSEZ2vTwHjXwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TLAf_bLowNI/AAAAAAAADZw/xFxjzY9HQY4/s800/IWG_Russia_0744.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />Spread out gear.<br /><br />The quality is topnotch, as you would expect. The tarp has catenary curves everywhere - ridgeline, front, end and sides - and instead of sewing them, which would weaken the material, they're bonded. The tie out points are reinforced and it comes with custom made, that means in HMG's colours, guylines. My problem with the guylines is that they're a bit heavier than other lines, and also they're not reflective. I like reflective guylines, as they help other people not to trip over them - that's my usual problem &amp; worry. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/wBu0ZSgDzcL22z6bTWpRxgaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQYFQzgHI/AAAAAAAADcM/Vc889bKUdmU/s800/IWG_Russia_0332.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />In case you're not using trekking poles, you also can cut &amp; sharpen sticks and pitch with them.<br /><br />On to the beak. A very nice addition for when wind and rain are coming down horizontal from every direction. It is easy to attach with the help of buttons, as you can see in the video or on the photo underneath. It comes with a two way zipper which is waterproof, and it runs very smooth and doesn't get stuck in other material. Now attaching should be done under the front guyline, but I always do it over the front guyline as that's easier for me. You can attach both beak and front guyline to the same peg, but I like to use two different pegs. Also, when using the beak you should tie out the sides, something I usually don't do. While possible to do without, it is tauter and more stable when you do. <br /><br />Furthermore, and these questions have been raised elsewhere as well, some might wonder why there's no beak or wall for the back - after all, when you pitch into the wind and then it turns 180°, what then? The reason (or my reason, for that matter =) is that HMG assumes you'll use the complete system, so tarp, beak and inner. The inner, as you'll see, has a full wall in the back and thus would, if used with the beak, provide 360° coverage. Just looking at the weights, I personally would rather have a wall or beak for the back instead of the inner, as that separate beak/ wall for the back would be lighter than the inner. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/XDWChtAWb8pN4Ym3XN-o0gaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQ0CDX93I/AAAAAAAADcg/saa_hDQMRzA/s800/P1030794.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />Buttons to attach the beak in front.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/httSBqgcXv8WsKUWTjGRLQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQxw-OzeI/AAAAAAAADcc/qHBriiN-42A/s800/P1030792.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />D-Rings to attach the beak at the side tie-outs.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/dJ92fzzUEmoNX_0YRBFXzwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQryvevwI/AAAAAAAADcU/p-pkcl1vRJI/s800/P1030786.jpg" height="800" width="600" /></a><br />Back wall of the inner.<br /><br />Thus the inner. The heaviest piece of the shelter system, it gets attached with bungee cords to the tarp and you can get it nice taut with the line-locks. I haven't used this at all yet on a trip, but given that you can pitch it on its own - bug invested summer days - or with the tarp - bug invested summer days with rain - I can see it as a possible replacement for the LightHeart Gear Solo tent I used last summer. It has a tough black cuben floor and high sidewalls, as well as the aforementioned cuben back wall. The top and front have no-see-um mesh, and the door is fully openable with a two-way zipper. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/bqtlR2O54llyuoimqOpYYQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQwWsFiQI/AAAAAAAADcY/0giIcbAxOEM/s800/P1030790.jpg" height="800" width="600" /></a><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/AdRYPXR70eAXjRoEVeX6WQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQ6LxwLaI/AAAAAAAADcs/brH19S0R9ZI/s800/P1030797.jpg" height="800" width="600" /></a><br />Front door of the inner, with and without beak.<br /><br />The inner is 185 long and tapers from 81 cm wide in the front to 51 cm in the back. It is enough for you and your sleep system, but your gear will stay outside. That shouldn't be a big problem, though, as there's still plenty of tarp covered space to hide under for it. You can peg out the inner with the loops at all four corners, which makes life a bit easier and also keeps it in place. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/El3ltoZeTspIBUo9-EwfPQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQoQUgPWI/AAAAAAAADcQ/D9tfzGxHvyE/s800/P1030784.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />Full system - inner, tarp &amp; beaks.<br /><br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/cB8dZuPz4gqbxX0V1OkGbwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQAecuVWI/AAAAAAAADcA/Vzsfk6ihYGA/s800/IWG_Russia_0606.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />While moving in, pitching the front slightly higher. <br /><br />As the regular reader knows, I really enjoy tarping, so it is with great pleasure that I now carry even less weight with me when out on a trip. The modularity and high craftsmanship of the Hyperlite Mountain Gear ECHO I is its strongest selling point. You buy one system to suit all your needs. For spring and autumn you take the tarp and maybe beak, in the summer its the inner and tarp and in winter you take all three to have a bomb-proof shelter. <br /><br />What I could imagine, taking HMG's modular approach on step further, is that they could introduce a full cuben inner with small mesh windows at the top for winter use. In winter I'd like to keep the wind at bay, and with a double-wall shelter I even might gain a degree or two in warmth. I also can imagine that it's lighter than the mesh version =) I'd also like to see a beak/ wall for the back on those days where I wouldn't take the inner but would like full 360° protection. <br /><br />To conclude, I really like the ECHO I and I believe it could become my dedicated solo trip shelter. Its small footprint, light weight and modularity all speak in favour of it. It is easy and fast to pitch, looks great, and it is a joy to wake up under! It packs very small and I carry it, like my other tarps, in the outside pocket of my pack so it is easy &amp; quickly accessible. Finally, I will use this shelter during the coming winter, so you can expect a long-time review sometime next spring.<br /><br />The price for the ECHO I is 490$ plus shipping, and you can order one directly at &lt;a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/echo-i-ultralight-system.html"target="_blank"&gt;Hyperlite Mountain Gear. If you want to learn more about HMG, check out the &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-from-hyperlite.html"target="_blank"&gt;interview with Mike St. Pierre, the Founder and CEO of the company, which I did a while back.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8_tzsXiKBLBabpHzjEIIUQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQS9RyfdI/AAAAAAAADcI/cOnKmL_OLGQ/s800/IWG_Russia_0298.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />Pitch on a ridge with a view.</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gossamer Gear SpinnTwinn Review + Video]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/gossamer-gear-spinntwinn-review-video.html"/>
    <updated>2010-06-29T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/gossamer-gear-spinntwinn-review-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
In my effort to lighten my load, I decided to try out tarps. It took me a while to decide, after all we are so used nowadays to be inside that it seems very common to stay inside if it comes to shelters when backpacking. By the time I made the decision the temperatures were already under zero and the earth was covered in snow. Not being shy or scared of a challenge, I decided to try them out just then in winter, because I might as well collect these experiences right then and there - after all, tarping in summer is relatively easy.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/lhdALE1HNVO580JmnAJklp2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmvQaBBi8I/AAAAAAAAC10/bdUoWf_i11s/s800/P1030665.jpg" /></a><br /><br />Besides the aim of going lighter it was also the idea of being closer to nature and enjoying the views. Being in a tent, even a tarptent, puts you in a confined space away from nature and your surroundings. That can be a nice thing when the air is buzzing with insects or if a snowstorm is going down, but only very few folks will find themselves in the latter conditions outside and for the former there are also solutions when tarping available. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/9amM1WVd8elOpuxnBqa1-Z2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmvc1cqIVI/AAAAAAAAC14/hef1aQMXjiI/s800/P1030670.jpg" /></a><br />A palace for one.<br /><br />So I got a <a href="http://www.gossamergear.com/cgi-bin/gossamergear/Spinn-Twinn.html">Gossamer Gear SpinnTwinn</a>, which is including guylines 282 g. Lets put that into perspective with this list of shelters I own (I reckon I will get rid of some of them soon, no need for that much):<br /><br /><a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/04/msr-hubba-hp-2010-review.html">MSR Hubba HP</a>: 1385 g (all included)<br /><a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2009/08/gear-talk-tarptent-scarp-1-initial.html">Tarptent Scarp 1 Mk I</a>: 1347 g (all included)<br /><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4ZsbeJsibRo">Lightheart Gear Solo tent</a>: 754 g (excluding pegs, poles &amp; stuff sack)<br /><br />It is thus fairly light, but to be honest one needs to add to the SpinnTwinn the pegs and the poles. Now, I am not a big user of trekking poles - I rather walk hands free - but for crossing streams and for pitching a tarp they are mighty useful. The poles I have for the SpinnTwinn are 80 g for front and rear pole, versus 200 g for a pair of Gossamer Gear LT4 trekking poles, the difference ain't too bad and the user of trekking poles will certainly use them. Add in your favourite set of pegs, which can be anywhere between 5 to 33 g for a peg, and you're looking at a trail weight of about 400 - 450 g for the SpinnTwinn, which is over two thirds less than the above two tents and half of the LightHeart Gear Solo tent.<br /><br />I had some time on my hands during my spring trip to the north and made this little video of how I set it up on snow, have a look. <br /><br /><object width="853" height="505"><param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/fPKXZfT78fg&amp;hl=en_US&amp;fs=1&amp;color1=0xe1600f&amp;color2=0xfebd01" /><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always" /><embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/fPKXZfT78fg&amp;hl=en_US&amp;fs=1&amp;color1=0xe1600f&amp;color2=0xfebd01" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="853" height="505" /></object><br /><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fPKXZfT78fg">Watch it in HD</a> - click the link and choose 720p from the drop down menu.<br /><br />Its fairly easy to set up with the two poles, with the trekking poles I find it less straight forward because you'd need to find the right height for them - I don't carry a tape measure with me outdoors, so it is by trial and error that I find the correct height. Other than that I can nowadays pitch it in about three to five minutes until it is nearly perfect.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/FnQRtafMYns5mAIJ7nqNn52eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmv8a3ZRRI/AAAAAAAAC18/jUT1RvKfMA4/s800/P1040210.jpg" /></a><br />Mucho espacio!<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/FIuGwkHAGOaLxcV4AEyhXZ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmwK0LAmgI/AAAAAAAAC2E/wCDWqEq3cDs/s800/P1040228.jpg" /></a><br />Side view, pitched high.<br /><br />So how do I like tarping? Short answer: I love it. It is absolutely fabulous, I sleep far better than in a tent, I enjoy that I can right away see and hear everything that is happening around me, the fresh air, minimal condensation, lots of space - there is plenty to like about tarping. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/rQw-C5yfjS4_FXXHsFU6X52eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmzrreYB9I/AAAAAAAAC2M/QOR_3iENp90/s800/P1040247.jpg" /></a><br />Sitting under the SpinnTwinn in my sleeping bag.<br /><br />The SpinnTwinn is a fantastic shelter. Fantastic, because at 175 dollars it is very affordable and allows the beginner as well as the pro to gain a great shelter made of Spinnaker. Spinnaker is lighter than Silnylon and does away with the sagging that is so common of silnylon shelters. I also find it very resistant against abuse, it is not easily pierced through, and there's also not any problems with water spraying through it. My subjective feeling is that it sits right between cuben and silnylon and combines the best of both: affordability of silnylon, lightness, zero sagging, no water spraying and the abrasion resistance of cuben.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/DssmTQbWf31wsDhB_S-RHJ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm-kIUNt2I/AAAAAAAAC3A/x6Ni2uPxgZc/s800/P1040748.jpg" /></a><br />SpinnTwinn next to a MLD Cuben DuoMid and a MLD Silnylon Trailstar.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/OV78g-iTnJc-NX8sGbOTUJ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm-yV4FqcI/AAAAAAAAC3E/8OoOiqNMmyI/s800/P1040737.jpg" /></a><br />Same shelters, different view. Phil checking out the SpinnTwinn.<br /><br />I know that some stay away from tarps because they life in areas with heaps of insects, especially the blood sucking kind. In those environments you're glad if you can stay in a shelter where you can keep your sanity and blood. Going lightweight doesn't mean that you can not stay away from the insects and need to go mad. The solution is a bivy or a bug net, the latter being a simple tent made of mesh, giving you that insect free zone. Another argument against tarps is that they can't stand adverse weather conditions.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/C2LLmqEXxu-PLOqpglhn3J2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmz6ZOHQYI/AAAAAAAAC2Q/AtYhjkycJsk/s800/P1040276.jpg" /></a><br />My tyvek bivy protects my sleeping bag from eventual snow or rain which might be blown under the tarp, or insects in the summer.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/77p9r8E_-BU9gxytSn41KJ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmz-80VYzI/AAAAAAAAC2U/Ba8v1m6Di78/s800/P1040279.jpg" /></a><br />Inside loops allow for the hanging of a line, or as in my case, an attachment point for my bivy.<br /><br />I get that. In Finland, and much of the Nordic countries, we have plenty of forests which are great for keeping the wind at bay and thus allow one to often find a sheltered camping spot. The scenery is different in the north, though, where treeless fjells will allow the wind and elements to run free and you won't find any protection besides your shelter. That is where the majority of folks will take their "bombproof" shelters, because the wind and rain/ snow could make life hard. Not having camped under those conditions yet, I nevertheless believe that the SpinnTwinn would be just fine and offer sufficient protection from the elements - if pitched correctly. That would mean to pitch low and with one side into the wind, make sure your pegs are well dug in and don't come out, and you hopefully have a bivy to protect your down quilt from rain/ snow. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/99p0EkV-gRW29BHn3A5cDp2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm0c7ikFpI/AAAAAAAAC2g/biY4OZKTh9Y/s800/P1040341.jpg" /></a><br />Morning view.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/LQm7HfMA1BPmlGXTjxfaCZ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm-E3n1z-I/AAAAAAAAC24/_bAnEdljh_M/s800/P1040749.jpg" /></a><br />Evening view.<br /><br />There will be those who might disagree, and because of my lack of experience of tarping in the fjells I can only speak hypothetically. And I would trust the SpinnTwinn (or any other tarp) to protect me also in more adverse conditions when out on the fjell. I will keep this opinion until I have gathered sufficient experience to proof this right or wrong, but for me UL backpacking has as much to do with skills as it has to do with the gear. <br /><br />Back to the SpinnTwinn. As you can see from the photos, I have used the tarp during winter and spring, on snow and on earth, in rain &amp; snow and in sunshine, with strong winds going and without even a breeze. Once I learned to pitch it correctly - that took pitching it once or twice - it is easy and fast to set up. While it is a two person tarp I haven't yet tried it with someone else, but I am very confident that two could be very comfortable under it, even in the rain. As you can see above, it offers sufficient head room in the front (I'm 175 cm tall, no idea how tall I am when sitting) and changing clothes or packing your rucksack is no problem.<br /><br />I also like that it packs very small, and it fits perfectly in the front pocket of my <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/05/packing-your-frameless-backpack.html">LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK</a> besides all the other stuff, where it can dry out when it is wet - that allows me to take it without stuff sack as well, saving a further 11 g! <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/18UoROMrx4XIi1wFF4Am9Z2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm0S4NcxgI/AAAAAAAAC2Y/snfewpoB3vY/s800/P1040325.jpg" /></a><br /><br />As you can see, I like this tarp a lot. For the price you're hard pressed to find something lighter which has so much features. And as far as I know Gossamer Gear is one of the two companies which makes tarps out of Spinnaker (the other one being MLD which have usually an eight week waiting queue), and the benefits of the material I already discussed above. My conclusion is: If you're looking for a light tarp which is affordable, doesn't sag and offers a lot of space, look no further than the Gossamer Gear SpinnTwinn. It is your cheapest start into lightweight tarping (MYOG aside) and lets you find out in the best way if tarping is something for you. I really love it =)<br /><br /><a href="http://flattr.com/thing/985/Hiking-in-Finland-Ultralight-Backpacking-Blog" target="_blank"><img src="http://api.flattr.com/button/button-compact-static-100x17.png" title="Flattr this" border="0" /></a></div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
