<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: trip report | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/trip-report/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-02T23:41:11+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Koli National Park | Ultralight Summit 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/01/koli-national-park.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-14T18:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/01/koli-national-park</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m not a big fan of November backpacking. Though somehow that hasn’t hindered me in the last years to plan week-long backpacking trips in what I find the worst time of the year. And to top things off, I always manage to convince other people to join me on the trips. These time my companions came from as far away as Japan and the United States of America, to experience what Finland (<em>does not</em>) have to offer in November. <em>An Ultralight Summit trip report.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943410053/" title="UL Summit 2013 View?"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2842/11943410053_ca62a790f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 View?" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We had big plans for the Ultralight Summit last year. That we’d be hiking in November in Finland wasn’t part of it, but if you manage to </p>

<ul>
  <li>Keep busy</li>
  <li>Still want to meet with your friends</li>
  <li>Need to write a story about <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/koli/Pages/Default.aspx">Koli</a></li>
  <li>Said friends want to go hiking in Finland</li>
</ul>

<p>Well, you catch my drift. Benjamin, Jotaro, Takashi and Hideyuki arrived in early November in Helsinki, and on a Monday morning at 7:12 o’clock we sat in a train to Joensuu. Four and half hours in a train with free Wifi, electric outlets and a decent Board Restaurant can still be long, and it was nice to stretch the legs shortly in Joensuu before getting a ride from a good friend to Koli. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943558004/" title="UL Summit 2013 Koli Visitor Centre"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7335/11943558004_7205d851ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Visitor Centre" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943394843/" title="UL Summit 2013 Ukko-Koli view by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5538/11943394843_395f411f1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Ukko-Koli view" /></a></p>

<p>And then we are there. Nearly at the top of this 400 something metre high hill, there’s a sweet looking hotel (although in cold wind probably any hotel looks sweet &amp; inviting) and a visitor centre - which, with our luck, was closed. Good timing, there. We tried to reach Takashi and Hideyuki who traveled here already a few days earlier, but as we couldn’t reach them we set off towards Ukko-Koli, Akka-Koli and Paha-Koli, the three peaks from where one has very nice views over the lake towards <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/from-russia-with-love.html">Russia</a>. It’s as we stand on the third peak that I get a message from Takashi - they’re at the hotel now, where shall we meet? Ten minutes later - Takashi and Hideyuki ran <a href="http://www.theomm.com/events/">The OMM</a> in Wales before they came to Finland - we meet, and agree to get together at the first camp spot later. </p>

<p>While Ben, Jotaro and me set off, the weather is changing from cloudy and windy to cloudy, windy and drizzly with increasing Darkness™. We descent from the Koli peaks, past pastures of old, over soft grass fields, along a bit of road until we ascent and head for the Kota at Ryläys. It’s pitch black and snowing as we hike via duckboards over a hanging bog towards the Kota, and are quite relieved as we see the humble abode for the night.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943963106/" title="UL Summit 2013 Joulu Olut"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5495/11943963106_7b2fd9c207_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Joulu Olut" /></a></p>

<p>We saw and chop wood and the fire is just going as Hideyuki &amp; Takashi arrive. We welcome them to our massive shelter for the night, put on a couple more logs, and I finally can get the heavy load I carried till here out: To celebrate this first night I brought a <a href="http://www.olvi.fi/web/fi/68">Olvi Joulu Olut</a> for everyone along - well over 1,6 kg! I reckon this makes the first night sort of a <a href="http://www.backpackingnorth.com/2013/07/brovernighter-with-korpijaakko.html">Brovernighter™</a>. Anyway. Fire. Shelter. Snow. <a href="http://locusgear.com/products-2/bivys/pneuma-bivy-event?lang=en">A new bivy</a>. After eating well I decide to take the new bivy outside into the snow and sleep there - it’s the perfect, safe opportunity to do so. I slide into the red bivy, snow falling strongly around me, zip it almost closed, change socks, and fall asleep. Three hours later I wake up, and decide that it was enough - the top of my <a href="http://bit.ly/18Wo3Sr">sleeping bag</a> was a bit moist, and I rather have a completely dry sleeping bag, so I pack the whole shebang up, sneak inside, put another log on the fire so I see something, and fall asleep next to my fellow lightweight backpacking friends.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943566324/" title="UL Summit 2013 Kota"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2816/11943566324_02f2cf419c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Kota" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943133225/" title="UL Summit 2013 Warm &amp; comfy"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2875/11943133225_52edba0b99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Warm &amp; comfy" /></a></p>

<p>The next morning we’re in winter wonderland. Everything is white - the trail, the kota, the trees, the ground. We smile. Light the fire. Eat breakfast. Enjoy the silence of the snow, the mist in the tree tops, we wander around the cozy Kota with its warm fire inside. But even the cosiest Kotas can not hold back eager backpackers, and so a while later five hikers emerge from the wooden structure, around them the snow melting &amp; dripping from trees. The thermometer has slipped just a degree or two above Zero, enough to make the snow starting to melt and dribble on us. </p>

<p>We ascent the hill we’re on, upwards to the look-out tower with the broken ladder. It’s so misty that we wouldn’t have seen further than 50 m from up there either way, and so we walk a bit further, have a group photo at the “Waterfall of Rocks” (hidden in the mist) and continue. The trail winds along the top of a ridge, goes a bit down into the forests where we cross fast flowing small streams by jumping from tree roots to tree roots, and then ascents again a few dozen meters, back to hard, wet granite under our trail runners. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943394503/" title="UL Summit 2013 Reflections"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5475/11943394503_24d07604b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Reflections" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943117845/" title="UL Summit 2013 Early winter"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3798/11943117845_e8977fa4e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Early winter" /></a></p>

<p>Then comes the moment that Hideyuki &amp; Takashi need to turn back. As they came before us, they will leave us already today. I show them on the map that it might be faster to come with us another few kilometres to one of the forest roads, which should be quicker to hike back to the Visitor Centre. But the two, quite rightly in hindsight, decide to hike the same way back we just came. They just finished The OMM, so this certainly isn’t a problem for them. As we say our good byes, it always feels a bit sad to say bye to people whose company you enjoy, but that’s life. We’ll hike again together this year.</p>

<p>Ben, Jotaro and me carry on, the mist and dripping snow our constant companion while we walk high. As we descend, the snow is largely gone, we can see further, and the trail gets wider. We hike for a while on a forest road, but also here we encounter no one. It’s far past noon as the three of us arrive at a laavu - or the ashen remains of it, all that is left standing a oven in front of the burnt down structure. The wind is blowing strongly from the lake and the fire doesn’t really want to bring our pots with water to a boil, even more wood and a windshield do little to improve the situation. After what seems like forever warm drinks &amp; soups are hungrily consumed, jokes are made, pots cleaned, the fire is put out, and we walk back to the adventure centre. </p>

<p>That’s the desolated adventure centre. A wet hammock swings in the wind, the camping ground - pitching your tent here costs 10€ - is flooded, and the small cabins are all locked. We walk down to the strait, where a rope between two pulleys, connected to a raft, is drifting in the middle of it. We pull the raft to our side of the strait, board it, and while I take action photos of the crossing Jotaro and Ben bring us safely to the other side. There we stand, laughing about this interesting way to cross a water body, take a few more photos, and then head onwards. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943959786/" title="UL Summit 2013 Pull!"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7333/11943959786_e793dccfd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Pull!" /></a></p>

<p>The path on the island goes very closely along the shore, and often is either flooded, muddy, or both. At a fire place in the centre of the isle we look north from the shore, seeing the mountains we stood on the day before, grey clouds and mist hanging not far above their summits. Water drops from leaf-less twigs paint circles as they hit the lake. We snap photos, have a kuksa of lake water, and continue. The other strait is crossed via a lovely wooden bridge, and we walk along signs telling us that we should stay on the trail. Obvious the summer cottage owners right next to the path have had their fair share of hikers pick their berries.</p>

<p>We hike on as dusk is setting in. It quickly gets dark in the forest, and every time we cross a glade it gets lighter again, the eyes try to adjust, but we’re so quickly in the dark of the trees again, they don’t have time. As we reach the final clearing at Lakkala, it is the camping place we will stay at this night. An old crofters lodge, with various stables, fields and little laavus for the sheep who graze here in the summer is where we will pitch our pyramids this night. Once we found dry spots, that is.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943576414/" title="UL Summit 2013 Birch? by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3767/11943576414_1719dff5fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="341" alt="UL Summit 2013 Birch?" /></a></p>

<p>The field which is designated as a camping place for pitching tarps and tents is ABOUT 75% flooded. Nevertheless, Ben, Jotaro and me find each a spot where our pyramids go up, with enough dry space to unroll our sleeping pads, bivies and quilts. Then the task of making a fire begins. I carried a first load of split logs to the flooded fire circle, and start the task of making feather sticks and building the fire, while Ben &amp; Jotaro carry each a couple of arms full of wood to me. In this rain &amp; wind, we’ll need fuel. Armed with two hands of dry birch bark and half a dozen of feather sticks the fire is roaring in no time. We keep it going strong, the wind blowing in gusts from the lake while the rain keeps falling at a steady pace. Dressed in eVent and Gore-Tex we sit around the fire, split logs as little footstools to keep our soaked trailrunners out of the puddles around the fire. </p>

<p>Despite the miserable weather we sit there, eat, drink and laugh. We put more logs on the fire, trying to find the optimal spot for out titanium pots to boil one more cup of water, and then at 19 o’clock head each to our shelters. In the glow of my headlamp I read a couple more chapters of Terry Pratchett’s latest novel, before I switch the Nao off and lay down. The wind howls over our little shelters, and pulls at the cuben and dyneema cords. But everything holds, and in the next morning I awake as I hear Jotaro’s camera shutter opens and closes. It’s still dark, it’s still wet, and there’s still wind going. Eventually I slip out of my warm down cocoon, into wet socks and shoes which are quickly warmed up by running a few hundred meters on the trails. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943405823/" title="UL Summit 2013 Lakkala Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3672/11943405823_65a06d3b20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="UL Summit 2013 Lakkala Camp" /></a></p>

<p>A fire is started again in the middle of that puddle while grey clouds race over the sky, giving glimpses of blue. We’re so absorbed with looking at the fire and eating that we are surprised as the sun sends a few rays through the forest in our back. We pack up what is dry, though our shelters are not in that category. We’ll return via another ridge to Ukko-Koli today and a campground close to the town, and as we shoulder the packs, now wonderfully light as less and less food is carried, the sun illuminates the hills on the opposite shore. </p>

<p>The trail is nice today, it changes between hard granite and softly-cushioned pine needles with a few duck boards in between. We get glimpses from the top to the surrounding lakes, forests and hills, but are blasted by a relentlessly cold wind and I’m happy to wear a fleece under my softshell. It doesn’t take us long to come to a crossroad, where we stash the packs behind a tree and hike the kilometre and a bit to the Devil’s Church, a 33 m deep cave in a Z form. Without packs the pace is fast as we hike steadily down. We cross a wide forest road and descent wooden stairs to the cave, and climb in. It is moist, green moss grows on the walls. We spend a little time in there before we head back, all the way up to our rucksacks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943134585/" title="UL Summit 2013 Green"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5537/11943134585_1138e4fd01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Green" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943124865/" title="UL Summit 2013 Inside the Devil's Church"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7384/11943124865_8a0a215fd0_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="UL Summit 2013 Inside the Devil's Church" /></a></p>

<p>On the next stretch it feels like we spook up Western Capercaillies with every third step. These large birds of the grouse family are in such abundance here that thoughts of a Capercaillie hunt cross my mind. But without a bow &amp; arrows, this idea stay in the realm of fantasy, while the realities are boiling water for soups-in-a-cup with bread and snacks. After our last lunch on the trip, at a fire pit which offered so wet wood that we were well smoked afterwards, we continue for a bit on a forest road. As we come to a junction, where the trail takes a turn into the forest and heads uphill, Jotaro &amp; Ben tell me they’d prefer to continue on the road to the campground. It’s easy enough, so I leave the two and head up the ridge to Mäkrä hill. </p>

<p>I run parts of the trail, happy to go at my own speed, and also in a hurry because the Golden Hour is about to begin any moment now, and I’d rather see it from the top than from the middle. My speed pays off, and I see how the sun sends its last rays towards Russia, while it sinks down behind Sweden, Norway and the lands beyond. The forest opposite of the lake is illuminated by the light, a pulsating movement as clouds whisk by the sun, that descends further and further. I walk along the ridge, more Western Capercaillies taking flight as I approach, and as the western horizons is adorned with an orange band, I take a last look East, then West, and descend. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943389463/" title="UL Summit 2013 Golden Hour view towards Russia"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5538/11943389463_1a71e8fe90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Golden Hour view towards Russia" /></a></p>

<p>I emerge out of the forest at the Mäkränaho clearing, and choose the wide trail back towards the Visitor Centre. Along the trail I pull the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/petzl-nao-headlamp/">Petzl Nao</a> once again out of my <a href="http://www.zpacks.com/accessories/backpack_lid.shtml">ZPacks Multipack</a> as darkness engulfs me. It does not take long for me to reach the Parking Lot of the Visitor Centre, and I run the stairs up to the Hotel &amp; Visitor Centre, where the trail to Turula continues. Again I hike down a wide, well-maintained trail and as I arrive at the campsite Ben &amp; Jotaro have already pitched their shelters. </p>

<p>We gather wood once more from the close by wood-shed, fully-loaded with split logs and generous amounts of birch bark, and soon sit again, with our wet shoes propped up on a log close by the fire, around it. Water we get from a nearby well at a farm-house, but only on the second try we locate the right well - the first one we filled our Platypus bottles up from had E.coli bacteria, as the owner of the house informed us. We sit long around the fire, and are a bit startled as a trailrunner runs past us and our shelters, the beam of his headlamp jumping along the field and roads until it disappears. Before heading to sleep I give my <a href="http://bit.ly/1bcnz0i">NeoAir XLite Sleeping Pad</a> a few additional puffs, before I slip into the <a href="http://bit.ly/18Wo3Sr">Therm-A-Rest Antares sleeping bag</a>. The wind gives a few kind tugs at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">UltaMid</a>, and a few raindrops hit the cuben, though overall it is a silent night. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943409303/" title="UL Summit 2013 Ben tending his fire"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3782/11943409303_4663af0f36_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="UL Summit 2013 Ben tending his fire" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943122365/" title="UL Summit 2013 Delicious breakfast"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7386/11943122365_156f2899fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="UL Summit 2013 Delicious breakfast" /></a></p>

<p>The next morning Ben and Jotaro are well up before me, and I lay long in my sleeping bag. The sound of fire, which Ben started, finally rouses me and I join the two outside. Starbucks Via and a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/trek-n-eat-muesli-schweizer-art-mit-vollmilch/">Trek’n Eat Swiss Müsli</a> are for breakfast, and especially the latter is superb. I’ve tried many ready-made trekking müslis, and non were good which is why I usually made my own, but this one was so tasty that it’s a serious alternative to MYOM-üsli. </p>

<p>Sleep systems and gear are again packed, shelters shaken to make them a bit less wet, and we set oFf towards the Koli Village. I arranged for a Taxi to pick us up there at 11, but the two kilometres from the campsite to the village, along old Farm buildings on what is in winter a skiing track, does not take us long. We have so much time till the Taxi comes that we sit down in the Café and order salty crepes and coffee, skim through Finland’s worst outdoor magazine, and enjoy being indoors in the warmth after all the snow, rain &amp; wind outside.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943400053/" title="UL Summit 2013 Stream by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3794/11943400053_2af4f9524e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Stream" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943111545/" title="UL Summit 2013 Last bit by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3831/11943111545_7e62193630_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Last bit" /></a></p>

<p>Back in Joensuu, civilisation has us back. We visit a lunch place and supermarkets, have coffees and wait till the train takes us back to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html">Helsinki</a>, where Ben &amp; me will meet <a href="http://www.valppaus.com/">Joni</a> for an overnighter in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/run-or-die-nuuksio-classic-trail-marathon.html">Nuuksio</a>. <em>But that might be another story.</em></p>

<p>More photos on <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157637917534175/">Flickr</a>. The UL Summit 2014 will be in Nippon. Watch this space and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> if you’d like to join.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943571914/" title="UL Summit 2013 The Crew"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7412/11943571914_2af055e3e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 The Crew" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untold Trip Reports]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/untold-trip-reports.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T11:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/untold-trip-reports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Unsung heroes, untold stories. So much time outdoors, so little time to write about them.</em> <strong>These are the Untold Trip Reports.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9537611324/" title="Dusk by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7312/9537611324_1787dd85ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dusk" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="packrafting-in-ruunaa">Packrafting in Ruunaa</h2>

<p>I was just back from the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">OutDoor Fair</a> when I saddled two packs with packrafts on my shoulders to travel to Ruunaa, where I was teaching a packrafting course. It was a very wet weekend, though we laughed, paddled and hiked a lot. One more packrafting aficionado joined the tribe, eagerly waiting to acquire his own, taking it on future adventures on rivers and lakes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715313/" title="Wet by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/9559715313_228cbc97ab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wet" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9562508942/" title="Time to pick some berries by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/9562508942_5af0666233_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Time to pick some berries" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715473/" title="Water by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5532/9559715473_6d6f4ee7e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Water" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715389/" title="Fire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7314/9559715389_6c714de875_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="backpacking-in-seitseminen">Backpacking in Seitseminen</h2>

<p>Another course with three superb clients, we were backpacking for three days in the beautiful Seitseminen National Park and learned about ultralight skills and gear. Gathered mushrooms, swam in the lake, sat around the fire and slept warm in hammocks and quilts, while the sun shone down on our trail. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9519459009/" title="Ultralight camping by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3793/9519459009_f7441f5148_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ultralight camping" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9537712134/" title="Mirror II by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/9537712134_1c135a66d0_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Mirror II" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9534948843/" title="UL Tenkara fly fishing setup by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2821/9534948843_b9483f1f44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Tenkara fly fishing setup" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9534922329/" title="Ramaria flava by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5471/9534922329_a1b6a2e21f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Ramaria flava" /></a></p>

<h2 id="kungsleden">Kungsleden</h2>

<p>A failed trip is also a trip. After the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> I had an ambitious plan to ski a loop on the Kundgsleden, though as I took a fall while ice climbing where I injured my knee the skiing was just too painful, and so I returned after having skied 20 km on brand-new skis which I would have loved to take up some fjells. Alas, it was not meant to be, though I will return soon enough for a re-match.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571269176/" title="Dynafit Broad Peak by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7348/10571269176_24320b56c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dynafit Broad Peak" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571517553/" title="Shadowboxing I by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5485/10571517553_1cf154a314_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Shadowboxing I" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9129268734/" title="Khufu on the Kungsleden"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2850/9129268734_56263af54b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Kungsleden" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571514423/" title="Dusk by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7335/10571514423_5fbb1fcc56_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dusk" /></a></p>

<h2 id="dayhikes--overnighters">Dayhikes &amp; Overnighters</h2>

<p>The largest amount of untold stories are the dozens of <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/WorldHeritageSites/kvarkenarchipelago/activities/Pages/Default.aspx">dayhikes</a> and overnighters here in the region. Plenty of great outdoor destinations around Vaasa, not only the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/a-family-hike-on-the-bodvattnet-runt.html">Kvarken Archipelago</a> which it counts to explore - by bike, packraft, on foot, and soon again on skis and snowshoes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410128705/" title="Dawn by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/10410128705_2ce65c655f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Dawn" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410103134/" title="Skis, carried. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3704/10410103134_a0acf19995_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Skis, carried." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9982464505/" title="Reflection. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2813/9982464505_bbbbcd925d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="909" alt="Reflection." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8839376917/" title="052113_1264 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7307/8839376917_73a7be00b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="052113_1264" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632582072/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8389/8632582072_9c86a0a5ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p><em>These are the Untold Trip Reports, and there will be more of them in the future.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Urho Kekkonen National Park]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T15:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>One National Park</li>
  <li>Two brothers</li>
  <li>Three Lenses</li>
  <li>Four Feet</li>
  <li>Five Nights</li>
  <li>Six Days</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html" title="Fire"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2889/9763148185_31286687eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The travel up north started in Tampere, the rainy city which welcomed us with sunshine. A good omen? Possibly. Re-packing, dinner, beer, and off to the night train. A cabin was paid for, 30€ extra well spent as it meant we arrived rested in Rovaniemi. Also here: Sunshine. A stroll to the waiting bus, backpacks down into the luggage compartment, and off we went. We turn right past the glass igloos and arrive four hours later at Kilopää Station, a packed parking lot letting us wonder how many people we would meet this week. But once we passed the bus-loads of pensioners on their way up to the Kilopää summit and back down, people got fewer. And once we left the marked trail behind, they disappeared.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763646456/" title="Wideangle"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5462/9763646456_3764c0da5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wideangle" /></a></p>

<p>At the Rautulampi hut we drink tea. We meet a few people, but it being so early we decide to push on. A short bit on trail, before we leave it behind again. After the yellow birches: Wide views. We arrive at the hut, and decide to stay in it. Water is boiled, food eaten, drinks drunk, fire made. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763854414/" title="Navigation in autumn can be colourful"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/9763854414_9995bc480b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Navigation in autumn can be colourful" /></a></p>

<p>We leave under a grey sky the next morning, but the sun comes through once in a while. The trail disappears at times, but we arrive at the first bridge after a couple of hours, lunch, tea, and off into the wild again. Traversing a mountain till we reach the other “bridge”. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763631271/" title="Bridge"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3809/9763631271_9270fc0f99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bridge" /></a></p>

<p>Easier trails follow. Even the sun comes through more often. Up another hill, and more wide views.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763850285/" title="Sun &amp; Clouds"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7335/9763850285_bbb51e324f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sun &amp; Clouds" /></a></p>

<p>Another night in a hut. The morning brings rain, and a German-Finnish doctor on his way back to civilization. We chat for a long time, waiting for the rain to stop. With hardshells on, we leave, but soon enough the sun comes through and we switch back to windjackets.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763991044/" title="That way"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2809/9763991044_e50a703e0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="That way" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763769821/" title="Moody I"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3708/9763769821_ed2d1baeab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Moody I" /></a></p>

<p>Paradise Gorge is beautiful indeed, and a nice scramble up. I pitch the TrailStar for a tea break, before we head to the second highest summit. A rainbow hangs in the sky to the left as we descend to the Devil’s Gorge, and on the way to the break hut a short rain shower sees us putting the hardshells on again.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764143326/" title="Up Paradise Gorge"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3770/9764143326_5c798e849b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Up Paradise Gorge" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764147934/" title="Paradise Gorge"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7348/9764147934_fe3a0854f1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Paradise Gorge" /></a></p>

<p>As we arrive at Muorravaarakka hut the sun shines down from a blue sky again. A Dutch family tells us that we <em>just missed the rain</em> and then set off to Anterinmukka hut. We pack the hardshells away for the 2nd time today, eat, refill our bottles and then set off again. Twenty-five minutes later we catch up with the family, who have a coffee break at the top of the hill, enjoying the view. “See you at the hut. We’ll keep the Sauna warm for you!” we tell them.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764301996/" title="Devil's Gorge"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2828/9764301996_cbb1cfb5a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Devil's Gorge" /></a></p>

<p>The sauna is still warm, so we pitch the shelters, grab the whiskey, kuksas and towels and head in. The river water is cold, refreshing. As we go back up, the Dutch family has just arrived, and they happily head to the warm sauna.</p>

<p>We sleep under Silnylon and Cuben, cocooned into our warm quilts and sleeping bags. The next morning brings a grey sky yet again, but it looks like it will stay dry and get sunny. Coffee and müsli is our fuel, we pack and leave on a Quad trail onwards, following the river up in which we swam last night.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764208401/" title="Fireplace"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7316/9764208401_fe3dd21a8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fireplace" /></a></p>

<p>At a lone fireplace we again leave the trail behind, following another river until we reach its origin, where it splits: One part goes east, the other west. We head north, across extensive boulder fields, through a lost valley of Eden, and up even more boulder fields. Sokosti, Eastern Finland’s highest summit, is our goal, but it’s ugly: A radio tower, two support huts and an array of solar panels crown it, but no rest place for hikers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769576353/" title="Towards Sokosti"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7429/9769576353_1cdd00a4b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Towards Sokosti" /></a></p>

<p>The descent is an exercise in finding the path. We give up, make our own, and before we reach the tree line sit down for the last tortilla and cheese lunch. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764088782/" title="There's the Sauna?"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2836/9764088782_aa74826384_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="There's the Sauna?" /></a></p>

<p>At Luirojärvi another Sauna waits, and images worth of postcards. We enjoy the warmth of the sauna, the coldness of the lake, before we head on to pitch the TrailStar, make a fire, boil the chantarelles I found earlier in the morning, and enjoy this fine, starry evening.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769497594/" title="Mirror Image II"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3665/9769497594_ee42f5826b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mirror Image II" /></a></p>

<p>The morning brings fog and sunshine. It’s a spectacle worth seeing every time, and under a blue bird sky we pack and start the longest stretch of the journey. Hills covered in red, orange and yellow, wide moors and Rock Ptarmigans accompany us. It is so warm, we hike in T-Shirts, and I enjoy the opportunities to wade through cold rivers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769573263/" title="Mirror image by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5447/9769573263_d2796379b3_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Mirror image" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769608944/" title="Autumn trail"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/9769608944_765f986ac6_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Autumn trail" /></a></p>

<p>Kilometers fly by, and we encounter more and more people heading in the opposite direction. Heavy-loaded external frame backpacks are still the norm, as are complaints by their bearers about aching knees and blisters. We load up on water, leave the gathering at the laavu behind and head up.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769707276/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7412/9769707276_aeb0f94db0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid" /></a></p>

<p>The sun sets, but the blood red sky at the horizon lingers on for what seems like forever, until darkness from the east consumes it and shrouds the sky into its black cloak with blinking white stars. No Northern Lights, though, no matter how long I sit outside watching the sky.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769778313/" title="X"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3748/9769778313_e05e51f5af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="X" /></a></p>

<p>Mist is moving across distant mountain tops in the morning, while the sun tries hard to break through the clouds. As it finally does, we start to walk. By the time we reach the Station at Kilopää we already have encountered more than two dozen hikers and backpackers. Yes, the wilderness definitely lays now behind us, and civilization has us back again.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769750802/" title="Grey, yellow, blue"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7328/9769750802_cbfe175257_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Grey, yellow, blue" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157635543361552/">More photos</a>. Read more about it in the upcoming issue of <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/">trekking Magazin</a>.</p>

<h3 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h3>

<p>Flying is the fastest and often also the cheapest choice. There’s connections from Helsinki to Ivalo, and from Ivalo airport you take the bus south to Saariselkä, Kilopää or Koilliskaira.</p>

<p>More environmentally friendly and a lot more time consuming is the train + bus combo. Head on the night train to Rovaniemi, get a cabin, sleep, then hop in the morning on the bus to Saariselkä, Kilopää or Koilliskaira to start your adventure.</p>

<p>Saariselkä has an <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/saariselka">Partioaitta</a> outdoor shop where you can get gas canisters and gear. The village also has a few supermarkets which will let you shop for food. If you have spare time in Rovaniemi, head to the <a href="http://www.prisma.fi/market/prisma?a_Visit:rajaa=1&amp;osuuskauppa=ARINA&amp;pageName=Main&amp;b_haku.paikka=Rovaniemi">Prisma</a> there for a very wide variety of outdoor gear and food at more reasonable prices.</p>

<p>The National Park is divided into four zones with different regulations in terms of wild camping. Outside of the Basic Zone trails are not marked, and you should know how a compass works, best in conjunction with a map. Speaking off, the Koilliskairan ulkoilukartta map is the best map if you want to explore the wild side of the National Park. Sadly it’s just a crappy paper map and will fall apart after a week of use.</p>

<p>There’s six Saunas in the National Park, plenty of huts, both free (<em>Autiotupa</em>) and reservable (<em>Varaustupa</em>), as well as two dozen laavus and several turf huts. The price of a reservable hut is 10 euro/ night/ bed and all beds will be sold if there’s demand. Daytrip huts are not for overnight stays, and if you go to the dry toilet throw some of the wood stuff from the box over your business. You can drink water everywhere, though if you have a sensitive stomach boil it first.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/urhokekkonennationalpark/Pages/Default.aspx">Urho Kekkonen</a> NP page with more Information.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.retkikartta.fi/index.php?lang=en&amp;id=868">Digital map</a> for planning.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.vr.fi/en/index.html">Train schedules</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="www.matkahuolto.info/lippu/fi/connectionsearch">Bus schedules</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.backpackingnorth.com/p/gear-rental.html">Packraft rental</a> at Backpacking North.</li>
</ul>

<p>Don’t want to go on your own? Keep an eye on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/guided-trips/">Guided Trips</a> as there will be winter and packrafting tours in UKK in 2014.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Last Day of Winter]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/05/last-day-of-winter.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-01T22:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/05/last-day-of-winter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The venerable overnighter has been modernised a few times in the last years: Two, three years ago they were called <a href="http://ryanjordan.com/blog/">24</a> adventures by Ryan, about two years ago Alastair started to call them <a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com/microadventures-3/">Microadventures</a>, and Aaron called them <a href="http://aaronteasdale.blogspot.com/">S24O</a> (Sub-24 hour Overnighter) somewhere in between. I went on one of these S24O-Microadventure-Overnighters on one of the last cold days in April.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631516475/" title="Sunset by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8262/8631516475_c299f19e4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sunset" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I kissed my wife and son Good Night, grabbed my ready-packed <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/packs/3400-porter-pack.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Porter</a>, skis attached to it, and walked the two kilometres to the nearby recreation area, Pilvilampi. The sun was just disappearing behind the trees as I arrived on skis at the frozen lake. I wanted to ski for some three to four kilometres to the other end of the lake, and pitch my shelter over there. </p>

<p>There are tracks on the lake, but we already had a wonderfully warm March and so much of the ice was in less-than-perfect skiing conditions. But my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">Madshus Glittertind MGV+</a> had good grip, and after a quick decision I just left the rubbish tracks behind and made my own ones. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632582072/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8389/8632582072_9c86a0a5ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p>It didn’t take me long to arrive at the place I wanted to pitch, and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hilleberg-brg.html">Hilleberg Anjan 2</a> I loaned from a friend came out. I practiced pitching it a few times before, so it was quickly up and ready. The thermometer was wandering in the direction of -10°C, and I enjoyed the evening, with the stars coming out, the sun fading away far in the west, and some Whopper Swans arriving from their winter quarters with their loud calls.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631552987/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8265/8631552987_36fa0a9212_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p>I took a few fun photos, and then heated up some water with the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Kueche/MSR-Reactor-1-0-L::601.html?refID=hif">MSR Reactor 1.0 l</a> for a late night hot chocolate. Even at -11°C it had the half litre of water boiling in less than three minutes, and inner warmth soon returned. Donning the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/rab-infinity-endurance-jacket/">Rab Infinity Endurance</a> down jacket I enjoyed the gorgeous night sky a bit more, knowing that soon the stars won’t be seen for the lack of darkness that we have here during the summer in the far north. Even if I planned to go to sleep early, it was past 23 o’clock as I crept into my quilt. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632700218/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8388/8632700218_9b72195ced_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Sonic Boom</strong>. Well, not quite. But minutes after I was tucked in, the ice decided to start it’s concert of booms and creaks. The mind plays funny things at those moments, and so I was wondering if I’ll be able to get out of the tent in case the ice under me should collapse and I’m engulfed by freezing cold water. Then the other side of the brain told me that I need not worry, as I’m either way camped close to a small island and hence the water couldn’t be deep under me. And either way, the ice is still over 20cm thick. So the concert continued throughout the night, and I drifted in and out of sleep. A loud <strong>boom</strong> had me sitting almost upright in the tent, and I welcomed the first rays of sunlight close to 7 o’clock.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631779593/" title="Cold morning by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8631779593_b240668ae3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cold morning" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631612299/" title="Morning by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8544/8631612299_ca3d6a0c76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Morning" /></a></p>

<p>There was a bit of hoarfrost on my gear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631603519/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8253/8631603519_e6a2ab33d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632731688/" title="Guyline by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8540/8632731688_8e40fcf26a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Guyline" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632720204/" title="Hoarfrost by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8540/8632720204_afc82f4d32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hoarfrost" /></a></p>

<p>I melted a bit of snow, put on my <a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/176-westcomb-switch-lt-hoody.html">NeoShell Westcomb Switch LT Hoody</a> and enjoyed the scenery with a cup of coffee in hand. A man who was well in is sixties skied past by me at 7.30 o’clock, at a speed which would have me made him guess 40 years younger. He looked surprised, as did I. <em>A quick lap before work, to stay healthy.</em> That’s the Nordic way.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631665847/" title="Breakfast by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8119/8631665847_1f4c43f5ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Breakfast" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631656205/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8112/8631656205_a3694af548_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631642589/" title="Toughstake by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8545/8631642589_c914f7ba42_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Toughstake" /></a></p>

<p>Then it was time to pack. The tent was rolled up and put back in its stuff sack, gear found it’s way into the HMG Porter, I switched from my wonderful <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/mukluk">Mukluks</a> into the skiing boots, stepped into the bindings and skied off towards civilization. The improvised skiing poles I left at the trail head, and was in time for a second coffee at home, having enjoyed the last cold night of winter before the snow and ice melted away just days later.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631464645/" title="Snow by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8125/8631464645_fc905e9739_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Snow" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632601812/" title="Skiing Poles, improvised by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8109/8632601812_db099cf5e9_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Skiing Poles, improvised" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631589275/" title="Way home by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8102/8631589275_72963e0640_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Way home" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On The Rocks]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/on-the-rocks.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-22T21:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/on-the-rocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The sun was shining, it was a balmy 11°C and I was sitting on the backseat of a car, heading away from the coast. The conversation was about <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-dragon-cam-klemmgeraet/">dragons</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-demon-cam-klemmgeraet/">demons</a>, and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-starters-nut-set-klemmkeile-set/">nuts</a>, and I was full of anticipation for the first outdoor rock climbing session of 2013.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669659242/" title="001 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8404/8669659242_0564544c50_o.jpg" width="4121" height="2975" alt="001" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We took a left and were on forest road, passing fields and hay barns, until Minna parked the car and declared “<em>We’re here.</em>” All four of us got out, grabbed our backpacks from the trunk and headed along towards the crag. It was the first time I was at Falkin Kallio in Ylistaro, and I immediately liked it: A nice short approach, and great routes for every taste. We put our harnesses and helmets on and then Mikko was off on a bolted route. Once up, he installed a top rope for Minna and me, while he and Outi practiced a few things further on the left. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669647942/" title="Mikko catching a glimpse of the cranes which flew by by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8401/8669647942_c3629f968d_o.jpg" width="4912" height="3264" alt="Mikko catching a glimpse of the cranes which flew by" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669637440/" title="Nice cracks by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8379/8669637440_840ca54e9b_o.jpg" width="3264" height="4409" alt="Nice cracks" /></a></p>

<p>Minna let me go first, and so I got my climbing shoes on, made my Figure 8 Knot, and got up on the rock. Yes, it was dry. But it also was cold. And there were no big jugs as easy holds like at the gym - small cracks, tiny crimps, and some slippery moss here instead. I slowly made my way up, remembering what I have learned in the past. I also wasn’t afraid to fail, because only when you fail, you get better. On the final few meters I burst out laughing: As I moved my foot over a ledge to get up the final few meters my leg started to shake rapidly. “<em>Elvis has entered the building</em>” Mikko laughed after I told them. I took a small break, relaxed my arms, and then made the move without problems. The scariest part of any climb with a new person is for me the being let down part. “<em>Will they be able to hold me? How do I get over the ledge?</em>” are the thoughts going through my head. I know I shouldn’t hold on to the rope, but it’s a reflex with each first abseil with a new person. But Minna let me down safe and comfortable, and I thanked her. Her turn, my belay. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669612936/" title="Mammut Smart &amp; Tendon Master = Awesome by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8388/8669612936_4e851867b9_o.jpg" width="3264" height="2448" alt="Mammut Smart &amp; Tendon Master = Awesome" /></a></p>

<p>We each climbed the route a couple of times, and then all four of us sat down for some coffee and snacks. More talks about cams and nuts, climbing destinations near and far, future climbing trips. Then we geared up, and tried a new route - a small crack running top to bottom. At the bottom water was running out of a crack, and I duly slipped. Minna caught me, and suggested I try the dry rock on the right. Much better. Crack climbing is utterly new to me, and it was immense fun. Fun now, that I think about it, but back there I was wondering how to get further up. Fingers jammed into cracks where I wondered what will happen to them if I now fall. I was halfway in a hard move as Minna informed me that the rope is stuck. </p>

<p>Exquisite. It’s the stuff you want to hear when your fingers are jammed in a crack and you’re trying to work out how to get further up. I looked up, and saw that the rope was twisted. “<em>Hold me</em>” I told Minna, as I was untwisting the rope by crawling underneath it and stepping back over it. “<em>How is it now?</em>” I inquired. “<em>Still stuck</em>” came the reply. Just as well. “<em>I will go a bit further and see what’s the problem</em>” I let her know, and after a bit of fresh chalk on my fingers I jammed my fingers back in that crack and pushed myself up. “<em>Stuck in a crack</em>” I called down - “<em>Now is good again</em>” came the reply. I finished the climb, sat down in my harness, hands by my side, while Minna expertly let me down. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669729870/" title="The routes of the day by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8388/8669729870_37d41fd3b4_o.jpg" width="3264" height="2448" alt="The routes of the day" /></a></p>

<p>After Minna did the crack route we headed a bit further along to a slab with a couple of bolts to practice lead climbing. With snow still at the bottom and plenty of moss on the rock it looked a bit sketchy, but it was nice and easy. Well-sized pockets made for good holds, and for me it was a great first experience at lead climbing. The kind of thing were you can get a taste for it, build up the skills and confidence, so that when the harder routes are to be lead you can look back and think “<em>Yeah, I can do this. And failing isn’t a problem, either.</em>” We each lead the two different routes, before it was again coiling up the rope, getting into my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/salewa-wildfire-gtx-approachschuhe/">approach shoes</a>, packing up and heading back to the car. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669616136/" title="Minna leading by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8398/8669616136_2e79d2fc14_o.jpg" width="4912" height="3264" alt="Minna leading" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669602724/" title="Second lead by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8394/8669602724_8791c1a90b_o.jpg" width="4912" height="3264" alt="Second lead" /></a></p>

<p>Five fine outdoor climbs, the first of the season. New rocks, new routes, new friends, new experiences. This summer sure looks like it will be a lot of fun =)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
