<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Trip Report | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/trip-report/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-24T14:09:40+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sea Stack Climbing in Ireland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-20T23:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ashfall Quartz. Ebb. Tide. Swell. Mix it together, throw in a rubber dinghy and you have the stuff for a Sea Stack climbing adventure.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002240157" title="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/17002240157_6342150a0a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>From the distance Berg Stack looks like a wee little rock in the North Atlantic Ocean, just off the cost of An Port in County Donegal, Ireland. We - Iain, our guide, a photographer and an US American journalist - slept the last night in the Port Cottage and now a blue sky &amp; sunshine have us frolicking in the superb weather. <em>“Lets go and check out the swell and tide”</em> Iain announces. We pack up our climbing gear and the 40€ rubber dinghy, bought at a Toy Shop - three at a time, they’re not that durable and walk the <a href="http://www.walkni.com/iat/">IAT</a> path up to the sea stack.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589476163" title="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8697/16589476163_e1526639df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left" /></a></p>

<p>What looked like a wee sea stack from the lawn of the cottage turns out to be a 25 m high sea stack with a large ledge at the bottom, beautiful cracks and pin scars lining it from bottom to top and a Great black-backed gull with its nest on top. Oh, and an angry Atlantic Ocean with a two to four metre swell, making for not a good time to cross. We still inflate the unnamed dinghy, Iain gives me the instructions of how to assist him when he will board the sea worthy vessel to establish a tyrollean traverse on Berg Stack so I can get over, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17023512169" title="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8693/17023512169_4922bee743_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The we sit &amp; wait. Observe the swell. Finally Iain decides we’ll come back at high tide later in the afternoon, when the sea should be calmer. Adrenaline that was build up in anticipation disappears, shoes go back on and we go for a nice hill walk, checking out Cnoc na Mara - the Sea Stack we had originally planned to go up, but with this sea that would have been too much risk. The views are spectacular, the valley deserted and I can make out a dozen of superb spots for a wild camp.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021928808" title="A look up Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5322/17021928808_206ed924b5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look up Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>Sea stack climbing is less about climbing, really. Sure, it helps if you can climb well and know how to place gear - it’s all trad - but it is just as much about the skill set an Alpinist has: Patience, Risk Assessment, Speed &amp; Efficiency. Maritime skills &amp; knowledge are also essential, knowing when the tide is coming in, how high the swell is, if it is safe, being patient. Finally, a bit of daring for an adventure is also needed. After all, if you think paddling in a toyshop rubber dinghy on the Atlantic is insane, then sea stack climbing is nothing for you.</p>

<p>We’re back on the main land and observe the sea. It is high tide, the swell is still high but every now &amp; then there’s a calm moment - and one of these Iain uses to paddle over to Berg Stack. An euphoric cry echoes over the sea and you can see how a load is off his shoulders. He sets up an anchor for the tyrollean traverse, and during the next calm moment he’s back on the main land. We discuss the strategy and then it all goes quick: the dinghy is back in the water and Iain is in it, surfing the swell, a 240 cm sling connecting him to the tyrollean. A calm moment comes, he paddles in and I jump in - and just as quick out again off on Berg Stack. We both howl a cry of victory, a victory over the tide and swell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021935758" title="Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5343/17021935758_1ab7fb492e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>From here on it’s all basic rock climbing: Harness and rock shoes come on, Iain racks up and we tie into the rope. I stand barefoot on the ledge, the swell crashing on the rocks around. Iain leads up a variation the <em>Cormorant</em> which he probably has climbed a dozen times and before long an “Off belay” call echoes down to me. It is a nice route with great hand and foot holds up till the middle to the arête, then it goes around the arête and up a wet corner, which is also the toilet of the Great black-backed gull and its offspring which were kind enough to let us top out there. A moment later I stand on the top of Berg Stack next to Iain, high-fiving him, and again we both let out a howl of victory. But this is not a sports climb where you just clip into the chain and then rappel off. No, this is a sea stack. And the sea is angry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002250497" title="Roping up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7651/17002250497_95a7de41ea_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Roping up" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002062747" title="Me on Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8706/17002062747_44b293c870_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Me on Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17209684205" title="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5448/17209684205_822563f419_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The easiest way off the top back to the ledge is to down-climb a corner to about two meters above the rushing sea, and then traverse the sea stack on superb ledges &amp; holds back to where we started. We short-rope and five minutes later stand next to our dinghy. The sea is lower, more rocks can be seen as the ebb comes in, but the swell is still high. <em>“Lets wait till the tide is out and then walk off”</em> Iain says, and so we deflate the dinghy which has served us so well on the way here, pack up and wait. Wait for the water to retreat, for the swell to let us escape from this rock.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589483823" title="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5342/16589483823_e771dc38d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183741396" title="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8700/17183741396_a98415b910_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell" /></a></p>

<p>The sea does not see a reason for letting us off, it wants to keep us. The swell is high and white foam rushes over the barnacle-covered rocks, which would otherwise allow us to easily walk off. The sun throws its last rays on the main land, we can see the hut from our ledge and the comfort of the warm fire in the cozy cottage and slowly we’re getting cold &amp; hungry. Low tide arrives, but the swell still throws up large, foamy waves over the rocks we should have just walked off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183747146" title="Cold feet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17183747146_b904d8e834_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Cold feet" /></a></p>

<p>Iain goes first, jumps the large gap and makes it just to the top of a big rock when a wave comes in. He brings me my approach shoes and throws them over, as I do not fancy jumping barefoot on wet, slimy rocks and risking a broken ankle. Waiting for the right moment I too make the jump, and a final victory cry echoes from the rocks - the land has me again. We pack up and in the falling dusk walk to the cottage, where a warm fire and cool beer are waiting for us. My appetite for sea stack climbing is awakened, but first I’ll need to hike further on the International Appalachian Trail to Northern Ireland, to return another day for more sea stack climbing adventures.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17022143920" title="Patience by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17022143920_703730e92f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patience" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>
<p>There’s a <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/sea_stack_guide">free Sea Stack Guide book</a> if you want to go sea stack climbing - it has almost all sea stacks in it. A selection of sea stacks you also find in the <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a> book. I would suggest you do your first sea stack with Iain from <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/">Unique Ascents</a> and learn the ins &amp; outs from him about the sea and getting safely on and off the sea stack. He’s also a great guy and you’ll have a lot of fun on a day out with him. You’ll need a sea-worthy vessel - maybe <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Rentals:::34.html">loan a packraft</a>, but be sure you also know how to use it and have an idea about the tide, swell and weather forecast. If a sea stack is too much adventure, check out the <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/undiscovered_donegal">Donegal rock climbers guide</a> and visit one of the local crags, though there are also <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=CfM3DTcHcS8">calm days on Berg Stack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17208905321" title="Port Donegal Cottage by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8763/17208905321_de9c296ae9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage" /></a></p>

<p>If you plan to climb in the area around An Port stay in the <a href="http://port-donegal.com/">Port Donegal Cottage</a> - either book via their website or on <a href="http://www.ownersdirect.co.uk/accommodation/p8069109">Owners Direct</a>. It has a wonderful cozy feel and relaxing in the bathtub after a day out on the sea will be so good that you don’t wanna go out. It sleeps eight and with some luck Roland, the owner, will be around and delight you with his stories from far away places.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021740458" title="Port Donegal Cottage Inside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7725/17021740458_6b9517e048_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage Inside" /></a></p>

<p>The nearest village via a road is Ardara where you find several accommodation options like the <a href="http://www.bayviewcountryhouse.com/">Bayview Country House</a> and also shops and the <a href="http://www.nancysardara.com/">Nancy’s of Ardara Pub</a> for a after-climb pint, though it adds at least 45 minutes driving to your approach. For rest days go to Glencolmcille in the neighbouring valley and visit the <a href="http://glenfolkvillage.com/">Folk Museum</a> where you can see how people lived in the last centuries in the area, grab a good cup of coffee and a bite.</p>

<p>Gear wise you will need Trad gear as there are no bolts. Bring cord and slings if you want to abseil and need to build an anchor. Most of all, be patient with the sea and be open for the adventure!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Family Adventures in Pyhä-Luosto]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-08T23:41:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The common human relationship with winter seems to go like this: As a child you love winter. In your twenties you could life without it. And from your thirties onwards you fall in love with winter &amp; snow again. In our family we’re all winter lovers, and as winter didn’t really visit us in Vaasa we decided to find it up north at <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/eng/">Pyhä Tunturi</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075087012" title="That one next, dad! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7599/17075087012_e945efd6da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="That one next, dad!" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="prologue">Prologue</h2>

<p>Climate change is a real bummer for winter lovers in Southern Finland. While I did get to ski and fatbike in the snow a bit back home, winter in Vaasa was a mix of snow + cold and then rain + warm temperatures which resulted in a less than nice winter. With a week of winter vacation that we could each take of, M and me decided to search winter in Lapland. After some discussions of what we wanted we quickly settled on the <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/eng/">Pyhä Ski Resort</a> as the best destination for us this year as it had plenty of fun winter activities to offer for all three of us, from skiing and hiking over sledding to ice climbing and fatbiking, with great <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/accommodation/">accommodation</a> options, too. </p>

<p>A car was rented, <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel?s=8">AirBnB accommodation</a> in Oulu was organized and the luggage was packed. It was a nice Sunday morning as we started the drive north, and it was around Oulu - 300 km from Vaasa - that we saw the first signs of Winter again. The next day we continued via a stop in Rovaniemi onwards to Pyhä, and already from a distance we could see the iconic fjells of the ski resort and <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/pyha-luostonp">National Park</a>, with lots of snow around us and a beautiful bluebird sky promising a great week of winter fun! We checked in to the <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1128&amp;submenu=3657">Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartment</a>, heated up the Sauna and enjoyed seeing the stars in the crisp, black sky.</p>

<h2 id="winter-fun-for-kids">Winter fun for Kids</h2>

<p>We found Pyhä a great location for our three year old. He loved the snow and we were daily at the sled hill, which was a five minutes walk from the <a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/pyha-luostonluontokeskus">Nature Centre Naava</a> (which is in the centre of the village and hence an easy reference point). The two sled hills were good fun and E didn’t get tired of sledding for many hours each day, with little rest breaks at the conveniently located open hut at the foot of the hill. Being allowed to throw another log of wood on the fire was equally nice as making snow angles and sledding together <em>superfast</em> with dad. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889011560" title="Pyhä Sled Hill by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7713/16889011560_3351fc57fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Pyhä Sled Hill" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076568685" title="Sled Hill break hut by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8752/17076568685_cb2b65aa11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sled Hill break hut" /></a></p>

<p>There’s a ski school for kids in Pyhä too, though we decided to wait for another year to put him on downhill skis. There were lots of kids skiing, though, and the Family slopes were full with parents and kids of all ages. Close to our apartment was also a reindeer enclosure and visiting Rudolph and his friends was every time again fascinating. E also enjoyed looking how other people skied down the hills so fast, and going up with the Polar Express to the top of the fjell made him smile from ear to ear. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075825821" title="Top of the fjell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8798/17075825821_e54ca475a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Top of the fjell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="skiing">Skiing</h2>

<p>M and me have the same shoe size, which was convenient as we loaned cross country skis and boots. M enjoyed skiing the tracks while I went a bit off-piste and explored the nearby National Park and swamp on skis. There’s surely a hundred kilometre or more of groomed cross-country skiing tracks at Pyhä and M liked the little huts and Laavus along the tracks, as they were ideal to have a short break and then ski back. The tracks vary in difficulty, from a super easy loipe that goes around a mire with zero elevations to more demanding loipes. You even can ski around the whole Pyhä-Luosto National Park on groomed tracks, which is - depending on the route you choose - between 70 or more kilometres. For early morning and late night skiers there’s also a pretty long illuminated track which is lighted up from 6 in the morning till 23 at night.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075080162" title="Skiing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/17075080162_2149394d66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Skiing" /></a></p>

<p>But of course cross-country skiing is just one sort of skiing you can do in Pyhä! It’s very well known in Finland to be <em>the</em> Backcountry destination, as you can take the lift up and then pretty much ski down where you please. Sadly my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">DPS Tour 1 skis</a> didn’t arrive in time otherwise I would have been out on the slopes and made some pretty turns after skinning up the hills. There are lots of great ski-touring options at Pyhä, so if that’s your kind of skiing make sure to take your gear along! Also for downhill and Freeskiers Pyhä is a great destination, with 9 lifts, 14 prepared slopes - the longest slope being 1800 m - and the same ski pass being valid at Ruka as well Pyhä is a great destination to go snowboarding and skiing. Add in that the lifts are working super efficient and queues were non-existent and you have the ingredients for lots of skiing and fun.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16890340699" title="Top of the fjell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8716/16890340699_d85b8eda66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Top of the fjell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ice-climbing">Ice climbing</h2>

<p>One of the reasons why Pyhä won for us as a destination is that you can go <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/ice-climbing/customized-ice-climbing/">ice climbing at Tajukangas</a> which is a short stroll from the slopes and the Pyhätunturi Hotel. My friends from <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/">Bliss Adventure</a> run the ice climbing crag there, and I was very happy that my friend <a href="http://aleksimehtonen.fi/">Aleksi</a> and his colleague Mikko were there with me and were the belay masters while I was whacking some ice. And whacking ice I did!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16454119254" title="My first ice lead at Tajukangas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7665/16454119254_4f6f3c878e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="My first ice lead at Tajukangas" /></a></p>

<p>After a couple of warm-ups and checking out the routes I did my first ice lead ever, and while I was a bit nervous while tying in to my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.fi/en/mammut-genesis-8-5-half-rope-red/?pid=81">Mammut 8.5 Genesis Ropes</a> and racking up the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/petzl-laser-speed-ice-screw/">Petzl Laser Speed ice screws</a> as soon as I was on the ice and put my mind on the task ahead the fear was gone, tranquility and enjoyment flowing through me. As far as ice leads go this wasn’t the most difficult route ever, though I found the company and encouragement from Aleksi &amp; Mikko superb and they helped me to trust myself and lead on ice. Now I’m hungry for more and hope that next winter will be much better than this one, so that there will be much more ice climbing and leading!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075086492" title="My first ice lead at Tajukangas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8723/17075086492_4b88107d6d_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="My first ice lead at Tajukangas" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hungry">Hungry?</h2>

<p><a href="http://pyhawurst.fi/">Pyhä Wurst</a> is a cozy little Restaurant/ Café at the bottom of the Northern Slope. They serve, as the name suggest, a variety of different sausages, and all three of us really found our food extremely tasty. Our son devoured a Hotdog - his first one! - and would have liked a second one, while M and me enjoyed a Bratwurst Hotdog and a Riistakäristys. They place was very popular with skiers &amp; snowboarders, walkers, cross-country skiers and families alike, so check them out when you’re in Pyhä and would like to taste some good Wurst!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050601976" title="PyhäWurst by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8732/17050601976_5f89cb12f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="PyhäWurst" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.cafeloimu.fi/en/">Café Loimu</a> was another Café which we enjoyed visiting almost daily as they served some super-tasty pancakes and good coffee. They’re located in the same building as the Nature Centre Naava so kids can even go and explore the museum on their own while the parents can enjoy a moment in the Café. Café Loimu is right in the middle of the village and also has an Á la carte Menu if you want to eat a bit more than pancakes or a sandwich.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/restaurants/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1019&amp;submenu=138">Hotel Pyhätunturi Restaurant</a> has a gorgeous Panorama view over the surroundings and is an ideal place to conclude a nice day outdoors, especially if the Northern Lights decide to show up and play a show over the forests and mires. M ate the best Sautéed reindeer (<em>poronkäristys</em> in Finnish) in her life at the Restaurant and found it so tasty that she still talks about how good it was. I enjoyed <em>The Poro</em> which was equally delicious, while E had problems finishing his kids meal of spaghetti and meatballs. The atmosphere and service at the Hotel Pyhätunturi Restaurant were excellent and if you stay in Pyhä we strongly recommend that you visit the restaurant.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16457137153" title="The Poro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8686/16457137153_4fe83a661d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="659" alt="The Poro" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.huttu-uula.fi/">Restaurant Huttu-Uula</a> has won an Chaîne des Rôtisseurs award and is located at the foot of the Polar slope. Every Thursday it serves a <a href="http://www.huttu-uula.fi/files/uula_puffee.pdf">Lappish Food Buffet</a> with lots of delicious dishes from Lapland. The friendly atmosphere together with the good buffet food make this a recommended visit on a Thursday evening, though you should reserve well in advance as the Buffet is very popular and was fully booked out when we were there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889741440" title="Leipäjuusto by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7681/16889741440_7557737323_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Leipäjuusto" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fatbiking">Fatbiking</h2>

<p>Since I got my <a href="http://salsacycles.com/bikes/mukluk">Fatbike</a> cycling has been a lot of fun in winter. Riding over the frozen Baltic Sea, shredding over the single track in the forest and doing laps on the groomed trails are just a lot of fun, so of course I took the opportunity to go on a <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/fatbikes/">Fatbike Adventure at Pyhä</a>. I was very lucky that my friend Artturi was my guide for the morning, and after familiarizing myself with bike and hearing what Artturi had planned for us we hit the trails.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16888790748" title="Fatbiking, skiing or hiking? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7676/16888790748_0235d89209_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fatbiking, skiing or hiking?" /></a></p>

<p>After some beautiful, flow-y single track trails we arrived at a large mire which was a lot of fun to ride across. We had a short break at a bird watching tower which allowed for wide views over the National Park, before continuing across the mire - fat tires rock in that terrain! Slowly narrow tracks brought us back to our starting point, and after a nice climb back up to the Hotel this little Fatbike adventure was done. You also can rent a Fatbike for half a day or longer from Bliss in case you want to explore the National Park on your own. Hats off to Bliss Adventure for offering this service, I think they’re spot on with it and I saw daily very happy fatbike cyclists riding on the trails and snow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076575735" title="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8797/17076575735_d5ec086d2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456411083" title="Selfietime! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7610/16456411083_2d9c29dd7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfietime!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076574115" title="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17076574115_7c29a3b793_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park" /></a></p>

<h2 id="snowshoe-hiking">(Snowshoe) Hiking</h2>

<p>There is a dedicated <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/video-msr-lightning-ascent-review.html">snowshoe</a> hiking trail in Pyhä, though it was so hard packed that one didn’t need snowshoes to walk on it. So we had a nice little family hike to the Isokuru gorge and back, which includes a steep descent and climb from the nice Isokuru Kota. The hike seems to take the route of the summer nature trail as we passed quite a few signs which gave information about the forest and land, and is ideal if you’d like to be outdoors for a couple of hours. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050611986" title="Danger! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8813/17050611986_396e0e5472_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Danger!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456419973" title="Family Hike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/16456419973_19757d8746_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Family Hike" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075086052" title="Fire by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17075086052_af66532256_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="nature--silence">Nature &amp; Silence</h2>

<p>Despite all the activities you can do in Pyhä, there are two things in Pyhä-Luosto everywhere, and they’re for free: Nature and Silence. Even with a Baltic Ski Cup going on while we were in the village, we just needed to walk for five minutes towards the <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/en/pyha-luostonp">National Park</a> and there was a calmness that was just once in a while interrupted by birdsong or the wind blowing through the trees. Pyhä-Luosto National Park is home to the southern most big fjells in Finland, beyond them towards the south starts the flat land. Though this does make them popular I had at no time the feeling that there were too much people around me, for example the lines at the lifts were pretty much non-existent despite there being a bunch of people, and also in the Cafés and Restaurants there were never masses of people. As someone who values silence a lot I found Pyhä a great place, with easy access to nature and the possibility to <em>“escape”</em> the main slopes and head into the National Park, where even on blue bird days I didn’t meet more than a handful of people. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16869172217" title="Silver by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7613/16869172217_7c288c4b9e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Silver" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050598466" title="Snow &amp; Birch by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8690/17050598466_e512ff6074_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Snow &amp; Birch" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p><strong>Where to stay?</strong></p>

<p>We stayed at a <a href="http://www.ski-inn.fi/majoitus.asp?prodtype=30&amp;lang=eng&amp;tunturi=&amp;day=&amp;endDay=">Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartment</a> which was ideally located right next to the slopes. The apartment was super family-friendly and had two bedrooms, a small kitchen, living room, balcony, a own Sauna and a drying cabinet to dry wet garments and gear (super handy with kids!). There are plenty more options in town, from the nice <a href="http://www.ski-inn.fi/majoitus.asp?prodtype=41&amp;lang=eng&amp;tunturi=&amp;changeMonth=">Ski-Inn Hotel Pyhätunturi</a> to many, many cozy <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=cabins&amp;submenu=3660">cabins</a> and even a <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1106">caravan site</a> if you’re coming with your own accommodation. You’ll surely find something to your liking, keep an eye out for deals, though, as at e.g. the Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartments ski passes can be included in the price saving you a bunch of money!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16869175557" title="PyhäSuites by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7703/16869175557_09002a90bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="PyhäSuites" /></a></p>

<p><strong>How to get there?</strong></p>

<p>As we don’t own a car we rented one for a week and drove up north. Vaasa - Pyhä is around 660 km and with a toddler along we decided to split the journey in two and spend a night in Oulu. If you come from abroad you might want to fly directly to Rovaniemi and take the <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/info/?file=content_exec&amp;id=2292&amp;submenu=3890">SkiBus</a> to Pyhä, or take the (overnight) train from Helsinki and then jump on the SkiBus. In the village you can walk pretty much everywhere within 15 minutes, and there’s a variety of shops to suit your needs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157651506091295/">More Photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16454124174" title="No sledding by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8787/16454124174_baa0f5cd6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="No sledding" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075081902" title="Aurora Borealis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7644/17075081902_4025b6fd68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p><em>Thanks to the Pyhä Ski Resort and their Partners which invited us up north.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking &amp; Scrambling in the Polish Tatras - Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-03T10:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">climbing &amp; mountaineering in the Polish Tatras</a> to hiking and backpacking. In the rain &amp; sunshine, up high in the mountains and low in the valleys.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397717831" title="Focus on the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397717831_9014d3f632_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Focus on the rain" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rain--misery">Rain &amp; Misery</h2>

<p>As we wake up at the <a href="http://www.piecstawow.pl/en/">Przedni Staw Polski Refuge</a> and I look out from my window the mist hides the mountains and the rain drops leave little circles on the lake. Everything is wet. Marcin and I silently get out of bed and move to the big common room, give in our orders for breakfast and enjoy the tasty food that comes through the small window from the kitchen. Slowly it gets busy, people packing, but with the rain keeping up a constant drum on the roof none leave the hut. At ten we’re the first ones to venture outside, curious looks on us in our rain gear, and as Marcin tells where we headed people just look even more confused.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214238360" title="A look back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214238360_3bfa19dbfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin gave me a few options: Walk the easy trail through the valley to the Schronisko Murowaniec refuge, or the shorter but high route across a pass at the end Orla Perć. We had light packs, good gear and so it was easy to make the decision to go via the pass. I either way was a bit disappointed that we didn’t take my original route, but plans are plans: Drawn on paper, dreamed up looking over maps in the warm comfort of home. When the weather turns it’s best to adapt them and stay safe - something I can now say in hindsight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400893955" title="Crossing snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15400893955_db1585c08f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crossing snow" /></a></p>

<p>We walk by the mist-enshrouded lakes, cross the stream via the little bridge and hear the waterfall thunder down towards the valley while we slowly ascend. I carry my camera underneath my jacket so I can keep on making photos, but in the drizzle and thick mist there isn’t much to see. We cross small streams, old snow, and steadily keep on walking uphill. Once in a while the mist has a gap and we can see a bit further - the other side of the valley, further up, down the valley.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397714501" title="Slippery by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/15397714501_32e8d0e031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slippery" /></a></p>

<p>To be able to continue to take photos I left <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hestra/">my gloves</a> in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">my pack</a> - a decision I regret the higher and windier it gets. I also ponder why I decided to put on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1BD2sfW">Alpha Comp Jacket</a> instead of my <a href="http://bit.ly/1rRRHpb">Patagonia Alpine Houdini</a> rain jacket as I start the get wet inside - or then it’s the sweat from hiking and scrambling up? At least I’m warm and the jacket and pants keep the wind outside. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214147809" title="Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/15214147809_699c6e2391_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up" /></a></p>

<p>We scramble up steep passages, rain and small streams making things slippery - it’s a good thing I’m wearing my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a> boots, that way I have good grip on the wet rocks and half-way dry &amp; warm feet. Soaked we arrive at the pass and the wind howls past us. I shelter behind a big rock, but Marcin lets me know we should push on. So on we push.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14363720837" title="Wind. Rain. Honesty. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14363720837_7ac4627792_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wind. Rain. Honesty." /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400901985" title="At the top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/15400901985_9d8d44d8b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the top" /></a></p>

<p>On the way up I thought about how nice it will be to go down in the downwind side. But I must have misunderstood Marcin, as we hike down on wet talus fields on the upwind side. At a narrow stretch of path between the talus I finally decide to go search for my gloves in my pack, as my hands started to be just too damn cold in the strong wind. When I finally have managed to get my soaking wet &amp; cold hands in the gloves they need a moment to warm up, but then it’s infinitely more comfortable. The same time I pack away my camera, so I can concentrate on the path. We down climbing a few sections and then slowly are getting lower. </p>

<p>We hike over snowfields and I can believe it as down, out of the treacherous wind, we see a solitary figuring coming our way, wearing a Poncho. Marcin chats with him, and as we continue to walk I hear a similar story like the ones I have heard the days before: First time in the mountains, wants to continue to the hut we started out from. A bit later we meet a couple who also have the same plan and think that now they’re at least three if they catch up with the guy, which makes it a bit safer. We pass a high-alpine lake and low pines are starting to appear. <em>“Not long anymore”</em> Marcin tells me - he must see that I’m not feeling too great: By now I’m drenched. Soon we are walking through a pretty pine forest in the mist. After a final small uphill we stand in front of the massive <a href="http://www.murowaniec.e-tatry.pl">Schronisko Murowaniec refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214246510" title="Schronisko Murowaniec by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15214246510_1e268ebe57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schronisko Murowaniec" /></a></p>

<p>We head inside and it is full of people - some dressed in dry clothes, others looking just as wet &amp; miserable as we. Marcin shows me the drying wall, where I hang my wet gear after I slipped into my dry layers. Then it’s feasting time - I’m starving and munch away a soup and pancakes, a hot tea and coffee give more warmth. We sit for a while at the hut, with people coming and going. My clothes still moist but a bit drier I put them back on after almost two hours inside. Outside it’s still as misty as before, but the rain has become just the faintest drizzle. </p>

<p>Steadily we go down, soon the rain stops while the mist lingers on. We descend on paths that get broader and broader to a wide meadow. The mist mixes with the clouds and hangs above us while we walk towards Kuznice, a suburb of Zakopane and the start of a gondola up to Kasprowy Wierch.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214316898" title="Down by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15214316898_c764198aa9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Down" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214153899" title="Green under grey by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214153899_189ef3dfff_b.jpg" width="863" height="1024" alt="Green under grey" /></a></p>

<p>Here Marcin and I separate for a while - he needs to run an errand in town and hopes to catch a bus from here - we’ll meet up at the refuge later. After checking out the the small settlement with the gondola station and resisting buying some more food I hike up the broad cobblestone trail and take the first possibility into the forest.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400906185" title="Cobblestone by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15400906185_c9f9fbcb40_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cobblestone" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214397527" title="Fast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214397527_125435355d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fast" /></a></p>

<p>There’s several possibilities to visit shrines and monasteries along the trail, but I just want to reach the refuge to finally strip out of all the moist clothes, take a hot shower, dress in dry clothes and eat some good food. But the scenery is lovely on the way, and so I stop here and there to take photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400582682" title="Tranquility by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3915/15400582682_cba7c400f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tranquility" /></a></p>

<p>As the forest disappears another wide meadow comes into view, with the pretty <a href="http://schroniska.pttk.pl/kondratowa/pl">Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali refuge</a> sitting at its side. I go in and am welcomed by smiling faces in the common room. While I don’t speak a word of Polish I still am able to communicate with the wonderful owners of the refuge and she shows me the room I am staying in. I put down my pack, get rid of the wet clothes and then just am for a moment. Then the rest of the evening is just as I imagined it would be: Hot shower, dry, warm clothes, good food, early to bed. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214400107" title="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/15214400107_6ca4d4a074_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ridges-and-summits">Ridges and Summits</h2>

<p>I slept great after the day before, and as we get up at 6 in the morning the sky is blue and the sun is already shining across the summits opposite my window. Marcin and I head silently down, where the two ladies of the refuge have a breakfast waiting for us! We eat, pack, and are out of the hut by 7 and make our way to the pass.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214320388" title="Up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214320388_576117b4da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>The sky is blue with the occasional white cloud running across it and we quickly are hot from the sun and hiking. At the final spring we refill the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/platypus/?pid=81">Platypus</a> bottles with cold, clear water and then walk on. Soon we are at the pass where we drop our packs into the shrubbery and almost run up to Giewont, so light we are!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397733501" title="Further up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3866/15397733501_cb1086ff52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Further up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377897226" title="Final bit up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15377897226_c0ec8a1c1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Final bit up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214268900" title="Summit of Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3848/15214268900_d99bdd983e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit of Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400602172" title="Down from Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3853/15400602172_b9e263692a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Down from Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>It doesn’t take us long and we’re standing on the summit, underneath the massive iron cross which can be seen from Zakopane. The views are hazy but good nevertheless: Zakopane towards the north with the small villages surrounding the city towards east &amp; west, and you even can glimpse into Slovakia from here. On the way down we encounter a lonely, old chamois and then soon are back at our packs. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214337218" title="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/15214337218_b8187c6356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377902416" title="A look down at the valley by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/15377902416_901ef59a4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look down at the valley" /></a></p>

<p>The trail to Kondracka Kopa is a long, steady climb over a wide ridge. Clouds float over the ridge and surroundings summits, while alpine flowers are adding bright colours to the grey &amp; white of the sky. On my left I can see the lower hills of the Tatras and the meadow and refuge we slept in last night, and on the left zig-zags the trail down to the meadow from my original route. It does not take long and we’re on the summit of Kondracka Kopa, and now we will walk on the border of Poland and Slovakia while ticking off the next few summits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214340958" title="Along the border by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15214340958_71b3d109f2_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Along the border" /></a></p>

<p>We stay now almost all the time above 2000 m elevation while we hike in the clouds from Kondracka Kopa to Malolaczniak, Krzesanica, Ciemniak and then Twarda Kopa. Once in a while the clouds rip open and we can see the lower Tatras in Slovakia, narrow valleys, high walls, streams running towards the far off sea. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214423037" title="Towards Twarda Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3844/15214423037_2c456098d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Towards Twarda Kopa" /></a></p>

<p>From Twarda Kopa we can see Giemont in the distance, now in the clouds - but more worrisome is the helicopter which flies up to it from the valley. We don’t know what happened, but hope no one died.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400937025" title="A look back to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2943/15400937025_742b942b3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin waits for me at a large summit cairn and suggests we take the green trail down to the next refuge. It’s just around 11 and we have the whole day really in front of us still, so I agree and we take a turn from the big main path and walk on a very narrow path in a hanging meadow towards the Western Tatras.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214191449" title="Down 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3852/15214191449_334c07144a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="964" alt="Down 2" /></a></p>

<p>The views and the trail are spectacular. A narrow singletrack trail that’s demanding and exposed, but with gorgeous views on the lower-lying mountains, valleys, meadows - and in front of us, the Western Tatras. A pair of chamois give us a show as they are fighting in a couloir, but my view often just drifts to the horizon, where large mountains try to reach the sky with their summits. At a turn in the path we sit down and have a snack &amp; drink, while Marcin names the peaks and valleys and tells me anecdotes about geographical features. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377924676" title="A look back up the green trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2941/15377924676_45d34c6126_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="A look back up the green trail" /></a></p>

<p>Too soon we reach the tree line, but the path continues to be lovely. It gradually widens and Marcin tells me that it has been an old road for an iron ore mine, and I again wonder about how much work it must have been to clear the forests to create it. While we talk we reach the meadow and a group of fully loaded foreign backpackers pass us, just as amazed about the beautiful scenery around them as we are. The trail now runs next to a stream, and it does not take long until we reach the <a href="http://www.schronisko-ornak.pl">Schronisko Ornak refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397759651" title="Schronisko Ornak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397759651_65b41d3012_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Schronisko Ornak" /></a></p>

<p>It is busy outside and not even 13 o’clock. I check in with the help of Marcin and then accompany him down the valley - our hike ends here today, and I will be venturing on for the next two days on my own. The trail is now a wide dirt road and full of people, with plenty of trails going off on the right and left - trails which I will explore on my way back up to the refuge, I decide. And as Marcin tells me about the long caves up on the mountains which one can explore my afternoon suddenly looks like it will be filled with plenty of adventure!</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Climbing & Mountaineering in the Polish Tatras]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-26T10:32:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In June I visited a country which has since a long time fascinated me: <a href="http://www.poland.travel/en/">Poland</a>. Friendly people. Forests. The Baltic. Great food. And the Tatra Mountain Range. Plenty of reasons to pay a visit to this lovely country, but it was the latter one which brought me here, and which I set off to explore for a week of climbing, mountaineering and hiking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14810289940" title="Early morning at Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5565/14810289940_6369caa369_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Early morning at Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-approach">The Approach</h2>

<p>I arrived after a short flight in Krakow, got my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">backpack</a> and then started the ride to <a href="http://www.zakopane.pl/en">Zakopane</a>. It was almost 23 o’clock as I arrived at the <a href="http://www.skalny.com.pl/">Hotel Skalny</a> and then just took a quick shower before I fell tired into my bed.</p>

<p>After a delicious breakfast and the best scrambled eggs I have ever eaten I pack my hiking gear, deposit some stuff at the reception and then walk to the centre. Zakopane has a nice pedestrian shopping street and it felt like every third store was a outdoor shop, so if I’d had forgotten something there’d been plenty of chances to stock up on gear. I only needed a map which I found from one of the various stalls along the street. Then I took out some Polish Zloty from an ATM, bought a few more snacks and walked to the bus station - Zakopane is small city and I found I could walk everywhere.</p>

<p>The bus to Polana Palencia/ Morskie Oko was quickly found and at noon the bus left punctually. We drove through the centre of Zakopane, suburbs and then slowly in a wide curve to where I would start my walk in the Polish Tatras. Along the way always in view on my right: The Tatras. A compact mountain range these mountains are a natural border between Poland and Slovakia, and for many of their citizens a prime destination to visit. The infrastructure in place is very good, with plenty of huts and signs along the often very well maintained trails. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856089468" title="Road to Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3889/14856089468_4a9f8815b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Road to Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>As I arrive at the parking lot at Polana Palencia I pay the 25 Zloty for my 7 Day ticket to the National Park and then started the 9 km walk to the Morskie Oko Refuge. Around half way I switched from my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX boots</a> into my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a>, and am very happy I took them along on this trip. Nuns in white dresses pass me, a sight one not often sees on other trails.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042318042" title="Nuns by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3862/15042318042_58997ddf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="632" alt="Nuns" /></a></p>

<p>There are plenty of people on the road and regularly horse-drawn carriages go up and down. For a small fee these take you up &amp; down and shave some 6 km off the approach to the Morskie Oko Refuge. Between the spruces, far away, distant peaks come into view. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042321752" title="White Tatras by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3926/15042321752_f73f0894fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="773" alt="White Tatras" /></a></p>

<p>I come to a large oval where the horse carriages disembark their cargo and their passengers head for refreshments at the near restaurant. People with ice creams and cool drinks pass me, some looking happy, some exhausted, and I can understand why: It’s hot and humid. The last few hundred meters to the refuge I only have my eyes on the grand scenery which unfolds in front of me and I see the peaks I will be climbing the next couple of days, and many more which would make any alpinist, climber and mountaineer happy. As I round a corner my day dreams of summits are interrupted: Dozens of people mingle in front of the beautiful old wooden building, taking in the mountains and the clear lake which lays at the bottom of them. Morskie Oko. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042286112" title="Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/15042286112_f2b6ce6b1a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>I check in, drop my pack in my room and then head out for a stroll around the lake. Finally I am walking on beautiful, narrow paths along the shore. Waterfalls come rushing down to the lake. People sit at the water, take in the view. I am one of them. Bliss.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856084348" title="Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5556/14856084348_ac58545096_b.jpg" width="1024" height="401" alt="Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>Back at the refuge I spend small money on delicious local food: Soups, sausages, pancakes, a beer. I sit on the terrace, waiting for Marcin, the Mountain Guide with whom I will be spending the next few days climbing &amp; mountaineering in this cradle of Polish Alpinism. He arrives as the sun is setting in the west and quickly identifies me, even if we have never seen before =) We eat dinner together, quickly understanding each other well and making plans for the following days.</p>

<h2 id="mountaineering">Mountaineering</h2>

<p>It’s Tuesday, 6 o’clock in the morning. Our Alarms ring, we get up and take a look out of the window. The weather looks mixed, Marcin says - lets sleep another hour and then see how it looks. At 7 the weather looks similar in my opinion, but we start to pack either way. We have a light breakfast as the kitchen is still closed, so I pack a couple of extra bars and then we’re off. To Rysy. Poland’s highest summit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14994487991" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/14994487991_897226ec65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>We hike around the lake, ascent to the 2nd lake above it and see that we are not the only ones. A couple of German girls are before us. A few lone hikers further ahead. We walk around the higher lake and cross the first snow fields. A wrong step and you’d slide into the ice cold lake, and there’s evidence of some of these wrong steps in the snow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14810877719" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5571/14810877719_c1b80e274b_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Around us steep walls and high peaks. Marcin tells me about alpine and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ice-climbing/">ice climbing</a> routes and adventures, but right now my mind is set on our summer mountaineering route ahead of us. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14974591296" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3850/14974591296_103d187940_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Soon the path gets steeper. We traverse a few more snow fields, kicking steps, still crampons aren’t needed. Marcin leads the way, he has hiked this trail so often that he can not even remember the amount of times that he has summited Rysy.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14997563215" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3837/14997563215_33337048d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>He is also working for the local Mountain Rescue group, and gets at times a bit agitated when we pass solo hikers. As he chats shortly with them I can not make out anything of their conversation and when I enquire what they talked about it’s often the same answer: The person is the first time ever in their life in the mountains. Has no crampons nor ice axe along. No experience of how to traverse steep snow fields. But they want to stand on the summit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14997199162" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/14997199162_242889170f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Some turn around and listen to his advice, to wait a few more weeks till the snow is gone. Some ignore it and push on. At least until the large snow field which then is in front of us and needs to be traversed to get to the summit. Which is where I put on my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-air-tech-light-new-classic-wide-steigeisen/">Grivel Air Tech Light crampons</a> and take my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-air-tech-racing-eispickel/">Grivel Air Tech Racing ice  axe</a>. I put my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Sirocco helmet</a> on, we rope up and then front point the snow field up. We ignore the path others have made and take a direct route till the rocks. It takes us not long, maybe 15 to 20 minutes, and we are where the chains start. But without crampons and an ice axe you do one wrong step and then slide down the 50° slope for a long time. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14811061178" title="Rysy Summit Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5557/14811061178_47a7e85fd0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rysy Summit Selfie" /></a></p>

<p>Snow and ice are along the route up, it’s some serious scrambling at times, and exposed. After a while in the clouds I can make out other shapes in front of us. And then we’re at the summit. Clouds hang around us, it’s windy. I put my <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/product_info.php?cat=110&amp;products_id=373">PHD Ultra Down Jacket</a> on to stay warm, scramble to the summit marker and take a Selfie. Have a snack. Wait for the clouds to part. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14994583221" title="Rysy Summit View by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3854/14994583221_a0835797ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rysy Summit View" /></a></p>

<p>They cooperate only a bit, but what they reveal is beautiful. Views into Slovakia and the easy path up to Rysy. Deep valleys. Steep walls. Many possibilities. After a while we pack up again and start the descent. It goes fast, we make good speed and are at 15 o’clock back at the refuge. And I reward myself with them delicious pancakes!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856826070" title="Pancakes by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5567/14856826070_d14f461315_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pancakes" /></a></p>

<h2 id="climbing">Climbing</h2>

<p>It’s 4 am as our alarms ring in unison the next morning. We eat the breakfast we bought the evening before and then silently leave the hut. The lake lies silently on our left as we ascent the beautiful path which runs up on the right of the lake. We cross clear streams, the water running noisily down to the lake. And always in front of us: Mnich. The beautiful spire we’re about to climb.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856082608" title="Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3873/14856082608_23c6383a49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>We left most of our gear at the refuge, and I’m only carrying my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts.html">DMM Nuts</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/dmm-dragon-cams.html">DMM Dragons</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-demon-cam-klemmgeraet/">DMM Demons</a>, some quick draws and screw lock carabiners, harness and climbing shoes. After a mere 45 minutes we stand at the crossroad, and Marcin is a bit surprised about the speed we were able to come up here.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14855955819" title="Approach to Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5585/14855955819_2b5e7f275c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Approach to Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>We walk another 20 minutes and then are at the start. We put on harnesses, I rack up and slip into my climbing shoes. We walk a bit further till the beginning of the route and then I tie in. Marcin gives me some general advice in which direction the route goes, and off I go. Placing gear wherever I can, but it ain’t much. I’m using an old, massive bolt and wonder how many climbers have used it before me. Then I reach a good ledge and build a belay to bringing Marcin up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14855951469" title="Climbing on Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3908/14855951469_a4a7103933_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Climbing on Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>Another pitch and we are on the top of Mnich. On the way lots of scratches tell the story of alpinists climbing this route in winter with crampons. But right now the sun bathes us in its golden light and warms us up while a light breeze goes through the air. We’re sitting on the dining table big top of this 2.068 m high spire, happy about the fast ascent and the good weather. But from the south-east already some clouds are coming over the ridge line we see. I snap a few more photos, then thread the ropes through my <a href="http://bit.ly/1qp0MV4">Reverso 4</a> and start the rappel.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042304012" title="Selfie on top of Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5560/15042304012_db42d936f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Selfie on top of Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>I go first again, clip in at the large bolt, let Marcin know that he can come down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042862322" title="Rappel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15042862322_10e8af3874_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rappel" /></a></p>

<p>Twenty minutes later we are down where we racked up earlier. I slip out of the climbing shoes, put the OSOs back on, pack and then we’re off. Back to Morskie Oko.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856070018" title="Back to Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3923/14856070018_a4d994b7cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Back to Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>We arrive well in time before Check-out and I’m having a coffee and pancakes. Then it’s packing up and leaving for the Przedni Staw Polski Refuge in the neighbouring valley. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856065398" title="Easy path by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3921/14856065398_24143e8845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Easy path" /></a></p>

<p>The path goes from easy to steep in no time, and I start to wonder what classifies as <em>easy</em> for Marcin. But then he has walked these paths for years. As we start to overtake other hikers I get a sense of what he might mean.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15039600801" title="Path by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3894/15039600801_ce0db4cb87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="612" alt="Path" /></a></p>

<p>I take a last look back on Morskie Oko and the surrounding mountains, this cradle of Polish Alpinism, and know I will be back when they will be wearing their white dress. So many possibilities. So beautiful. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042865632" title="Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3870/15042865632_bb65f7e793_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Storm" /></a></p>

<p>The weather turns fast and as we reach a pass also the rain reaches us. We put on our <a href="http://bit.ly/1qeJIQv">rain jackets</a> and pants, I have another quick bite from a Müsli bar and then go on. Light showers come down on us, but my view is set on our right.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856100147" title="Hiking in the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5586/14856100147_5784882629_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hiking in the rain" /></a></p>

<p>There is Orla Perć, the most difficult <em>“trail”</em> in all of the Tatras, and we plan to hike it the next day. A magnificent ridge walk, all of it above 2.000 m, much of it on steep, exposed terrain.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856097037" title="Valley of Five Polish Lakes by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3850/14856097037_d825f77c5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Valley of Five Polish Lakes" /></a></p>

<p>After a shortcut we top out on a small summit which gives a superb view over the Valley of Five Polish Lakes, and down at the shore I already can make out the refuge. We don’t need long till we arrive at it, and are happy to be inside as the rain sets in. The large, wooden common room is full of other hikers, it’s noisy and humid, but people are happy. Good food leaves the kitchen, tasty smells wafting pass me. I can’t resist long.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15043223405" title="Przedni Staw Polski Refuge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3845/15043223405_de16d20beb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Przedni Staw Polski Refuge" /></a></p>

<p>I feast yet again on pancakes, have another cup of coffee, and then set out with Marcin for a quick stroll while the rain has stopped. We go and check out some high water falls, the lakes, walk on narrow trails, and then the rain comes. Lots of rain. We walk back to the refuge, I accelerate, feel the joy of running in my Luna Sandals in the mountains. And it feels like the rain wants to make sure it puts as much water drops down on us before we reach the warm, dry refuge. We arrive dry at the hut, but the weather forecast is not very positive. There’s rain and thunderstorms coming our way, which turn to snow and hail above 1800 m, and I wonder if we’d be able to continue the route I have planned if the weather is like this.</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
