<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Scarpa | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/scarpa/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-22T17:43:35+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-05T10:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A shoe that lets you climb almost like <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">Ueli Steck</a>: The Rebel Ultra GTX from <a href="http://www.scarpa.it">Scarpa</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15890321735" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7570/15890321735_fac69de43c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received the Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX over a year ago in November 2013. I climbed ice in Korouoma, Vaasa and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html">Abisko</a> with them and was mountaineering in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Chamonix</a> and the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">Polish Tatras</a>. All in all they have seen over four weeks of use and have been used for ice climbing, mountaineering and hiking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14604399775" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX &amp; Grivel Air-Tech crampons by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3863/14604399775_16e2e604d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX &amp; Grivel Air-Tech crampons" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>Similar to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html">Scarpa Rebel Ultra</a> the Rebel Ultra GTX is made for technical mountaineering, rock climbing and speed climbing on ice &amp; mixed terrain with snow. It can be used with a wide variety of crampons.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15888352111" title="Grivel G20 Crampons &amp; Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7528/15888352111_9a89f61bba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grivel G20 Crampons &amp; Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Scarpa Sock-Fit plus</strong> is the tongue, flex-point and collar made from a single piece of S-Tech Schoeller® elastic fabric that’s both tough and breathable</li>
  <li><strong>Re-Active AC XT sole</strong> </li>
  <li>The <strong>KCN-Tech fabric</strong> is made from Kevlar®, Cordura® and Nylon that’s woven together to form a hard-wearing, waterproof &amp; breathable fabric</li>
  <li><strong>Carbon Fibre insole</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Y-Structure</strong>: Is the microfiber calf support with injected exoskeleton plates and a mesh endoskeleton for good structure and maximum lightness</li>
  <li><strong>Vibram® Mulaz sole</strong></li>
  <li>A <strong>Gore-Tex® Duratherm lining</strong> keeps your feet dry &amp; warm</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15704309739" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX and Grivel G20 Crampons by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7473/15704309739_0e40dcf6b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX and Grivel G20 Crampons" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Again Ueli Steck has helped to develop this boot, and you can see it from the weight and the technical features. While the sock-gaiter-construction isn’t new I have not seen a lot of mountaineering boots which use it. The Y-Structure, KCN-Tech fabric and Re-Active AC XT sole stand out on this booth, as does the very good fit &amp; the light weight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15889704852" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7473/15889704852_aecafa05ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The shoe is hand made in Italy and is from a quality point of view absolutely superb. The fit is impeccable and even after four weeks of hard use the boots still look like new. Only the reflective tape in the back of the shoe shoes some wear, otherwise boot and sole still look like new.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417800278" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5078/14417800278_0203ed722c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>773 g per boot in Size 42,5 or 1.546 g for the pair. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15704318359" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7499/15704318359_c268bdd03c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>The boots are hand made in Italy. If you have worn it out you could have it resoled at your local shoemaker or you can recycle it via your local recycling scheme.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15270675413" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX - Back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7567/15270675413_b4b29d5fe3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX - Back" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p><strong>Ice &amp; Mixed climbing</strong> I did with the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/grivel-g20-crampons.html">Grivel G20 crampons</a> to the boot and it’s a fantastic combination. The G20 are 424 g per crampon which means one shoe &amp; boot are 1197 g, which is about 150 g lighter than with the Phantom Ultra boots on. This might seem trivial but feels like a big difference. What I enjoy most with the Rebel Ultra GTX is, however, the freedom of movement my feet have in them. I can pretty much fully move my feet like I could in a trailrunner, with the difference that I can connect a pair of crampons to them and climb ice with them. This is especially useful for mixed climbing, but also on more tricky ice climbs in narrow places this freedom of movement helps in better foot placements. The high sock works like a gaiter &amp; keeps water and snow out and the carbon insert makes the sole nicely rigid for climbing. In short, the climbing in them is great, I really loved the freedom of movement they gave me. </p>

<p>The last winter was super mild and I wasn’t able to test the boots in severe cold weather, but the -5°C I used them in, often while standing around on snow and ice, where no problem for them and I had warm feet and toes in the boots. When constantly moving one might be able to wear them in even colder temperatures, say to -10°C, but beyond that I reckon they will be not warm enough and it’s better to put a warmer boot on. One option that I haven’t tried is using an overboot with them in colder weather for a little bit of extra insulation, though I almost think that just using a warmer boot would be lighter - though less versatile.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15864534166" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX in Chamonix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15864534166_7c1da26c08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX in Chamonix" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Hiking</strong> in these boots is possible but really wasn’t something I liked. While they allow great freedom of movement they are lined boots, so walking from the Chalet to the Cable Car in Chamonix, a 15 minutes walk, was not enjoyable as it was +35°C in the valley, which meant I had super-sweaty feet by the time I arrived at the house. In the Tatras I hiked on two occasions with the Rebel Ultra GTX boots, once in warm weather which again was not good, and once in the pouring rain, where they were fine. I had moist feet &amp; boots after hiking four hours in the rain in them, but they were warm so it was OK. They did also dry almost completely over night. However, when I know I need to hike long distances in the summer I would always take my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals OSO</a> along for it, as I much prefer to hike in warm weather in them.</p>

<p><strong>Mountaineering</strong> in the Alps and Tatras I did most of the time with the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-air-tech-new-matic-steigeisen/?pid=81">Grivel Air Tech New-Matic</a> (453 g per crampon) but I also tried the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-xlc-390-steigeisen/">CAMP XLC 390</a> (254 g incl. optional Antibot). The weight difference between these two crampons is almost 200 g so not trivial. I did climb more with the Grivel Air Tech New-Matics and do like them a lot, and these two crampons show that you can use the Rebel Ultra with either a plastic harness or a front bale. The light weight and freedom of movement of the boot of course are great for alpine climbs and the sole is sticky on rock and allows for precise foot placements. I still would switch to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/scarpa-stix.html">climbing shoes</a> for more demanding/ technical climbs, but if it are easy routes you’re doing the Rebel Ultra GTX are more than capable. Add in good grip on snow &amp; ice and you have a very efficient mountaineering boot.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083979134" title="Scottish Mixed, Swedish style by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3529/13083979134_05c1a80c5f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="877" alt="Scottish Mixed, Swedish style" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>The <a href="">Scarpa Phantom Ultra</a> is a warmer and heavier boot which might attract the same people who’re curious about the Rebel Ultra GTX. If we look at other brands the <a href="http://bit.ly/1xAiXwT">La Sportiva Trango Cube GTX</a> and the <a href="http://bit.ly/1AhNGww">La Sportiva Batura 2.0 GTX</a> are both lightweight mountaineering boots which can be used for the same activities as the Rebel Ultra GTX.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15889670892" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7471/15889670892_4fe3a5cbc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I’m hard-pressed to come up with something that could be better in this boot. I am sure Scarpa and Ueli had their reasons to use Gore-Tex® instead of OutDry® for this shoe, personally I feel OutDry® is slightly better at keeping moisture out, dries faster and breathes better, but I think the Gore-Tex® lining does a good job in this boot. So really nothing to complain.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15890337425" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX with Grivel G20 Crampons attached by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7497/15890337425_9735b0f75f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX with Grivel G20 Crampons attached" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX is a beautiful <em>and</em> ultralight mountaineering boot that is excellent for early and late season ice &amp; mixed climbing and summer mountaineering. It keeps your feet &amp; toes warm till at least -5°C even if you’re just standing around in the snow or hang in the belay, and with the Vibram® sole it is also well suited for easy alpine climbs. I think if you look to up your ice, mixed and alpine climbing by shedding weight and going lighter the Rebel Ultra GTX is the right boot for you. I love my pair and am always happy to put them on, because I know a good day in the outdoors lies ahead of me with them on my feet.</p>

<p>Some more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157645579555695/">Rebel Ultra GTX Album</a> on Flickr.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Buy your Rebel Ultra GTX Boots at <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/tuotemerkit/scarpa">Partioaitta.fi</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx-bergschuhe/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/scarpa-rebel-pro-gtx-mountain-boots/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Backcountry.com</a> (<strong>Best Deal!</strong>), <a href="http://bit.ly/140EvFm">Campsaver.com</a>, <a href="http://camu.fi/pages/miesten_asusteet/kengat/kengat/rebellitegtxvuoristokengatpetrolorange.html">Camu.fi</a>, <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorstore.com/haku/?q=Scarpa">ScandinavianOutdoorStore.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1K6s7EI">REI.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15702812168" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7550/15702812168_3958206a3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scarpa Stix]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/scarpa-stix.html"/>
    <updated>2014-06-03T13:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/scarpa-stix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Climbing shoes. Like other <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shoes/">shoes</a> they can be a source of much discussion. The <a href="http://www.scarpa.net/en/stix.html">Scarpa Stix</a> was popular long before I started climbing, was shelved and now makes a return - and it’s easy to feel when climbing with it why this shoe was and is so popular.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14359890633" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/14359890633_7b1bf6b62b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I like Scarpa’s climbing shoes. The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/ultralight-climbing.html">Feroce</a> still gets regularly used on rock and plastic, though since I got the Stix late in 2013 it has been my climbing shoe of choice. There’s much to like about the shoe: There’s the weight of just 402 g for the pair in Size 41, the sticky rubber and the precise feel. One thing which really rules for me is that they’re quick and easy to put on and take off. With the Feroce I had three Velcro straps to open and close and the <a href="http://www.scarpa.net/en/techno-x.html">Techno X</a> uses laces. The Stix uses neither - it’s a slipper that hugs my foot for a wonderful snug fit without being constricting or uncomfortable. In case you’re wondering if it easy to lose the shoe - for example when heel or toe hooking: Nope, no chance. The Stix fits like a glove and doesn’t budge.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14153208177" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3914/14153208177_215c9320e1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14153085520" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5477/14153085520_d4f50c85cd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>

<p>Much of that superb fit can be attributed to Heinz Mariacher who designed the Stix - a name very closely connected to high-quality climbing shoes. And this shoe does pack a few high-quality features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A <em>Vibram® XS Grip 2</em> sole gives grip on rock and plastic alike</li>
  <li>The <em>X-Tension Randing</em> cradles your foot and heel to enhance your toe power</li>
  <li><em>REB - Reinforced Elastic Band</em> are the blue stripes on top of the shoe which improve the fit of the shoe</li>
  <li>Superb craftsmanship and construction</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14316563156" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5526/14316563156_2cb639dd93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>

<p>But back to fit for a moment. Once you slip into the shoe, which is easy thanks to the two large tabs at the back and the one on the instep, your large toe right away finds its spot, with the other toes falling in line. While the rubber isn’t super thin, it’s thin enough for a precise feeling of the rock underneath: With the pointy toe box you’ll find pockets without problems, while on tiny ledges you feel like you can reliably and safely weigh down on your foot and know that it will stick. If you prefer slabs (and I really do!) or the climb just has no footholds you will be glad to hear that it’s a fine shoe for smearing. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14153076640" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2913/14153076640_520b2ace9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14336362111" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3864/14336362111_e3dbfb6566_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>

<p>Which brings us to toe and heel hooking. I like Scarpa shoes because they fit me so well - it sometimes feels like they were designed for my feet - and the heel cup on the Stix is no difference here. A narrow, hugging heel cup without any dead space makes it easy to do precise heel hooks, with sticky rubber going far up the heel on all sides for extra friction. Toe hooks are similar: Because of the great fit for all my toes and the rubber on top it’s comfy &amp; easy to hook with the shoe. As it’s fast to put on &amp; off it’s easy to take the shoes off between pitches or when taking a break from a boulder problem. Even on hot, sunny days the shoe is comfortable to wear and does not create hot spots or overly sweaty feet. </p>

<p>The Stix is reasonably priced for such a high-quality shoe, and using it now since five months a couple of times a week on rock and plastic it feels like they still have a lot of climbing left in them. If you’re in the market for new climbing shoes and Scarpa’s shoes fit your feet well, I’d highly encourage you to try the Stix if you’re bouldering and sports climbing. It’s a highly comfortable shoe which is lightweight with great sensitivity and support that offers grip on narrow ledges, tiny pockets and lets you walk up steep slabs in comfort.</p>

<p>Get your pair at <a href="http://shop.boulderkeskus.com/en/shop/bouldering/climbing_shoes/">Boulderkeskus</a>, <a href="http://camu.fi/">Camu</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/scarpa-stix-kletterschuhe/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/scarpa/klettern/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/131V0vk">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1hsLtJp">Backcountry</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1kBUV7C">REI.com</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14152999898" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2905/14152999898_ed629031fa_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ueli Steck Interview]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-20T18:38:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What would you ask one of the world’s top alpinists?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com/" title="Ueli Steck, Cholastse, Khumbu Region, Nepalese Himalaya"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7354/9548496706_af9de20aec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ueli Steck, Cholastse, Khumbu Region, Nepalese Himalaya" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Thanks to <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com/">Mountain Hardwear</a> I had the chance to meet <a href="http://uelisteck.ch/">Ueli Steck</a> at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">OutDoor 2013</a>. At first I couldn’t believe my luck - I, meeting Ueli Steck, a person I admire a lot? Yes, my contact at Mountain Hardwear confirmed me, I was booked into his calendars and would be able to interview him at the fair. Wow.</p>

<p><a href="http://uelisteck.ch/" title="Ueli Steck"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7386/9545651517_144bf24f4d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ueli Steck" /></a></p>

<p>And so the quest of what to ask him ensued. I asked a few good friends before the interview about suggestions for questions - kiitos Mikko ja Sami, ありがとう Chris - and also my lovely wife contributed a question. Further questions I penned down while on the plane, and then just made some up on the spur of the moment as we were talking. Well, without further ado, here’s the interview in all its video glory (Youtube fans can watch it <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EIpU7SCrW3M&amp;feature=share&amp;list=UU927vE_KkPy6pFJboaJ9Lig">here</a>):</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/71808626?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Ueli was completely relaxed, a very easy going person to be around. My nervousness was away seconds after the introduction, and after a bit of small talk we started the interview. I decided from the start that I’d like to do the interview in German, as it’s both out mother tongue and felt more natural than two German-speakers talking in English. Adding subtitles was easy enough so that also others can understand what we talked about =) After I switched off the cameras we talked a bit more in private, and I even got a autograph card for a friend. Then the Swiss Machine and I headed back out to the Mountain Hardwear booth and chatted there a bit more, before I said my thank yous and good byes and headed to the next meeting, though truth be told I’d have gone to Switzerland with Ueli for some climbing and hiking in a hardbeat!</p>

<p>Thanks to my wonderful contact at Mountain Hardwear, Ueli Steck and <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">Benjamin</a> who loaned me his GorillaPod. It was a meeting I won’t forget for a long time =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9508186573/" title="Ueli Steck &amp; me =) by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3812/9508186573_b170e2fd8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Ueli Steck &amp; me =)" /></a></p>

<p>Photos 1 &amp; 2 are © <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com/">Mountain Hardwear</a>/ <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/">Jonathan Griffith</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
