<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mattresses | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mattresses/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-30T10:28:50+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-14T12:37:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/ie/therm-a-rest/mattresses/fast-and-light/neoair-xlite/product">Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite</a> lets you sleep comfortable &amp; warm all night long and won’t slow you down or take up a lot of space in your pack while you’re hiking. After over a year of use on different trails the verdict is out: This is one of the best 3-Season sleeping pads on the market. <em>Read all about it in my in-depth review.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376802441" title="Bed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5515/14376802441_7b2115dea3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bed" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I’m sleeping on the NeoAir XLite Regular since August 2013 when it’s the season. It was along in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho-Kekkonen National Park</a>, on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/koli-national-park.html">2013 UL Summit</a> and every hike of 2014. I slept over 50 nights on this mat and it still works superb.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14915727601" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3883/14915727601_8491b07928_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>Like the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">NeoAir XTherm</a> the XLite’s function is to provide you with a warm and comfortable bed at camp while being small &amp; light when being carried in your pack. The mattress is insulating you towards the ground so you can sleep warm.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732150280" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, inflated by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5552/14732150280_caed27a91e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, inflated" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>My Regular length XLite has the following specs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>R-Value 3,2</li>
  <li>183 cm long, 6 cm thick, tapers from 49 cm to 38 cm (that’s the real inflated width)</li>
  <li>Reflective ThermaCapture™ technology traps radiant heat </li>
  <li>Triangular Core Matrix™ construction minimizes convective heat loss</li>
  <li>Made in Ireland</li>
</ul>

<p>The XLite is available in three sizes (S = 119 cm long, 230 g/ Regular = 183 cm long, 353 g/ L = 196 cm, 460 g) and a Women’s Version (168 cm, 340 g) which has a higher R-Value.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732146959" title="Sleep &amp; shelter system by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/14732146959_1ed65c71de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sleep &amp; shelter system" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The Reflective ThermaCapture™ technology is an innovation. It are reflective layers inside the NeoAir mattress that reflect radiant heat back to your body, and so amplifys the warmth without the bulk, weight or durability issues of down and synthetic fills. Also the Triangular Core Matrix™ construction is an innovation, this construction combines two layers of triangular baffles to create over a hundred insulating cells in the mattress and so slowing down convective heat loss as well as delivering very good stability for maximum comfort.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918803885" title="75% of the sleep system deployed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5563/14918803885_16ef248408_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="75% of the sleep system deployed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After over 50 nights on thee mattress it still works and looks great and shows no signs of weaknesses. It’s a durable mat and can take the abuse of what you encounter when you’re backpacking.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Regular length XLite is 353 g.</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>The XLite is made in Ireland of oil based materials and has a coating on the inside, so shouldn’t be thrown in the garbage like ordinary rubbish. You could try to either recycle it via your local outdoor shop or inquire from Therm-A-Rest how to recycle the mat at the end of its life cycle.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918814195" title="Valve by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3906/14918814195_4dd814de57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Valve" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>15 large breaths, that’s how often a non-smoker will need to inhale and exhale to make out of the small, rolled up package a fully inflated, comfy mat. If you like it softer, maybe 13 or 14 are enough, and if you have a small lunge volume it might be more, but 15 breaths is what it takes me to inflate this mat. If that seems too much for you then Therm-A-Rest has a a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-neoair-mini-pump/">Mini Pump</a> for you which will add 65 g to your pack or an <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-neo-air-pumpsack/">Pump Sack</a> that adds 77 g to your packed weight and make life on the trail slightly easier. Of course then you just also could take a self-inflating mat or a closed cell foam mat and be done and never inflate a mattress again. </p>

<p>But those mats are quite a bit larger in packed size and often also quite a bit more heavy. So with a mat like the XLite you get a light mat that packs up small - about 1 l rolled up is what it will take of the space in you pack. Speaking of the rolled up mat, deflating is just as easy as inflating. Open the valve and it will largely empty itself, but to speed things up you can kneel on it. When it’s fully deflated I lay it out flat, fold it twice into the middle and then roll it up, that way I get an approximately 23 cm long package that’s about 9 cm in diameter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732244997" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, folded by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3904/14732244997_e1fbff813e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, folded" /></a></p>

<p>One of the reasons you will consider the XLite is Comfort. At six cm thick the XLite is fully inflated a very comfy mattress, and if you like more cushy/ soft mattresses just open the valve to adjust it to your liking. It also makes camping fairly flexible as you’re less dependent on 100% even surfaces - if theres a root protruding from the spot you want to camp the XLite is able to comfortably lay on top of it and you’d have never known. Similarly it’s great for camping on the rocks, for example if you want to bivy on a summit. While it’s a durable mat I do carry a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/exped-doublemat-evazote-sleeping-mat.html">very thin Exped CCF pad</a> along which I lay underneath the XLite to protect it a bit from sharp, small rocks or stuff I might have not seen. It’s also a good back-up and adds a bit of extra warmth.</p>

<p>Warmth is one of the other things where the XLite shines. It’s a warm mattress - I had it down to around -5°C and was toasty on it and never knew I’m on a 3-Season pad. Which means you’re good to go till late autumn with this mattress, and if you like to use a CCF pad in winter as a back-up either way you even might be able to use the XLite in mild winters. For serious cold winters I’d still use the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">XTherm</a>, though.</p>

<p>Finally, the XLite fits well into my different bivys. While in SUL bivys which are not very high you might run into trouble, my tyvek, Pertx and Cuben bivys are all wide and spacious enough to accommodate this inflated mattress. If you use a thin mattress right now and your bivy is a bit tight already it might be useful to get a more spacious bivy at the same time that you’re getting the XLite. If you don’t use a bivy this obviously will be of no concern =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13982574636" title="Good night! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7203/13982574636_c7f96370bb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Good night!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a few mattresses that fill the same niche as the XLite: There’s the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/exped-synmat-7-isolierte-isomatte-kunstfaserfuellung/">Exped SynMat 7</a>, the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-light-pump-mat-ul-isomatte/">Mammut Light Pump Mat UL</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/vaude-norrsken-primaloft-isomatte/">Vaude Norrsken</a> and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/trangoworld-micro-air-isomatte/">Trangoworld Micro Air</a> which all have a similar pack size and warmth rating but most of these are heavier. </p>

<h2 id="what-could-be-better">What Could Be Better</h2>

<p>I have no complains about the XLite. Sure, at some point in time it’d be nice to get the same warmth &amp; comfort for less weight, but for now I’m happy. Those that always thought the XLite and XTherm were to loud, Therm-A-Rest has heard you and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html">from 2015 on the mats will be more silent</a>. And those that would like to not have to inflate their XLite but still want a 5 cm thick pad should get the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html">EvoLite</a> in 2015.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>After many years of backpacking and sleeping outside it’s pretty straight forward for me when I pack the sleep system: Spring till autumn it’s the XLite, winter and high-altitude it’s the XTherm. The XLite packs small in my pack when on the trail and is lightweight with just 353 g for the 183 cm long mattress. After 15 puffs of air at camp I have a comfy mat to chill and sleep on that keeps me well insulated against the ground. It makes finding a 100% perfect camp spots less of a hassle as I can lay comfortable above roots and round rocks on this 6 cm thick pad. Most important, I get a great nights sleep on it every time and am ready for another good day on the trail, where the small packed mattress again disappears in my pack. If you want comfort &amp; warmth paired with a light weight and small pack size, look no further than the Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Buy your XLite at <a href="http://bit.ly/Vpj8J3">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-neo-air-xlite-small-isomatte/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite-isomatte/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1bcnz0i">Campsaver</a>, <a href="http://tinyurl.com/pacvgwc">Cotswold</a>, <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite-200118/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Globetrotter</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/VmUMQt">REI</a> or the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Isomatten/Therm-A-Rest-NeoAir-XLite::458.html?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732238277" title="Day-Dreaming by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3867/14732238277_8e75eeaf30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Day-Dreaming" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XTherm]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-11T16:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While the UL scene rejoiced when the original NeoAir came on the market, I never have been a big fan of it. It was just too cold for me, even on a warm summer night with a CCF pad underneath it. I quickly got rid of it, and have been using CCF pads and self-inflatable mats pretty much exclusively since then. But then Therm-A-Rest presented us the <a href="http://cascadedesigns.com/therm-a-rest/mattresses/fast-and-light/neoair-xtherm/product">NeoAir XTherm</a>, with a R-Value of 5,7, and they got my attention for that. Now that I have been using this mat since over a year, it is time to take a good, close look at it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8594192687/" title="Inflated top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8594192687_811819c147_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Inflated top" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>
<p>The NeoAir XTherm arrived in 2011 and I have been using it a lot since, even on trips where I was wondering if it is smart to take such a mat with me. The mat has been holding up very well and shows no signs of usage after over 30 nights on it. It’s stored at the moment deflated &amp; rolled up to safe space, though once I’m moving I will store it unrolled &amp; inflated as it is recommended.</p>

<p>It got used on the UL Summit in Slovenia, Bikepacking, Autumn hikes on the Pirkan Taival and winter hikes in the Helvetinjärvi National Park, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html">Korouoma</a> and overnighters. </p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>
<p>The XTherm’s function is to provide you with a warm and comfortable bed at camp while being small &amp; light when being carried in your pack. In both aspects, camp-use and during hiking, it performs superbly. It has a small enough pack size, inflates fully with 15 to 20 puffs, and is warm and very comfortable in use. </p>

<p>What this means in practice is that when you’re hiking the XTherm won’t take a lot of space in your pack, and when you arrive at camp it isn’t too strenuous to inflate the mat - you could even use the pack sack as an inflation bag if you’re out of breath. The mat is a superb padding on hard and uneven undergrounds, and insulates you against the cold that creeps up from the ground, even in the depth of winter. It works very well together with <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/11/quilt-101.html">quilts</a> but sleeping bag users will like it just as much.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8594211097/" title="Size by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8231/8594211097_96530624a7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Size" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<p>The XTherm has horizontal, over 6 cm thick baffles and is tapered at the ends, and has a friction surface which stops you from sliding around. The pack sack functions as a inflation bag though I never have bothered with that, although the idea is that it helps to avoid getting moisture inside which could possibly freeze and damage the internals of the mat. That hasn’t been a problem for me yet, even if the XTherm has been outdoors a lot in cold temperatures. It comes with a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-fast-and-lite-repair-kit.html">repair kit</a>, too.</p>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>
<p>The XTherm comes in four lengths, and I decided to get the Regular length. I have had a Short NeoAir in the past which was not comfortable for me, as the drop-off was at my knees. I tried putting thicker equipment under my legs to make the height difference bearable, but in the end wasn’t happy with the solutions. The Regular length XTherm, 183 cm long, is superb for me (175 cm tall, 63 kg light). I can sleep comfortably on the mat, be it on my side, back or stomach. I also never compress the mat enough to touch the ground with my hips or elbows when on the mat, which sometimes can happen for side sleepers on thin mats. Its tapered at the ends, but is still wide enough so that head and feet stay on the mat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8638950503/" title="Sleeping by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8638950503_b06042fdd4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sleeping" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>
<p>The <em>Reflective Barriers</em> used in the XTherm are a new technology which Therm-A-Rest is using in this mattress, which help to save weight and bulk. Four layers of this reflective material recycle body heat and create air pockets that reduce convective heat loss. Additionally Therm-A-Rest developed a <em>Triangular Core Matrix</em> construction which provides stability and comfort. In practice these have been working for me indeed as claimed, the pad is very warm and stable to sleep on, be it on my back, side or belly.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595308334/" title="Deflated by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8509/8595308334_f7cc248b58_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Deflated" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>
<p>I need to say that thus far (30+ nights) I am amazed about the quality of the XTherm. I know that e.g. <a href="http://tramplite.com/">Colin</a> has had less luck with other NeoAir models, which have developed a “pillow” after 60 nights on them, but so far I have not had any problems with my XTherm. It’s also surprisingly durable, in that it has been laid down on rough mountain floors and hard, ice covered snow &amp; ice and has withstood that without problems. If it doesn’t develop the <em>pillow</em> then I am sure that I will get many years use out of this mat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8594196409/" title="Inflated top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8369/8594196409_2f0fc1af78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Inflated top" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>
<p>My XTherm in Regular length (183 cm long) is 427 gram. It is a lot warmer than my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-ridgerest-solar-matte.html">RidgeRest Solar</a>, packs A LOT smaller and is lighter, too. Overall I rate this a the go-to mat for weight conscious backpackers who sleep outdoors in real cold weather.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8639086145/" title="XTherm vs. RidgeRest Solar by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8532/8639086145_0480bcbb35_b.jpg" width="1024" height="574" alt="XTherm vs. RidgeRest Solar" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>
<p>It’s made of oil based materials and has a coating on the inside, so shouldn’t be thrown in the garbage like ordinary rubbish. You could try to either recycle it via your local outdoor shop or inquire from Therm-A-Rest how to recycle the mat at the end of its life cycle.</p>

<p><em>More coming later.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595294416/" title="Inflated top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8101/8595294416_f1f611b950_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Inflated top" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>
<p>I have used the XTherm pretty much always with a CCF pad, mostly the superb <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/exped-doublemat-evazote-sleeping-mat.html">Exped Doublemat</a> which I have cut in half for 3 Season use, or a <a href="http://www.multimat.uk.com/store/products/summit-xl">Multimat Summit XL</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-ridgerest-solar-matte.html">RidgeRest Solar</a> in winter. In winter it’s to get a little bit of extra warmth, in summer to protect the pad slightly better from sharp rocks or sticks. Inflating it is easy even after a 30 km day, and it takes me less than 2 minutes to get the mat fully inflated. Before I go to sleep I add a few extra puffs - I like to sleep on a hard mat - and that is it. </p>

<p>In the mornings the deflating and rolling up is similarly easy, I fold the pad a couple of times and then knee on it, and then just roll it up. I don’t use the pack sack (heavy!) and just pack it fairly in the middle of my pack with the shelter and bivy. The noise the internal baffles make is not a problem for me, though if you camp with other people in the same shelter and move a lot in your sleep, it might be something that could bother. It will not impact your sleep in any way, though. </p>

<p>I have slept down to -12°C only with the NeoAir XTherm on the ground and down to -17°C with a CCF pad underneath it. In both setups I was comfortably warm and didn’t feel any cold coming up from the ground through the mat. I feel confident to take the mat out in up to -30°C nights together with a CCF pad in winter.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7783259222/" title="Open Doors by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8307/7783259222_fbc46ab400_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Open Doors" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re now under the impression that the XTherm is only a winter mat, let me correct that view right away! While it certainly shines in cold temperatures, it is also great in summer. So have I used it for example for one week on the Ultralight Summit in Slovenia last year, where we were in August. During the day we had temps of over 35°C but at night high up in the mountains it quickly got cold once the sun set, and during the night temperatures were as low as 5°C. In these situations I was happy that I had the XTherm with me, as the rocks on the high plateau were not warm! Also here in the north, especially above the Arctic Circle, temperatures in the summer can sometimes drop down to 0°C and in those situations a mat like the XTherm comes in very useful, guaranteeing you a comfortable night.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>
<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/exped-synmat-ul-7-isolierte-isomatte-kunstfaserfuellung/">Exped Synmat UL 7</a> and the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/exped-downmat-7-daunengefuellte-isomatte/">Exped Downmat 7</a> both are similarly warm, yet sadly Exped’s quality control lets quite a few faulty mats end up in customer hands so reviews are mixed. The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-softskin-mat-aufblasbare-isomatte/">Mammut SoftSkin Mat</a> too has a good R-Value, as does the <a href="https://www.bigagnes.com/Products/Detail/Pad/qcoresl">Big Agnes Q-Core SL</a>. </p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>
<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/sleeping-mats-hyalite-peak-elite-ac-and-thermarest-neoair-xtherm">Michael likes the XTherm</a> and compares it to two other mats. <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Sleeping-Pad-Reviews/Therm-a-Rest-NeoAir-Xtherm">Max from the Outdoor Gear Lab</a> gives the XTherm five stars. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595275160/" title="At Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8365/8595275160_8c6acc852b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="At Camp" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>
<p>Quite easily the best all-season mat I have slept on to date. Lightweight, small pack size, warm and comfortable, the NeoAir XTherm ticks a lot of boxes that are important for backpackers that value a good nights sleep while not carrying heavy, bulky mats. If I know that I want a good nights sleep then I bring along the XTherm, which lately has been pretty much always. </p>

<p>If you only want one inflatable mattress for all your trips, be they in winter or summer, for an overnighter in the nearby forest or for an high alpine adventure in the Alps, then the NeoAir XTherm is your mat of choice.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633104057740/">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-neoair-xtherm">Where to buy the NeoAir XTherm</h2>
<p>Buy it at <a href="http://bit.ly/128XiGA">Backcountry</a> $190 | <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm-isomatte/">Bergfreunde</a> 140€ | <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-neo-air-xtherm-isomatte.html">Bergzeit</a> 170€ | <a href="http://bit.ly/TVCVNY">CampSaver</a> $190 | <a href="http://bit.ly/128YMAG">REI</a> $180 </p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>
<ul>
  <li>More on Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Disclaimer</em><br />
Therm-A-Rest provided me the XTherm free of charge for testing, and paid me 1 million € to review it.*</p>

<p><sub><sup><sub><sup>* One of these statements is not true.</sup></sub></sup></sub></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595282884/" title="At Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8102/8595282884_af20f61bcf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="At Camp" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
