<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OutDoor Fair 2015 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2015/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-12T10:33:31+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2015 - II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T23:29:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More new kit for trailrunners, lightweight backpackers, mountaineers, climbers and outdoor lovers from the world’s biggest outdoor fair!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686321301/in/dateposted/" title="Always bring the Houdini"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5715/20686321301_c0847978f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Always bring the Houdini" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>These posts do take a lot of time to write so I am happy if you’d <a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">get me a coffee</a> as a payment for my work =)</em></p>

<h2 id="marmot">Marmot</h2>

<p><a href="http://marmot.de">Marmot</a> had a wide range of new kit on the show so lets dive straight in. The Red Star Jacket for Men/ Starfire Jacket for Women is the first 3-layer jacket to incorporate the exceptionally breathable, very robust and waterproof NanoPro™ membrane. It’s very stretchy, 100% seam taped, has a fully adjustable hood with a laminated brim to keep your sight dry, and will weigh 425 g. The Red Star Pants has 3/4 Length Water-Resistant Side Zippers and will tip the scales at 470 g and should make for a breathable &amp; waterproof combo which keeps you dry in heavy rain.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679565205/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Star Jacket"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5620/20679565205_85257c0dea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Star Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056996144/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot NanoPro 3-layer"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/608/20056996144_ce232512a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot NanoPro 3-layer" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Graviton 38 backpack weighs 1.080 g and comes with a ventilated suspension (carrying) system. The series - there’s four different sizes in total - features a single-piece aluminum uniframe which should have good load stability and features soft pads in the shoulder and waist areas for improved carry comfort. Compression
straps on the sides and base, trekking pole attachment and several easily accessible pockets round out this pack. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491534738/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Graviton 38 backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/638/20491534738_b95bf1624d_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Marmot Graviton 38 backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Helium Sleeping Bag tips the scales at 935 g in Regular length and is filled with 560 g of hydrophobic, RDS certified down, which should keep you toasty till around -9°C Comfort. Really cool was the “Fold-Down” second zipper on the right which provides more ventilation and easy access. The Full Length Locking YKK Two Way Zipper has a Zip-Guard Slider which prevents the lining from getting stuck in the zipper, which solves a common problem in (sleeping bag) zippers. Overall a nice looking sleeping bag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653304776/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Helium &amp; Ion Sleeping Bags"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5715/20653304776_de7ae465b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Helium &amp; Ion Sleeping Bags" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491568270/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Helium Sleeping Bag Zipper"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/715/20491568270_b1baf24d69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Helium Sleeping Bag Zipper" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Vapor FC 2P is a 2.520 g 2 Person tent with a size of 107 x 137 x 224 cm and a spacey vestibule. The doors got bigger for easy access, a lamp shade pocket in the roof lets you read at night without a headlamp on and the color-coded pole clip system makes it easy to pitch. It looked like a nice 3-season tent for couples, but there’s also 3 and 4 Person tents available of the Vapor for families and small groups.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056994454/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Vapor FC 2P Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/724/20056994454_177aab81d7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Vapor FC 2P Tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the climbing garments corner there were lots of clothes for your favourite pastime. Cool designs in combination with functional &amp; stretchy materials make for sweet shirts, pants and hoodies to hit the crag in. Add in a new climbing pack called the <em>Gear Hauler</em> and you have all you need for a fun day climbing. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491536718/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/730/20491536718_690fde99ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="scarpa">Scarpa</h2>

<p>Wow, I really was surprised by all the new shoes from <a href="http://scarpa.it">Scarpa</a>! Lots of trailrunning/ ultralight backpacking shoes from them, and I found they actually looked good! The Proton is a shoe made for heel strikers which gives you good support on long runs. Will weigh around 360 g per shoe and has a Vibram® Genesis sole and lots of cushioning in the heel.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491564180/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Proton"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5726/20491564180_8969bb3378_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Proton" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Atom certainly was the most interesting shoe in the line, and at 260 g per shoe it was also rather light. Colour &amp; sole-wise it gets big thumbs up from me, the Vibram®  Genetic Lite reminds me of a trailrunning shoe I have used a lot. Scarpa says it <em>“Created for athletes with a perfect running style who weigh less than 70 kg, they will find this shoe is very reactive and it suits the athlete who favors a running style based on the toes”</em>. Well, if that doesn’t sound like a great shoe for me, I don’t know! Add in a breathable mesh upper and you will have a shoe which could become very popular.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653292466/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Atom"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5634/20653292466_a275b465eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Atom" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Neutron weighs 295 g and has a Vibram® Genetic sole that should give good grip on any kind of wet or dry terrain. It’s available as a fabric version, a special Women’s version and for Winter runs even as a Gore-Tex lined shoe. Still light enough for UL backpackers, but with more support and cushioning. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057014404/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Neutron"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5740/20057014404_560df31ac3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Neutron" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Scarpa Mountaineering boots aka the Phantom Line is awesome. It’s designed by Ueli Steck which means this are the boots that Ueli designed and uses himself - be it climbing Annapurna or on his 82 Summits project. There’s three new boots and they all feature the new zipper which runs around the shoe. It looks cool but I am a bit wondering how practical it will be in use when you need to pull a zipper behind your leg, and of course such a long zipper also adds weight and complexity aka a place where it can fail. Scarpa writes that the <em>“innovative “orange peel-like” closure with Flexseal® Waterproof zip avoids any inconvenience to the ankle movements”</em> so I guess it will have a benefit. Anyway. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20058614443/in/photostream/" title="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/611/20058614443_2482540e7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There’s three new boots - the Phantom 8000, the Phantom 6000 and the Phantom Tech. All have a gaiter made from KCN-Tech Fabric, S-Tech Fabric and an Outdry® membrane , which I like as I find OutDry better working as Gore-Tex. All three boots also have a Carbon insole and a Vibram® Gravity sole. The Phantom Tech is the lightest boot at 830 g per boot and also the least warm, but as it has a Primaloft® insulation layer I have no doubt that it will be a great alpine climbing/ ice climbing boot (in the photo underneath is the Tech on the right and the 6000 on the left).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679570315/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5827/20679570315_29ac835ee9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Phantom 6000 and 8000 come with a removable liner boot that has a Primaloft® lining and a 4 mm thermo-insulating EVA sole. The 6000 is made for peaks up to 6000 m and weighs 995 g per boot while the Phantom 8000 is made for the highest summits of the globe and weighs 1310 g per boot. The hole line looked sweet, curious to try out the Phantom 6000 in the Karakoram in the future!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20670328742/in/photostream/" title="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5687/20670328742_fe268302e1_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s Drago, the new climbing shoe. Made for bouldering, hard sports climbing indoors and outdoors the Drago is close in design to the Furia but has a Velcro strap for a good fit. The rubber on the upper goes really high for sticky toe hooks. The shoe is soft and gives you good control on small ledges and difficult placements.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057007954/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Drago Climbing Shoe"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/676/20057007954_6eb66f1fcb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Drago Climbing Shoe" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="haglfs">Haglöfs</h2>

<p>Haglöfs is a big company with many lines so it’s always a bit difficult to grasp all the new gear, especially as there’s so much new interesting kit. The Roc Helios 25 backpack is an OutDoor Award winner that’s made from XPac and has a back opening to access your gear. It’s made for mountaineering so has all the details you want from a rucksack for the mountains, but should do well when abused for backpacking, too. No info on weight, sorry.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461137721/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Roc Helios 25 backpack"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3814/20461137721_acafbdf705_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs Roc Helios 25 backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Herakles Jacket is 455 g in Size L and made from a 3-layer Gore-tex with the new CKnit backer. It’s a mountain jacket with a helmet-compatible hood, an articulated design for freedom of movement and high pockets. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20268246879/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Herakles Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/415/20268246879_e39a6fb420_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haglöfs Herakles Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Gram Pulse trailrunners - the Women’s model is in the photo - will weigh 215 g for a Women’s shoe and 260 g for a Men’s shoe. The sole pattern looks familiar and thus should be good, and on top there’s non-absorbing fabrics which should maintain a low weight in wet conditions. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461140421/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Gram Pulse Shoe"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/458/20461140421_b578c49369_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haglöfs Gram Pulse Shoe" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s another backpack, the LIM Strive Backpack. Can’t give the weight on this pack either, but it felt light for being a 50 l pack. The front zipper makes for easy access to gear, the lid can be removed for more weight saving. The hipbelt pockets were pretty big, made from a stretchy mesh and looked great, and the material is bluesign certified 100HT Robic™, which also some cottages use for making their packs. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20454898805/in/dateposted/" title="LIM Strive Backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/439/20454898805_f9e2a1f04c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="LIM Strive Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="vaude">Vaude</h2>

<p>I’m pretty psyched about the biggest news for backpackers from <a href="http://www.vaude.com">Vaude</a>, and that’s the Alpstein 450 DWN quilt. Why? Well, I’m pretty proud that <a href="http://blog.fastpacking.de">Carsten</a> and me helped during the development of this quilt. We both have tested early prototypes and gave the designer a lot of feedback on what we liked and what could be better. I think I’ll give some insights on this quilt further down the road in a separate post, but the cool things are: 450 g of RDS certified down in the Alpstein 450 DWN (200 g in the Alpstein 200 DWN), total weight 750 g (550 g), and a unique attachment system which allows you to attach the quilt pretty easily to any sleeping pad. Oh, and it’s pretty cool that the quilt won a OutDoor Gold OutDoor Award, too! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20516026200/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Alpstein 450 DWN quilt"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/723/20516026200_795ffbd627_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Alpstein 450 DWN quilt" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then there’s the Citus 24 LW Backpack, a 500 g 24 l Volume pack that’s made from a siliconizied 40 D Rip-Stop. Special is that is has a Aeroflex back panel which should keep you dries aka less sweaty on your summer hikes. It has a zippered lid pocket, mesh side stretch pockets and a compression system that also lets you carry wet gear on the front. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20516112978/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Citus 24 LW Backpack"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5643/20516112978_a85234b05f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Citus 24 LW Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Pro Windshell Jacket weighs less than 80 g and is a cycling windjacket which packs tiny when not needed. Reflective details, long back, stretch inserts on the sides for freedom of movement and breathability and a PFC-free Eco Finish water repellency treatment that makes it water-resistant, its a wind jacket you can wear cycling or when out on the hills.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20710926061/in/dateposted/" title="Pro Windshell LW"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5652/20710926061_7afc5fae6a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Pro Windshell LW" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And as we’re already talking cycling the Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes are environmentally friendly made flat pedal cycling shoes. The Moab Low AM and Moab Mid STX AM fulfil the strict Vaude <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQgt80pO0YM">Green Shape</a> criteria and still will perform great on the trail. A great move to get a difficult product likes shoes fulfil this standard, and I hope we’ll see more of this in the future, also from other manufacturers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20694848822/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/762/20694848822_079c2a46ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="norrna">Norrøna</h2>

<p>The news from <a href="https://www.norrona.com">Norrøna</a> included the bitihorn alpha60 Jacket which is a 250 g insulation piece that’s filled with Polartec Alpha. The shell is wind and water resistant so it also can be worn on its own, but it should be a good midlayer, too. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261529486/in/dateposted/" title="Norrøna bitihorn alpha60 Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/395/20261529486_55568dd61a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna bitihorn alpha60 Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now available is the fjørå line for Women (Men’s have been available for a while already). These are really great for riding on single track trails or shredding down hills, made from good materials and give good wind protection but also keep you cool on the uphill.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101181829/in/dateposted/" title="Norrøna fjøra line"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/456/20101181829_5747a8e82c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna fjøra line" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Lifestyle lines were a big trend at the OutDoor, and it’s understandable. Norrøna’s 29 line is very stylish and a mix of technical and functional fabrics. There’s a cool limited edition Denim Anorak which will make you stand out at the camp fire or in the office. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261544666/in/photostream/" title="Norrøna Lifestyle 29 Line"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3678/20261544666_2f1e05181a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna Lifestyle 29 Line" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="montane">Montane</h2>

<p>I only had a brief visit at <a href="Montane">Montane</a> so can’t give all the details on the lightweight new kit from them - which is a shame, as they had a very cool looking cuben fibre pack on display! But what I saw and tried were the new Ultra Tour packs, which did remind me design-wise from a now bankrupt lightweight company from the USA. Which isn’t bad, as that pack has been super popular. The Ultra Tour is available as a 22, 40 and 55 l volume pack, which will weigh 540 g, 725 g and 840 g respectively. There’s a roll-top closure, large stretch side pockets, a Comfort Vent Back Pad and Contact Air Mesh shoulder straps which will keep you cooler on long hikes with heavy loads, hip pockets and a front pocket/ compartment. These looked very good and if priced right (= affordable) these could become great entry-level UL packs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679558375/in/dateposted/" title="Montane Ultra Tour backpacks"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/693/20679558375_815277e522_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Ultra Tour backpacks" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Minimus 777 Pull-On is a 134 g hardshell that packs tiny and should be very breathable. The construction is of a very high quality that’s made to last, and in orange it also looks really sweet. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20670323222/in/dateposted/" title="Montane Minimus 777 Pull-On"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5693/20670323222_a126f9bded_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Minimus 777 Pull-On" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As I said, a shame I didn’t snap photos of the other new kit, as with the <em>ultra alpine 38 + 5</em> (a 547 g alpine climbing pack with a sweet design), the <em>hyper tour 38</em> (a 639 g cuben fibre hiking pack that can be stripped to 478 g) and several great garments there would have been plenty of interesting kit for lightweight backpackers, Alpinists and trailrunners!</p>

<h2 id="nikwax">Nikwax</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.nikwax.com/en-gb/">Nikwax</a> Down Wash Direct is an aftercare product which lets you clean and improve the performance of regular and hydrophobic garments/ quilts/ sleeping bags alike. What’s really cool is not just that Down Wash Direct is environmentally friendly but that it makes your down kit hydrophobic, even if it hasn’t been hydrophobic down to begin with. That’s a great way to make your favourite down jacket hydrophobic - both the down and the DWR of the shell. An exciting product that I’m curious to test with some of my down kit and see how it improves performance.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056991504/in/dateposted/" title="Nikwax Down Wash Direct"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5689/20056991504_3456b34bee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nikwax Down Wash Direct" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="omm">OMM</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.theomm.com">OMM</a> makes sweet kit that makes ultralight backpackers and fell runners alike happy. The Phantom 25CL was the highlight, a great pack that would be ideal for a fast &amp; light weekend in the hills or an OMM event. It has a integrated sleeping mat and a carbon suspension system. The back length can be adjusted via an easy system, the stretchy side pockets were super easy to reach and the compression system could be adjusted with the pack on. Tipping the scales at just 400 g the Phantom 25CL is a great pack that works a charm if you go fast.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686315741/in/photostream/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/718/20686315741_c65a6a6a53_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686306421/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5670/20686306421_5c125f020c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491570540/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/750/20491570540_d77bb3e1f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Ultra 8 is a new pack that will be super affordable and great for training or a SUL overnighter. Mesh side pockets, a good carrying system and a 8 l main compartment let you carry all you need for a day out running in the hills.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057013414/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Ultra 8"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/757/20057013414_c51cbdd786_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Ultra 8" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you need some more space on your existing pack, take a look at the Compressor Pod. It can work as a UL pack on its own, but it’s designed to be attached to a OMM pack or another pack and gives you more protected carrying space. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653312566/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Compressor Pod"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/629/20653312566_f41a8c4c0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Compressor Pod" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, the Grid Longsleeve is simply a functional &amp; good-looking longsleeve for runners &amp; outdoor enthusiasts alike. The cool contour lines on the sleeves are a nice detail.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057005354/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Grid Longsleeve"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/663/20057005354_d9447135b5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="OMM Grid Longsleeve" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="jetboil">Jetboil</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jetboil.com">Jetboil</a> had two interesting news on the show: A Basecamp stove and the MicroMo - the successor to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti.html">Sol Ti</a>. Lets take a look at the MicroMo first. It weighs 340 g all in and the pot has a volume of 0,8 l. You can store a 100 g cartridge inside the pot with the burner unit and on the outside a cozy lets you handle the pot with its hot content. Burning time for half a litre is supposed to be 2:15 min and it should be less ideal for cooking/ simmering than the MiniMo. The pot et al. is now made from Aluminium, so there should hopefully not be any melting fluxrings anymore.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653299766/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Micro Mo"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5787/20653299766_ffd9bf075d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Micro Mo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Genesis on the other hand is found at the opposite side of the spectrum of the MicroMo and weighs 4.100 g. I don’t know how light that is for a basecamp stove, but it sounds pretty good. A 5 l pot lets you cook for the team and the pan is ideal for bacon and eggs in the morning. The 2-Burner stove fits inside of the pot with the pan on top. I can see this coming in handy for car camping, glamping and canoe trips, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686316111/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/626/20686316111_3a0afa0678_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686313981/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/772/20686313981_f49269f40a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679567065/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/588/20679567065_a3e3181c92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="stay-tuned-for-the-next-part-coming-soon">Stay tuned for the next part, Coming Soon™!</h2>

<p>You can see a lot more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157656356655229">OutDoor 2015 Flickr Album</a>. And if you liked this follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for more gear &amp; outdoor updates.</p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2015 - I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-10T23:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What new gear is coming in 2016 for lightweight backpackers, mountaineers, climbers and outdoor lovers? </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665148874/in/dateposted/" title="OutDoor Award Showcase"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/559/19665148874_502f67dd93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OutDoor Award Showcase" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-research">Outdoor Research</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com">Outdoor Research</a>’s big news was that they now have a new investor on board, which allows them to invest more into R&amp;D and tap into the knowledge of the new partner. The first result is the <strong>Precipice Jacket™</strong> which uses the new AscentShell™ fabric technology, a 308 g (Size L) hardshell that’s made of 100% nylon 20D mechanical stretch ripstop face with a 100% Polyester 12D backer. The jacket is fully seam-taped and has a laminated construction with Dynamic Reach™ Underarm Panels which allow great freedom of movement. A helmet compatible Wire-Brimmed Halo-Hood™ keeps the head dry and one of the internal pockets doubles as a stuff sack. An interesting jacket with a new technology, curious to see if it performs better than existing hardshell fabrics.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279450652/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/376/20279450652_26a25f52f2_b.jpg" width="694" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Next up was the <strong>Ferrosi Summit Hooded Jacket™</strong> which adds a more durable, rugged jacket to the Ferrosi family that is still highly breathable while offering protection  for full mountain conditions. It is 526 g in Size 34 and has all the bells &amp; whistles you need from a mountain jacket: A helmet-compatible Wire-Brimmed Halo-Hood™, zippered chest &amp; hand pockets, Dynamic Reach™ Underarm Panels and being of course water-, wind-, and abrasion-resistant. Also new to the Ferrosi family is the <strong>Ferrosi Crag Pants™</strong> which will tip the scales at 314 g in Size 34 and comes with articulated knees, a gusseted crotch and a low-profile waist with Knit Stretch Panels for freedom of movement in the mountains.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665150104/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/393/19665150104_302f925916_b.jpg" width="597" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I really loved the look of the <strong>Women’s Ferrosi Knickers™</strong> which had a great orange (that was slightly difficult to photograph). It’s a rock climbing pants that has stretch knit panels at the waist which allows you to easily wear a harness over it. The lightweight stretch-woven construction is highly durable, for fun days at the crag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666841233/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Women’s  Ferrosi  Knickers™"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/487/19666841233_2bcc39743d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Women’s  Ferrosi  Knickers™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Already available are the <strong>Splitter Gloves™</strong>, OR’s take on crack gloves. These were very comfortable thanks to the synthetic suede on the inside and a non-slip  synthetic leather on the outside gives you grip in cracks and protects your hands. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099785740/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Splitter Gloves™"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/20099785740_b33bc64944_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Splitter Gloves™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Completely new is also the <strong>Sensor Dry Series</strong> which come in Premium &amp; Standard versions. Both are waterproof according to the IPX-8 Standard, fully touchscreen (and camera!) functional, have welded seams and are fairly lightweight. The Premium versions come with waterproof pins for your headphones and can swim when dropped into the water. Available for normal sized smartphone, massive smartphones and tablets.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101180819/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3709/20101180819_8489a1fa22_b.jpg" width="735" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099794998/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/327/20099794998_0cf1f64428_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And finally there were plenty of new hats, like the <strong>Helium Rain Bucket™</strong>, a waterproof hat; the <strong>Mesa Verde Sun Hat™</strong>, a 78 g light sun hat for the ladies; and the <strong>Springboard Cap</strong> I am sporting there, a lightweight cap for your trail adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101172829/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Helium Rain Bucket™"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/465/20101172829_070b5efe52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Helium Rain Bucket™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099780118/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Mesa Verde Sun Hat™"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3717/20099780118_b0cba6e0cf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Mesa Verde Sun Hat™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287808785/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Springboard Cap"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/507/20287808785_b89171d0e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Springboard Cap" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="cilogear">CiloGear</h2>

<p><em>“Have you seen anything new &amp; interesting yet?”</em> is the standard conversation opener at the fair. In years past my reply was usually <em>“Nope”</em> but this year I passed Graham from <a href="http://www.cilogear.com">CiloGear</a> as I had some time to spare and walked with him to his booth where he showed me something. What I saw then was not new, but it was for me the coolest thing on the fair which I told everyone who asked me the opening question then. Graham had a pack along - the first preproduction <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/30wwo.html">3030</a> ever made - which had seen roughly 900 (!) days outdoors, including two expeditions to Pakistan and was along establishing a new route on K7, a 6,934 m peak near the Charakusa Valley in the Karakoram. The owner sent it in to get the extension collar renewed, but the rest of the pack - seams and material - were still in great shape (albeit a tad dirty, but what do you expect after over two years in the mountains!). For me the most interesting thing in the show, not just because it shows that small manufacturers produce superb gear that lasts, but also because of the stories this pack would tell. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261525866/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/517/20261525866_0308c0f8e0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293723261/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/337/20293723261_cba928572c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099796360/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/496/20099796360_40b3658e5d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx">Arc’teryx</h2>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> was their <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-acrux-ar-alpine-boot.html">2016 Footwear</a> which I already have presented to you in June. The next big news was the <strong>Atom SL Hoody</strong>, an ultralight summer insulation piece that will weigh 285 g for a Men’s Medium. The Coreloft 40g/m² insulation is quilted to the liner while on the side and arm panels a soft fleece material helps with ventilation. Really interesting is the No-Slip-Zip™ front zipper which works like a series of speed bumps that keep the zipper from self-opening. It packs tiny and so can always be along in your backpack on your mountain adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099806578/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Atom SL Hoody"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20099806578_9a436d4504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Atom SL Hoody" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That backpack could be one of the new <strong>Cierzo Packs</strong>, Arc’teryx’s updated alpine climbing pack (in the centre of the photo underneath). Available as a Cierzo 18 (375 g) and a Cierzo 28 (550 g) they open via a pull to open, pull to close drawcord system like the Alpha FL packs, but also feature a SwiftCord™ drawstring compression system which is versatile in use and can be stored away when not needed. You can carry ice tools with them, and the Cierzo 28 has a padded back panel that can be removed to save more weight. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665147454/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx 2016 Backpacks"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3796/19665147454_f7b2ba9550_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx 2016 Backpacks" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Interesting for hiking &amp; backpacking was also the <strong>Pelon Comp SS</strong> which is made from core-spun Merino wool and has durable nylon inserts in high wear areas as the shoulders. They weigh 145 g in Size M and have a Regular fit and should be pretty good for long trips in the outdoors thanks to the properties of Merino wool.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287804825/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Pelon Comp SS"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/458/20287804825_9135589edc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Pelon Comp SS" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="petzl">Petzl</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a> had a lot of new gear on their booth, and they were also celebrating 25 years of the GriGri, probably the most popular belay device amongst all sorts of climbers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287806355/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl 25 years GriGri"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20287806355_da5ee93c48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl 25 years GriGri" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But the new gear! All of the IRVIS, VASAK, SARKEN, LYNX, DARTWIN and DART crampons get technical upgrades, making them even more effective, durable and practical. Effective: the horizontal structure of the frame brings the boot sole as close to the crampon as possible for increased sensitivity and precision. Durable: a special steel, chosen by Petzl for its rigidity and strength, allows a reduction in thickness to offer light weight crampons with sharper points. Practical: user-friendly binding systems, ANTISNOW and interchangeable front sections.</p>

<p>The <strong>IRVIS, VASAK and SARKEN Crampons</strong> have front sections that are interchangeable and available as accessories, which means you can have one crampon for all your needs and don’t need two or more of crampons in the house. Now you can simply &amp; fast convert for example a technical mountaineering crampon into one for glacier travel. All of them come with the new ANTISNOW, which limits snow balling up under your crampon. The VASAK will weigh 810 g, the IRVIS 710 g and the SARKEN 810 g, all with the FLEXLOCK binding. The linking bar in all three can be shortened to fit small sizes (Size 36 is the smallest size all three will fit, with Size 50 being the max).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261527636/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl Vasak Crampon"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/266/20261527636_0a5b15084a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Vasak Crampon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>ELIA</strong> is a new Women’s helmet with the OMEGA headband system. The notch in the back is for the long hair and allows ladies to put the helmet on and off very easily with a lot of comfort. It is 285 g light and also has a new webbing adjustment mechanism which allows the helmet to be precisely adjusted for different head shapes. The ABS shell and expanded polystyrene liner will keep the wearer save.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099784168/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl Elia helmet"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/367/20099784168_48ce174be7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Elia helmet" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>TIBLOC</strong> has been around for a while and gets a update for 2016. The new ultralight emergency ascender gets a system that automatically presses the carabiner against the rope to initiate the clamping action on the rope. You can see this advantage in comparison to the current TIBLOC in the 2nd photo underneath. The new TIBLOC has a rope compatibility from 8 to 11 mm and weighs 35 g.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279450132/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl TIBLOC"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/255/20279450132_475d419f27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl TIBLOC" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099789690/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl TIBLOC New &amp; Old"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/270/20099789690_24cc760bea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl TIBLOC New &amp; Old" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Furthermore there’s two new <strong>Semi-static ropes</strong> coming, two new <strong>carabiners</strong>, the <strong>ALCANADRE</strong>, a large volume pack for transporting canyoning equipment and the <strong>BUG</strong>, a small backpack for single-day multi-pitch climbing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101171129/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/256/20101171129_1a96229815_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293742921/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/532/20293742921_ae05b89662_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="rjk">Röjk</h2>

<p>Doesn’t the <a href="http://rojksuperwear.com/en/">Röjk</a> booth look fantastic? Of course it does - Linus &amp; Jan shanghaied me in helping it putting it up! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287797785/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/315/20287797785_a0bb2fee35_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That’s the Guys PrimaLoft Zippen Hood in purple, which rocks. It’s a S.O.A. Winner, too. But new is the <strong>Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood</strong> that Linus models underneath. It’s a lighter weight hoody jacket. The PrimaLoft Polyester makes it lightweight and nicely soft on the skin, is wicking very fast while the Merino wool makes it stay fresh. The cool look makes it a fine choice for chilling at the campfire or going to town. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261528726/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3791/20261528726_0343b99044_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Somehow I managed to not take a photo of Röjk’s new T-Shirt designs for the <strong>SuperTee</strong>, which is a shame because they were awesome. Röjk continues their Inka, Maya &amp; Aztec theme with very pretty designs on their 60% Merino wool &amp; 40% Modal shirts for Chicks and Guys, so please excuse the absence of the photos and believe me: They rock. What I did photograph, though, is the new <strong>Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody</strong>. These are made from Merino wool and Lyocell for a lightweight and comfortable backpacking hoody that stays fresh and cool for a long time. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665161864/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/473/19665161864_18f7e5c3ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Sadly not pictured are the great looking <strong>SuperTank</strong> tops, which are made from Merino wool and Modal and also come in sick Inca patterns. What I can show you is the <strong>PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock</strong> which should be super breathable thanks to the open mesh structure on top and help avoid sweaty feet. Made from PrimaLoft Yarn, Merino wool and Polyamide they should be durable, keeping your toes warm, dry and looking good!  </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666843133/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/552/19666843133_73ca83b1b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Most importantly, you can shop their gear online right now in the <a href="http://rojksuperwear.com/en/">Röjk online shop</a>!</p>

<h2 id="ortovox">Ortovox</h2>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://www.ortovox.de/">Ortovox</a> were the backpacks, especially the <strong>PEAK</strong> which has a unique SWISSWOOL back system that’s made from pressed Swiss wool. The ideas is that in exactly the same way as with clothing you would benefit from the wool’s great moisture and microclimate management and therefore the backpanel feels comfortable and dry on your back. Otherwise the PEAK is a good looking climbing backpack with a c circumferential front zipper for easy access. Will be interesting to see if the backpanel works as imagined or if it just sucks itself full with sweat and stays wet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261545696/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/323/20261545696_888b79ac59_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287805525/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack Swisswool backpanel"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/284/20287805525_5ba8004bda_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack Swisswool backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293731291/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/298/20293731291_2701787a89_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET</strong> is from Ortovox’s new softshell line (called, yes, MERINO SHIELD SHELL) and will weigh 353 g (Size ?). The line is made for high-alpine tours and has hence the features you’d want from a jacket for such outings: Freedom of movement, high abrasion-resistance, breathability and comfort. It has a protective shell made from Cordura®, the outer side of front pocket is made of felted wool and has an athletic fit. It was a comfortable jacket and felt very nice.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101189529/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/395/20101189529_1064533f20_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kitka">Kitka</h2>

<p>It was pretty cool to meet the guys from <a href="http://kitkaclimbing.com">Kitka Climbing</a> at the fair, especially with their own booth! Kitka makes polyurethane climbing holds, handcrafted in Finland, with a lot of unique &amp; cool shapes. They felt great and I reckon I will need to get a few sets for my own boulder wall!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293717451/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Kitka Climbing Holds"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/461/20293717451_35656e4206_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kitka Climbing Holds" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="rab">Rab</h2>

<p>As always I enjoyed my visit to <a href="http://rab.equipment/">Rab</a>, and their new kit really rocks. There was a lot of new lightweight gear for the ladies, like the fine <strong>Women’s Flashpoint Jacket</strong> which is made from 3L Pertex Shield+ Fabric and will weigh 160 g for a Women’s 12. It has a helmet compatible hood with a lightweight &amp; flexible polymer peak to keep your eyes dry in the rain. It’s designed as the jacket that you have along in case the rain hits you while you are on a Multi-Pitch route or an alpine ascent, and as it is so light you don’t need to ponder if you take it along. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261546376/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Rab Women’s Flashpoint Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/303/20261546376_843ff13911_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Rab Women’s Flashpoint Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>New is also the <strong>Women’s Continuum Jacket</strong> which will be the lightest option in the women’s insulation range at 240 g in Size 12. It’s filled with 100g of 850FP European Goose Down that’s hydrophobic. It will pack down also very small and thus also can always come along on your mountain adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20266787270/in/dateposted/" title="Rab Women&#x27;s Continuum Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/397/20266787270_c43e929260_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab Women&#x27;s Continuum Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And I liked the new Rock Climbing garments immensely. Functional and stylish, the assortment of pants - from the <strong>Oblique &amp; Rockover Pants</strong> to the <strong>Rampage Jacket</strong> and the many great T-Shirts and hoodies, the Rock Climbing &amp; Lifestyle Collection is great for days at the crag - be it in Kalymnos, Olhava or the Peak District. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461137201/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/490/20461137201_b89427b206_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20268246319/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/351/20268246319_3f8c184aab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20446195202/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/402/20446195202_d09a4723c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sea-to-summit">Sea to Summit</h2>

<p>After not visiting <a href="http://www.seatosummit.com">Sea to Summit</a> in 2014 I was happy to check out what they had new this year. The <strong>XSet Pots</strong> are collapsible cooking pots, which should be ideal with simple gas or alcohol stoves. The bottoms are made from hard anodized aluminium with food-grade &amp; heat-resistant silicone walls that fold down for transport, making for small packages while in your pack. The 3 piece kit consists of a 1,3 l kettle, one 2,8 l pot and a 8” frying pan that weigh together 756 g. The kettle on its own is 186 g and the lightest of the whole series and could be all a lightweight backpacker needs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099778470/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit XSet Pots"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/433/20099778470_24e75f5526_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Sea to Summit XSet Pots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>New is also the <strong>Aeros Pillow Ultralight</strong> which will weigh 70 g and packs as big as a Kiwi. If you value a good nights sleep and want a lightweight pillow that is very comfortable, this looks like an interesting new offering to the market. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666823983/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Aeros Pillow Ultralight"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/544/19666823983_8fcaf2283a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Aeros Pillow Ultralight" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Ground Control Tent Pegs</strong> are made from high-quality aluminium, weigh 14 g each and have a luminescent pull loop which is easily seen at night, adding a bit more security to your nightly stumbles around your tent. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261534766/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Ground Control Tent Pegs"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/508/20261534766_ee6a63a867_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Ground Control Tent Pegs" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Self-Adhesive Lash Points</strong> should be especially interesting for packrafters. These allow you to add extra tie-down points to your packraft, either to tie down gear, install thigh straps or or or. And at 18 g per lash point they’re ultralight, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666827693/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Self-Adhesive Lash Points"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/536/19666827693_a44f650efd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Self-Adhesive Lash Points" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="vertical-life">Vertical Life</h2>

<p>New at <a href="https://www.vertical-life.info">Vertical-Life</a> was the <strong>Zlag Up!</strong>, a variation on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/zlagboard-pro-review.html">Zlagboard</a> which I use. It’s a smart pull-up bar which works like the Zlagboard with an App on your smartphone to keep track of your training, and as a very special extra there’s the rolley bar which is pretty cool to train your balance.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279448742/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Zlag Up"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3786/20279448742_904d6fd21e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Zlag Up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="http://guide.vertical-life.info/en/app/">Climbing App Guides</a> also get a lot of new topos all the time, and you can test the app for South Tyrol’s crags for free (I wish I’d known this before my trip to the Dolomites!). </p>

<h2 id="stay-tuned-for-the-next-part-coming-soon">Stay tuned for the next part, coming soon™!</h2>

<p>As usual you can see a lot more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157656356655229">OutDoor 2015 Flickr Album</a>. Sweet. And if you liked this follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for more gear &amp; outdoor updates.  And <a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a> as a payment for my work =)</p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
