<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ice climbing gear | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/ice-climbing-gear/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-05T22:13:33+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assorted Ice Climbing Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/assorted-ice-climbing-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-19T21:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/assorted-ice-climbing-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Besides boots, crampons, ice axes and a backpack there’s a few more pieces of gear an ice climber needs - ice screws, belay devices, slings, quick draws, and and and. In this article I highlight some of the assorted ice climbing gear which I have used during this years ice climbing exploits.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661762203/" title="Assorted climbing gear by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8250/8661762203_070d206c29_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Assorted climbing gear" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="black-diamond-express-ice-screws">Black Diamond Express Ice Screws</h2>
<p>The Gold Standard in ice screws, the Black Diamond Express have the best price/ quality ratio and perform superbly on the ice. Easy to screw into the ice with one hand thanks to the crank and with to two carabiner holes to clip in, the Express ice screw helps you to secure yourself quickly when the going gets tough. Petzl will bring out a similar design next winter which performs very well, and Grivel’s <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-ice-screw-360-kurbeleisschraube/">360 ice screws</a> too is great. However, at the moment Black Diamond makes the lightest screws and they’re very well priced, thus these excellent ice screws shouldn’t be missing on any ice climbers rack.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-express-ice-screw-eisschraube/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-express-ice-screw.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15pvcgK">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115SnGQ">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJ4OcT">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587935487/" title="Secured by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8241/8587935487_cc1e3ed8d0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Secured" /></a></p>

<h2 id="slings">Slings</h2>
<p>Slings are an important piece of gear when climbing ice whenever you don’t toprope. A 120 cm sling is essential to build a belay station together with two ice screws, and a daisychain or another 120 cm sling are needed to secure yourself at a belay station. They also can be very useful when setting screws and taking care that the rope isn’t making a wide curve (Imagine it a bit like this sign <strong>&lt;</strong> where the three points are ice screws and the line is the rope. With a sling and two ‘biners in the middle point you can make the rope run in a more straight line). Also when rappeling down slings come in handy, and they of course also can be used in rock climbing. A piece of gear that definitely needs to come along.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schlingen-reepschnur/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/schlinge-reepschnur.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15ptb3X">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/Zv14fB">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115RtdF">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662799740/" title="Slings &amp; Daisychain by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8245/8662799740_908fe80d94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Slings &amp; Daisychain" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quick-draws">Quick draws</h2>
<p>When you’re leading a climb you’ll need quick draws (Read Tomás superb article on <a href="http://www.scandinavian-hiking.com/2011/08/relatively-ultralight-quickdraws-petzl.html">Ultralight Quick Draws</a>). As so often, lighter quick draws means you either can take more or then safe a substantial amount of weight for the same performance. Some clip in easier and are better handled with gloves, so keep that in mind when building your rack.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/express-sets/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/express-sets.html?priceMin=&amp;priceMax=&amp;query=&amp;sort=&amp;_artperpage=">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15puIat">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176mNNe">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176mZw0">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662796740/" title="Quick draws by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8259/8662796740_9938e7249a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Quick draws" /></a></p>

<h2 id="carabiners">Carabiners</h2>
<p>I thought I’d be set with my two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-phantom-schraubkarabiner/">DMM Phantom</a> locking ‘biners, though I was wrong. And so I bought a few more locking carabiners, in slightly bigger sizes, because they’re easier to operate with gloves on. If you’re not toproping then a about five locking carabiners are good to have along: Three to set up a belay, one to clip yourself in with a sling, and one if you’re belaying someone else. A spare or two in these situations can’t hurt, either.</p>

<p>As for non-locking carabiners, I have been using the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-phantom-schnappkarabiner/">DMM Phantom gate ‘biner</a> and still think they’re superb. The gate opens easy, they’re light yet strong - a great biner to have along to rack gear.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schraubkarabiner/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/karabiner.html?Limit%5B%5D=Schraubkarabiner&amp;Limit%5B%5D=HMS-Karabiner&amp;priceMin=&amp;priceMax=&amp;query=&amp;sort=&amp;_artperpage=&amp;f=1">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZAAOxi">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJ9vn8">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115W5QI">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662797582/" title="Carabiners by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8251/8662797582_9b811ef47f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Carabiners" /></a></p>

<h2 id="camp-speed-helmet">CAMP Speed helmet</h2>
<p>I used the CAMP Speed helmet during all climbing, and really like the comfort of this helmet - light and protective, easy to adjust the size when I wear a beanie or not, not to hot nor too cold. I can wear shades or my googles underneath them, a Headlamp like the Petzl Nao fits easily on it, and it also fits under all my jacket’s hoods. However, with the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-vapor-hybridhelm/">Black Diamond Vapor</a> and Petzl Siricco helmets available, the Speed is no longer the lightest option, something too keep in mind when you’re buying a helmet (I used the Petzl Siricco and really like it, especially the magnetic closure that’s easy to operate with one hand is very good).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-speed-kletterhelm/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/camp-brg-5.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176wpYi">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661816397/" title="CAMP Speed Helmet by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8258/8661816397_2b4e3ce0b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="CAMP Speed Helmet" /></a></p>

<h2 id="poc-iris-3p-googles">POC Iris 3P Googles</h2>

<p>Because my helmet doesn’t have a visor to keep ice and water from flying in my face, I was wearing the comfortable <a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">POC Iris 3P Googles</a>. They have a superb view and while they on occasion were fogging up, the fog cleared up quickly. I can wear them with my Speed Helmet without problems, but had problems to get a comfortable fit with the new Petzl Helmet. The googles’ lens are antiscratch and have a oleophobic &amp; hydrophobic treatment which means it keeps fat and water off your lens very easily - a very welcome function when climbing ice where you sweat and ice is coming at you. A great pair of googles that I can recommend if you climb ice or ski.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">JK-Shop</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176xmjq">Backcountry</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662911976/" title="POC Iris 3P Googles by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8266/8662911976_1d5db327e1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="POC Iris 3P Googles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="petzl-reverso-4">Petzl Reverso 4</h2>
<p>I usually use a Petzl Verso, though enlightenment struck as I tried the Reverso 4. It’s only a tad heavier than the Verso but offers so much more functions: You can secure two climbers that are climbing after you, and connect it to your belay with the ring. As with the Verso, you can belay and rappel. When not toproping then definitely a piece of gear to take along. </p>

<p>There’s plenty of belaying devices around, though one to consider is the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/s/Mammut--Smart----Alpine/kategorie--klettern/">Mammut Smart Alpine</a> which offers similar functionality as the Reverso though has the added benefit of breaking the rope dynamically in the case of a fall. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-reverso-4-sicherungsgeraet/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-reverso-4-belay-device.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZABoLu">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/11m0gIL">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13qZm2O">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577735844/" title="Petzl Reverso 4 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8234/8577735844_86d4c770cb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Reverso 4" /></a></p>

<h2 id="tendon-master-97-rope">Tendon Master 9.7 rope</h2>
<p>A superb rope for toproping, also on ice. It’s my rock-climbing rope which I diverted from its intended use to toproping on ice. Super smooth handling, light, great knot-ability, and with a middle marking, this is a great piece of kit which does the job very well.</p>

<p>For lead climbing on ice a twin or half rope is needed, though, and also there the market offers plenty of great ropes for us ice climbers. I used a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beal-ice-twin-golden-dry-77-mm-zwillingsseil/">BEAL rope</a> which were very great to handle and didn’t soak out, and if you’re serious about ice climbing then you won’t get around getting a twin or half rope (<a href="http://www.highinfatuation.com/blog/straight-from-the-mammoths-mouth-half-ropes-are-not-twins/">Here’s an explanation on the difference</a>!).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/tendon-master-97-mm-einfachseil/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/tendon-master-9-4-complete-shield-kletterseil.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r7uA8">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r6YCt">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/17sOoX6">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8486287141/" title="Tendon Rope by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8372/8486287141_7f341247e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Tendon Rope" /></a></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-r320-harness">Arc’teryx R320 harness</h2>
<p>The Arc’teryx R320 has been my harness of choice and I like the racking capacity it has - plenty of gear fits on the four gear loops. For ice climbing a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-caritool.html">Petzl Caritool</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-ice-clipper.html">Black Diamond Ice Clipper</a> would have been useful, though I made work without this season. It’s comfortable, the leg loops are big enough to step through in case you put on your crampons before your harness (happens!) and with it’s good design it feels well over pants and jacket. If one is serious about ice climbing, the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-i340a-klettergurt/">Arc’teryx I340A</a> of course would be a nice harness to have, though for the time being the R320 is very good for my needs and can be used all year around.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-r-320-hueftgurt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-r-320a-klettergurt.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJanYJ">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/Z1PB8H">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/11m0I9Q">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="black-diamond-ice-box">Black Diamond Ice Box</h2>
<p>A backpack is the best way to get your gear from home to the ice fall. But what when between the ice fall and home there’s a airplane? Backpacks with the sharp tools outside aren’t great for travelling - enter the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633281180152/">Black Diamond Ice Box</a>. It fits four tools, one pair of crampons, up to ten ice screws, a mesh compartment for drying gear and still has plenty of space left for small stuff. For me very important too, is that its perfect to store the ice climbing gear safely and using minimal space at home, out of the reach of an exploring toddler. A great piece of kit for ice climbers that travel a lot and want to store their gear safely when not in use.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ice-box/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/17sM0zG">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r3DTL">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662893104/" title="Black Diamond Ice Box by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8248/8662893104_f8e2087b75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond Ice Box" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661794319/" title="Black Diamond Ice Box by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8260/8661794319_4c98c70443_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ice Box" /></a></p>

<p><em>Most of the ice-climbing related gear has been used for a week of ice climbing this season. These short reviews thus should be considered as an initial review, which will be updated during the next winter season when I have used the gear more. If you have questions, please use the comments to ask!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576458309/" title="Abisko Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8392/8576458309_581552ba62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abisko Canyon" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaiming the Disclaimer</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hyperlite Mountain Gear IcePack]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/hyperlite-mountain-gear-icepack.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-18T21:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/hyperlite-mountain-gear-icepack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ice climbing does involve a fair bit of gear. There’s tools and crampons, ropes, screws, a helmet and belay jacket as well as safety gear. You could start each approach wearing all of that gear, or you just could use a lightweight backpack and hike in comfort to the base of your climb. The <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/2400-ice-pack.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear IcePack</a> is such a lightweight backpack. <em>A Living Review</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595259281/" title="HMG-IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8243/8595259281_55c7b2c11e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG-IcePack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>
<p>I have used the HMG IcePack for six days of ice climbing and dozens of days of walking, hiking and cycling. One of the ice climbing trips was even a fast &amp; light trip, in which I was able to fit all my camping gear plus ice climbing gear in the pack! Overall I have used the IcePack well over a year.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8536787938/" title="The @HyperliteMGear Ice Pack also works very well as a filming bag. #photography #videography by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8386/8536787938_9ca7ced992_o.jpg" width="612" height="612" alt="The @HyperliteMGear Ice Pack also works very well as a filming bag. #photography #videography" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>
<p>The IcePack allows you to carry all your ice climbing gear, and includes dedicated attachment possibilities for crampons, ice tools, and ropes. It also works very well for backpacking with camera gear, as the crampon attachment can hold a heavy tripod (mine is 2,5 kg) without problems, and the ice tool straps can hold trekking poles.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659088153/" title="041713_1842 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8106/8659088153_c84555e7ba_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="041713_1842" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Exterior Dyneema patch with elastic straps for attaching crampons</li>
  <li>Two shock cord systems for securing axe shafts</li>
  <li>Two removable, shaped aluminium stays</li>
  <li>Padded back panel</li>
  <li>Roll-top closure</li>
  <li>Top Y-strap compression system designed to keep pack contents tight as well as to hold other gear and equipment</li>
  <li>Two side compression straps with side release buckles</li>
  <li>Padded shoulder straps</li>
  <li>Padded, removable hip belt with gear loops for racking carabiners</li>
  <li>Adjustable sternum strap with self-tensioning elastic</li>
  <li>Double-reinforced pack bottom</li>
  <li>Internal mesh pocket</li>
  <li>Haul loop handle</li>
  <li>Bar tacked reinforcements on all stress points</li>
  <li>100% rainproof</li>
</ul>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/65279320?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>
<p>I’m 175 cm tall and my Size M pack fits me perfectly. If you’re ordering a IcePack it is worth to take the time to measure your back to get the correct length.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659092873/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8111/8659092873_514deec3df_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>
<p>It’s a completely stripped down pack, which can be modified to suit your needs. It uses Hyperlite Mountain Gear’s Cuben Fiber/ Polyester hybrid material, and the crampon attachment is unique, too. Overall the innovations in this pack is more in what is NOT there. </p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>
<p>It’s a high quality pack, though some stitching could use a bit more attention to detail - it decreases the overall impression of what is otherwise a good backpack. The material is super durable and besides some cosmetic blemishes (mud and tree sap) the pack is still in top condition after over a year of use.</p>

<p><strong>Update May 2013:</strong> Hyperlite Mountain Gear informed me that the stitiching has been improved on the newer packs and shouldn’t disappoint anymore. Furthermore, they are now taping the seams of the body of the pack with cuben fiber tape, this further reinforces the stitching and enhances the already very good water resistance of the pack.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659090579/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8121/8659090579_da374d3ef5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660188178/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8109/8660188178_2ab7933695_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>
<p>The complete pack in Size M weighs 900 g on the spot. Here’s the breakdown of the weight</p>

<ul>
  <li>114 g removable stays</li>
  <li>152 g removable waist belt</li>
  <li>634 g backpack</li>
</ul>

<p>My preferred setup is without the waist belt, which brings the weight down to 748 gram.</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>
<p>The pack is made of HMG’s Cuben Fiber/ Polyester hybrid material and hence is made of oil based materials. Thus it shouldn’t be thrown in the garbage like ordinary rubbish, you could try to either recycle it via your local outdoor shop or inquire from Hyperlite Mountain Gear how to recycle the IcePack at the end of its life cycle.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659117043/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8101/8659117043_577b1d7105_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660218174/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8126/8660218174_6b1ed763f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659117449/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8116/8659117449_58ba259742_b.jpg" width="1024" height="428" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>
<p>I have used the IcePack more for hiking and cycling than for ice climbing, though it certainly excels for the latter activity. I have an <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/gregory-alpinisto-50-rucksack-alpine-gold.html">Gregory Alpinisto 50</a>, which should have a larger volume than the IcePack, though it is the other way around: The IcePack with its about 40 l of volume fits more gear, and more easily, than the Alpinisto. The IcePack also has a large opening and it is easy to pack and unpack. </p>

<p>Because there’s no separate internal pocket for small-ish stuff (at least not in my version, it looks like this might have been addressed in the newer packs) it’s not easy to organise in case you want that kind of stuff. The inside mesh pocket is “Meh” and while I haven’t yet cut it out I don’t see much use for it. But packing is rather straight forward: You just pack your gear bottom to top into the pack, close the velcro and roll it closed. Crampons and ice tools fit easily to the front and are very easy to attach, and a CCF pad or ropes can be attached via the top or side compression straps. This makes packing fast and convenient, though if you want a place to store your keys, wallet and cellphone you either should take a small stuff sack for them, or keep them on you.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660209450/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8110/8660209450_47065266dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659120151/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8659120151_8cb1afc771_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659119769/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8108/8659119769_e98ffc3bc7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<p>I rarely use the hipbelt, because I feel that even with a heavy rope and a full pack it’s not needed, hence I detached it. The pack carries with the stays very well, and while with a light load and without the stays it still is good to carry you gain a lot of extra carrying comfort with the stays, so I always have them in. On the trip to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html">Korouoma</a> I carried about 10 kg of gear in it, and it was still perfectly fine to carry without the hipbelt and just using the padded shoulder straps. </p>

<p>HMG advertises that the gear loops on hip belt can be used for racking carabiners or ice screws, but for ‘biners the loops are rather tight and wide so I wouldn’t bother with it - they’re too difficult to get in or out, unless you want to attach them permanently for racking gear or use Ice Clipper ‘biners - then . If you use the Petzl ice screws with the flute storage, then racking them on the hipbelt is easy, though I prefer to rack all gear on my harness. I haven’t climbed with the backpack on, though, so if you climb very long multi-pitch routes you might find the hipbelt’s storage possibilities useful, though on the other hand the hipbelt might get in the way with your harness.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660197492/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8124/8660197492_79db1d095d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660199762/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8109/8660199762_ef098a88e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>
<p>There are heaps of ice climbing specific packs available, but only a few which are truly lightweight. <a href="http://www.mchalepacks.com/">McHale</a> makes exclusively custom-made backpacks which are raved about by their owners, and <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/packs.html">CiloGear’s WorkSacks</a> also have been very positively reviewed. The <a href="http://www.ks-ultralightgear.com/p/ks-alpisack.html">KS Alpisack</a> is an ultralight climbing pack Made in Japan, and also some European companies like <a href="http://www.camp.it/EN/template01.aspx?codicemenu=1170">CAMP</a>, <a href="http://grivel.com/products/ice/rucksacks/">Grivel</a> and <a href="http://www.crux.uk.com/en/rucksacks.php">Crux</a> produce lightweight backpacks. From the big players <a href="http://www.blackdiamondequipment.com/">Black Diamond</a> and <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com/">Mountain Hardwear</a> make very good and light climbing specific backpacks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587936563/" title="All packed up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8365/8587936563_6ac57e172b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="All packed up" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>
<p>Nick has put his <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/?p=563">HMG IcePack</a> through a lot of climbing and hiking, and finds it superb. <a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/the_gearcaster/2011/12/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ice-climbing-pack-review.html">Amy likes the IcePack</a> for its major reduction in weight, and <a href="http://larsonweb.com/blog/?p=296">Kai liked his pack</a> so much that he bought a 2nd one. Finally, the <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Alpine-Climbing-Pack-Reviews/Hyperlite-Mountain-Gear-Ice-Pack">Outdoor Gear Lab gives it 4 Stars</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>
<p>Overall it’s a great pack in use: At the base of a climb or the start of the approach you easily can get your crampons and tools off the pack, and they’re as easily attached back to the backpack after a climb. The rather big storage of the 2400 cu model is big enough for fast &amp; light climbing &amp; camping weekends as well as for backpacking trips and the pack carries extremely well thanks to the stays. While the padded back is minimal it does the job well. The IcePack is very durable and takes the abuse from sharp tools and crampons without problems, and the material is thus far 100% waterproof - in neither rain nor snow the gear inside got wet. It is easy to attach gear to the outside to the backpack: The side compression straps with their buckles can hold a Z-Lite or thin CCF pad, and the top Y-Strap keeps your rope and helmet in place.</p>

<p>A couple of points of improvement would be to pay attention that the stiching is top everywhere, the option for a side pocket to easily store a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos flask</a>, and a zippered inside pocket for small items. Other than that the IcePack is my top choice for ice climbing trips, as I value its great carrying capabilities while still being lightweight.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633269353761/">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-hyperlite-mountain-gear-icepack">Where to buy the Hyperlite Mountain Gear IcePack</h2>
<p>Buy it at <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/index.php?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a> | <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/2400-ice-pack.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660188966/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8109/8660188966_81cb96b5b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>
<ul>
  <li>In the next season I will add more on how the pack performs when climbing, if there were any failures, and more overall experiences</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Disclaimer</em><br />
Trekking-Lite-Store.com provided me the IcePack free of charge for testing, and paid me 1 kazillion € to review it.*</p>

<p><sub><sup><sub><sup>* One of these statements is not true.</sup></sub></sup></sub></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Petzl Nomic Ice Tools]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-17T21:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After boots and crampons ice tools are the third essential piece of gear when climbing ice. As with the other equipment, I did plenty of research online, in magazines and books before I decided to get the <a href="http://www.petzl.com/en/outdoor/ice-climbing-tools/nomic">Petzl Nomic ice tools</a>, and once I used them I understood why they’re so highly regarded. <em>A Living Review</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576322159/" title="Great Ice! by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8251/8576322159_bf671406fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Great Ice!" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>
<p>I have used the Petzl Nomic ice tools for seven full days of ice and mixed climbing. This review thus should be considered as an initial review, which I will update during the next winter season when I have used them more. </p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>
<p>Ice tools replace your hands when climbing ice falls or mixed terrain. The Nomics are to be used in a pair, and excel in climbing steep ice and mixed routes, though can be used on alpine ascents if you’re aware of their shortcoming for these undertakings.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8656049698/" title="Petzl Nomic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8103/8656049698_a9f2a24da7_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Petzl Nomic" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Ergonomic, offset handle design - can be used with both hands</li>
  <li>Modular head for adapting the ice axe to the activity you’re doing: Without weights for drytooling, with weights for ice climbing, and a possibility to attach an adze and a hammer to place pitons</li>
  <li>Interchangeable pick: ICE for ice climbing, DRY for drytooling</li>
  <li>Serrated blade on the bottom of the griprest</li>
  <li>Adjustable Griprest: Pivots to accommodate larger and smaller hands/ gloves</li>
  <li>Great griptape above handle</li>
  <li>Leashless</li>
  <li>Strong curve for ice and mixed climbing</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8654940515/" title="Petzl Nomic Grip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8122/8654940515_c2f027864d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Nomic Grip" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>
<p>The Nomics arrived in a Medium setting on the Griprest, which suited me just fine in my ice climbing gloves. With the supplied Allen key it is easy to change the size if one has bigger or smaller hands. If you need an adze or hammer, or want to use the Nomics for drytooling, then it is equally easy to attach these accessories or remove the weights on the head. </p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>
<p>My research indicates that Petzl was partly responsible for the introduction of leashless climbing tools with the first iteration of the Nomics in 2008. Leaving something away - in this case the leashes - is a form of optimising and minimalizing a design, which set a standard back then which other companies have followed since.</p>

<p>The overall design has a few innovations (serrated blade on grip rest, you can attach hammer and adze) though please check the other reviews listed below to read up them as some of these climbers have used the old and new tools. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8655076087/" title="Petzl Nomic Grip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8120/8655076087_fc3d88d9ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Nomic Grip" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>
<p>Exceptional quality as always from Petzl. The Nomics are very well made tools, from the overall design which swings superbly to the use of material, even on details like the griptape which gives a bit of insulation and lets you grip the tool safely (as in it doesn’t slip). Made in France, 3 years of guarantee. </p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>
<p>The Nomics weigh 608 g per tool including the weights on the head. Take these off with the supplied Allen key and the weight drops to 544 g per tool. Without the weight they are better for Drytooling, with the weights they’re superb for ice climbing as the added weight improves the swing and helps to drive the pick better into the ice. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8654949139/" title="Petzl Nomic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8102/8654949139_5138d21d58_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Nomic" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8654952203/" title="Petzl Nomic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8102/8654952203_ff4a44dc0d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Nomic" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8656158690/" title="Petzl Nomic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8117/8656158690_db3838c378_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Nomic" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>
<p>Steel is used in the pick and spike, the shaft is made of an aluminium alloy and the grip is of plastic with a rubber griptape. You could recycle the pick easily, though as grip and shaft are one unit you might want to take them to your outdoor shop and let them handle the recycling of the tool. Unless you knock up the shaft a lot while drytooling I don’t expect that one needs to replace them at all, and happily it is very easy to replace the picks, which is the part which sees the most use. Though at 50€ a pick that can become rather costly, especially if you do a lot of mixed climbing.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>
<p>The swing of this tool feels great. It is a very well-balanced tool, with a beautiful swing. Reading up on technic I started with a big swing, but quickly realised that I didn’t need it to drive the pick into the ice. A small to medium move with a good wrist flick at the end is on all but the driest ice sufficient, as the head weights help sink the tool into the ice very effectively. The pick thus goes easily into the ice, and just as easily comes out again. </p>

<p>The blade at the bottom of the griprest - mine is set to medium to accommodate my small-ish hands, buffed up with a thick pair of gloves - grips well into the ice on steep terrain, and helps in going up steep ice. Also the angle of the shaft and handle help to reduce knuckle bashing - something that with straighter tools in the past was a problem. Even as a beginner I haven’t hit my knuckles once on ice or rock with the Nomics, which I’m very happy about.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8656167084/" title="Petzl Nomic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8111/8656167084_1f9aef50de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Nomic" /></a></p>

<p>Leashless climbing seems to be the norm nowadays, and while the danger of dropping a tool was something I was concerned about it really wasn’t an issue. I once dropped a tool - two meters above ground the first time I was climbing - and if dropping a tool is something you’re worried about then a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/camp-x-gyro-leash.html">springer leash</a> is a useful accessory to get. Leashless ice tools make it very easy to swap tools on the ice. They’re also not restricting blood circulation as could be the case if you hang in your leashes. Thus switching tools on a route was very easy, and once I realised that I have this possibility it made some climbs significantly easier. For me the biggest benefit of this possibility was that I’m stronger with my right arm, and hence could first place the right tool, then switch hands and place also the second (left) tool with the right arm in those situations where the ice was crappy.</p>

<p>I tried a pair of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-quark-hammer-ice-tool.html">Petzl Quarks</a> and did not like their grip. The GRIPREST/ TRIGREST piece in the grip was above my index finger, which hindered blood circulation and I got cold hands - colder hands than I never got with my Nomics. You can apparently flick the Trigrest up and eliminate this problem. I also tried a pair of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-quantum-tech-eisgeraet.html">Grivel Quantum Tech</a> tools which were wonderfully light, though their owner commented that he liked the slightly heavier Nomics as they go easier into the ice - with the Quantum Tech, which don’t have extra weights on the head, a little bit of extra power is needed for a good placement. These are not concerns for me at the moment, as these kind of factors are getting important if one climbs routes with 5+ Pitches and I’m not just there, yet =) </p>

<p>The Nomics are made for vertical, technical routes. Because of the aggressively curved shaft and angled pick it is easier to clear bulges and other features on ice routes, but if the ice gets less than 80° steep, the Nomics start to be less than optimal - for topping out on a climb they’re fine, though if you’re planning to get up a long, mildly steep ice field there are better tools available.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8655067165/" title="Petzl Nomic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8116/8655067165_a4732968cc_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Petzl Nomic" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>
<p>The <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/edelrid-rage-eisgeraet.html">Edelrid Rage</a> is 660 g, the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-fusion-ice-tool.html">Black Diamond Fusion</a> is 672 g and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-quantum-tech-eisgeraet.html">Grivel Quantum Tech</a> is 520 g. There’s probably more, please feel free to let me know in the comments (include a link to the tool, please).</p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.sheldonkerr.com/?p=447">Sheldon Kerr reviewed the Nomics</a> for Alpinist Magazine and gave them 4 Stars. Dave Burdick compares the <a href="http://cascadeclimbers.com/black-diamond-fusion-vs-petzl-nomic-review/">Black Diamond Fusion &amp; Petzl Nomic in a Review</a>. Dane from Cold Thistle compares the <a href="http://coldthistle.blogspot.fi/2010/11/old-nomic-and-new-nomic.html">Old versus New Nomics</a>. Kevin Avery reviews them favourably on <a href="http://www.ukclimbing.com/gear/review.php?id=1790">UK Climbing</a>. Genevieve Hathaway also finds the <a href="http://www.pembaserves.com/2011/02/petzl-nomics-the-ice-climber%E2%80%99s-samurai-sword/">Petzl Nomics</a> a superb choice for vertical, aggressive, and technical routes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8656163088/" title="Petzl Nomic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8121/8656163088_03e8d78479_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Nomic" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>
<p>The Nomics are easy to use and I felt confident with them on the ice. Getting a good placement with them didn’t needed a lot of power, also because the superb ICE picks go into the ice like a hot knife into butter. Also getting them out again is easy, and thanks to their aggressively curved shaft and great grip I didn’t hit my knuckles once this season. Sometimes you need to grip your tool a bit higher on a climb, and thanks to the rubber griptape you can do so without fear of slipping. Switching tools is easy thanks to the Nomics being leashless and helps on difficult routes or rotten ice. The serrated blade at the bottom gives a bit of extra hold on steep ice, and if you need a hammer or an adze then you can attach them easily. </p>

<p>They are very well made tools with innovative details which make ice climbing a tiny bit easier and comfortable. I’m super happy with them, and look forward to using my two Nomics again next winter!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633258195413/">Plenty more photos on Flickr</a>. </p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-petzl-nomic">Where to buy the Petzl Nomic</h2>
<p>Buy them at <a href="http://www.camu.fi/pages/kiipeily/vuorikiipeily/jaahakut/nomicjaahakku.html">Camu</a> | <a href="http://www.mountainshop.fi/">Mountain Shop</a> ON OFFER - only 200€! | <a href="http://www.varuste.net/Petzl+Charlet+Nomic+2012">Varuste</a> | <a href="http://bit.ly/16YR1l6">Backcountry</a> | <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-charlet-nomic-eisgeraet/">Bergfreunde</a> | <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-nomic-eisgeraet.html">Bergzeit</a> | <a href="http://bit.ly/15gFks0">CampSaver</a> 20% off - only $240 | <a href="http://bit.ly/16YR8gx">REI</a></p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Replacement <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-ice-ersatzhaue/">ICE Pick</a></td>
      <td> Replacement <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-dry-ersatzhaue-fuer-eisgeraete/">DRY Pick</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8656176754/” title=”Petzl Nomic</td>
      <td>Serrated Blade on the Grip Rest by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8100/8656176754_0a9e54fa36_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”680” alt=”Petzl Nomic</td>
      <td>Serrated Blade on the Grip Rest”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>
<ul>
  <li>In the next season I will add more on how they’re in use climbing ice and mixed, possibly for alpine trips, if there were any failures, and more overall experiences</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Disclaimer</em><br />
Petzl’s <a href="http://www.vandernet.com/">Finland Distributor Vandernet</a> provided me the Nomic ice tools free of charge for testing, and paid me 1 bazillion € to review them.*</p>

<p><sub><sup><sub><sup>* One of these statements is not true.</sup></sub></sup></sub></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Grivel G20 Crampons]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/grivel-g20-crampons.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-16T21:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/grivel-g20-crampons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you climb up an ice fall a pair of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/steigeisen-eisklettern.html">crampons</a> are necessary - unless you’re Superman and just fly up (where’s the fun in that?). As I set out to climb ice, a pair of yellow Grivel G20 crampons arrived at La Maison Morkel - they are the lightest crampons available, thus it was an easy choice! <em>A Living Review</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8649612650/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8400/8649612650_10ac812b35_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>
<p>The <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-g20-cramp-o-matic-steigeisen.html">Grivel G20 crampons</a> have been used for seven full days of ice climbing. This review should be considered as an initial review, which I will update during the next winter season when I have got more use with them.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8649587814/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8395/8649587814_b29e132ee2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>
<p>Their function is to add more traction if you’re traversing glaciers, are climbing in the mountains and on ice falls. During the course of this year they will likely be used for all three of these activities, though thus far they were used on approaches and for <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/eisklettern.html">ice and mixed climbing</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8652492151/" title="Grivel G20 crampons by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8405/8652492151_b7b023edd8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Grivel G20 crampons" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The G20 is a mono-point crampon, which also has a short secondary front point</li>
  <li>It has a antibot plate in the back which works very well</li>
  <li>The step-in binding is closed with the Cramp-O-Matic system in the back, a wire bail in the front and a safety strap over the ankle</li>
  <li>11 point and a half one =)</li>
  <li>It’s made of Chromolly steel</li>
  <li>It’s an asymmetric crampon with a semi-rigid design</li>
  <li>Has two points under the middle foot</li>
  <li>Comes with an extra com bar</li>
</ul>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/64554113?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>
<p>Fitting the G20 to my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html">Phantom Ultra boots</a> was super easy: In the back you lift the small lever to adjust the length of the crampon to your boot - they suit boots from size 37 to 48. Once the correct length was found I simply slid the boot in the front wire bail, pulled the Cramp-O-Matic lever up and adjusted the tightness via the small dial to the correct fit. Then just close the safety strap and you’re wearing the crampon! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8652497303/" title="Grivel G20 crampons by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8540/8652497303_e788627a45_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Grivel G20 crampons" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>
<p>The <em>pro-active anti-balling plate</em> (or Antibot) is the first of its kind: It gets rid of the snow with every step taken, using its flexibility and the climber’s movement. </p>

<p>The Mono-Rail technology distributes the 11 points in an intelligent and original way, with two points under the middle foot. There’s less bulk because of the Mono-Rail and when not used the crampons pack in a small, tight package.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8653601534/” title=”Grivel G20 crampons</td>
      <td>Antibot by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8266/8653601534_f7ed541c76_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”680” alt=”Grivel G20 crampons</td>
      <td>Antibot”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>
<p>The G20 crampons are Made in Italy. Grivel has made it one of their hallmarks to produce their equipment in Europe. For me the G20 are impeccably made, with lots of attention to detail and innovative ideas. So far I haven’t observed any faults or problems with them. </p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>
<p>848 g for the pair or 424 g per crampon. That’s 54 gram over claimed weight, but still acceptable. Together with my Phantom Ultra that makes a combined weight of crampon and boot of 1342 gram per foot. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8649548598/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8114/8649548598_acd6d0756e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>
<p>The materials used in the G20 are Chromolly steel, Dyneema for the strap, and a bit of plastic and nylon. With the right tools you can take apart the different parts easily and could recycle the crampon easily.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>
<p><em>“Why Grivel and not <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-steigeisen.html">Petzl</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-steigeisen.html">Black Diamond</a> crampons?”</em> some might be wondering. Well, I find <a href="http://grivel.com/">Grivel</a> a very sympathetic company, and it’s a company which since 1818 produces mountaineering equipment in Italy at the foot of the Mont Blanc. They have quite a few innovations to their name, and still continue to produce amazing equipment for Alpine adventures. And with the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-g20-cramp-o-matic-steigeisen.html">G20 crampons</a> being the lightest crampon on the market it was an easy decision for me to get them.</p>

<p>They G20 crampons were super easy to fit my boots, are a compact and light package when not worn, are very easy and fast to put on, and perform for me very great on the ice, mixed and on approaches. On the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> I tried a pair of Petzl Dart mono-point crampons, though they didn’t feel as stable as my G20s. The small extra front point and their asymmetrical design work very well for me, and climbing in them was easy and good fun.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8648625247/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8244/8648625247_b9b2b81d56_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<p>There seems to be some discussions that mono-points aren’t a good choice for beginners, as Dual Points are considered more stable on the ice. I haven’t tried Dual Point crampons yet, so can’t comment on that, though I imagine there’s some truth to that. Mono-points on the other hand are considered the best tool for mixed and harder routes. As a beginner I felt that the G20 were a good choice, and while there were blow-outs these were most often because of sloppy placements and not because of a missing second front point. </p>

<p>Climbing ice and mixed with the G20s felt agile and precise. Especially on rock the mono-point was superb, and the third points were useful for hooking on rocks. On ice the front point was easy to place well, and the second points were, after I reminded myself mentally of a <em>heels down</em> easily connecting to the ice and making for a secure and good stand.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8648541881/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8532/8648541881_aa7feac39e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<p>Because the non-modular points of the G20 need to be sharpened to stay useful for climbing, they get shorter with wear. This means that after a couple of years (or however much one climbs/ sort of climbing) a new pair will be needed, or you just <a href="http://bit.ly/11iHTp3">replace the front piece</a>. The steel used in the G20 is of a high quality, though, and should keep me climbing for a couple of seasons without problems. Furthermore, these one-piece forged crampons are lighter than modular crampons where you can switch the front points. Also, since there are no moving parts, you don’t have to worry about screws coming loose or something which could go broken.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>
<p>The <a href="http://www.petzl.com/en/outdoor/ice-climbing-crampons/dart">Petzl Dart</a> and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-stinger-pro-crampons.html">Black Diamond Stinger</a> are both mono-point crampons, weighing claimed 824 g and 940 g respectively. The Stinger has an Antibot included, the Dart hasn’t - that’s extra weight coming on top to avoid balling. Also the <a href="http://www.camp.it/EN/template01.aspx?codicemenu=1069">Cassin CC</a> is a mono-point crampon and has a claimed weight (without Antibot) of 850 g.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8653596706/" title="Grivel G20 crampons by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8537/8653596706_88ca886f39_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Grivel G20 crampons" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>
<p>Dave Searle reviewed the G20 on <a href="http://coldthistle.blogspot.com/2011/11/grivels-g20-monopoint.html">Cold Thistle</a> and he rates the G20 very high for climbing ice and mixed - read his review to gain further insights on how great these crampons are. The G20 are also Viv Scott’s <a href="http://www.ukclimbing.com/gear/review.php?id=3284">Pick of the Season in this UK CLimbing article</a> (scroll down).</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>
<p>I am very happy with the Grivel G20 crampons. Lightweight, nimble and precise in use, compact and light when carried, fitting my boots perfectly, these were for me the right crampons to start ice and mixed climbing with for me. They’re impeccably made, the Antibot works great and snow building up underneath the crampon is not a problem. The G20 stay sharp rather well and I only needed to take a file to them twice - if you do more mixed or walk over rocks this will be more, obviously. All things considered a superb crampon for what I am doing, and if you’re looking to start ice climbing and want the lightest crampon on the market - then look no further: The Grivel G20 is a great crampon and very light.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633246431786/">Plenty more photos on Flickr</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZvqQfO">Great intro article about crampons on REI</a>.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-grivel-g20">Where to buy the Grivel G20</h2>
<p>At <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-g20-cramp-o-matic-steigeisen.html">Bergzeit</a> they are currently 10% off and cost only 180€.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8648632797/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8542/8648632797_484ff06fe8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>
<ul>
  <li>In the next season I will add more on how they’re in use climbing ice and mixed, for alpine trips and glacier travel, if there were any failures, and more overall experiences</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Disclaiming the Disclaimer.</em><br /></p>

<p><sub><sup><sub><sup>* One of these statements is not true.</sup></sub></sup></sub></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scarpa Phantom Ultra Boots]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-15T21:44:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://en.scarpa.net/products/high-altitude/phantom-ultra/">Scarpa Phantom Ultra</a> is one of the lightest technical climbing boots on the market - for someone like me thus the only real choice for a crampon compatible mountaineering boot for ice climbing. <em>A living review.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8648393473/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8259/8648393473_2acae62fed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>
<p>I have used the Scarpa Phantom Ultra boots for seven full days of ice climbing and a couple of days of walking. This review thus should be considered as an initial review, which I will update during the next winter season when I have got more use with them. </p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>
<p>The function of these boots is manyfold:</p>

<ul>
  <li>keep your feet warm and dry in cold temperatures and wet conditions</li>
  <li>crampon compatible</li>
  <li>comfortable to walk in on long approaches</li>
  <li>rigid sole for climbing</li>
</ul>

<p>So how does the Phantom Ultra do these things? </p>

<ul>
  <li>Dry: Thanks to OutDry’s windproof and waterproof breathable membrane the boots stay dry in wet conditions, while letting your feet’s sweat escape. Don’t expect wonders, though: After a day of climbing the boot will be moist on the inside.</li>
  <li>Warm: They are warm, warmer than any other shoe or boot I have worn in winter, even after a long day outdoors. They are not as warm as double boots like the <a href="http://en.scarpa.net/products/high-altitude/phantom-guide/">Phantom Guide</a> or <a href="http://en.scarpa.net/products/high-altitude/phantom-6000/">Phantom 6000</a>, but for my needs they offer plenty of warmth. If you get very easily cold feet then one of the aforementioned Phantoms might be a better choice, though for me they offer plenty of warmth when out on a -15°C day climbing on frozen waterfalls.</li>
  <li>Crampon compatible: Sure thing, or did you think I climb ice without crampons?!</li>
  <li>Comfortable: As you know, I’m a trailrunner kind-of-guy. I wear them each day on all occasions, so getting into a boot was a new thing. Well, the Phantom Ultras were hailed as very comfortable boots in reviews, and I will join in that song. They are very comfortable. After I got used to walk in boots it was nice to put them on each morning and walk to the ice falls, and even on longer approaches they didn’t harm my feet. So far there have been no blisters or other foot problems, and just a very good, comfortable feeling.</li>
  <li>Stiff sole: The sole on the Phantom Ultra is a Pentax Speed sole, which is considered soft in the midsole. I haven’t been able to feel that, as a soft sole is for me something like the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/07/inov-8-x-talon-190.html">X-Talon 190</a> and the Phantom Ultra are for me rigid. As I have only used the Ultras I obviously can’t compare them to other technical mountaineering boots. Keep in mind though that I have quite small boots (Size 42.5) which are inherently more rigid than larger sized models, where this soft midsole could be easier felt.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8648505633/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8263/8648505633_bddd40045b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<p>Some of the features you already read about above, other things which I really liked:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The laces are great: Easy to knot and open, just the right length and a great match for this boot</li>
  <li>Integrated gaiter means no need for an extra gaiter to keep snow out of your boots</li>
  <li>A Vibram Sole which won’t let you slip on wet rocks</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8648587539/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8399/8648587539_d85e1735a7_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>
<p>My pair is a Size 42.5 and they fit very well. I took them a half number bigger so that I’m not hitting my toes against the inside of the shoe when kicking the crampons in the ice, and that works well.</p>

<p>The boots fit me perfectly. Out of the box. There was no long, painful walks required to make them comfortable and fitting my feet, they just were perfect from the start. Plenty of room for the toes, even in thick socks, a tight fit in the heel, comfortable around the ankle and lower leg, a little bit of flex when walking, rigid enough for climbing. </p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/64554113?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>
<p>Ueli Steck helped develop this boot, and on his recommendation Scarpa partnered with OutDry which provides the WPB membrane for the boot. I feel that OutDry dries faster than Gore Tex in shoes, at least my shoes where, when overnight indoors, dry again the next morning. </p>

<p>Of course the weight of these boots is one of the biggest innovations, there were, as these boots came out, not many comparable boots which were as light and warm. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8649675898/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8253/8649675898_704ce60888_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>
<p>These boots are 100% Made in Italy, and if you know a thing or two about shoes then you likely are aware that the Italians are great craftsman which can make superb shoes and boots. This pair is no different, and the Phantom Ultras are impeccably made. From a smooth outer which is waterproof and which offers no place for stones, snow, dirt and dust to enter or a crampon to snatch a lace to a comfortable inner these boots are exceptionally well made. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8649657680/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8404/8649657680_450088aa26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>
<p>My Phantom Ultras are 1845 gram for the pair or 918 g per shoe, Size 42,5. That’s slightly over the claimed weight of 850 gram per boot but still acceptable for me. The new La Sportiva Batura 2.0 is lighter, as are the new <a href="http://en.scarpa.net/products/tech-mountain/rebel-ultra-gtx/">Scarpa Rebel GTX</a>.</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>
<p>I expect these boots to hold very long. Probably the zipper or the gaiter will be the first ones to go broken, but the sole and boot itself make a very durable impression on me. And even when the sole will wear down, you can get them resoled.</p>

<p><em>More in the future.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8649503430/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8542/8649503430_5321526e53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>
<p>Before I decided to get the Phantom Ultra I did quite a bit of research. Dane from <a href="http://coldthistle.blogspot.com">Cold Thistle</a>, <a href="http://www.relaa.com/">Artturi</a>, <a href="http://lightfromthenorth.blogspot.com">Toby</a>, <a href="http://www.valppaus.com/">Joni</a> and <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/">Nick</a> all have helped me to make the decision. Especially Nick and Dane who also both use the Phantom Ultras have been answering my questions about warmth and sizes - again many thanks for that.</p>

<p>Once the boots were here I decided to go for a walk in them. It’s surprising how different boots feel after years of using only trailrunners and slip-ons. I got used to it pretty quickly though, and appreciated how warm they were. On their <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/climbing-ice.html">first outing</a> we had a short walk-in in deep snow, and walking wasn’t a problem by now anymore. Climbing then.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8495038643/" title="Going up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8086/8495038643_9fc37b4a8f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Going up" /></a></p>

<p>After I put on my crampons, a first for me, I walked up to the ice and started my first ice climb. It wasn’t that cold that day, and my skills were at the beginning, but what they were supposed to do they did: I had warm feet, happily kicked my crampons in the ice and didn’t hit my toes. In <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html">Abisko</a> then the walk-ins were equally short, but in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html">Korouoma</a> we were hiking for up to 45 minutes from the camp (and the hike out back to the car was a strenuous 30 minutes uphill hike!). In these situations the boots performed great too, the secret is to not lace them up to tight - that way the walking is more comfortable. But also because they have a bit of flex they’re good to walk in.</p>

<p>Once I broke through the ice underneath a fall and stood till my knee in ice cold water, but thanks to the integrated gaiter only a tiny bit came inside. But even after this accident I didn’t get cold feet at temperatures of around -10°C, standing on ice at the bottom of a fall belaying my partner leading up a route, which was evidence for their warmth for me.</p>

<p>In Korouoma I also slept outside, and after a full day of climbing the boots were slightly moist from sweat. In the hut I was able to dry them a bit by the stove, but they were next to me in my shelter during the night. As I woke up in the morning it was -15°C and getting in the frozen boots was difficult, but once inside and walking they quickly got warm again, and there were no problems with cold toes/ feet.</p>

<p>Overall I rate them very high: Comfortable to walk in on approaches, rigid soles for climbing, warm when standing on ice and belaying, and keeping my feet dry from the water you’re bound to encounter when ice climbing.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595259545/" title="To-camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8529/8595259545_41385a0094_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="To-camp" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>
<p>A whole lot, but only a handful in the same weight category: the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/la-sportiva-batura-2-0-gtx-schuhe-black-yellow.html">La Sportiva Batura 2.0 GTX</a> is claimed 1800 gram for the pair. It’s the lightest alternative I’m aware of, although the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-nordwand-tl-bergstiefel/">Mammut Nordwand TL</a> is only a few dozen of gram heavier with a claimed weight of 1888 gram. The new <a href="http://en.scarpa.net/products/tech-mountain/rebel-ultra-gtx/">Scarpa Rebel GTX</a> are lighter too, but have no integrated gaiters. If you know other lightweight boots please leave a comment (incl. weight if possible!) and I’ll add them here.</p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>
<p>Dane from <a href="http://coldthistle.blogspot.com/2010/09/scarpa-phantom-ultra.html">Cold Thistle</a> rates the Phantom Ultras very high, as does <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/">Nick</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8648513761/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8111/8648513761_9eb1d3be8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>
<p>I’m very happy with the <a href="http://en.scarpa.net/products/high-altitude/phantom-ultra/">Scarpa Phantom Ultra</a> boots and can recommend them for anyone who is looking for a lightweight boot for ice &amp; mixed climbing and winter mountaineering. They’re warm enough reasonably cold conditions (about -20°C I’d say), keep your feet dry and are comfortable to walk in. They’re great for climbing both ice and mixed, easy to put on and also look very good in my opinion. And after all: Boots that are used by <a href="http://www.uelisteck.ch/en.html">Ueli Steck</a> just can’t be bad =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633246431786/">Plenty more photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-phantom-ultra">Where to buy the Phantom Ultra</h2>
<p>Only the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/scarpa-phantom-ultra-bergstiefel/">Bergfreunde</a> have the Phantom Ultra in stock. However, <a href="http://bit.ly/YimWaK">Backcountry</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/index.php?cl=search&amp;query=Scarpa+Phantom&amp;ref=header">Bergzeit</a> have other Phantom models in case you’re looking for double boot, or contact them and ask if they can get the boots for you.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8648632797/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8542/8648632797_484ff06fe8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra &amp; Grivel G20" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8649527748/" title="Scarpa Phantom Ultra by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8390/8649527748_8e317de4d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scarpa Phantom Ultra" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>
<ul>
  <li>In the next season I will add more on how they’re in use climbing ice and mixed, if there were any failures, and overall experiences</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Disclaiming the Disclaimer</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
