<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: paddling | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/paddling/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-27T22:28:08+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adventures around Lago d'Idro]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/adventures-around-lago-didro.html"/>
    <updated>2012-06-11T10:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/adventures-around-lago-didro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mountains. There’s a distinct lack of them on the coast of Finland. Italy on the other hand has a fair amount of them, and as an invitation to visit the mountains and lakes of the Brescia Province landed in my inbox, with the promise of outdoor adventures, Italian cuisine and hospitality I didn’t need long to think if I’d like to go. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322116630/" title="Lago d'Idro in the morning by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7087/7322116630_b3ff0f31eb_c.jpg" width="800" height="509" alt="Lago d'Idro in the morning" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>A few weeks later I sat on a plane south, from Vaasa via Riga to Milano. Coming out of the airport, I realized that the fleece and hardshell where not needed, and they disappeared in my GORUCK. Driving past by the vast fields and urban sprawl of Northern Italy, soon the Alps, who’s snow-capped tops I saw just a bit earlier from a few thousand meters up high, came into view, and the smile on my face grew. As we drove through the rolling foothills, I spotted high tops &amp; steep cliffs, and as we exit the mountain tunnels narrow valleys with picturesque villages squeezed on its sides appear, and I’m very happy to be here, indeed.</p>

<p>We stopped in a village called Tre Capitelli on the the west shore of Lago d’Idro, in a <a href="http://www.trecapitelli.com/en/home/Welcome.php">holiday village</a> of the same name. I was the first to arrive and had a few hours free time to explore the surroundings until I would be treated to the fine Italian cuisine. Up the mountain or around the lake, what should it be? Easy. I filled up my Osprey HydraForm, which in a wise moment of inspiration at home I threw into the one backpack I took, packed the map I got a bit earlier at the reception in my pants pocket and set off, upwards.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175494975/" title="Untitled by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7227/7175494975_1ce0781aa2_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Untitled" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175491191/" title="Snakes on the trail. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7071/7175491191_cabeb10cb5_c.jpg" width="800" height="384" alt="Snakes on the trail." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175494629/" title="Wildflowers and mountains by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7103/7175494629_487b6bd8a8_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Wildflowers and mountains" /></a></p>

<p>I got a bit lost on the way to the trail, and was walking up steep roads, lined with small cottages, trees in blossom and a wild variety of flowers. After having explored the wrong trail until I came to the conclusion that it can’t be the right one I headed back, took another street up and almost immediately happened on the red-white markings which indicate the trail. I had about two hours until dinner, and put on some speed in my ambitious goal to reach the ridge, a mere five hundred something meters of ascent.</p>

<p>It didn’t take long till the sweat started running in the 26°C we had, and me realizing that fivehundred meters ascent aren’t to be made in one and half hours. I lowered my goal, and continued until six o’clock, leaving me an hour to get back down and take a shower. Having given up on my goal, I was able to enjoy the trail more, I felt, taking in the different scents and colours around me, listening to the birds singing. A bit after I started going down, a thunderstorm was making itself known further up the valley, and I decided I made the right move to not continue.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175502571/" title="Follow the red white markings by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8018/7175502571_d6ee22f3e8_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Follow the red white markings" /></a></p>

<p>After a refreshing shower and slipping into the other pants and shirt I brought along and having washed the sweaty one and hanging it up to dry, I commenced to the <a href="http://www.laterrazzaidro.com/joomla/">Restaurant La Terrazza</a>, where I meet with Roberto of <a href="http://www.bresciatourism.it/">Brescia Tourism</a> and Nadja from Nomad Earth, one of the other five bloggers who were invited to this trip. We had an Aperitivo on the terrace, overlooking the Idro Lake, and soon were having great conversations about Lago d’Idro, Brescia Province, Italy, food, blogging and life.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175514161/" title="Aperitivo by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7211/7175514161_550959385a_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Aperitivo" /></a></p>

<p>Thursday morning I woke early, heading down to the shore to take some photos of the gorgeous, silent lake with the mountains mirroring themselves in it. At breakfast I met David of Pure Outdoor, and soon we were chatting lifely about our families and outdoor adventures, me happily listening to his tips for going outdoors with babys. After gathering our gear we headed over to Camping Azur and <a href="http://www.surfpoint.it/english/index.htm?english">Surfpoint Vantone</a> on the other side of the lake, where we took open top Kayaks for a paddle on the lake.</p>

<p>“<i>Do you want a neoprene suit</i>?” asks Leo, the owner. “<i>Nah, I don’t plan to get wet</i>” I answer. “<i>How about cliff jumping? We installed ropes for climbing up the cliff and jumping into the lake</i>”. Minutes later, I’m squeezing myself into a neoprene suit. The lake is silent in front of us, but Leo assures us that in 30 minutes the wind will come up. We paddle over the lake, enjoying the gorgeous scenery. The mystique emancipating from the mountains engulfs me, wisps of cloud hanging in the neighboring valley, while a red kite circles above us and lands on the cliff. I put my <a href="http://bit.ly/PSvHLe">GoPro HD HERO2 Camera</a> on, climb up, and jump. The water was colder than expected, but after a few seconds the neo does its job, and it ain’t too bad anymore. Again and again David and I take turns to climb and jump, until the wind comes, as Leo said, and we decide to return.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322578004/" title="Open top kayaking on Lago d'Idro by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7102/7322578004_b8caed53f7_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Open top kayaking on Lago d'Idro" /></a></p>

<p>Back on land we meet Axel from <a href="http://outdoorseite.de/">Outdoorseite.de</a>, Michael from mountainzones.com and Mario from SchoeneBergtouren.de and the group now complete, we head for lunch. While we eat we chat lively over past trips, future trips, the excellent food and ignore the rain which falls now. As the rain stops, and we have an hour to be in Vesta, we decide to walk there; the narrow road along the shore of the lake makes for a pleasant stroll, tunnels, forests and cliffs making the scenery interesting.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175522231/" title="After the rain by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7223/7175522231_da48c42a02_c.jpg" width="800" height="339" alt="After the rain" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175521481/" title="Tunnels by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7238/7175521481_dc413da760_c.jpg" width="800" height="532" alt="Tunnels" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322595244/" title="Streetart by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8154/7322595244_5232563f07_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Streetart" /></a></p>

<p>At the beach in Vesta we meet Guido, an International Mountain Guide for <a href="http://www.liberavventura.it/www.liberavventura.it/Home_page.html">LiberAvventura</a>, who is going to take us via ferrata-ing up a wall, rappeling it down, and then climbing it up again. This was for me easily one of the best activities, not only because of the superb location of the rock and Guido being an excellent Guide, but because I really love climbing. All six of us enjoyed ourselves immensely, and time flew by - too fast for my taste, but then I always can come back!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7360748974/" title="Map by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8150/7360748974_010eb45a20_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Map" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322616380/" title="Up Resy by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7081/7322616380_5eab4fcd87_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Up Resy" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175529295/" title="David rappeling by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7099/7175529295_126a8d7526_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="David rappeling" /></a></p>

<p>We walked the path back to the beach, where six mountain bikes were waiting for us, sans a cycling Guide. Helmets were equipped with GoPro HERO Cameras and soon we were on the road around the lake, cycling back to our accomodation. A fine climb made us lose our breath, and on the start of the descent I tested my frontwheel brake and caught my ensulting fall on camera, good fun! First Aid was applied to my hand, and the journey continued, down 20% steep streets, through narrow village streets back to the shore and onwards home. A cold beer was how we rewarded ourselves, before getting ready for the fine food at the La Terrazza restaurant - and excellent it was! Local delicacies were consumed, while conversation around the table was merry till late in the evening.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322748122/" title="Our group &amp; MTB Guide by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7103/7322748122_5f8d51ec9b_c.jpg" width="800" height="381" alt="Our group &amp; MTB Guide" /></a></p>

<p>Friday morning after breakfast we were picked up by three <a href="http://www.liberavventura.it/www.liberavventura.it/Parapendio.html">Paragliding</a> Pilots, who took us in two groups of three up a gorgeous alp. While Axel, Nadja and me ran around snapping photos of the gorgeous scenery, our Pilots made our Parachutes ready for take off. Strapped in into harnesses and getting instructions on how to start, we took off; running down the alp until the wind lifted us of our feet and we were flying! Under us the roofes of tiny mountain villages, the narrow streets obscured by red tile roofs, Andrea, my pilot, hands me the straps for flying the parachute, and directs me where to go. Flying over the blue water of the Idro lake, Andrea asks if I’m ready - and upon my positive reply, we head down in a twister movement towards the lake, adrenaline rushing through my body. He pulls us back up, a short moment of weightlessness before we fall into a second twister towards the landing area. As we lost enough altitude, we go back to smooth sailing, and to quickly I’m back on my feet again, a massive grin on my face.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322765454/" title="Paragliding by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7241/7322765454_0c452d504d_c.jpg" width="800" height="374" alt="Paragliding" /></a></p>

<p>The other three guys head up the alp to take their flights, and we wander around at the landing space, waiting to see their parachutes appear in the sky. As also they have landed, Guido is appearing, and brings us over to the Garda lake, where we will spend the afternoon. But first, lunch at <a href="http://www.rimbalzello.com/">Rimbalzello</a>. Nothing beats the Italian cuisine, and satisfied and strengthened the seven of us head over the street to the <a href="http://www.rimbalzelloadventure.com/">Adventure Park</a>, where we complete the “difficult” route in no time. This was just the warm-up, though, the real highlight was yet to come.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322783306/" title="Untitled by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7081/7322783306_413a8b7ff2_c.jpg" width="800" height="410" alt="Untitled" /></a></p>

<p>We drove onwards, passing the busy shore towns of Lake Garda, and took a left, driving serpentine roads up the mountain. As we stop, Guido hands us neoprene suits, neoprene boots and a harness, which we all put dutifully on, before commencing on a hike over lush forest paths, leading us further down the gorge. Hiking in a neoprene suit at 27°C is a great way to lose weight, btw. But soon we arrive at the cool, refreshing stream which has formed deep pools, slides and waterfalls on its way down the valley over the thousands of years it runs down here. GoPros are switched on again (resulting in a outtakes video of “<i>Is my camera on?</i>” scenes) and then it is off down the canyon, doing some serious canyoning. We start easy, if you consider rappeling down a waterfall easy, that is. Guido tells us when it is safe to jump, how and when to slide down a chute, and belays us when we rappel down. The jumps and rappels get longer and longer, and at the biggest jump, some ten meters over a waterfall into a deep pool, it is Nadja, the only girl, who jumps first &amp; shows us guys how it is done! </p>

<p>And so we travel down the canyon, swimming in pools, seeing the gorge how you can only see it if you travel it down this way. At the longest rappel and slide, some 50 meters of descent, a green roof engulfs the deep pool in which we land, a great place for a swim. As we’re all safe down, we continue onwards, jumping in pools and sliding down more chutes, until we arrive at the take-out; where a police woman waits for us; Guido produces his ID and she checks it, as well as if this trip has been declared - there are unauthorized groups with dodgy equipment offering tours down the canyon, and Guido tells scary stories of how people with electrical wires in jeans where attempting to do what we just did.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7360768678/" title="Hiking in neoprene suits by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7214/7360768678_86a74e63d9_c.jpg" width="800" height="493" alt="Hiking in neoprene suits" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322809850/" title="Canyoning by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7224/7322809850_9ea96e189d_c.jpg" width="800" height="557" alt="Canyoning" /></a></p>

<p>We ride back to the Café where we slip back into our dry clothes, and drink a cold beer, remembering the experience. Sitting in the hot sun, we soon wish back the cold pools for some refreshment, but we head on, to the <a href="http://www.zanzanu.it/en/">Zanzanu Hotel</a>, for a shower, as the sun already is slowly sinking toward the mountains in the west, casting long shadows over the Lago di Garda. We ride to the gorgeous <a href="http://www.agrilambic.it/">Agriturismo Al Lambic</a> restaurant, and seated in a thousand year old cellar I enjoy the best food yet on this trip. Local cheeses, house made chestnuts Tortelloni with mountain butter and Tiramisù make for an perfect dinner. We all chat lively about the past days, in which we squeezed a great amount of exciting outdoor activities; and how we plan to return with our families in the future. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322827920/" title="Untitled by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7214/7322827920_7f088a15d6_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Untitled" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322829472/" title="Cheese! by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7245/7322829472_0463cd513a_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Cheese!" /></a></p>

<p>Back at the hotel, we sip a final beer on the terrace, overlooking the silent Garda lake, illuminated at the shore by lights from villages, street lanterns and the moon. Tomorrow we are all again on the way back home, to Austria, Germany and Finland, but the memories of Lago d’Idro and Lago di Garda will stay with us for a long time.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7360769040/" title="Morning glory by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7229/7360769040_b467a27c3c_c.jpg" width="800" height="349" alt="Morning glory" /></a></p>

<p>So what was the best thing on this trip? While I am tempted to say rock climbing &amp; canyoning, it really were the people who made this trip so great. Meeting Roberto, who did a superb job in organizing this trip for us, and Nadja, Axel, David, Michael &amp; Mario was a pleasure and I dare say we were a great group who had a great few days. Guido was one of the best guides I have meet; the staff at the hotels and restaurants was a prime example of Italian hospitality and friendliness. <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157630015454288/">More Photos</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/43411086?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=f2070b" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<p>
<a href="http://vimeo.com/43411086">Adventures around Lago d'Idro - Teaser</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/hendrikmorkel">Hendrik Morkel</a> on <a href="http://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p>

<p>A full short movie is coming soon-ish - check the Teaser above to get a taste!</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Getting there</strong>: All major airlines fly to Italy; the nearest airports to Lake Idro are Milano and Bergamo, from where you can get with the a bus or taxi to Lago d’Idro. Check <a href="http://www.hipmunk.com/">Hipmunk</a> for flights; I flew with airBaltic who were punctual, had friendly service and flew directly from Vaasa.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7175543401/" title="Untitled by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7225/7175543401_6ff4ec0e65_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Untitled" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Staying there</strong>: There are various accomodation options around the lake, from camping places over holiday cottages to hotels. <a href="http://www.trecapitelli.com/en/home/Welcome.php">Villagio Tre Capitelli</a> was a very friendly place in a great location, and would work great as a basecamp for outdoor activities around the lake. They offer a guided mountain walk up to the ridge behind the village. On the east side of the lake_href=”http://www.azur-camping.de/nord-italien/idro.html”target=”_blank”&gt;Azur Camping&lt;/a&gt; offers camping possibilities for those who rather go that route; they also have modern Mountain bikes for rent, as well as open top kayaks &amp; a surf school. Full list of <a href="http://www.lagodidro.it/lang/EN/homepage">Lake Idro accommodation</a> possibilities.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7322576248/" title="Tre Capitelli apartments by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7076/7322576248_6438b0e1a2_c.jpg" width="800" height="420" alt="Tre Capitelli apartments" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What to do</strong>: There are plenty of great outdoor activities available at Lago d’Idro and Lago di Garda. My recommendations are Canyoning and Rock Climbing, and with <a href="http://www.liberavventura.it/www.liberavventura.it/Home_page.html">LiberAvventura</a> you will be in friendly and professional hands for these activities <a href="http://www.italianoutdoor.it/">Guido’s English site</a>. Rent a mountain bike and explore the mountains with pedaling power, or get a kayak and see the lake &amp; mountains from the water. If that’s too much using own energy, go paragliding and see the area from above; which definitley will be something you will remember. Andrea, Alberto &amp; Giulio have thousands of flights amongst them and will treat you to a very special experience.</p>

<p><strong>Eating</strong>: Going to Brescia Province you want to taste the local food, which, in case you didn’t get that yet, is superb. For me the Italian cuisine is the best in the world and this trip was a pleasure in culinary terms. From the excellent cheeses from the region over the cured meats to the tasty fresh salads, make sure to experience the full Antipasti, Primero, Secundi and Dolci Menu. I can highly recommend the Restaurant <a href="http://w_grilambic.it">Agriturismo Al Lambic</a> which is one of the secret tips of the region and is popular with locals and visitors alike. Best of all is that eating out in the region is very affordable, a delicious three course meal will usually not be more than 25€ excluding drinks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7360769944/" title="Pizza by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr._/7082/7360769944_0835d59b45_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Pizza" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Lago d’Idro and Lago di Garda</strong>: While Lago di Garda is a big lake with a Mediterranean flair &amp; temperatures, touristically fully developed; La_‘Idro is a small lake which you can’t even completely drive around. Idro lake is a lot more relaxed, with less bustle, and is excellent for those people who want to do outdoor activities in a calm atmosphere; while Garda lake offers you activities around the clock. Both have plenty to offer, you just need to know if you want it more relaxed [<i>Idro</i>] or want more possibilities and night life [<i>Garda</i>]. In the end they’re only about 45 minutes by car apart, so you can experience both if you’re in the region!</p>

<p><strong>What else</strong>: Italy has the Euro and is for us Northern Europeans very affordable &amp; offers great value for your money. Italians are friendly and _pful, even if they do not speak English, and Italian hospitality is something to experience.</p>

<p>If you look for a bit of variety between your outdoor adventures, then the amount of culture the country has to offer will not disappoint you. Wa_hrough narrow conblestone streets in villages and towns which are many hundreds of years old, visit old castles towering over medival cities and museums. Sip an espresso on a terrace of a Café, or eat an ice cream while walking along the shores of the lake.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The five other bloggers and me were invited by Brescia Tourism to this trip, and they paid for our transporation, food, accomodation and activities.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jongunjoki and Ruunaa River Paddling Expedition - Part III]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/06/jongunjoki-and-ruunaa-river-paddling-expedition-part-iii.html"/>
    <updated>2011-06-14T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/06/jongunjoki-and-ruunaa-river-paddling-expedition-part-iii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
And the final installment of this rather long trip report!<br /><br />---<br /><br />On the way to the &lt;a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/page.asp?Section=5445"target="_blank"&gt;Ruunaa Hiking Area we stopped in a small village, where we shopped some groceries - that means German Bratwurst, bananas, apples and more chocolate for me! After this brief stint into civilization we continue to the next basecamp, the Siikakosi parking and fire site at the end of the Ruunaa river. The site was "meh" in regards to "Great places to pitch" but I found a halfway decent site with a nice view on the river, even though the wind was blowing mighty fine where I was located.<br /><br />The evening exercise was to scout the two last rapids which we would run tomorrow. Now Jongunjoki was a small river, and Ruunaa was quite a different ballgame. A good thirty or more meters across, deep and fast this was a big river, and so where its rapids. The last rapid was Siikakoski, a mere Class I - but because of its 1,2 km length, and being right after the Class II Murrookoski, quite different from the Class I rapids on Jongunjoki.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xPTTeGtoKkFDtvPSOec38-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-04C-SgK7egg/TeJ-v9TWg9I/AAAAAAAAEf4/BJfZjoJELIY/s640/P1020284.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Off you go.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/E3dYE67mY1PEINZCTiY4XeAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-bnt22B_51e4/TeJ-xiUYCOI/AAAAAAAAEf8/g1vleU5Allc/s640/P1020287.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Siikakoski bridge. In the Ruunaa Hiking area there were plenty of bridges for walkers to cross the river on dry feet.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/kfHShTuVRgzJTB5UoX18iOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-uSgG4nbAu6M/TeJ-_dTXwRI/AAAAAAAAEgM/ydfK6_rB8Vg/s640/P1020313.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/QLthVCECJqw9tLhnR5FnFeAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-zIOVWCVwDD8/TeJ-2WIWgxI/AAAAAAAAEgA/3kRbpEmQKS8/s640/P1020302.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />One of the surely dozens of laavus along the river, a fine view and great soundscape. Fishermen will love the installed smoke ovens where you can smoke your freshly caught trout and grayling!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/PH-ljsN3lIo4pP-9xLw5f-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hzwIcXgwW-g/TeJ-8WH11UI/AAAAAAAAEgE/O564NcHOkHY/s640/P1020312.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Jeq0xQF53F5LAMP3jZ-n4OAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-uZ3rZs9cWoU/TeJ_DG0b2CI/AAAAAAAAEgQ/x4NgQqM0pc8/s640/P1020315.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Murrokoski rapid, a fast Class II<br /><br />Tuesday, a full day paddling on Ruunaa. Wake up early, breakfast, pack the belongings needed for the day, hop on the car and drive up to Matkalahti. While we unpack and load the canoes and kayaks, and generally lounge in the sun, the cars depart back to camp and one comes back. A lot later than expected we start, happily the weather is brilliant, warm sunshine makes paddling a bliss and even makes the strong headwind less of a problem - at least on the first stretch.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ocZamQhY9bi9ZAbIcwMYm-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-yOgfOWs49jM/TeJ_QvxZi8I/AAAAAAAAEgk/as3PEXb0N1g/s640/P1020334.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Departure.<br /><br />Haapavitja was the first serious rapid that day, Class II, some two or three very deep haystacks, big rocks, more haystacks, several hundred meters long. Being with someone in a canoe I haven't paddled with before, this was a serious test for our teamwork. Despite some very different approaches (I was the bow paddler, my preferred position in a canoe) we managed to go down the rapid without capsizing, despite going sideways into the haystacks. Some miraculous saves on both ends were likely responsible for that, and down the rapid we went to collect the canoe of some classmates which were less lucky. <br /><br />As we had two capsizes at this rapid, and it already being fairly late, we had lunch at the Korpiniemi laavu before continuing. The wind picked up, and our traverse of the Neitijärvi lake was quite strenuous despite trying to stay in the wind-sheltered side of the lake. After a good hour of paddling into the headwind we reached the Neitikoski rapid, Class II that day due to the "low" water. A big stopper wave right there in the middle, followed by some deep haystacks.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/QmbRd3gHZtMC9KvB5gLD9OAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Gy8lB9BxVPc/TeJ_XDxkVAI/AAAAAAAAEgs/W-X18iErVOQ/s640/P1020346.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Neitikoski. <br /><br />Kayaks were to go first, with canoes to follow, one at a time. Daily leader in kayak: Pass. Petri: Pass. Teacher: capsize. Next kayak: capsize. First canoe: capsize. 2nd canoe: capsize (that was us). Third canoe: capsize. Fourth canoe: Pass! (That were our two 50 year old ladies - really awesome =). Final kayak: capsize.<br /><br />What a ride. The key success is simple: Either go full power forward for the stopper wave and paddle like a madman (or woman!) to get over it, or backwards ferry-glide on the right side of the deep stream in order to go down the right, easy side, bypassing the stopper wave. The latter was our plan, but our communication and different paddling techniques made short work of that plan - the main stream picked us and all I said was "Full power forwards" with my stern paddler saying "wtf? Oh no..." as we went diagonal for the stopper wave. For a moment it looked like we could make it over it, and possibly we were, but then we tipped backwards and took a bath in the cold stream, holding on to our paddles and canoe.<br /><br />Petri was there right away to tow our canoe, and us holding on to it, to the nearest shore. From there we saw how the other canoes and kayaks, one for one, capsized and were rescued. Our two ladies, who made it through, reported that they were sitting nearly knee-deep in water and that there wasn't much space left and they also would have capsized. But as it were, they were the only ones who made it through in a canoe - Congratulations again on this way! <br /><br />As nearly 80% of the class and a teacher took a dip, we stopped at the laavu not far away from the rapid, lighted a fire and dried ourselves. I grabbed some nuts, dried fruits and a Snickers Bar I had saved just for such an occasion (!) to warm myself up from the inside, while drying out my clothes by the fire. But we only had come half way, so soon we continued, over another lake into the headwind. <br /><br />Over the next few rapids - Kattilakoski, Murrookoski and finally Siikakoski - people started to shiver, lose motivation and concentration and hence we had quite a few more capsizes. My stern paddler and me, well, we had a few more miraculous saves from near-capsizes, conversations which are too foul to write down here (What happens on the river, stays on the river!) and picked up a few more paddles, canoes and swimmers until we made it to the campsite. <br /><br />After this long hard day, paddling on a big river, we all went off to our shelters, switched into dry clothes and grabbed our cooking gear to head back to the common fire, where everyone was cooking while we discussed the day gone by. Preparation for the final day. The day that my classmate and me would be daily leaders.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/T1ujSznxLWTkBiCeMFigv-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-IvDKCIQj6ac/TeJ_JyryTEI/AAAAAAAAEgc/B3hh4FArVNY/s640/P1020328.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />The end of the Siikakoski rapid. On the right side by the yellow speck (its a rowboat) was our camp.<br /><br />I wake up on Wednesday morning at 6.30 and the sound of rain on Spinnaker informes me of less than great weather. On my round to wake up the other people, the feeling that some are less motivated and interested in paddling is split pretty much in the middle. As we gather around 8.30 around the fire to discuss the day ahead, it becomes clear that we have a good 50% of "difficult" clients which don't want to paddle but would prefer hiking - the many capsizes from yesterday together with the rain and wind make makes this quite understandable. Negotiations with Petri and our teacher, and among my daily leader partner and me bring different possibilities to the front, and after we made one decision, some more thinking and discussing, and a final decision we decide to split the group in two - paddlers and hikers. This way we make everyone happy, a much better decision than the compromise we decided on earlier - it is good to be flexible in decision making =)<br /><br />Everyone grabs the gear and we drive off to Neitikoski, where the hikers started their day trip back to camp while the paddlers try their luck against Neitikoski again and then continue to paddle to camp. My daily leader partner, an additional driver (as I don't have a driving license) and me stay with with the cars and organize the afternoon and evening programme. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xqWrf_bVmvGIvwPkzdHTBeAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-2AMiHEy6oTM/TeJ_dkxirRI/AAAAAAAAEg0/qD4VrA184ew/s640/P1020375.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/YGTKU6iEFOafVdutfxLTmOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WktlkdEvqEA/TeJ_f-FRNMI/AAAAAAAAEg4/OPOzbr0-mIE/s640/P1020376.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/UTTYeLRDoQ-beuwcDrSX4uAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-tVv-HT_V0Ss/TeJ_ikBXEwI/AAAAAAAAEg8/cjSBitXIiK4/s640/P1020377.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/7FUj2DaZfVvaakGyjJDEsOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-dEpHuzza_Wg/TeJ_mL20yjI/AAAAAAAAEhA/piQ2E-nPO08/s640/P1020401.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Also teachers and paddling instructors capsize sometimes at Neitikoski =)<br /><br />With watching the paddlers try their luck over Neitikoski (only one who made it over it!) and checking with them that they're OK, we head of to the nearby Nature Centre to pick up the key for the Sauna, have a look at the exhibition, a coffee and pulla before checking out a nearby bird watching tower. Back at camp I start a fire and not too soon at all, as the paddlers already arrive. They didn't take a lunch break and paddled all the way down, and hence are happy about the fire and being able to eat now. <br /><br />I check with Petri if it is OK for me to wander off and do Siikakoski in my packraft, on my own. Permission granted, I wander the 1,5 km up, inflate, motivate, put on my helmet and PFD and jump in. An interesting ride, and very different from the previous ones: Deep haystacks with headwind mean I need to give 110%, leaning forward and paddle strongly to not flip over and capsize. In the end I make it without problems, and even was able to practice a bit of eddy hoping and ferry gliding in the Alpaca. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/gk_EOse74Q5-7P72FNTbL-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-HqtLOUVIfCI/TeJ_spPAjJI/AAAAAAAAEhI/cVxk2We_Jx4/s640/P1020410.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Packraft vs. kayak!<br /><br />I arrive with a smile on my face back at camp, around the same time that the sun is making an appearance. A tad later our hikers arrive, and with the clients gathering their sauna gear we set off in the cars. We drop off my daily leader partner to start heat the sauna while I take the "clients" to a nearby bird watching tower at the Reposuo mire area, and after having a look around we head back to the warm sauna. Ladies first, men next (men just need a lot longer in sauna =), sausages, pancakes, banter, a rain shower, sunshine, happiness.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/E6U075k3AuqYaWE-EGN6pOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-wJKxcxrx_yY/TeJ_vPdPteI/AAAAAAAAEhM/fnB7nOc_giw/s640/P1020412.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/OlzM4u4toWnQxqrGrpQLhuAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-eq-iHgYYudE/TeJ_zGpZs5I/AAAAAAAAEhU/6W53mbxs9eE/s640/P1020421.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Reposuo info board and part of the mire. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/amjETY3UVsSkHO6CnDzWp-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-XCgYFwoeiuo/TeJ_2pUcAOI/AAAAAAAAEnw/s5XhHAikWm4/s640/P1020428.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />View from the Sauna.<br /><br />We get feedback on our daily leader performance, which was largely positive though a comment came up that none of us two daily leaders where actually with the "clients" but that on the other hand it would not have worked any other way. Everyone is happy, pancakes are shared and after that we leave the sauna and head back to camp. A final fire, instructions for the next day, and we head of to bed. <br /><br />The next day is getting up at 6.30 o'clock, packing, breakfast, loading the car and heading back home. A way too long nine hour drive and we're back in Kuru, unloading personal gear and heading soon after to the local pizza &amp; beer joint!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/gtkRTHxBd2aFOsQJQ4YLzOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-t7XEveuupxQ/TeKAH5Hif6I/AAAAAAAAEn4/wL00aMC8YDQ/s640/P1020450.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />Basecamp the last three nights.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Xl6Fil3xvj6ZcznIXpeRZ-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-NYhpVlLb6RE/TeKAJYuUJUI/AAAAAAAAEh8/W8Rm9IGO-h4/s640/P1020457.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Last morning - time to head home!<br /><br />So that was the final expedition-like trip of the Kuru International Wilderness Guide school, and in my opinion the best one. Responsible for that is largely Petri, who was an excellent teacher and who made paddling fun, interesting while also on land disclosing some useful tips &amp; tricks for us Wilderness Guides to-be. And of course, for me personally, for being so cool and supporting with the packrafting - not a given, and very appreciated. <br /><br />Reflections then? Well, canoeing is fun. While UL principles are not super necessary (canoes can carry plenty of gear without much influence on how the canoe runs), I think they allow for nicer paddling if you're lightly loaded. Paramount to good paddling is good communication and a similar paddling style - I only had that with one person, communication was perfect: It was without words. Whatever my action in the bow, I knew my partner in the back would do the corresponding strokes, resulting in a perfect paddle, be it on a lake or down a Class II+ rapid. Without a good partner canoeing is still fun, but adds a bit of unneeded stress - thoughts like "Will he/ she jump ship/ get nervous/ remember the right strokes/ clamber the railing?" will go through my head, and that's stuff I don't need. <br /><br />Kayaking is fun as well. It is fast - I imagine 60 to 80 km days under fine conditions are no problem, given that you're starting early and paddle late. Navigating the seakayaks on rapids was "meh" and I am not intending to do that again; however, play kayaks and white water kayaks like the red one next to my packraft above should be fun on rivers. <br /><br />Problem of both canoe and kayak is that they are made for paddling, and not hiking &amp; paddling (let alone cycling). That is fine if you want to paddle, but is a problem if you want to combine different activities. Yeah, portage is possible, but doing any serious distance with carrying/ pulling such a vessel on a trolley is not possible. Which brings us to the packraft.<br /><br />The perfect vessel for hiking AND paddling (AND cycling). Very forgiving on white water - it was by far the easiest vessel to run rapids with, and a lot more fun. But forget paddling lakes, especially if it is windy - that's where you roll it up, strap it to your pack and walk. It probably looks a lot more dangerous, (my teacher kept on referring to it as a "playboat" whereas Petri saw the options it opened for combined activities) but given that you're alone and it being a very forgiving vessel, I think even complete novices will find running up to Class II rapids no problem in it, and once you have experience even Class III and IV should be no problem - with and without a load. <br /><br />The packraft is pretty hard to capsize. I didn't yet once capsize in one, and a good friend, who paddles a lot more canoe &amp; kayak, had a very hard time to capsize in it (he managed it in the end =). However, going down those deep haystacks at Siikakoski, with headwind, I realized that if you just sit back and paddle in a relaxed way, capsizing is definitely possible and will happen. You need to concentrate, and you need to know how to read waterways. If you have gained that experience, then complete new adventures open up to you, in which you for a weight gain of some 3,6 kg (Packraft including a spraydeck and a paddle) gain endless new opportunities to explore and experience nature. <br /><br />So much for the moment. I shall follow up with the by now traditional &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/search/label/food"target="_blank"&gt;Food For Thought and a &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/search/label/Gear%20Talk%3A%20Gear%20that%20worked%20and%20gear%20that%20didn%27t"target="_blank"&gt;Gear that worked and gear that didn't posts in the near future =)</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
