<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bouldering | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/bouldering/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-05T16:28:38+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Petzl RocTrip 2014 - Eastern Europe]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/petzl-roctrip-2014-eastern-europe.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-28T18:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/petzl-roctrip-2014-eastern-europe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Romania, Bulgaria, Macedonia, Greece and Turkey are host to the 2014 Petzl RocTrip which this year takes the form of a road trip. Come and join this great event and hang out with the likes of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">Ueli Steck</a>, Saïd Belhaj, Dave Graham, Mélissa Le Nevé, Nina Caprez and many more while exploring the crazy good climbing that can be had in Eastern Europe!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14843495327" title="Petzl RocTrip 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14843495327_53dc68084a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl RocTrip 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The first time I became aware of the <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en">Petzl RocTrip</a> was in 2011, when I saw some photos from the event in China. Then in 2012 the video of the event was published and it was mind-blowing. I still love to watch it, and if you have a moment watch it here.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/EcU255XBlcI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In 2013 the Petzl RocTrip traveled to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QllWNEGBKic">Argentina</a> and it was equally inspiring. In 2013 it returned closer to home to the Gorges du Tarn, and now in 2014 the event is back and takes a new, unique format: A road trip across five countries in Eastern Europe. This is a great idea on so many levels, as it promotes what climbing is about in many ways: Travel to new crags, explore new countries, meet new people, climb new types of rock, experience different cultures. In a way it is promoting the dirtbag lifestyle, in a slightly more comfortable way! The teaser sets the mood well:</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/92311979?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>What is special about the RocTrip are the low costs for taking part in the event: It’s just 15€! Comparing that to the costs of some other events this is <em>very affordable</em>. It’s well organized (<a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/practical-information">check the practical information</a>) and you get the opportunity to climb in some unique locations with members of the <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/news/spend-time-your-favorite-athletes-during-2014-petzl-roctrip">Petzl Pro Team</a>. </p>

<p>Interested? Then <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/join-us">pre-register until August 31th, 2014</a> to one (or all!) of the camps you would like to join. <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/practical-information#Transport">Organize your transportation</a>, for example join the carpool or get a ride in the Petzl bus. Book your flights (I’m flying to Antalya which is a smooth connection if flying from Helsinki, Stockholm or Oslo). Then start your <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html">climbing training</a> so you’re fit for the hundreds of routes which will be waiting for you! The Petzl Roctrip website has a lot more information available, so check it out, pick the locations you want to join and pre-register! </p>

<p>I will be joining the Roctrip on the last two stops in <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/base-camp/geyikbayiri-turkish-style-columns">Geyikbayiri</a> and <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/base-camp/olympos-climb-sky-fall-water">Olympos</a> and you’ll be able to read about it here and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>. But I really hope to meet some of you in Turkey =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en" title="Petzl RocTrip 2014 website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5593/14867744620_2815c6ed8c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="640" alt="Petzl RocTrip 2014 website" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gimme Kraft!]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html"/>
    <updated>2014-06-10T10:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lacking <em>Kraft</em> to do your project or carry your UH pack? Then <a href="http://gimmekraft.com/">Gimme Kraft</a> is the book that helps you develop the power you need to send your next problem.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3890/14385371581_1329c62e2d_b.jpg#tl-532816872920317954;1043138249" class="alwaysThinglink" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Kraft, die [kraft]: Vermögen, Fähigkeit zu wirken; [körperliche oder geistige] Stärke</em> / <em>Kraft is German for power, force, strength</em></p>

<p><strong>It’s not about power, it’s about technique</strong> was my bouldering teachers opening line to our group of eager students. And seeing him - a thin and tall guy - climb several rounds upside down in our boulder cave, it’s easy to agree. We went on to learn proper boulder technique, first indoors, then took it to the rocks of Vaasa. But of course some Kraft does help, especially if you already have a good technique. However, Kraft does not magically appear from going climbing - that much I have learned in the three odd years since I have rekindled my passion for the art. Kraft comes from training. Being dedicated in developing a training routine, sticking to it and mixing it up as needed, that’s what this fine book from one of Germany’s best climbing gyms, <a href="http://cafekraft.de/">Café Kraft</a> helps you do. </p>

<p>When you pick up the book you realize that here people were writing who know what they’re talking about. The authors have worked with athletes like Alex Megos, Mayan Smith-Gobat, Stefan Glowacz, Sasha DiGiulian and many more, and have sat down to write this fine training book. It’s bi-lingual in English and Deutsch and comes with a DVD where the exercises can be viewed, as well as extra footage of Wolfgang Güllich training. The book starts out with an introduction to effective climbing training - you get a password to download the full 16 page introduction pdf online - and then sets out with dozens of exercises. The exercises are divided into different categories, like the Bouldering Wall, Pull-Ups, Rings, Floor &amp; Minibars, amongst others.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2908/14202091729_e331c948dd_b.jpg#tl-532816872635105282;1043138249" class="alwaysThinglink" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<p>This really being the first time I set out to train (apart from many years of Kenjutsu) I adhered to the books tips to do most of my training as climbing. In the Bouldering Wall chapter there’s several good exercises which not just train you, but also help you to improve your technique. At home I do the floor exercises and train on the two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/metolius-rock-rings-3d-trainingsgriffe/">Metolius Rock Rings</a>, though I will need to switch the exercises up soon (the book recommends you change up your training routine at the latest every six weeks as otherwise you’re stagnating). I definitely have seen an increase in power, stamina and also feel like I climb better since I started to work out, and as the book is small and light I also usually carry it along to the boulders to see if there’s a new exercise I could try. </p>

<p>One critic I have about the book it’s that they put the video instructions on a DVD. Living in a household without TV (and DVD Player) and also all our computers being without DVD Drives, I have no opportunity to watch the videos. I’d rather would have seen the videos being available online to stream or download, which makes a lot more sense than a DVD. </p>

<p>Other than that this book really is great, and not just for climbers - though they obviously will benefit the most from reading it and doing the exercises. If you’d like to get more Kraft, get this book, make a personal training plan, stick to it, and see how your climbing and power will improve. Then take it out to the rocks and send your project!</p>

<p>You can order the book online at <a href="http://cafekraft.de/laden/produkte/GK">Café Kraft</a> and <a href="http://shop.boulderkeskus.com/fi/kauppa/muut/kirjallisuus/gimmekraft.html">Boulderkeskus</a> and with some luck buy it at your local climbing gym. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scarpa Stix]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/scarpa-stix.html"/>
    <updated>2014-06-03T13:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/scarpa-stix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Climbing shoes. Like other <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shoes/">shoes</a> they can be a source of much discussion. The <a href="http://www.scarpa.net/en/stix.html">Scarpa Stix</a> was popular long before I started climbing, was shelved and now makes a return - and it’s easy to feel when climbing with it why this shoe was and is so popular.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14359890633" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/14359890633_7b1bf6b62b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I like Scarpa’s climbing shoes. The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/ultralight-climbing.html">Feroce</a> still gets regularly used on rock and plastic, though since I got the Stix late in 2013 it has been my climbing shoe of choice. There’s much to like about the shoe: There’s the weight of just 402 g for the pair in Size 41, the sticky rubber and the precise feel. One thing which really rules for me is that they’re quick and easy to put on and take off. With the Feroce I had three Velcro straps to open and close and the <a href="http://www.scarpa.net/en/techno-x.html">Techno X</a> uses laces. The Stix uses neither - it’s a slipper that hugs my foot for a wonderful snug fit without being constricting or uncomfortable. In case you’re wondering if it easy to lose the shoe - for example when heel or toe hooking: Nope, no chance. The Stix fits like a glove and doesn’t budge.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14153208177" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3914/14153208177_215c9320e1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14153085520" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5477/14153085520_d4f50c85cd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>

<p>Much of that superb fit can be attributed to Heinz Mariacher who designed the Stix - a name very closely connected to high-quality climbing shoes. And this shoe does pack a few high-quality features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A <em>Vibram® XS Grip 2</em> sole gives grip on rock and plastic alike</li>
  <li>The <em>X-Tension Randing</em> cradles your foot and heel to enhance your toe power</li>
  <li><em>REB - Reinforced Elastic Band</em> are the blue stripes on top of the shoe which improve the fit of the shoe</li>
  <li>Superb craftsmanship and construction</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14316563156" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5526/14316563156_2cb639dd93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>

<p>But back to fit for a moment. Once you slip into the shoe, which is easy thanks to the two large tabs at the back and the one on the instep, your large toe right away finds its spot, with the other toes falling in line. While the rubber isn’t super thin, it’s thin enough for a precise feeling of the rock underneath: With the pointy toe box you’ll find pockets without problems, while on tiny ledges you feel like you can reliably and safely weigh down on your foot and know that it will stick. If you prefer slabs (and I really do!) or the climb just has no footholds you will be glad to hear that it’s a fine shoe for smearing. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14153076640" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2913/14153076640_520b2ace9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14336362111" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3864/14336362111_e3dbfb6566_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>

<p>Which brings us to toe and heel hooking. I like Scarpa shoes because they fit me so well - it sometimes feels like they were designed for my feet - and the heel cup on the Stix is no difference here. A narrow, hugging heel cup without any dead space makes it easy to do precise heel hooks, with sticky rubber going far up the heel on all sides for extra friction. Toe hooks are similar: Because of the great fit for all my toes and the rubber on top it’s comfy &amp; easy to hook with the shoe. As it’s fast to put on &amp; off it’s easy to take the shoes off between pitches or when taking a break from a boulder problem. Even on hot, sunny days the shoe is comfortable to wear and does not create hot spots or overly sweaty feet. </p>

<p>The Stix is reasonably priced for such a high-quality shoe, and using it now since five months a couple of times a week on rock and plastic it feels like they still have a lot of climbing left in them. If you’re in the market for new climbing shoes and Scarpa’s shoes fit your feet well, I’d highly encourage you to try the Stix if you’re bouldering and sports climbing. It’s a highly comfortable shoe which is lightweight with great sensitivity and support that offers grip on narrow ledges, tiny pockets and lets you walk up steep slabs in comfort.</p>

<p>Get your pair at <a href="http://shop.boulderkeskus.com/en/shop/bouldering/climbing_shoes/">Boulderkeskus</a>, <a href="http://camu.fi/">Camu</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/scarpa-stix-kletterschuhe/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/scarpa/klettern/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/131V0vk">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1hsLtJp">Backcountry</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1kBUV7C">REI.com</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14152999898" title="Scarpa Stix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2905/14152999898_ed629031fa_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Stix" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview: Tomi Lindroos, Author of the Southern Finland Bouldering Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/07/interview-with-tomi-lindroos.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-01T11:23:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/07/interview-with-tomi-lindroos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bouldering is a new hobby of mine, and living in Vaasa means I have superb possibilities to head out in the afternoon or evening to tackle a problem - right in front of my door. However, South Finland too has a lot of great problems to offer, and the new Southern Finland Bouldering Guide shows you where to go look for those sweet rocks. Tomi Lindroos, one of the authors of the book, sat down with me, answered my questions and tells us more about the book.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9173720563/" title="hevossaari-tomi by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3821/9173720563_c04fa3cb68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="hevossaari-tomi" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hei Tomi, thanks for taking the time for this interview. For those who don’t know you, can you please introduce yourself briefly?</strong></p>

<p>Hi, and thanks for the interest in the book and the story behind it. My name is Tomi Lindroos, I’m 30 years old and I live in Helsinki.</p>

<p><strong>You are into climbing &amp; bouldering. When and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>I first tried indoor climbing when I was 12 years old and didn’t like it at all. After spending my time with books and martial arts, I refound climbing in 2007. Back then, the time was right and I fell in love with climbing.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9173710265/" title="pinsio-santeri by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7337/9173710265_9fdde08847_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="pinsio-santeri" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Climbing &amp; bouldering are social sports, but not team sports. Are you a member of a climbing club, or a clique which heads out to the crag together?</strong></p>

<p>I climb a lot with my friends. We have a group of people going to the crags and indoors together. Often there’s some company available for every day. </p>

<p><strong>Helsinki has a few really high quality climbing gyms - which one is your favourite?</strong></p>

<p>Personally I prefer Salmisaari and Pasila, because the first is next to my office and the second is next to my flat. To give a little add here, Salmisaari offers really good quality routes while routes at Pasila are freaking hard and teach you a lot. Together they have offered me many good days.  </p>

<p><strong>But we know that indoor climbing is just “meh” compared to real rocks! So which is you favourite boulder problem in a) Helsinki b) Finland c) the world?</strong></p>

<p>Of those which I have climbed:</p>

<p>a) <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/munkkiniemi/routes/valtiovierailu">Valtiovierailu</a><br />
b) <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/palkkivehmas/routes/comfort-zone-10460">Comfort Zone</a><br />
c) <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/albarracin/routes/supermafa-tacho">Supermafa Tacho in Albarracin</a><br /></p>

<p>And of those which I can (yet) only dream of:</p>

<p>b) <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/fagelberget/routes/neverland">Neverland</a> and <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/grottan/routes/supermartikainen-ss">Supermartikainen</a><br />
c) <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/franchard-carriers/routes/rainbow-rocket">Rainbow Rocket in Fontainebleau</a> and <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/rhino/routes/rhino">Rhino in Rocklands</a>.<br /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8995545800/" title="Southern Finland Bouldering Guide + Rock &amp; Ice by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3773/8995545800_c5e9dce7de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Southern Finland Bouldering Guide + Rock &amp; Ice" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Which brings us to the book you just published with two friends, the Southern Finland Bouldering Guide. It’s a complete self published book from what I can tell - Nancy did the layout, you drew the maps, and Samuli, Nancy and you wrote it. How long was the book in the works?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, it was completely self published. Nancy did the layout and some proof reading while me and Samuli produced the material. </p>

<p>In total, the work spanned over 3 years. The first two years were mostly planning and just grasping the amount of the work. We started to make a demo version last spring with Samuli and got it done by the summer. After that we recieved plenty of feedback and started to work with the rest of the material. The most hectic part of the work was spring 2013 when we put all the material together to a book.</p>

<p><strong>You cover a few distinct regions - besides the Metropolitan Region there’s also Hämeenlinna, a few selected other regions and Åland. Which of these was the most fun to research?</strong></p>

<p>I personally enjoy the atmosphere of Åland the most, but I absolutely love to explore new places everywhere!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9173850351/" title="fogel-samuli by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3714/9173850351_d2ec5c4408_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="fogel-samuli" /></a></p>

<p><strong>If any boulders from outside Finland reading this interview would ask you where they should visit for a week if they come bouldering to Finland - what would be the itinerary you’d plan for them?</strong></p>

<p>One possible itinerary without a car could be to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Visit some local rocks in Helsinki, such as Pihlajasaari, and take tours around the city.</li>
  <li>After a day or two, take a Ferry to Åland, climb there and come back to Helsinki just before the departure.</li>
</ul>

<p>If a car is available, there’s many beautiful places within 1 hour drive from the Helsinki such as Lappnor, Palkkivehmas and Siiri.</p>

<p><strong>Lets talk shortly about gear - what are your favourite climbing shoes, which crash pad do you use and which brand of chalk will we find in your chalk bag?</strong></p>

<p>I’m not a big gear fan. I have an old <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/crashpads/">crashpad</a> which I’ve been filling regularly to make it a bit more safe. My shoes are <a href="http://bit.ly/19MgMXe">Pythons</a>, because they are so comfortable for my foot and still work on real rock. I don’t have a clue about the brand of the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/chalk-chalkbag-bouldern/">chalk</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9173860313/" title="E75-samuli by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3714/9173860313_d0b37fe4c4_b.jpg" width="731" height="1024" alt="E75-samuli" /></a></p>

<p><strong>27crags.com features heavily in the book - what’s your involvement with the site?</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://27crags.com/">27crags</a> has a wide amount of information available. We’ve been using that information in the book and contributed some more to the website. </p>

<p><strong>Finally, as I’m living in Vaasa and we have some of the best boulders of Finland here (or so I’m told =) - will a Western Finland Bouldering Guide follow at some point?</strong></p>

<p>Actually, you’re not the only one who has been asking. At the moment we want just to rest and enjoy the summer. Maybe we’ll start that project a bit later!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9173827243/" title="hakunila-samuli3 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5464/9173827243_e326b3aed5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="hakunila-samuli3" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Tomi, thank you for taking the time to do this interview! Any shout-outs?</strong></p>

<p>Thank you. Just one quick shot out: Go out there and enjoy the day!</p>

<hr />
<p><br />
<em>You can <a href="http://media.boulderkeskus.com/media/pdf/bouldertopo_demo.pdf">take a look in the book here</a>. Stores which carry the book include <a href="http://camu.fi/shop/kiipeily/kalliokiipeily/lehdet_ja_videot/etelasuomenbouldertopo.html">Camu</a>, <a href="http://shop.boulderkeskus.com/fi/kauppa/kirjallisuus/etelasuomenbouldertopo.html">Boulderkeskus</a>, <a href="http://www.mountainshop.fi/kauppa/product_info.php?products_id=1087">Mountain Shop</a> and <a href="http://www.kletterfuehrer.net/product_info.php?language=en&amp;info=p989_Southern-Finland-Bouldering-Guide.html">Kletterführer</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
