<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gear | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gear/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-08T06:57:59-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc'teryx Procline Carbon Lite Ski Boot]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/arcteryx-procline-carbon-lite-ski-boot.html"/>
    <updated>2015-12-11T23:55:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/arcteryx-procline-carbon-lite-ski-boot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>1.190 g light, freedom of movement and great for alpinists and ski-tourers alike: The Arc’teryx Procline Carbon Lite Ski Boot and its siblings, the Procline Men’s Lite &amp; Procline Women’s Lite.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23233644179/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5694/23233644179_77ae9e38a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I was lucky enough to witness on Monday afternoon the unveiling of the <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> ski boot line. It was a much rumoured development and what we saw today was even better than what the rumors suggested. As I have a severe Jetleg I will just make this a short and sweet post with some key points, and after (possibly maybe) having used the boot a bit more over the following few days up in the mountains I will update this post, so please stay tuned. It is smart to follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> as with some luck there will be live updates from the mountains about this boot and the new Voltair Avalanche Airbag there, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23519476391/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/709/23519476391_c5e65555f2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Coming in Fall 2016 are the <strong>six alpine touring ski boots from Arc’teryx</strong>, and together with eight colleagues from Europe and North America I am heading out to test these new boots and the Voltair Avalanche Airbag over the next three days so I will be able to give more insights on those on Friday. Here’s what I can tell you from trying on the boot and checking it out today at the exclusive product launch. The Six models are called </p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Procline Carbon Lite</strong>, the top of the line Unisex model which tips the scales at 1.190 g and will cost 730€ retail. </li>
  <li>The <strong>Procline Carbon Support</strong> will be 1.260 g in MP Size 27.5 abd costs 700€</li>
  <li>The <strong>Procline Men’s Lite</strong> will be 580€, 1.190 g in MP Size 27.5 while the <strong>Procline Men’s Support</strong> is 1.260 g and 550€</li>
  <li>The <strong>Procline Women’s Lite</strong> tips the scales at 1.060 g and the <strong>Procline Women’s Support</strong> is 1.120 g - prices are the same as the Men’s models but both have a women’s last</li>
</ul>

<p>The difference between the Lite and Support models are the liners and cuffs. The Lite liners are about 90 g lighter as the support liners and fully thermo-mouldable. Both liners are designed in-house, but are different: The <em>Lite Liner</em> is made for uphill agility and great if you have a talented ski boot fitter at hand, while the <em>Support Liner</em> is slightly better for ski performance and if you don’t have access to a ski boot fitter. The Support Liner also has, as the name suggests, more tongue and collar support. The Women’s model will have a women’s last, and all liners have a removable strap closure system. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23306141770/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5788/23306141770_d7edb81816_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The special thing about the boot - besides the ridiculously light weight of 1.190 g for the Procline Carbon Lite - is the agility it gives you. The 360° Rotating Cuff makes the boot feel more like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx.html">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a>. Unlike normal cuffs this cuff - available in two different configurations, one from Carbon fibre with over-injected Grilamid and in the Men’s and Women’s models the cuff is made from carbonfibre charged Grilamid  - is cut in half. Yes, you read that right: The cuff is cut in half in the back of your calf. Together with the rest of the cuff his gives you a <strong>Lateral rotation of 23° inwards and 13° outwards</strong>, which should make it much more better for skinning up difficult, steep snow or make it more agile for climbing.</p>

<p>Speaking of alpine climbing, one of the re-occurring points the designer <strong>Federico Sbrissa</strong> (keep that name in mind, I have a feeling we can expect much more great footwear innovations to come from him!) made is that these boots were <em>designed for the alpinists and also great for every ski-tourer</em>. It’s a point worth thinking about, because the things alpinist (climbers) want in boots often will be much appreciated by skiers. I mean, more agility in your boot that allows you to skin longer and keep the crampons in your pack? Great! More edge control on steep snow traverses? Yes please! More agility when using crampons? Heck yeah! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23234109229/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/583/23234109229_7920fba1dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Nice about these carbon fibre cuffs is also that the pivot points - the places where metal rivets go through them - are made from plastic. And they connect to plastic. Which makes them a lot more durable than 100% carbon cuffs, which tend to wear out at the points where they touch metal. As here plastic touches plastic, they should last much longer, which is pretty cool. Once you decide to ski pull the buckle down and can hit the pow. Locking pins on the divided cuff lock into the rear spine and you have a nice, stiff boot to go down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22975559223/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot -Cuff inside"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/659/22975559223_96c5b221af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot -Cuff inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23520236251/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot - Cuff Pivot Point"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/573/23520236251_2211b8dfc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot - Cuff Pivot Point" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The other great innovation - well, there’s many more, but I have that jetleg and tomorrow’s another long day - is the full coverage gaiter. Made from Cordura with a PVC coating it is waterproof, a thing that both climbers and skiers will appreciate: If you climb ice in boots you don’t want ice or water coming in, and on Champagne Powder days you neither want snow in your boot, be it skinning up or shredding down. This gaiter, which is integrated with the boot shell, gives you a lot of protection and toasty feet in any conditions, be it skiing down or climbing up.</p>

<p>The Hybrid Closure System is a mix of buckle and lacing - think a Boa® closure that actually stays shut. The buckle is integrated with the cable, has 15 different positions for adjustment for an individual fit, and as the cable is connected to the buckle - once the buckle is locked in, it stays put! The cable is made from steel and the buckle from aluminium, and it is pretty amazing how well you can adjust the fit on these. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23519518161/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot - Hybrid Closure System"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/707/23519518161_b99c9dfedf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot - Hybrid Closure System" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There’s a lot more - a Power Strap without Velcro, buckles that keep in place when opened, a rockered tow, Dynafit certified toe and heel inserts, a crampon optimized toe shape with rubber cover and a Vibram sole - but I’ll tell you more about these on Friday. Until then check the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157661451499809">photos in high-res on Flickr</a>, follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and read <a href="http://backcountrymagazine.com">what</a> my <a href="https://www.wildsnow.com">colleagues</a> <a href="http://www.fall-line.co.uk">have</a> to <a href="http://www.friflyt.no/Ski/ArcteryxProcline">say</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22973797184/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5717/22973797184_35af5922aa_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2015 - II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T23:29:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More new kit for trailrunners, lightweight backpackers, mountaineers, climbers and outdoor lovers from the world’s biggest outdoor fair!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686321301/in/dateposted/" title="Always bring the Houdini"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5715/20686321301_c0847978f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Always bring the Houdini" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>These posts do take a lot of time to write so I am happy if you’d <a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">get me a coffee</a> as a payment for my work =)</em></p>

<h2 id="marmot">Marmot</h2>

<p><a href="http://marmot.de">Marmot</a> had a wide range of new kit on the show so lets dive straight in. The Red Star Jacket for Men/ Starfire Jacket for Women is the first 3-layer jacket to incorporate the exceptionally breathable, very robust and waterproof NanoPro™ membrane. It’s very stretchy, 100% seam taped, has a fully adjustable hood with a laminated brim to keep your sight dry, and will weigh 425 g. The Red Star Pants has 3/4 Length Water-Resistant Side Zippers and will tip the scales at 470 g and should make for a breathable &amp; waterproof combo which keeps you dry in heavy rain.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679565205/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Star Jacket"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5620/20679565205_85257c0dea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Star Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056996144/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot NanoPro 3-layer"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/608/20056996144_ce232512a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot NanoPro 3-layer" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Graviton 38 backpack weighs 1.080 g and comes with a ventilated suspension (carrying) system. The series - there’s four different sizes in total - features a single-piece aluminum uniframe which should have good load stability and features soft pads in the shoulder and waist areas for improved carry comfort. Compression
straps on the sides and base, trekking pole attachment and several easily accessible pockets round out this pack. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491534738/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Graviton 38 backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/638/20491534738_b95bf1624d_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Marmot Graviton 38 backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Helium Sleeping Bag tips the scales at 935 g in Regular length and is filled with 560 g of hydrophobic, RDS certified down, which should keep you toasty till around -9°C Comfort. Really cool was the “Fold-Down” second zipper on the right which provides more ventilation and easy access. The Full Length Locking YKK Two Way Zipper has a Zip-Guard Slider which prevents the lining from getting stuck in the zipper, which solves a common problem in (sleeping bag) zippers. Overall a nice looking sleeping bag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653304776/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Helium &amp; Ion Sleeping Bags"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5715/20653304776_de7ae465b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Helium &amp; Ion Sleeping Bags" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491568270/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Helium Sleeping Bag Zipper"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/715/20491568270_b1baf24d69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Helium Sleeping Bag Zipper" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Vapor FC 2P is a 2.520 g 2 Person tent with a size of 107 x 137 x 224 cm and a spacey vestibule. The doors got bigger for easy access, a lamp shade pocket in the roof lets you read at night without a headlamp on and the color-coded pole clip system makes it easy to pitch. It looked like a nice 3-season tent for couples, but there’s also 3 and 4 Person tents available of the Vapor for families and small groups.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056994454/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Vapor FC 2P Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/724/20056994454_177aab81d7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Vapor FC 2P Tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the climbing garments corner there were lots of clothes for your favourite pastime. Cool designs in combination with functional &amp; stretchy materials make for sweet shirts, pants and hoodies to hit the crag in. Add in a new climbing pack called the <em>Gear Hauler</em> and you have all you need for a fun day climbing. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491536718/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/730/20491536718_690fde99ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="scarpa">Scarpa</h2>

<p>Wow, I really was surprised by all the new shoes from <a href="http://scarpa.it">Scarpa</a>! Lots of trailrunning/ ultralight backpacking shoes from them, and I found they actually looked good! The Proton is a shoe made for heel strikers which gives you good support on long runs. Will weigh around 360 g per shoe and has a Vibram® Genesis sole and lots of cushioning in the heel.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491564180/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Proton"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5726/20491564180_8969bb3378_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Proton" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Atom certainly was the most interesting shoe in the line, and at 260 g per shoe it was also rather light. Colour &amp; sole-wise it gets big thumbs up from me, the Vibram®  Genetic Lite reminds me of a trailrunning shoe I have used a lot. Scarpa says it <em>“Created for athletes with a perfect running style who weigh less than 70 kg, they will find this shoe is very reactive and it suits the athlete who favors a running style based on the toes”</em>. Well, if that doesn’t sound like a great shoe for me, I don’t know! Add in a breathable mesh upper and you will have a shoe which could become very popular.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653292466/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Atom"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5634/20653292466_a275b465eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Atom" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Neutron weighs 295 g and has a Vibram® Genetic sole that should give good grip on any kind of wet or dry terrain. It’s available as a fabric version, a special Women’s version and for Winter runs even as a Gore-Tex lined shoe. Still light enough for UL backpackers, but with more support and cushioning. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057014404/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Neutron"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5740/20057014404_560df31ac3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Neutron" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Scarpa Mountaineering boots aka the Phantom Line is awesome. It’s designed by Ueli Steck which means this are the boots that Ueli designed and uses himself - be it climbing Annapurna or on his 82 Summits project. There’s three new boots and they all feature the new zipper which runs around the shoe. It looks cool but I am a bit wondering how practical it will be in use when you need to pull a zipper behind your leg, and of course such a long zipper also adds weight and complexity aka a place where it can fail. Scarpa writes that the <em>“innovative “orange peel-like” closure with Flexseal® Waterproof zip avoids any inconvenience to the ankle movements”</em> so I guess it will have a benefit. Anyway. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20058614443/in/photostream/" title="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/611/20058614443_2482540e7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There’s three new boots - the Phantom 8000, the Phantom 6000 and the Phantom Tech. All have a gaiter made from KCN-Tech Fabric, S-Tech Fabric and an Outdry® membrane , which I like as I find OutDry better working as Gore-Tex. All three boots also have a Carbon insole and a Vibram® Gravity sole. The Phantom Tech is the lightest boot at 830 g per boot and also the least warm, but as it has a Primaloft® insulation layer I have no doubt that it will be a great alpine climbing/ ice climbing boot (in the photo underneath is the Tech on the right and the 6000 on the left).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679570315/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5827/20679570315_29ac835ee9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Phantom 6000 and 8000 come with a removable liner boot that has a Primaloft® lining and a 4 mm thermo-insulating EVA sole. The 6000 is made for peaks up to 6000 m and weighs 995 g per boot while the Phantom 8000 is made for the highest summits of the globe and weighs 1310 g per boot. The hole line looked sweet, curious to try out the Phantom 6000 in the Karakoram in the future!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20670328742/in/photostream/" title="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5687/20670328742_fe268302e1_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s Drago, the new climbing shoe. Made for bouldering, hard sports climbing indoors and outdoors the Drago is close in design to the Furia but has a Velcro strap for a good fit. The rubber on the upper goes really high for sticky toe hooks. The shoe is soft and gives you good control on small ledges and difficult placements.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057007954/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Drago Climbing Shoe"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/676/20057007954_6eb66f1fcb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Drago Climbing Shoe" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="haglfs">Haglöfs</h2>

<p>Haglöfs is a big company with many lines so it’s always a bit difficult to grasp all the new gear, especially as there’s so much new interesting kit. The Roc Helios 25 backpack is an OutDoor Award winner that’s made from XPac and has a back opening to access your gear. It’s made for mountaineering so has all the details you want from a rucksack for the mountains, but should do well when abused for backpacking, too. No info on weight, sorry.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461137721/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Roc Helios 25 backpack"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3814/20461137721_acafbdf705_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs Roc Helios 25 backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Herakles Jacket is 455 g in Size L and made from a 3-layer Gore-tex with the new CKnit backer. It’s a mountain jacket with a helmet-compatible hood, an articulated design for freedom of movement and high pockets. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20268246879/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Herakles Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/415/20268246879_e39a6fb420_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haglöfs Herakles Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Gram Pulse trailrunners - the Women’s model is in the photo - will weigh 215 g for a Women’s shoe and 260 g for a Men’s shoe. The sole pattern looks familiar and thus should be good, and on top there’s non-absorbing fabrics which should maintain a low weight in wet conditions. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461140421/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Gram Pulse Shoe"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/458/20461140421_b578c49369_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haglöfs Gram Pulse Shoe" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s another backpack, the LIM Strive Backpack. Can’t give the weight on this pack either, but it felt light for being a 50 l pack. The front zipper makes for easy access to gear, the lid can be removed for more weight saving. The hipbelt pockets were pretty big, made from a stretchy mesh and looked great, and the material is bluesign certified 100HT Robic™, which also some cottages use for making their packs. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20454898805/in/dateposted/" title="LIM Strive Backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/439/20454898805_f9e2a1f04c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="LIM Strive Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="vaude">Vaude</h2>

<p>I’m pretty psyched about the biggest news for backpackers from <a href="http://www.vaude.com">Vaude</a>, and that’s the Alpstein 450 DWN quilt. Why? Well, I’m pretty proud that <a href="http://blog.fastpacking.de">Carsten</a> and me helped during the development of this quilt. We both have tested early prototypes and gave the designer a lot of feedback on what we liked and what could be better. I think I’ll give some insights on this quilt further down the road in a separate post, but the cool things are: 450 g of RDS certified down in the Alpstein 450 DWN (200 g in the Alpstein 200 DWN), total weight 750 g (550 g), and a unique attachment system which allows you to attach the quilt pretty easily to any sleeping pad. Oh, and it’s pretty cool that the quilt won a OutDoor Gold OutDoor Award, too! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20516026200/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Alpstein 450 DWN quilt"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/723/20516026200_795ffbd627_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Alpstein 450 DWN quilt" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then there’s the Citus 24 LW Backpack, a 500 g 24 l Volume pack that’s made from a siliconizied 40 D Rip-Stop. Special is that is has a Aeroflex back panel which should keep you dries aka less sweaty on your summer hikes. It has a zippered lid pocket, mesh side stretch pockets and a compression system that also lets you carry wet gear on the front. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20516112978/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Citus 24 LW Backpack"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5643/20516112978_a85234b05f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Citus 24 LW Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Pro Windshell Jacket weighs less than 80 g and is a cycling windjacket which packs tiny when not needed. Reflective details, long back, stretch inserts on the sides for freedom of movement and breathability and a PFC-free Eco Finish water repellency treatment that makes it water-resistant, its a wind jacket you can wear cycling or when out on the hills.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20710926061/in/dateposted/" title="Pro Windshell LW"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5652/20710926061_7afc5fae6a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Pro Windshell LW" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And as we’re already talking cycling the Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes are environmentally friendly made flat pedal cycling shoes. The Moab Low AM and Moab Mid STX AM fulfil the strict Vaude <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQgt80pO0YM">Green Shape</a> criteria and still will perform great on the trail. A great move to get a difficult product likes shoes fulfil this standard, and I hope we’ll see more of this in the future, also from other manufacturers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20694848822/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/762/20694848822_079c2a46ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="norrna">Norrøna</h2>

<p>The news from <a href="https://www.norrona.com">Norrøna</a> included the bitihorn alpha60 Jacket which is a 250 g insulation piece that’s filled with Polartec Alpha. The shell is wind and water resistant so it also can be worn on its own, but it should be a good midlayer, too. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261529486/in/dateposted/" title="Norrøna bitihorn alpha60 Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/395/20261529486_55568dd61a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna bitihorn alpha60 Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now available is the fjørå line for Women (Men’s have been available for a while already). These are really great for riding on single track trails or shredding down hills, made from good materials and give good wind protection but also keep you cool on the uphill.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101181829/in/dateposted/" title="Norrøna fjøra line"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/456/20101181829_5747a8e82c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna fjøra line" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Lifestyle lines were a big trend at the OutDoor, and it’s understandable. Norrøna’s 29 line is very stylish and a mix of technical and functional fabrics. There’s a cool limited edition Denim Anorak which will make you stand out at the camp fire or in the office. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261544666/in/photostream/" title="Norrøna Lifestyle 29 Line"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3678/20261544666_2f1e05181a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna Lifestyle 29 Line" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="montane">Montane</h2>

<p>I only had a brief visit at <a href="Montane">Montane</a> so can’t give all the details on the lightweight new kit from them - which is a shame, as they had a very cool looking cuben fibre pack on display! But what I saw and tried were the new Ultra Tour packs, which did remind me design-wise from a now bankrupt lightweight company from the USA. Which isn’t bad, as that pack has been super popular. The Ultra Tour is available as a 22, 40 and 55 l volume pack, which will weigh 540 g, 725 g and 840 g respectively. There’s a roll-top closure, large stretch side pockets, a Comfort Vent Back Pad and Contact Air Mesh shoulder straps which will keep you cooler on long hikes with heavy loads, hip pockets and a front pocket/ compartment. These looked very good and if priced right (= affordable) these could become great entry-level UL packs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679558375/in/dateposted/" title="Montane Ultra Tour backpacks"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/693/20679558375_815277e522_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Ultra Tour backpacks" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Minimus 777 Pull-On is a 134 g hardshell that packs tiny and should be very breathable. The construction is of a very high quality that’s made to last, and in orange it also looks really sweet. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20670323222/in/dateposted/" title="Montane Minimus 777 Pull-On"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5693/20670323222_a126f9bded_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Minimus 777 Pull-On" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As I said, a shame I didn’t snap photos of the other new kit, as with the <em>ultra alpine 38 + 5</em> (a 547 g alpine climbing pack with a sweet design), the <em>hyper tour 38</em> (a 639 g cuben fibre hiking pack that can be stripped to 478 g) and several great garments there would have been plenty of interesting kit for lightweight backpackers, Alpinists and trailrunners!</p>

<h2 id="nikwax">Nikwax</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.nikwax.com/en-gb/">Nikwax</a> Down Wash Direct is an aftercare product which lets you clean and improve the performance of regular and hydrophobic garments/ quilts/ sleeping bags alike. What’s really cool is not just that Down Wash Direct is environmentally friendly but that it makes your down kit hydrophobic, even if it hasn’t been hydrophobic down to begin with. That’s a great way to make your favourite down jacket hydrophobic - both the down and the DWR of the shell. An exciting product that I’m curious to test with some of my down kit and see how it improves performance.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056991504/in/dateposted/" title="Nikwax Down Wash Direct"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5689/20056991504_3456b34bee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nikwax Down Wash Direct" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="omm">OMM</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.theomm.com">OMM</a> makes sweet kit that makes ultralight backpackers and fell runners alike happy. The Phantom 25CL was the highlight, a great pack that would be ideal for a fast &amp; light weekend in the hills or an OMM event. It has a integrated sleeping mat and a carbon suspension system. The back length can be adjusted via an easy system, the stretchy side pockets were super easy to reach and the compression system could be adjusted with the pack on. Tipping the scales at just 400 g the Phantom 25CL is a great pack that works a charm if you go fast.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686315741/in/photostream/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/718/20686315741_c65a6a6a53_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686306421/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5670/20686306421_5c125f020c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491570540/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/750/20491570540_d77bb3e1f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Ultra 8 is a new pack that will be super affordable and great for training or a SUL overnighter. Mesh side pockets, a good carrying system and a 8 l main compartment let you carry all you need for a day out running in the hills.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057013414/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Ultra 8"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/757/20057013414_c51cbdd786_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Ultra 8" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you need some more space on your existing pack, take a look at the Compressor Pod. It can work as a UL pack on its own, but it’s designed to be attached to a OMM pack or another pack and gives you more protected carrying space. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653312566/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Compressor Pod"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/629/20653312566_f41a8c4c0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Compressor Pod" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, the Grid Longsleeve is simply a functional &amp; good-looking longsleeve for runners &amp; outdoor enthusiasts alike. The cool contour lines on the sleeves are a nice detail.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057005354/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Grid Longsleeve"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/663/20057005354_d9447135b5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="OMM Grid Longsleeve" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="jetboil">Jetboil</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jetboil.com">Jetboil</a> had two interesting news on the show: A Basecamp stove and the MicroMo - the successor to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti.html">Sol Ti</a>. Lets take a look at the MicroMo first. It weighs 340 g all in and the pot has a volume of 0,8 l. You can store a 100 g cartridge inside the pot with the burner unit and on the outside a cozy lets you handle the pot with its hot content. Burning time for half a litre is supposed to be 2:15 min and it should be less ideal for cooking/ simmering than the MiniMo. The pot et al. is now made from Aluminium, so there should hopefully not be any melting fluxrings anymore.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653299766/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Micro Mo"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5787/20653299766_ffd9bf075d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Micro Mo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Genesis on the other hand is found at the opposite side of the spectrum of the MicroMo and weighs 4.100 g. I don’t know how light that is for a basecamp stove, but it sounds pretty good. A 5 l pot lets you cook for the team and the pan is ideal for bacon and eggs in the morning. The 2-Burner stove fits inside of the pot with the pan on top. I can see this coming in handy for car camping, glamping and canoe trips, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686316111/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/626/20686316111_3a0afa0678_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686313981/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/772/20686313981_f49269f40a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679567065/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/588/20679567065_a3e3181c92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="stay-tuned-for-the-next-part-coming-soon">Stay tuned for the next part, Coming Soon™!</h2>

<p>You can see a lot more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157656356655229">OutDoor 2015 Flickr Album</a>. And if you liked this follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for more gear &amp; outdoor updates.</p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2015 - I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-10T23:57:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What new gear is coming in 2016 for lightweight backpackers, mountaineers, climbers and outdoor lovers? </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665148874/in/dateposted/" title="OutDoor Award Showcase"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/559/19665148874_502f67dd93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OutDoor Award Showcase" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-research">Outdoor Research</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com">Outdoor Research</a>’s big news was that they now have a new investor on board, which allows them to invest more into R&amp;D and tap into the knowledge of the new partner. The first result is the <strong>Precipice Jacket™</strong> which uses the new AscentShell™ fabric technology, a 308 g (Size L) hardshell that’s made of 100% nylon 20D mechanical stretch ripstop face with a 100% Polyester 12D backer. The jacket is fully seam-taped and has a laminated construction with Dynamic Reach™ Underarm Panels which allow great freedom of movement. A helmet compatible Wire-Brimmed Halo-Hood™ keeps the head dry and one of the internal pockets doubles as a stuff sack. An interesting jacket with a new technology, curious to see if it performs better than existing hardshell fabrics.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279450652/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/376/20279450652_26a25f52f2_b.jpg" width="694" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Next up was the <strong>Ferrosi Summit Hooded Jacket™</strong> which adds a more durable, rugged jacket to the Ferrosi family that is still highly breathable while offering protection  for full mountain conditions. It is 526 g in Size 34 and has all the bells &amp; whistles you need from a mountain jacket: A helmet-compatible Wire-Brimmed Halo-Hood™, zippered chest &amp; hand pockets, Dynamic Reach™ Underarm Panels and being of course water-, wind-, and abrasion-resistant. Also new to the Ferrosi family is the <strong>Ferrosi Crag Pants™</strong> which will tip the scales at 314 g in Size 34 and comes with articulated knees, a gusseted crotch and a low-profile waist with Knit Stretch Panels for freedom of movement in the mountains.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665150104/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/393/19665150104_302f925916_b.jpg" width="597" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I really loved the look of the <strong>Women’s Ferrosi Knickers™</strong> which had a great orange (that was slightly difficult to photograph). It’s a rock climbing pants that has stretch knit panels at the waist which allows you to easily wear a harness over it. The lightweight stretch-woven construction is highly durable, for fun days at the crag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666841233/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Women’s  Ferrosi  Knickers™"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/487/19666841233_2bcc39743d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Women’s  Ferrosi  Knickers™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Already available are the <strong>Splitter Gloves™</strong>, OR’s take on crack gloves. These were very comfortable thanks to the synthetic suede on the inside and a non-slip  synthetic leather on the outside gives you grip in cracks and protects your hands. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099785740/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Splitter Gloves™"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/20099785740_b33bc64944_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Splitter Gloves™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Completely new is also the <strong>Sensor Dry Series</strong> which come in Premium &amp; Standard versions. Both are waterproof according to the IPX-8 Standard, fully touchscreen (and camera!) functional, have welded seams and are fairly lightweight. The Premium versions come with waterproof pins for your headphones and can swim when dropped into the water. Available for normal sized smartphone, massive smartphones and tablets.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101180819/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3709/20101180819_8489a1fa22_b.jpg" width="735" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099794998/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/327/20099794998_0cf1f64428_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And finally there were plenty of new hats, like the <strong>Helium Rain Bucket™</strong>, a waterproof hat; the <strong>Mesa Verde Sun Hat™</strong>, a 78 g light sun hat for the ladies; and the <strong>Springboard Cap</strong> I am sporting there, a lightweight cap for your trail adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101172829/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Helium Rain Bucket™"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/465/20101172829_070b5efe52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Helium Rain Bucket™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099780118/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Mesa Verde Sun Hat™"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3717/20099780118_b0cba6e0cf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Mesa Verde Sun Hat™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287808785/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Springboard Cap"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/507/20287808785_b89171d0e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Springboard Cap" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="cilogear">CiloGear</h2>

<p><em>“Have you seen anything new &amp; interesting yet?”</em> is the standard conversation opener at the fair. In years past my reply was usually <em>“Nope”</em> but this year I passed Graham from <a href="http://www.cilogear.com">CiloGear</a> as I had some time to spare and walked with him to his booth where he showed me something. What I saw then was not new, but it was for me the coolest thing on the fair which I told everyone who asked me the opening question then. Graham had a pack along - the first preproduction <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/30wwo.html">3030</a> ever made - which had seen roughly 900 (!) days outdoors, including two expeditions to Pakistan and was along establishing a new route on K7, a 6,934 m peak near the Charakusa Valley in the Karakoram. The owner sent it in to get the extension collar renewed, but the rest of the pack - seams and material - were still in great shape (albeit a tad dirty, but what do you expect after over two years in the mountains!). For me the most interesting thing in the show, not just because it shows that small manufacturers produce superb gear that lasts, but also because of the stories this pack would tell. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261525866/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/517/20261525866_0308c0f8e0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293723261/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/337/20293723261_cba928572c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099796360/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/496/20099796360_40b3658e5d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx">Arc’teryx</h2>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> was their <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-acrux-ar-alpine-boot.html">2016 Footwear</a> which I already have presented to you in June. The next big news was the <strong>Atom SL Hoody</strong>, an ultralight summer insulation piece that will weigh 285 g for a Men’s Medium. The Coreloft 40g/m² insulation is quilted to the liner while on the side and arm panels a soft fleece material helps with ventilation. Really interesting is the No-Slip-Zip™ front zipper which works like a series of speed bumps that keep the zipper from self-opening. It packs tiny and so can always be along in your backpack on your mountain adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099806578/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Atom SL Hoody"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20099806578_9a436d4504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Atom SL Hoody" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That backpack could be one of the new <strong>Cierzo Packs</strong>, Arc’teryx’s updated alpine climbing pack (in the centre of the photo underneath). Available as a Cierzo 18 (375 g) and a Cierzo 28 (550 g) they open via a pull to open, pull to close drawcord system like the Alpha FL packs, but also feature a SwiftCord™ drawstring compression system which is versatile in use and can be stored away when not needed. You can carry ice tools with them, and the Cierzo 28 has a padded back panel that can be removed to save more weight. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665147454/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx 2016 Backpacks"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3796/19665147454_f7b2ba9550_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx 2016 Backpacks" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Interesting for hiking &amp; backpacking was also the <strong>Pelon Comp SS</strong> which is made from core-spun Merino wool and has durable nylon inserts in high wear areas as the shoulders. They weigh 145 g in Size M and have a Regular fit and should be pretty good for long trips in the outdoors thanks to the properties of Merino wool.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287804825/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Pelon Comp SS"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/458/20287804825_9135589edc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Pelon Comp SS" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="petzl">Petzl</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a> had a lot of new gear on their booth, and they were also celebrating 25 years of the GriGri, probably the most popular belay device amongst all sorts of climbers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287806355/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl 25 years GriGri"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20287806355_da5ee93c48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl 25 years GriGri" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But the new gear! All of the IRVIS, VASAK, SARKEN, LYNX, DARTWIN and DART crampons get technical upgrades, making them even more effective, durable and practical. Effective: the horizontal structure of the frame brings the boot sole as close to the crampon as possible for increased sensitivity and precision. Durable: a special steel, chosen by Petzl for its rigidity and strength, allows a reduction in thickness to offer light weight crampons with sharper points. Practical: user-friendly binding systems, ANTISNOW and interchangeable front sections.</p>

<p>The <strong>IRVIS, VASAK and SARKEN Crampons</strong> have front sections that are interchangeable and available as accessories, which means you can have one crampon for all your needs and don’t need two or more of crampons in the house. Now you can simply &amp; fast convert for example a technical mountaineering crampon into one for glacier travel. All of them come with the new ANTISNOW, which limits snow balling up under your crampon. The VASAK will weigh 810 g, the IRVIS 710 g and the SARKEN 810 g, all with the FLEXLOCK binding. The linking bar in all three can be shortened to fit small sizes (Size 36 is the smallest size all three will fit, with Size 50 being the max).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261527636/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl Vasak Crampon"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/266/20261527636_0a5b15084a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Vasak Crampon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>ELIA</strong> is a new Women’s helmet with the OMEGA headband system. The notch in the back is for the long hair and allows ladies to put the helmet on and off very easily with a lot of comfort. It is 285 g light and also has a new webbing adjustment mechanism which allows the helmet to be precisely adjusted for different head shapes. The ABS shell and expanded polystyrene liner will keep the wearer save.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099784168/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl Elia helmet"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/367/20099784168_48ce174be7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Elia helmet" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>TIBLOC</strong> has been around for a while and gets a update for 2016. The new ultralight emergency ascender gets a system that automatically presses the carabiner against the rope to initiate the clamping action on the rope. You can see this advantage in comparison to the current TIBLOC in the 2nd photo underneath. The new TIBLOC has a rope compatibility from 8 to 11 mm and weighs 35 g.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279450132/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl TIBLOC"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/255/20279450132_475d419f27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl TIBLOC" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099789690/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl TIBLOC New &amp; Old"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/270/20099789690_24cc760bea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl TIBLOC New &amp; Old" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Furthermore there’s two new <strong>Semi-static ropes</strong> coming, two new <strong>carabiners</strong>, the <strong>ALCANADRE</strong>, a large volume pack for transporting canyoning equipment and the <strong>BUG</strong>, a small backpack for single-day multi-pitch climbing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101171129/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/256/20101171129_1a96229815_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293742921/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/532/20293742921_ae05b89662_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="rjk">Röjk</h2>

<p>Doesn’t the <a href="http://rojksuperwear.com/en/">Röjk</a> booth look fantastic? Of course it does - Linus &amp; Jan shanghaied me in helping it putting it up! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287797785/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/315/20287797785_a0bb2fee35_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That’s the Guys PrimaLoft Zippen Hood in purple, which rocks. It’s a S.O.A. Winner, too. But new is the <strong>Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood</strong> that Linus models underneath. It’s a lighter weight hoody jacket. The PrimaLoft Polyester makes it lightweight and nicely soft on the skin, is wicking very fast while the Merino wool makes it stay fresh. The cool look makes it a fine choice for chilling at the campfire or going to town. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261528726/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3791/20261528726_0343b99044_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Somehow I managed to not take a photo of Röjk’s new T-Shirt designs for the <strong>SuperTee</strong>, which is a shame because they were awesome. Röjk continues their Inka, Maya &amp; Aztec theme with very pretty designs on their 60% Merino wool &amp; 40% Modal shirts for Chicks and Guys, so please excuse the absence of the photos and believe me: They rock. What I did photograph, though, is the new <strong>Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody</strong>. These are made from Merino wool and Lyocell for a lightweight and comfortable backpacking hoody that stays fresh and cool for a long time. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665161864/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/473/19665161864_18f7e5c3ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Sadly not pictured are the great looking <strong>SuperTank</strong> tops, which are made from Merino wool and Modal and also come in sick Inca patterns. What I can show you is the <strong>PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock</strong> which should be super breathable thanks to the open mesh structure on top and help avoid sweaty feet. Made from PrimaLoft Yarn, Merino wool and Polyamide they should be durable, keeping your toes warm, dry and looking good!  </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666843133/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/552/19666843133_73ca83b1b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Most importantly, you can shop their gear online right now in the <a href="http://rojksuperwear.com/en/">Röjk online shop</a>!</p>

<h2 id="ortovox">Ortovox</h2>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://www.ortovox.de/">Ortovox</a> were the backpacks, especially the <strong>PEAK</strong> which has a unique SWISSWOOL back system that’s made from pressed Swiss wool. The ideas is that in exactly the same way as with clothing you would benefit from the wool’s great moisture and microclimate management and therefore the backpanel feels comfortable and dry on your back. Otherwise the PEAK is a good looking climbing backpack with a c circumferential front zipper for easy access. Will be interesting to see if the backpanel works as imagined or if it just sucks itself full with sweat and stays wet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261545696/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/323/20261545696_888b79ac59_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287805525/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack Swisswool backpanel"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/284/20287805525_5ba8004bda_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack Swisswool backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293731291/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/298/20293731291_2701787a89_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET</strong> is from Ortovox’s new softshell line (called, yes, MERINO SHIELD SHELL) and will weigh 353 g (Size ?). The line is made for high-alpine tours and has hence the features you’d want from a jacket for such outings: Freedom of movement, high abrasion-resistance, breathability and comfort. It has a protective shell made from Cordura®, the outer side of front pocket is made of felted wool and has an athletic fit. It was a comfortable jacket and felt very nice.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101189529/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/395/20101189529_1064533f20_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kitka">Kitka</h2>

<p>It was pretty cool to meet the guys from <a href="http://kitkaclimbing.com">Kitka Climbing</a> at the fair, especially with their own booth! Kitka makes polyurethane climbing holds, handcrafted in Finland, with a lot of unique &amp; cool shapes. They felt great and I reckon I will need to get a few sets for my own boulder wall!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293717451/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Kitka Climbing Holds"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/461/20293717451_35656e4206_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kitka Climbing Holds" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="rab">Rab</h2>

<p>As always I enjoyed my visit to <a href="http://rab.equipment/">Rab</a>, and their new kit really rocks. There was a lot of new lightweight gear for the ladies, like the fine <strong>Women’s Flashpoint Jacket</strong> which is made from 3L Pertex Shield+ Fabric and will weigh 160 g for a Women’s 12. It has a helmet compatible hood with a lightweight &amp; flexible polymer peak to keep your eyes dry in the rain. It’s designed as the jacket that you have along in case the rain hits you while you are on a Multi-Pitch route or an alpine ascent, and as it is so light you don’t need to ponder if you take it along. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261546376/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Rab Women’s Flashpoint Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/303/20261546376_843ff13911_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Rab Women’s Flashpoint Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>New is also the <strong>Women’s Continuum Jacket</strong> which will be the lightest option in the women’s insulation range at 240 g in Size 12. It’s filled with 100g of 850FP European Goose Down that’s hydrophobic. It will pack down also very small and thus also can always come along on your mountain adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20266787270/in/dateposted/" title="Rab Women&#x27;s Continuum Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/397/20266787270_c43e929260_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab Women&#x27;s Continuum Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And I liked the new Rock Climbing garments immensely. Functional and stylish, the assortment of pants - from the <strong>Oblique &amp; Rockover Pants</strong> to the <strong>Rampage Jacket</strong> and the many great T-Shirts and hoodies, the Rock Climbing &amp; Lifestyle Collection is great for days at the crag - be it in Kalymnos, Olhava or the Peak District. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461137201/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/490/20461137201_b89427b206_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20268246319/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/351/20268246319_3f8c184aab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20446195202/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/402/20446195202_d09a4723c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sea-to-summit">Sea to Summit</h2>

<p>After not visiting <a href="http://www.seatosummit.com">Sea to Summit</a> in 2014 I was happy to check out what they had new this year. The <strong>XSet Pots</strong> are collapsible cooking pots, which should be ideal with simple gas or alcohol stoves. The bottoms are made from hard anodized aluminium with food-grade &amp; heat-resistant silicone walls that fold down for transport, making for small packages while in your pack. The 3 piece kit consists of a 1,3 l kettle, one 2,8 l pot and a 8” frying pan that weigh together 756 g. The kettle on its own is 186 g and the lightest of the whole series and could be all a lightweight backpacker needs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099778470/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit XSet Pots"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/433/20099778470_24e75f5526_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Sea to Summit XSet Pots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>New is also the <strong>Aeros Pillow Ultralight</strong> which will weigh 70 g and packs as big as a Kiwi. If you value a good nights sleep and want a lightweight pillow that is very comfortable, this looks like an interesting new offering to the market. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666823983/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Aeros Pillow Ultralight"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/544/19666823983_8fcaf2283a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Aeros Pillow Ultralight" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Ground Control Tent Pegs</strong> are made from high-quality aluminium, weigh 14 g each and have a luminescent pull loop which is easily seen at night, adding a bit more security to your nightly stumbles around your tent. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261534766/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Ground Control Tent Pegs"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/508/20261534766_ee6a63a867_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Ground Control Tent Pegs" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Self-Adhesive Lash Points</strong> should be especially interesting for packrafters. These allow you to add extra tie-down points to your packraft, either to tie down gear, install thigh straps or or or. And at 18 g per lash point they’re ultralight, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666827693/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Self-Adhesive Lash Points"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/536/19666827693_a44f650efd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Self-Adhesive Lash Points" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="vertical-life">Vertical Life</h2>

<p>New at <a href="https://www.vertical-life.info">Vertical-Life</a> was the <strong>Zlag Up!</strong>, a variation on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/zlagboard-pro-review.html">Zlagboard</a> which I use. It’s a smart pull-up bar which works like the Zlagboard with an App on your smartphone to keep track of your training, and as a very special extra there’s the rolley bar which is pretty cool to train your balance.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279448742/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Zlag Up"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3786/20279448742_904d6fd21e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Zlag Up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="http://guide.vertical-life.info/en/app/">Climbing App Guides</a> also get a lot of new topos all the time, and you can test the app for South Tyrol’s crags for free (I wish I’d known this before my trip to the Dolomites!). </p>

<h2 id="stay-tuned-for-the-next-part-coming-soon">Stay tuned for the next part, coming soon™!</h2>

<p>As usual you can see a lot more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157656356655229">OutDoor 2015 Flickr Album</a>. Sweet. And if you liked this follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for more gear &amp; outdoor updates.  And <a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a> as a payment for my work =)</p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-4.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-10T23:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A bunch more new gear for the trailrunner, the backpacker, the climber, the skier, the cyclists and simply anyone who likes the outdoors, or gear, with a look at trends, a dozen other blogs that reported on the fair and a final conclusion of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">2015 ISPO</a> in München.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695647012" title="Audi &amp; Heimplanet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8581/16695647012_b34d002d69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Audi &amp; Heimplanet" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Late to the Party? Read the other updates for more Gear News: <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html">Part 1</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2.html">Part 2</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">Part 3</a>.</em></p>

<h2 id="petzl">Petzl</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578475520" title="Petzl Sitta harness by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8731/16578475520_e272aca434_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Sitta harness" /></a></p>

<p>There were four big news for me at <a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The new Sitta Harness</li>
  <li>The new RAD System</li>
  <li>The new positioning lanyards</li>
  <li>The updated headlamp line-up</li>
</ul>

<p>Lets look at these in detail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578288858" title="Petzl Sitta harness by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7609/16578288858_3e832e66ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Sitta harness" /></a></p>

<p>The new harness obviously immediately had my interest, as it’s lighter yet again as the Hirundos (that I have here and which is already damn light at 280 g in Size Medium) - the Sitta will be 250 g in Size Medium and a sweet 230 g in Size Small. The Wireframe Technology which this harness uses uses Dyneema strands in the waistbelt and leg loops and which replaces webbing and foam in normal harnesses. It’s a very compact harness with a beautiful design that’s slim but still packs all you need from a harness: Two rigid front gear loops, two flexible back gear loops, two Caritool slots and a rear loop for a haul rope. It’s made of Bluesign® approved fabrics, too. Psyched about this one!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764794052" title="Petzl RAD System by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8718/16764794052_1aa2dcaae5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl RAD System" /></a></p>

<p>The new RAD System, (<strong>R</strong>escue <strong>A</strong>nd <strong>D</strong>escent) is an all-in-one set for skiers that allows you to set up an crevasse rescue, rappel or rope up on a glacier. The set contains three Attache carabiners, one storage bag, one Tibloc, one Micro Traxion, one 120 cm sling and the 30 m RAD Line, a newly developed 6 mm cordage which allows you to do a crevasse rescue, rope up on a glacier or rappel. The whole set weighs in at 1.045 g which is quite a bit lighter as other options, and also very compact. The cord tips the scales at 660 g for the 30 m, that’s 22 g/ m. It’s a static cord with less than 2% stretch which makes it great for rappels and rescue actions and minimizes yo-yo effects. It’s something any backcountry skier usually will carry, though nothing yet packs down as compact and light as the RAD (4 l pack size!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143568884" title="Petzl Positioning Lanyards by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8580/16143568884_0dd68a1709_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Positioning Lanyards" /></a></p>

<p>The Positioning lanyards are interesting. They aim to replace your Daisychain/ 120 cm sling with which you clip into the belay station. The Connect Adjust is made for sports climbing and mountaineering, while the Dual Connect Adjust is for Multi-Pitch routes and mountaineering. You attach them with a girth hitch to your tie-in point and then clip them out of the way until you need them. The magic happens when you arrive at the belay. With the locking carabiner (not included in the sets) you clip in to the belay, and then can easily adjust the length of the lanyard with the Adjust ascender. The lanyard is a dynamic rope which can reduce the force in case of a short fall. The Connect Adjust tips the scales at 125 g and the Dual Connect Adjust at 160 g, and will need one or two locking carabiners respectively. Knowing how much discussions we have in our climbing club about slings/ daisy chains/ <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/metolius-personal-anchor-system-black/?pid=81">Personal Anchor Systems</a> I reckon these will be hotly discussed, too. Personally I think they are great ideas which can make adjusting the length at the belay a lot easier and possibly safer, though they’re a tad heavier than normal systems (which in turn are a lot heavier than just tying in with a Clove hitch).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578285888" title="Petzl Headlamps by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7593/16578285888_8def09b8d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Headlamps" /></a></p>

<p>The headlamps line got a refresh, and many models got more power (= Lumen) and there’s also a hole bunch of new, fresh colours. The Tikkina, Tikka and Zipka headlamps went up to 80, 100 and 100 Luen respectively, the Tikka + and the Tikka XP went to 160 and 180 Lumen and the Tactikka + and Tactikka +RGB are headlamps in more toned down colours (all black, desert and camo) are for hunters and fishermen. Both come with 160 Lumen output and have different light options which allow for stealth and keeping your night vision.</p>

<h2 id="scarpa">Scarpa</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765869135" title="Scarpa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8568/16765869135_77370356c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://scarpa.it">Scarpa</a> goes wild with the Mojito Wild. The upper is made of spotted or plain color “cavallino” leather and the sole is the Spider Trek sole in all black. They’re probably going to be wildly popular, as I imagine the Mojito Patchwork will be, where every shoe will be totally unique as they are hand-sewed, with each square being different thus making every upper completely unique. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578271698" title="Scarpa Alien 2.0 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7632/16578271698_070961ef9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Alien 2.0" /></a></p>

<p>On the other hand you have the Alien 2.0. It is a race boot that employs the Tronic technology – a ski/ walk mechanism that automatically blocks the cuff to the shell simply by inserting the boot into the binding which should give you an advantage during a race when every second counts. It has an internal gaiter and a full carbon shell and cuff and it is closed with the Alien Fast Buckle Closure and the Boa Closure System. </p>

<h2 id="the-omm">The OMM</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143535204" title="The OMM Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8646/16143535204_c40b372fa7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The OMM Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System" /></a></p>

<p>I really like to stop by at the guys from <a href="https://theomm.com">The OMM</a> as there is always cool gear to be seen. Take the Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System above. Both garments are filled with Primaloft Gold and weigh 390 g for the Jacket and 235 g for the half-bag. The Half bag connects via push buttons on the inside of the jacket to it to create one versatile sleeping system that weighs in at 625 g. The half-bag also has a draw string to pull it tighter and packs a mighty fine 16 x 11 cm when its in your pack. This will be a hot item for runners and (S)UL Backpackers alike I think, it’s a great execution of the <em>“Multi-use”</em> idea.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16739960016" title="The OMM Rotor Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7637/16739960016_563fa0f204_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The OMM Rotor Vest" /></a></p>

<p>The Rotor Vest tips the scales at 135 g and is filled with Primaloft Gold in a 40 g weight variation. It packs rather small as I show above when you don’t need it, but when you put it on you’ll be toasty. It has a zipper so you can dump heat, a hem drawstring and the chest pocket also functions as the stuff sack. The Purple colour above also looks superb!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764773562" title="The OMM Kamleika Race Smock II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7621/16764773562_ee7d0c4cd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The OMM Kamleika Race Smock II" /></a></p>

<p>The Kamleika Race Smock II above isn’t new but the colour combo is and I’m totally in love with it. </p>

<h2 id="extreme-food">Extreme Food</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765859435" title="Extreme Food Booth by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7599/16765859435_dae4ba6952_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Extreme Food Booth" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.extreme-food.eu">Extreme Food</a> had one of the most fun booths on the show. It was simple, but the juxtaposition of fine porcelain, sterling cutlery and wine glasses with a fine course of freeze dried food in a bag was just great. The food is made in the UK from high quality natural ingredients with no artificial colourings or preservatives, and I have seen some UK tweeps already tasting it and finding it delicious. And what’s pretty awesome about these meals is that breakfasts, mains and desserts all have a superb weight-to-calorie ratio: A minimum of 4.8 kcal per g! That means each pouch weighs 102 g and gives you 500 kcal, which is pretty lightweight. Best of all, they’re <a href="http://www.extreme-food.eu/stockists.html">available already</a>!</p>

<h2 id="salomon">Salomon</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076604673" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8673/16076604673_f38509f1e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.salomon.com/">Salomon</a> had so much new stuff on the show that it’s hard to narrow it down. Lets start with the shoes, shoes at Salomon are always worth checking out, because they’re damn good.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510388979" title="Salomon X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8640/16510388979_1e088bcaa5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe" /></a></p>

<p>The X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe is the small sibling of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-4.html">Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX</a>, the mountaineering boot I already found awesome at the OutDoor 2014. It also employs a carbon midsole that is laterally stable but otherwise flexible, so should be great on these Approach shoes. They should arrive for test this week, so keep an eye on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for some tidbits on them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076575143" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8664/16076575143_c4dd257abc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074215914" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16074215914_94ffd2974a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>The Salomon S-Lab gear is probably some of the most advanced kit on the market and Kilian Jornet’s thoughts and feedback go into it. The S-Lab Wings above is a universal shoe for your trail runs that excels on the way down. This gives you more protection on the downhill and has a great fit in the heel thanks to the combination of Descent Control and the SensiFit-System, so that your foot doesn’t move to the front or sides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509153630" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16509153630_8f0df0d707_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510408099" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8623/16510408099_88b6153059_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>Shoes for less serious trailrunning were abound, too. The Speedcross Vario is the shoe for harder trails in dry weather, while the Speedcross Pro is great on wet and soft terrain (= MUD!). They’re built on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/salomon-speedcross-3.html">Speedcross 3</a> model with different soles and thus if you love the Speedcross 3 but need a shoe that’s better in soft and moist terrain, grab the Pro, or if you run usually in dry, desert-like terrain on hard trails the Vario will be for you. Why? Well, the Vario’s profile is larger and hence gives more friction on the ground, and there’s also more cushioning. The Pro on the other hand has the Mud &amp; Snow Contragrip sole, with smaller and more aggressive cleats. In the Pro your foot sits deeper in the shoe for a better ground feeling, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510422379" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8648/16510422379_2fff5b2640_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>The Carbon Ski enthusiast will be delighted by this combo. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696559455" title="Salomon Skitracer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8620/16696559455_15231a99b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon Skitracer" /></a></p>

<p>And the Freerider/ Powder enthusiast might consider a Skitracer the next time he drops into 3 meters of fresh pow and loses a ski. Because with the skitracer he’s able to find the ski again when it has hidden in that sweet powder.</p>

<h2 id="klttermusen">Klättermusen</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558580277" title="Klättermusen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8641/16558580277_eba0b13136_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Klättermusen" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://klattermusen.se/">Klättermusen</a> now entered the leguminous plants business. I think that’s rather smart, beans are after all super tasty and if you can make shell material out of them instead of oil - hey, that might mean some idiot oil company might not need to go and ruin the Arctic for us and the polar bears! The Nylon in their new insulation garments is made of Castor Seeds, which Toray and Klättermusen have developed together. At the moment the Nylon is made out of 60% plant-based raw materials but both companies work hard to bring this up to 100%. The plant-based nylon is supposed to have the same qualities as crude oil nylon, and at least trying them one and checking them out I wasn’t able to tell a difference, which is positive. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695481312" title="Klättermusen Castor Seeds Nylon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8595/16695481312_0f6ac6ec97_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen Castor Seeds Nylon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695203101" title="Klättermusen Bore 2.0 Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8583/16695203101_27fc10abf2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen Bore 2.0 Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Bore 2.0 Jacket that Malin models above packs 300 g of 800+ cuin goose down and Primaloft Silver ECO in the shoulders and back of the arms. Its shell is made from the new “Bean Nylon” and has a PFOA-free DWR finish on it, is made in a box wall construction and to minimize seams and cold spots the pockets have been moved in line with the side seams. It’s a super-toasty jacket that has a very nice cut, though the price tag of 500€ is pretty steep. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509118970" title="Klättermusen Frö 2.0 Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/16509118970_cfb512ab41_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Klättermusen Frö 2.0 Vest" /></a></p>

<p>The Frö 2.0 Vest is a midlayer piece for winter use with an Primaloft Silver Active insulation. At 250€ it’s more affordable than the Bore 2.0 Jacket but of course not nearly as warm! The high collar keeps chilly winds from your neck and throat, you can adjust the arm openings to be closed for keeping the warmth inside or open them for a bit of ventilation. The asymmetric zipper is perfect (all zippers should be asymmetric at the top in my opinion) and if you’re not a Vest-kind-guy-or-gal then you also can get the Frö 2.0 as a jacket. </p>

<h2 id="onoo">onoo</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764802102" title="onoo Jackets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/16764802102_60c5935639_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="onoo Jackets" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://onoo.de">onoo</a> is a young start-up from Munich which gathers to the urban cyclists. It was a bit of luck that I met them and I did like what they had to show. The three jackets all have a cycling specific fit and are from materials that are not worried if rain, dirt and abuse is coming its way. I had fun trying them on and speaking with the founder, and do agree with what he said: People know which jacket will suit them. I tried that one above on first and really like how it looks and feels, and while <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558587877/">this one</a> is pretty swell as well it’s maybe a tad less my style?! <a href="http://onoo.de/collection/">Check their collection</a> and pick the jacket which suits yours!</p>

<h2 id="vibram">Vibram</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695377681" title="Vibram Megagrip by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8681/16695377681_42a821081c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vibram Megagrip" /></a><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510345879" title="Vibram Megagrip by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/16510345879_0724a351fc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Vibram Megagrip" /></a></p>

<p>Getting a meeting at <a href="http://vibram.com">Vibram</a> has been on my agenda for a looooong time, so I was happy that after three years of trying I finally was deemed worthy. The big news at Vibram was their Megagrip sole, which has apparently pretty awesome grip on wet granite. At least they had a nice test parcours built up where you could try that out, but as I was already running around for six hours on the fair I was a bit shy in sharing my sweaty feet smell with others and so kept my shoes on. I’m sure some Megagrip shoe will appear at HiF HQ some day in the future, though, and as we have lots of granite in Finland and also no shortage of rain I will see if it performs as claimed =) If you too want to have Megagrip, you’re in luck: A whole bunch of shoe companies, from Scarpa to Salewa &amp; Arc’teryx, have used the soles in their 2015 shoes which are just hitting the stores, so go and get a pair!</p>

<h2 id="vaude">Vaude</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16145939523" title="Vaude Alphapro Bib Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8743/16145939523_9186a9abb6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude Alphapro Bib Pants" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.vaude.com">Vaude</a> is the “small” Family business which still turns out a lot of new gear. Not everything is ultralight though what Vaude really knows is environmentally friendly production. Lots of good stuff they are doing, and either I’m getting older or they’re getting younger in their styles because I did like quite a few pieces from them. The Alphapro Bib Pants above are Winter Cycling insulation Pants with Polartec® Alpha insulation in them and an Vaude Eco Finish DWR. Mesh suspenders keep the bib in place and a Men’s Advanced Cycling seat cushion ensures you can sit long in the saddle. It will weigh around 440 g and is an ISPO Award winner.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16579728219" title="Vaude Primasoft Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7627/16579728219_bb717ea6e7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude Primasoft Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Primasoft Jacket is a ISPO Gold Award winner and another cycling jacket. It combines Primaloft insulation materials with softshell materials in 3 different zones and is aimed at mountain bikers who like to ride in winter (Wait, aren’t they called Fatbikers?!). It has Primaloft Silver in the front and back, breathable inserts under the arms and in the back, a softshell material with a membrane in the front and kidney area and reflective details so you’re seen between dusk &amp; dawn and tips the scales at 485 g. </p>

<h2 id="hestra">Hestra</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578458280" title="Hestra Gloves Moon Mitt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8740/16578458280_8c9da35550_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hestra Gloves Moon Mitt" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://hestragloves.com">Hestra Gloves</a> make awesome gloves. The Moon Mitt above has a Primaloft insulation, a lambskin palm so you can pick up the kettle and has a liner, too. Toasty hands guaranteed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373244439" title="Hestra Gloves - Bark Powder Tanning by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7436/16373244439_7e472f0544_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Hestra Gloves - Bark Powder Tanning" /></a></p>

<p>New too is their vegetable tanned leather. It has been tanned using natural tannins such as bark powder. The method produces a supple leather with a unique brown colour and is the oldest known way of tanning. As the Press Release reads, <em>“The look and feel of a vegetable tanned leather is hard to beat and it ages naturally in a beautiful way.”</em> and yes, I agree. These vegetable tanned gloves were pretty, and the Abisko and Helags Junior Mitt above were very sweet indeed. </p>

<h2 id="madshus">Madshus</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764783932" title="Madshus IntelliGrip Skin by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8610/16764783932_451518694e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus IntelliGrip Skin" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://madshus.com">Madshus</a> has been making the IntelliGrip Skins, a special climbing skin for XC skis, since five years. Other than the full-length skins for alpine touring skis, IntelliGrip has the climbing skin only in the grip zone of the ski – just like wax or klister. The entire front part is made from polyethylene, the same material as the base itself, and since it worked so well, Madshus now integrates IntelliGrip into the base of skis. The first model is the Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic, a ski made for ambitious cross-country skiers eager to take advantage of a high performance waxing ski but who want to avoid the disadvantages of a conventional NoWax-ski. It
never requires the application of grip wax and avoids the typical disadvantages of NoWax-skis: the glide is much better than on any kind of fish-scale patterns and there is no rattling noise in an icy track.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143559784" title="Madshus Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic Ski by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7283/16143559784_7e473db14e_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Madshus Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic Ski" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143551434" title="Madshus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8677/16143551434_31fa052024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143540654" title="Madshus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7619/16143540654_56f8d9dda7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764801372" title="Madshus Glittertind BC Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7631/16764801372_d8c8563f68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus Glittertind BC Boot" /></a></p>

<p>More interesting for the ski-touring/ backcountry cross-country skiing enthusiast, the Backcountry skis from Madshus got a face-lift and now looks freshers as <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">my old ones</a>. Also the Glittertind BC Boot got a small update as the cuff is now a lot higher and is made of MemBrain® softshell material, which I think is a good development. </p>

<h2 id="millet">Millet</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765840625" title="Millet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7650/16765840625_8e13df02a9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Millet" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.millet.fr/en/">Millet</a> showcased their Triology Series, which is made for alpine pursuits in winter: Ice climbing, mountaineering, winter ascents, mixed climbing. Inspiration for the line comes from the winter ascents of the Eiger, Matterhorn and Grandes Jorasses North Faces of Eric Escoffiers in 1987. The garments are made of the most modern materials available and the “ingredients list” reads like a who-is-who: Polartec® Power Wool™, Polartec® Thermal Pro® Highloft, Tecnowool®, Gore-Tex® Pro, Gore-Tex® Helios Stretch, PrimaLoft®, Windstopper®, Schoeller® Wool Naturetec and K DRY™ - you see these garments will be made for cold, harsh weather and will keep you toasty and dry. Just climbing you need to yourself!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764693751" title="Millet Trident Winter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7598/16764693751_001e6b1e7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Millet Trident Winter" /></a></p>

<p>The Trident Winter Mid from Millet is an ISPO Gold Award winner and a lightweight winter boot for all you winter activities - from snow shoeing to glacier hikes, the Trident does it all and keeps your feet toasty thanks to a Primaloft insulation. It’s waterproof and breathable, too, with a DRYEDGE Membrane, and a Vibram sole to give you grip. It is crampon compatible and should be ideal for snowshoeing. </p>

<h2 id="trends">Trends</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509125580" title="Klättermusen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16509125580_3756bb738e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074209864" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8606/16074209864_6e71e31b71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16701345681" title="Montane by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8635/16701345681_59f8599c6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Montane" /></a></p>

<p>I think about half of the garment manufacturers I visited had these cuffs where the stretchy rim which keeps the sleeve in place was a few centimetres inside, and not at the end of the sleeve. This does make a lot of sense: It’s easier to put gloves on, or have “free” hands when the gloves are off but at the same time they bring the insulation point further down over the wrist and make the end of the sleeve straighter. The cuffs themselves also should get less dirty and it also might mean warmer wrists as he puffy layer covers them rather nicely. I think it’s a nice development and I’m curious to see if it is better than the traditional cuffs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558575287" title="Scarpa Alien 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8568/16558575287_a6c24294df_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Alien 2" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16592948772" title="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8572/16592948772_a6ec53441e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557739541" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8580/16557739541_ecb01807ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.boatechnology.com">Boa Closure System</a> has found its way at this ISPO into a lot of shoes, ski and mountain boots. I tried it on a few shoes and it was indeed very nice to get a good, tight fit and easy to “open” the shoe again. Kamik even used this technology in kid’s boots, which could make it easy for kids to close their shoes on their own. But also trailrunners, hikers, Cross Fitters and Skiers will be able to use the Boa technology, and I reckon it will increase even more in the coming year.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696398812" title="Ortovox Merino Fleece &amp; 260 Merino Ultra Net Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16696398812_bcc607ff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox Merino Fleece &amp; 260 Merino Ultra Net Hoody" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936837154" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7449/15936837154_b9fb3230a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a></p>

<p>Body Mapping isn’t really anything new, but quite a few companies have made some nice efforts with their garments. It just makes a lot of sense that some garments are windproof in the front and super breathable in the back, with stretchy sides for freedom of movement and warm, toasty hoods. There was, however, still a lack of aymmetric zippers in the face area. Lets hope a designer or two reads this and pleases me with asymmetric zippers in the 2016/ 2017 line-up!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557706791" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8660/16557706791_2827d34acb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937067704" title="Salewa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7421/15937067704_fac8cdc72c_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salewa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16372133760" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16372133760_09e8029623_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533491386" title="Haglöfs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7445/16533491386_7bcbb1c691_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs" /></a></p>

<p>The development of Urban (Outdoor) Styles and collections also is on the rise. As I’m myself am getting more interested in this area you might be able to see some more articles on this topic in the future, but for now: If you’d like to wear a Gore-Tex coat because it pours cats &amp; dogs, there’s a handful of outdoor companies which make those - and many more casual outdoor garments - in urban styles, so you don’t need to wear your bright green hardshell to the next client meeting. This will only be of interest to those who really need to look the part when they go to clients, or those who simply don’t want to wear their “outdoor uniform” in the city. Although, then fellow citizens might not think you’re an <a href="http://www.der-postillon.com/2014/12/mann-mit-jack-wolfskin-jacke.html">Extreme Mountaineer</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074253404" title="Petzl Sitta by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8682/16074253404_1884e493af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Sitta" /></a></p>

<h2 id="other-ispo-reports">Other ISPO Reports</h2>

<p>There was a host of other great bloggers at the ISPO and I was fortunate to meet many of them. Here’s in no particular order the outdoor bloggers who also wrote about the ISPO 2015: <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2015/02/weltgroesste-sportmesse-ispo-2015-bunt-wars.html">Outdoor Mädchen</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Wandervideoblog">Wander Video Blog</a>, <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/ispo-2015-munchen-trends-and-happenings/">Klimbing Korns</a>, <a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/outdoor-ausrustung/auf-der-ispo-2015/">Auf-den-Berg.de</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoor-blog.com/ispo-2015-eindruecke/">Outdoor Blog</a>, <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/tag/ispo/">Zwerg am Berg</a>, <a href="http://linaluftig.de/impressionen-von-der-ispo-2015/">Lina Luftig</a>, <a href="http://www.uptothetop.de/2015/02/06/ispo-2015-fuer-trailrunner/">Up to the Top</a>, <a href="http://www.wusaonthemountain.at/2015/02/ispo-2015-neuheiten-und-bewahrtes-ein.html">Wusa on the Mountain</a>, <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/ispo-2015-die-gipfelglueck-highlights/">Gipfel Glück</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoor-blog.org/ispo-2015-meine-erlebnisse/">Outdoor-Blog</a>, <a href="http://wandersuechtig.de/outdoor-news-neuheiten-aus-dem-outdoor-bereich/item/1056-die-ispo-2015-das-top-thema-war-die-nachhaltigkeit">Wandersüchtig</a> and <a href="http://www.airfreshing.com/messe/ispo">airfreshing.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696486635" title="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8565/16696486635_d884e3755a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ispo-2015-conclusions">ISPO 2015 Conclusions</h2>

<p><em>“Have you seen something new yet?”</em> / <em>“No, pretty much all the same just with a new marketing twist on it”</em></p>

<p>I had close to 40 meetings in three full days, so you get slightly blind to the stuff you’re being presented. Some stuff is really nice, innovative and cool, while other things are just the same old in a new colour. There are these companies who are honest about that fact, while others do as if they re-invent the wheel every year anew. This can get rather tiring if you get to see yet another synthetic/ Merino wool fabric mix that’s supposed to be the best thing yet and hasn’t been done before. Strangely I have been wearing that kind of garments since a while, though they didn’t have the XYZ Logo on it but were from ABC. Ah well, better take another sip of that good Espresso so I have enough processing power for the rest of the meeting(s).</p>

<p>Similar feelings I get with <em>“Our Responsible Down Standard”</em> being flavoured in yet another new name you haven’t heard of before and a totally fascinating story, which, thanks to the coffee you just had, happily doesn’t make you yawn. I’m not working for one company, so I get to see a bit more. I also read (BOOKS! Magazines! Imagine, death trees) and am curious, trying to question some things. So that’s why I don’t make somersaults if presented the best new thing for 2015 since, ähem, yeah, wait, since when exactly?</p>

<p>Four weeks after the ISPO closed it’s gates I’m hard-pressed to tell you what super-duper awesome new gear should be on your must-watch list - but to be honest, already on the fair I had difficulties with that, as the intro sentence maybe showed. Nevertheless, looking back through my <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157650454379737/">ISPO photos</a> and re-reading my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">ISPO 2015 posts</a> I can say that yes, there has been some interesting new outdoor gear on the show and my top five would be (in no particular order):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ortovox SAM 3D</li>
  <li>The DPS Tour 1 ski touring skis</li>
  <li>The Arc’teryx gloves that can be layered</li>
  <li>The Petzl Sitta harness</li>
  <li>The OMM “sleep system”</li>
</ul>

<p>Except the first one - the Ortovox SAM 3D - nothing utterly blew my mind, but as I wrote in my post about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">Ortovox</a> news and the SAM 3D, I think this is a superb invention which was - when you see it - so obvious that one can but wonder why something like this hasn’t been thought of before. It’s a very nice executed thing that brings the outdoors indoors and makes your time in the mountains more safe and fun. And that’s what it’s all about, in the end, isn’t it? </p>

<p>And if you liked The ISPO News articles, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> and then share it with your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, because <strong>sharing is caring</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16372182530" title="VAUDE by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7362/16372182530_d165a44357_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="VAUDE" /></a></p>

<p><em>Ah ja, wait: I was handed a prototype of a fluffy thing that my ideas and feedback has been going in to since last year and which I have tested sicne I’m back home. That is a pretty neat thing, which definitely should be on your list of “things to watch” if you like fluffy warm things.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-03T21:33:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Where there is gear, there will be gear nerds.</em> ISPO News 3.0 - enjoy this edition responsibly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695183181" title="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/16695183181_479778a57b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rab">Rab</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076720273" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/16076720273_ea53aff4b5_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://rab.uk.com">Rab</a> had a bunch of really excellent kit on display. The eye-catcher at the start of the booth was the new Expedition 8000 Suit which comes as a Jacket &amp; Salopettes combination (1.340 g and 850 g respectively) or as a suit (1.990 g). Kit for seriously high peaks or when the next ice age comes, but not for this rubbish winter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509074268" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16509074268_1bce8e8408_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>Kit that is more suitable for this winter is the new Rock/ Lifestyle collection which comes with a mighty fine Rab hoody, cool shirts and nice trousers for climbing and chilling at the crag. Women and men will be equally able to dress up in these garments, which already now are very popular with the Rab athletes. The Headwall Hoody above (539 g) feels great, but I liked even more the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076700173/">Elevation Pull-On</a> which had a really nice hood design. The Rockover Pant (305 g) could also become popular with hikers, but it’s made for climbing and allows for freedom of movement.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695361681" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8639/16695361681_19203731d9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>But lets move on to more technical garments, and there was no shortage of these. A big news was that Rab now uses Fluorocarbon-free Hydrophobic Down in all their down garments, which is good news for those of us who use their down garments in cold &amp; wet environments. I tried on a handful of them and they had the Rab-typical great, alpine fit. Many down-garments also now get a body-mapping construction with using different baffles constructions in different areas, like the Electron Jacket pictured above (470 g) which has a Pertex Endurance shell and has Stitch-through Midi baffles in the torso, back and hood and smaller Stitch-through Mini baffles on the side and arms - if you look closely you can see the different baffle sizes in the photo. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16670728016" title="Rab Paradox Pull-On by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16670728016_2d12aeb551_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab Paradox Pull-On" /></a></p>

<p>But it ain’t all down. The Paradox Pull-On uses Polartec® Alpha™ insulation  with a super-stretchy lining and shell. A deep zipper helps with dumping heat on fast ascents or runs, and if you don’t need it the 360 g top packs away small. This was a really nice piece and would be great as a autumn layering piece or on its own on cool days.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509065258" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16509065258_987eed6411_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695337601" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/16695337601_74ef7c6005_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509251460" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8676/16509251460_80916e78a3_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076708763" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8591/16076708763_f2d4130b34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>There was a bunch more really innovative backpacking/ hillwalking/ climbing/ mountaineering &amp; lifestyle garments to be seen, so you can start saving your $€£ for the coming winter because you’ll want to pick up some of these.</p>

<h2 id="dps-skis">DPS Skis</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16670544676" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8617/16670544676_b52b5f54f1_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a></p>

<p>What I love about these trade fairs is meeting the people who love what they can do with their products. At <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com">DPS Skis</a> I asked my contact which of these he’s riding. <em>“I love the <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com/en/skis/all-mountain-mixed-snow/wailer-99.html">Wailer 99</a> with <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/dynafit-tlt-radical-st2-anniversary-touring-binding-90mm/?pid=81">Dynafit Radical bindings</a> and a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/la-sportiva-syborg-tourenskischuhe/">La Sportiva Syborg</a> boot”</em> he told me, and then and there I knew that we’d get along just fine! That’s a pretty awesome and lightweight setup, and best of all: You too could get it! Because unlike other manufacturers DPS Skis sells their brand-new and ISPO Award winning <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com/en/skis.html">Tour 1 Skis</a> already now. So the Tour 1 are lightweight (1.350 g for the 176 cm Wailer 99!) backcountry touring skis which also perform very nicely on the way down the mountain. Because you shouldn’t invest energy in long tours if you can not enjoy the descent!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076525313" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16076525313_102f653bcf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509082860" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16509082860_2ee66fff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a></p>

<h2 id="patagonia">Patagonia</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695584932" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8650/16695584932_5080e45b2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a> Backcountry Experience collection is divided into five lines: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Lift Access, for quick-strike, done-in-a-day missions</li>
  <li>Free Tour, for more committing powder missions that require traveling a little deeper into the backcountry</li>
  <li>Steeps, for descents extreme enough to require technical climbing skills</li>
  <li>Alpine Touring, for traveling deep and extensively through the snow-covered backcountry</li>
  <li>Approach, for when climbing is the primary objective and skis are necessary tools for access</li>
</ul>

<p>These lines have been developed in cooperation of the Snow and Alpine Teams from Patagonia, and what I saw at the fair looked really swell. Technical fabrics, functional fit and design, all made with the Patagonia-typical environmental thoughts in mind. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076667093" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8588/16076667093_4063b2fdd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia" /></a></p>

<p>Another big news is the completely renewed baselayer line-up. The collection is structured into four categories: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Daily, for the stuff you wear each day to the office or grocery shopping by bike in winter</li>
  <li>Lightweight, having the lightest-weight, fastest-drying and best-wicking baselayers</li>
  <li>Midweight, being the most versatile baselayer with the greatest comfort range</li>
  <li>Thermal Weight, the warmest, most breathable baselayer with minimal bulk</li>
</ul>

<p>This is applicable to both the Merino and Capilene® baselayers. Capilene® got an updated fabric that is made from recycled Polyester with better odour control and wicking. The fit has been made the “Slim Fit” across the last three categories (Lightweight, Midweight, Thermal Weight) and everything is recyclable through the Common Threads recycling programme. The baselayers felt soft and nice to the touch, but of course only wearing them one could start to make an opinion on them. The Merino line is made from Patagonian wool and has very nice stripe designs and also felt great. And as you can see above - the whole packaging has been renewed. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510473569" title="Patagonia Denim by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8658/16510473569_ae4d2de148_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Denim" /></a></p>

<p>And then there are Jeans. I haven’t worn a jeans in probably five years but it’s still the de-facto pants for many people. I know that Jeans/ Denim manufacturing is a filthy business, so it’s good to see that Patagonia is setting out to change that. Patagonia® Denim uses 100% organic cotton grown without polluting fertilizers, poisonous pesticides or herbicides. A low-impact dyeing process enables them to dramatically reduce water, energy and chemical use and produce less carbon dioxide. Patagonia also never distress their denim with harsh chemicals or other methods. And the garments are Fair Trade Certified™ for sewing, which makes Patagonia Denim the way denim should be made. Here you can read more about the <a href="http://www.google.fi/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;ved=0CCAQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.iswa.org%2Findex.php%3FeID%3Dtx_iswaknowledgebase_download%26documentUid%3D3184&amp;ei=RW71VPe1D-LXyQOetoDACA&amp;usg=AFQjCNHqwl6f-JkE2wcteEE4OLckX1xvWA&amp;sig2=PCCiF7jMnwRhXQBpOAYj9A&amp;bvm=bv.87269000,d.bGQ">Environmental impact of denim product</a>.</p>

<h2 id="marmot">Marmot</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16489359707" title="Marmot Cerro Torre Jacket, Quasar Hoody &amp; Alpinist Bib by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/16489359707_25edc395ba_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Marmot Cerro Torre Jacket, Quasar Hoody &amp; Alpinist Bib" /></a></p>

<p>The Cerro Torre Jacket from <a href="http://marmot.de">Marmot</a> got a full technical revamp and now promises even better performance than its predecessor. Made from the new 3-layer Gore-Tex® C-Knit fabric the jacket is super-light and stays durably waterproof and windproof. The C-Knit gives it a soft feel and an improved breathability rating, which means even better wear comfort. A snug fitting hood, pockets positioned above the level of a backpack waist belt or climbing harness, extra-long Pit-Zips and a two-way front zipper make this a versatile jacket that’s equally well-suited for hiking, trekking, all mountain skiing and freeriding.</p>

<h2 id="lundhags">Lundhags</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510378169" title="Lundhags Cobbler Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8680/16510378169_b0dc6473cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lundhags Cobbler Boot" /></a></p>

<p>It was my first visit at <a href="http://lundhags.se">Lundhags</a> and it was very nice. I got a pair of their superb <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/lundhags-guide-bc-backcountry-skischuhe/">Guide BC Boots</a> last year for Nordic Touring Skating and skiing and really like them, so it was good to see more of their gear. The big news at the Swedish company was their introduction of casual footwear. I like the look of the Cobbler Boot above, which has a mid height shaft that’s very flexible. I would have liked a more minimalist sole myself, but I reckon the majority of people will like it just as it is - after all, The Beatles wore shoes like this! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509112040" title="Lundhags Termik Jacket and Termik W&#x27;s Anorak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8674/16509112040_77a9bb082c_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Lundhags Termik Jacket and Termik W&#x27;s Anorak" /></a></p>

<p>The Termik Jacket and Termik W’s Anorak above are made of Lundhags Polycotton material that has a parafin wax layer. The material has a 16.000 g/ m2/ 24h breathability rating (minimum) and a 20.000 mm hydrostatic head. The Anorak has a separate inner pocket in the large chest pocket, and a long zipper for easy entry/ exit as well as ventilation. It’s a classic-looking garment made of modern fabrics (well, Polycotton has been around a bit under other names) that surely will find a lot of fans.</p>

<h2 id="ortovox">Ortovox</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16671498646" title="Ortovox SAM 3D by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8598/16671498646_6178105b7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox SAM 3D" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://ortovox.com">Ortovox</a> is a company I also really like. Creative &amp; innovative products, great materials and colours, friendly and passionate people - what’s not to like? Take the <a href="http://www.ortovox.com/accessories/e_329113">SAM 3D mountain model</a>: It’s a 3D mountain model for avalanche education that they created after a Mountain Guide contacted them and said <em>“Look, I have an idea”</em>. This model allows you to recognize and interpret topography, understand contour lines, lets you estimate slope steepness and and and. It comes with a map, a set of water-based markers, a handbook and a Clinometer. This is such an awesome and much needed product that one can actually just winder: Why hasn’t anyone thought of this before? That’s what the ISPO also thought and made it a Gold Winner!</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Kbok5Ie4Z4o" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696398812" title="Ortovox Merino Fleece by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16696398812_bcc607ff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox Merino Fleece" /></a></p>

<p>Alright, that’s not all though. The Merino Fleece Plus Jacket on the left use 350 g/ m2 of wool fleece and is mighty warm and looks stylish, too! Then there’s the Merino Ultra Net Hoody on the right above is a finely woven Merino shell and a large-mesh lining this should be bomber warm in really cold weather as it will trap a lot of air next too skin. The hoody will tip the scales at 300 g and because I love hoodies this one is high on my list of <em>“Wanna try!”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077491093" title="Ortovox Piz Palü Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8622/16077491093_50ab54c97a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Ortovox Piz Palü Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Piz Palü Jacket rounds out the layering system from Ortovox and is a super-technical jacket. It uses Pertex Microlight, schoeller naturetec, Swiss Wool and Merino wool to create one athletic touring jacket. It weighs 424 g and has a body-mapping construction which places the mentioned materials there where they make the most sense.</p>

<h2 id="black-diamond">Black Diamond</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509300620" title="Black Diamond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/16509300620_330b2ab9c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond" /></a></p>

<p>Since <a href="http://eu.blackdiamondequipment.com/en/homepage">Black Diamond</a> entered the apparel market they have been going from strength to strength, refining each season their line and making the garments better and better. This kind of approach is rewarded, and so their Misson Pants with Pieps Pocket won an ISPO Gold Award. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509299980" title="Black Diamond Viper Ice Tool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8599/16509299980_c69edd9bde_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Viper Ice Tool" /></a></p>

<p>I did like the Viper Ice Tool which weighs 570 g with the Hammer or 595 g with the Adze and has an adjustable FlickLock Pommel - which, yes, employs the same FlickLock system as you already know it from BD Poles. It has a Titan pick and the head is modular, so on days where you need two Hammers or Adzes you can leave the other one at home (saving 80 g/ 105 g respectively, which yes, means, the “naked” tool weighs 490 g). This makes it the lightest BD ice tool yet, and being made from hydroformed aluminium these will last, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695655422" title="Black Diamond Vapor Carbon 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8565/16695655422_8091aeb8cd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Vapor Carbon 1" /></a></p>

<p>The Vapor Carbon 1 poles weigh 310 g for the pair which makes it one of the lightest ski poles on the market. It’s a one-piece pole that’s made for ski-mountaineering - but that shouldn’t hinder the dedicated gram-weenie to use them for backpacking and pitching his shelter! Available in lengths of 115 to 145 cm in 10 cm steps they can be equipped with Powder Baskets and Freeride Baskets.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696687575" title="Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 32 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8634/16696687575_5c7ae756d5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 32" /></a></p>

<p>The Dawn Patrol 32 is a mid-sized lightweight ski pack that can accommodate either skis or a snowboard and is AvaLung-Ready. The AvaLung Element is a streamlined, modular AvaLung unit that attaches to AvaLung-Ready packs and is a lightweight, affordable avalanche safety technology that significantly increases your fresh air supply in the event of a burial. The <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-avalung-brg/?pid=81">AvaLung</a> almost triples the air supply when you’re in an avalanche and at 100€ it is substantially cheaper than ABS packs et al.</p>

<h2 id="haglfs">Haglöfs</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939316493" title="Haglöfs Hellner Gear by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7407/15939316493_bcfe6cd8b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs Hellner Gear" /></a></p>

<p>The new gear from <a href="http://www.haglofs.com/">Haglöfs</a> was interesting. The skiing gear developed with Marcus Hellner will delight the cross-country readers. Lots of Windstopper garments which keep cold wind out but are highly breathable, with body-mapping constructions and smart details like magnet closures. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373587917" title="Haglöfs Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/16373587917_55fcaed82a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket won an ISPO Gold Award and is a belaying jacket that’s mighty warm - too hot for me to wear indoors, so I quickly put it off again. Filled with QuadFusion™ Pro that has a windproof and waterproof membrane it keeps in the warm air generated by the body but is breathable enough to not be uncomfortable. The fit is to be worn over a Hardshell/ Softshell which is in my opinion also a great way to wear your insulation jacket during hiking/ skiing breaks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939328973" title="Haglöfs Mountain Pro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7454/15939328973_0e1627983c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs Mountain Pro" /></a></p>

<p>The Mountain Pro will only be available for Mountain Guides and SAR Employees - people who work in the mountains. Developed in cooperation with mountain professionals and the Swiss Alpine Rescue the garments are super burly and consists of the ROC Rescue Jacket, BARRIER Rescue Jacket, ROC Rescue Pants and ROC Rescue 40 backpack and are made to be
functional twelve months a year and be adaptable, not just to different weather conditions and temperatures, but also to different types of rescue missions. </p>

<h2 id="montane">Montane</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16080317554" title="Montane Primino Baselayer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8562/16080317554_d85f3c7c29_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Primino Baselayer" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.montane.co.uk">Montane</a>’s big news were the new Primino Baselayers, which combine Primaloft® yarns with Merino wool. These baselayers come 220 g and 140 g weights, with gloves, long johns and boxer shorts accompanying the tops. The idea is that the Merino wool draws vapour sweat away from the body whilst the Primaloft® yarns wick liquid sweat across the outer surface, allowing it to dry quickly. I got one here and will put it to the test so expect an update on them before next winter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16495352457" title="Montane Black Ice 2.0 Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8564/16495352457_026e758e44_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Black Ice 2.0 Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Black Ice 2.0 Jacket is Montane’s warmest down jacket and weighs 679 g in Size M. It is filled with 250 g of Primaloft Gold Insulation Down Blend and has a Freeflow Ultralite 38 g/m2 shell. The torso has a Boxwall construction while the sleeves have a Stitch-through construction. The hood has a wired peak and fits over a helmet. Toasty warm it was!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16701343571" title="Montane Hi-Q Luxe Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16701343571_986c395d26_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Hi-Q Luxe Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>Equally warm was the Hi-Q Luxe Jacket, which is filled with synthetic Primaloft Gold Luxe. Primaloft Gold Luxe is a new twist on the Thermoball technology of The North Face (which also was developed by Primaloft) I feel, which should be just like down but keeps you warm even when wet (unlike normal down, which collapses). The Hi-Q Luxe tips the scale at 575 g in Size M so isn’t too light, but it packs small and would make a good layering piece on cold days - but thanks to the Pertex Quantum shell you also can wear it on its own!</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
