<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-28T12:53:18+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-28T12:34:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <em>“Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off”</em> is open.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15897268395" title="HiF Advent Calendar Kick-Off by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7543/15897268395_9aeafa3031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HiF Advent Calendar Kick-Off" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>And so the merry countdown till Christmas begins, and again we kick it off with a fully loaded Day Zero Advent Calendar Door. Lets take a look what’s all in there, shall we?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/">Unterwegs</a> provides a sweet <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/ta-0211-496163.html?farbe=kauri&amp;groesse=19%20Liter">Tatonka TA 0211 Daypack</a> which is all the rage amongst us outdoorsy Lumbersexuals. It’s large enough to carry our provisions and a spare plaid shirt in case we get the one we are wearing dirty when chopping wood. It’s durable enough to survive a week in the forest and stylish enough to go to a trendy Café in town.</p>

<p>In our Daypack there’s a <a href="http://marmot.com/products/details/compact-hauler">Compact Hauler</a> from <a href="http://www.marmot.eu">Marmot</a>, a small and useful toiletry bag. It holds all the important cosmetics we need to care for our beards and skin, like the <a href="http://mawaii-suncare.com">mawaii</a> AllWeatherProtection, <a href="http://mawaii-suncare.com/Products.html">DuoCare SPF30 (Face&amp;Lips)</a>, AfterSun 75ml and LipCare. These help us care for our skin in summer as winter, in -20°C as well as +30°C.</p>

<p>That we can walk with the safety of a wild cat on frozen sidewalks in town we have <a href="http://www.edelrid.de/">Edelrid</a> <a href="http://www.edelrid.de/en/Edelrid/Sports/Ice-Axes-Crampons/Spiderpick-icemint.html">Spiderpick</a> snow chains on our shoes. These give us the grip we need on slippery surfaces and frozen lakes alike, and are easy to attach to our shoes and take off again.</p>

<p>On our head we have the <a href="http://www.mammut.ch/">Mammut</a> <a href="http://www.mammut.ch/de/productDetail/109004380_v_5617_one_size/Alyeska-Beanie.html">Alyeska Beanie</a>, which looks like our grandma knitted it herself for us, but on the inside a cuddly microfleece lining adds even more warmth. </p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=37&amp;products_id=51">eVent Mitts</a> on our hands ensure we don’t get cold and wet fingers in the snow and wind, and pack so small they fit without problems into our daypack.</p>

<p><a href="http://princetontec.com/">Princeton Tec</a> brings since almost 40 years light into the dark, and with their <a href="http://princetontec.com/sync">SYNC</a> headlamp we can continue to chop wood in the forest even after the night has fallen. The Dualbeam mode will make the night look like day and helps us to find the way back to our cabin when all the food is chopped.</p>

<p>Further inside our pack we find the <a href="http://www.vaude.com/de-DE/Produkte/Outdoor-Zubehoer/Drybag-Cordura-Light-20l-orange.html">Drybag Cordura Light</a> from <a href="http://www.vaude.com/">Vaude</a>, a waterproof and durable dry sack which has taped seams and weighs just 100 g. </p>

<p>Inside the dry bag we pack our <a href="http://bigskyproducts.com/Big-Sky-DreamSleeper-Deluxe-inflatable-pillow.aspx">Big Sky DreamSleeper Deluxe inflatable pillow with pillow case</a> from the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a>, for those afternoon power naps. A pillow is inherently more comfortable than a log to rest ones head on, and the Deluxe pillow ensure we can power nap in comfort.</p>

<p>Also in the dry bag we pack our <a href="http://www.whoopieslings.com">Whoopieslings.com</a> gear for our hammock. A pair of <a href="http://shop.whoopieslings.com/Whoopie-Slings-AWS.htm">Whoopieslings</a>, <a href="http://shop.whoopieslings.com/Tree-Huggers-TH.htm">Tree Huggers</a> and <a href="http://shop.whoopieslings.com/Toggles-Pair-TOG-WO.htm">Toggles</a> allows us to hang our hammock in the most convenient way possible.</p>

<p>So light and compact packs the <a href="http://www.traildesigns.com/stoves/caldera-keg-f-stove-system">Keg F Stove System</a> from <a href="http://www.traildesigns.com/">Trail Designs</a> that we also still fit it in our pack. With it we can easily heat up water for our afternoon coffee (black, no sugar!) or rehydrate meals when we’re for a long time out in the woods.</p>

<p>What now doesn’t fit into our pack anymore is our tenkara rod and flies for our after-work tenkara session. But that’s not a problem because we have a sweet <a href="http://www.zimmerbuilt.com/store/p20/Tenkara_Strap_Pack.html">Tenkara Strap Pack</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.zimmerbuilt.com/store/p39/Tenkara__QuickDraw.html">QuickDraw</a> combo from <a href="http://www.zimmerbuilt.com">ZimmerBuilt</a> to carry them with. The small Strap pack holds our small fly box, tenkara line, tippit and tools and the QuickDraw carries our rod and slides out of the way when we cast our fly to catch that trout for dinner.</p>

<h2 id="the-prizes">The Prizes</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15710705759" title="Tatonka TA 0211 Daypack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7468/15710705759_8fddfca730_b.jpg" width="783" height="1024" alt="Tatonka TA 0211 Daypack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15896741205" title="Marmot Compact Hauler by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7580/15896741205_e72bbdc27a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="808" alt="Marmot Compact Hauler" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15277092423" title="mawaii by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8629/15277092423_c1df819858_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="mawaii" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15896741195" title="Edelrid Spiderpick by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8571/15896741195_ee85c9c036_o.jpg" width="711" height="353" alt="Edelrid Spiderpick" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274473474" title="Mammut Alyeska Beanie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15274473474_eeb2c13972_b.jpg" width="854" height="1024" alt="Mammut Alyeska Beanie" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15894743421" title="MLD Rainmitts by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8649/15894743421_036125f384_o.jpg" width="648" height="656" alt="MLD Rainmitts" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15894743001" title="Princeton Tec Sync by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7471/15894743001_0d45660d5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="537" alt="Princeton Tec Sync" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15894742511" title="VAUDE Drybag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7468/15894742511_466dfe8dd8_b.jpg" width="421" height="1024" alt="VAUDE Drybag" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15709240378" title="Big Sky DreamSleeper Deluxe Pillow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8634/15709240378_444fbf1a68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Big Sky DreamSleeper Deluxe Pillow" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15896080742" title="Whoopieslings by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7474/15896080742_f613df4910_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Whoopieslings" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15709430200" title="Trail Designs Keg F by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8572/15709430200_affdc9bb82_o.jpg" width="857" height="582" alt="Trail Designs Keg F" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15710705269" title="Zimmerbuilt QuickDraw &amp; Tenkara Strap Pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7470/15710705269_dd71ffa46d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Zimmerbuilt QuickDraw &amp; Tenkara Strap Pack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="enter">Enter!</h2>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd89528/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd89528" data-theme="classic" data-template="" id="rcwidget_bgnu4db1">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/advent-calendar-2014-the-rules.html">Read The Rules</a>. All prizes are send directly from the manufacturer. You can choose the size of the Spiderpick snow chains (shoes NOT included). Also the tenkara rod and line are NOT included in the ZimmerBuilt kit.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar 2014 - The Rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/advent-calendar-2014-the-rules.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-28T11:06:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/advent-calendar-2014-the-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8230998731/" title="HiF Advent Calendar"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8350/8230998731_e265161b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HiF Advent Calendar Logo" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Welcome again to a new Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar! Like in the years before, a smooth foundation (so a good set of rules) makes running this a lot easier for everyone involved. Read them carefully and everything will be clear. </p>

<p>This years calendar will run 25 days (= 25 Doors), and behind each door you will find a fine piece of brand-new gear which should make your next outdoor adventure more fun and easy. Some information on the prizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>All prizes are sent directly from the company providing them. </li>
  <li>Sometimes it is possible that you can choose size, colour and other variables. Where this is the case, it will be mentioned in the text of the Door.</li>
  <li>This means garments can be either female or male, backpacks can be different torso sizes, shoes can be in different sizes, and meals can be vegetarian or with meat. Just the skis, those come as they are!</li>
</ul>

<p>So plenty of nice outdoor gear, and to enter a chance to win something you should check in each day here and enter the raffle. There are a couple of things to keep in mind, though:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You only can win once. If you don’t win one day, you still can try your luck the next day!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I am using a paid-for version of <a href="https://www.rafflecopter.com/">Rafflecopter</a> for the Give-Aways. With Rafflecopter you can get multiple entries by following someone on Twitter, Like a page on Facebook, Follow a Pinterest page or susbscribe to a Mailing List. This increases your chances to win, but is not mandatory.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Rafflecopter Widget is integrated with <a href="http://www.random.org/">Random.org</a> and it choses the winner. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Once you won, I contact you via the provided Email address and you have 24 hours to reply. If I don’t hear from you, I imagine you don’t want the item and will let Random.org chose a new winner.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Posts go online in the morning around nine-ish, and the raffles close at midnight - Finnish time. Rafflecopter then will show the name of the winner after I pushed that button, this keeps posts to a minimum.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It is open to everyone. As in from Afghanistan to Zambia, prices are send everywhere (unless noted otherwise).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can’t bribe me or anyone involved to win. You use the item(s) on your own responsibility. Use common sense.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That’s it, really. The Advent Calendar starts today, the 28th of November. Subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/105082905705272949032">Google+</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to stay up-to-date and don’t miss it!</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: All gear is sponsored. I try to not spend all time in front of a screen so relax if a post goes up a tad late or I don’t reply an email asap.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bouldering on Åland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/bouldering-on-aland.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-25T14:09:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/bouldering-on-aland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In September I was lucky enough to visit Åland, the magical island that’s right in the middle between two of the best countries on this planet. It’s well-known for many things: Fine cycling and sea-kayaking, a rich history, pleasant weather, friendly people, tasty apples and superb bouldering. The third week of our climbing road trip through Finland we directed our trusty touring van towards Turku, drove on a ferry and enjoyed the journey to Åland, the promised island of Nordic bouldering.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15876015612" title="Christoph on Game Over, 7c by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7483/15876015612_7334e07262_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Christoph on Game Over, 7c" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Once we arrived in Mariehamn, the capital of Åland, we made a stop at the office of <a href="http://www.visitaland.com">Visit Åland</a> to pick up maps and have a chat with our hosts. Then it was off to the calm pedestrian main street with nice shops and Cafés. People were sitting outside on terraces and as we were eating a sandwich we too shed layers until we sat there in our T-Shirts. This final leg of our journey started off well, with great weather and a gorgeous place to stay, the <a href="http://www.visitaland.com/en/services/dano-strandvillor/">Dånö Strandvillor</a> in Geta, almost at the other end of the island.</p>

<p>We drove there full of anticipation, and as we arrived at the beautiful beach villa it was even better than expected! Comfortable beds, great views, a sauna, a large kitchen and living room and even Wifi! We quickly went down to the beach to check out the sea, take a quick paddle and relax. In the evening the sauna was heated up, as it would be every evening, and we made a game plan on which sectors to visit when. </p>

<p>What follows is an introduction to the different sectors with links to their <a href="https://27crags.com">27 Crags</a> pages, though I highly recommend you to pick up the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/southern-finland-bouldering-guide.html">Southern Finland Bouldering Guide</a> as it covers the areas in depth.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15875744481" title="Our house at the beautiful Dånö Strandvillor by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7534/15875744481_eb79eecdb6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our house at the beautiful Dånö Strandvillor" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15258173273" title="View at Dånö Strandvillor by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8561/15258173273_c867565271_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View at Dånö Strandvillor" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fgelberget">Fågelberget</h2>

<p><a href="http://27crags.com/crags/fagelberget">Fågelberget</a> is the sector that’s furthest away - about 5 km of approach. If you’re going there for the first time like us, don’t make the mistake of following the electricity lines! After a bit of a detour we arrived after an hour of walking at the Puerto Rico block which would be our basecamp. We warmed up on some of its routes and then took a look at some of the other blocks around.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15688535418" title="Puerto Rico by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8616/15688535418_279ebcf532_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Puerto Rico" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15253782154" title="Moon Arête by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7581/15253782154_6013111b45_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Moon Arête" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15256394463" title="Nico on Orange, 7c by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8673/15256394463_f0d9ae67f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nico on Orange, 7c" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15253794814" title="Florian on the Finnish Roof, 7b+ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8671/15253794814_d2372a455c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Florian on the Finnish Roof, 7b+" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15690027729" title="Crimp! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7518/15690027729_2e8b030010_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crimp!" /></a></p>

<p>We tried some of the classics here, I did bit of theatre on a Highball, then we headed back with a stop at the roofs and then we walked out as dusk was falling. It was a mighty fine day and if it wouldn’t have been for the long approach we probably would have visited it again. Neverland was proud line that looked super high, and Florian tried the “Over the Moon” problem, a 7b Highball. Definitely an area you should visit on your bouldering visit to Åland, as even on a cloudy and windy day as we had it’s a good sector with dozens of high-class problems.</p>

<h2 id="kasviken">Kasviken</h2>

<p><a href="https://27crags.com/crags/kasviken">Kasviken</a> is the sector with the best approach: Park car responsibly next to the road, walk 2 minutes and you’re standing in front of Dodo in the centre of the sector! It’s also a sector where you really start to have fun if you climb 6c/ 7a and better, as there’s a lot of HARD problems here. There’s no shortage of 7c and up problems, most of it overhanging. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15252817094" title="Light &amp; Shadow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7471/15252817094_7332a02ba8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Light &amp; Shadow" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15877901405" title="Florian on Frispel ss, 7b by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8656/15877901405_02b141ac5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Florian on Frispel ss, 7b" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15877047812" title="Christoph trying Godspeed, 7c, Dyno by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7478/15877047812_70a9fb2bc2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Christoph trying Godspeed, 7c, Dyno" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15877181852" title="Looking down the Cortizone Crack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7567/15877181852_8848271506_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Looking down the Cortizone Crack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15875820601" title="Christop on Slobodan Monstrovich, 7b by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7481/15875820601_57d8a45c6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Christop on Slobodan Monstrovich, 7b" /></a></p>

<p>The location is beautiful up on a hill with well established paths and quite good landing zones. As it’s such a convenient place to go we went there twice and always met some people, but we never had to queue for a problem. There forest floor is also covered in blueberry shrubs, so a tasty &amp; healthy snack is never far away! We visited Kasviken two times and all five of us enjoyed the sector. This is definitely the sector to visit if you’re here only for a short time and don’t want to waste it on a long approach!</p>

<h2 id="grottan">Grottan</h2>

<p><a href="https://27crags.com/crags/grottan">Grottan</a>, also known as Djupviksgrottorna, was probably my favourite sector. The 2 km approach is along a super well-marked trail from the Soltuna Café - you basically walk on a nature trail there. The sector is on top of a hill with vast views and if t’s sunny you definitely want to bring enough to drink. Problems are mostly vertical and overhanging, and also here there’s a very high number of hard problems from 7b and up. Happily there were also plenty of easier boulders!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15690279358" title="On the way to Grottan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7539/15690279358_2529fdc504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On the way to Grottan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15252504814" title="Dust by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8670/15252504814_93030ed0f5_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Dust" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15692079647" title="Freddy on Hallonpingvin ss, 6c by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7461/15692079647_a869495cf9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Freddy on Hallonpingvin ss, 6c" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15257022793" title="Sunset in the forest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7509/15257022793_78a12a1355_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Sunset in the forest" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15691836959" title="Christoph on Supermartikainen SS, 7c+ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7491/15691836959_f3f740bd36_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Christoph on Supermartikainen SS, 7c+" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15690179748" title="Florian on Kalimist left, 7b, Dyno by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7490/15690179748_748e6aab60_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Florian on Kalimist left, 7b, Dyno" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15692018457" title="Sunset by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/15692018457_b91eed1fa6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset" /></a></p>

<p>Here I ticked a few nice problems and enjoyed the good atmosphere at the sector. Great views, a nice breeze to cool down, lots of autumn sun and an easy approach make this definitely the 3rd sector you should visit when on Åland for your boulder holidays! </p>

<h2 id="gunnarsklint">Gunnarsklint</h2>

<p><a href="https://27crags.com/crags/gunnarsklint">Gunnarsklint</a> seems a relatively new sector that’s also not that easy to approach. I think we were hiking for about 45 minutes through the forest until we were finally there. While there are some nice problems the area doesn’t seem to be visited that often, so you should bring a brush or two to clean the lines you want to climb. On the plus side were the nice views from the top of the hill!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15690345488" title="Warm-up wall at Gunnarsklint by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7487/15690345488_e5434648e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Warm-up wall at Gunnarsklint" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15876025062" title="View from Gunnarsklint by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7477/15876025062_cdfd4dd22b_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="View from Gunnarsklint" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15875738831" title="Nico on Superdyno SDS, 7a+ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7518/15875738831_b95ca7a3da_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Nico on Superdyno SDS, 7a+" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15692095117" title="Christoph on Mikon katto, 7b by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7466/15692095117_ac98824856_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Christoph on Mikon katto, 7b" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15851910266" title="View from Gunnarsklint by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7501/15851910266_19d697a89b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View from Gunnarsklint" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rest-days">Rest Days</h2>

<p>As you can’t climb every day hard we had a rest day, too. We visited an old ruin, went sea kayaking, played Mini Golf, went grocery shopping and simply relaxed in our fine house. Sauna, star gazing, eating, enjoying the stillness of the island - Åland is a gorgeous place and it would be easy to spend more than a week here and never get bored. There’s so much to see and try that it definitely is worth a visit, even if you don’t boulder!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15852090756" title="Blue bird day by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7569/15852090756_782332e3b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Blue bird day" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15877184802" title="Off for some sea kayaking by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7493/15877184802_586a0c9d34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Off for some sea kayaking" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15875853351" title="Barefoot and adidas terrex solo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8673/15875853351_7d331088de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Barefoot and adidas terrex solo" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15877145092" title="Buckthorn Berries by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7518/15877145092_2a8cf11d14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Buckthorn Berries" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15877244082" title="Åland! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8682/15877244082_503895c8dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Åland!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15301030592" title="Milky Way by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3886/15301030592_bb029c0f2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Milky Way" /></a></p>

<h2 id="thanks">Thanks</h2>

<p>This road trip wouldn’t have been possible without the support of many companies whom we’d like to thank for their support.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.visitaland.com">Visit Åland</a> arranged for us accommodation in the beautiful <a href="http://www.visitaland.com/en/services/dano-strandvillor/">Dånö Strandvillor</a> which we loved. When you go to Åland you can find ALL accommodation options on the <a href="http://www.visitaland.com/en/service_category/cottages-cottage-villages/">Visit Åland Cottages &amp; Holiday Villages</a>, <a href="http://www.visitaland.com/en/service_category/hotels/">Hotels</a> and <a href="http://www.visitaland.com/en/service_category/bed-breakfast-hostels/">B&amp;B</a> pages. There’s also <a href="http://www.visitaland.com/en/service_category/campsites/">campsites</a> if you prefer these. </p>

<p>A car is essential if you want to go on a road trip and travel on the Åland islands (although there are also busses there!). If you want to hire a car in Finland look no further than <a href="http://www.finnrent.fi/en/frontpage/">Finn-Rent</a>. They’re hands down the best place to rent a car with friendly service, competitive prices and great cars. We hired an <a href="http://www.finnrent.fi/en/category/minibuses/">Opel Vivaro Minibus</a> which carried all our gear, four crashpads and five persons in comfort and style. It also was super gas efficient and we drove over 1500 km on one tank load!</p>

<p>We got to Åland and back to Finland with <a href="http://www.sales.vikingline.com">Viking Line</a> and were especially lucky to be on the <a href="http://www.vikingline.fi/vikinggrace">M/S Viking Grace</a> on the way back which was a modern and beautiful ship. We enjoyed lounging on the comfy sofas and enjoyed the views from deck, and it was fast &amp; punctual, too!</p>

<p>We were very happy to visit <a href="http://www.boulderkeskus.com/fi/">Boulderkeskus Isatis</a> and enjoyed climbing there on our stops in Helsinki. It’s a great climbing gym with a well-sorted shop, Café and a cool gym to work out. You even can do yoga there and go to the sauna!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15690299018" title="Freddy on Angel, 6b+ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/15690299018_d82686c413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Freddy on Angel, 6b+" /></a></p>

<p>Gear-wise we had support from <a href="http://vandernet.fi/petzl">Petzl</a> and <a href="http://vandernet.fi/sport.php?k=16273">Jetboil</a> with a crashpad, rope and stove as well as crashpads from <a href="http://www.madrockclimbing.com">Mad Rock</a> via <a href="http://www.nihilclimbing.com">Nihil</a>. Without the crashpads there would have been no bouldering (or more broken ankles, which ain’t helpful on a boulder holiday) and the rope was very useful on our visits to some of the sports and trad crags. The Jetboil Joule boiled water for noodles and drinks in no time in group-sized measures. </p>

<p>In Vaasa we joined a day out bouldering with my climbing club <a href="http://www.highsport.fi">High Sport</a> and you can join them too for the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/756649124396284/">Vaasa BoulderFest 2015</a> which promises to be awesome. Vaasa offers some superb bouldering and there’s a dozen sectors with hundreds of problems within 10 km of the city centre!</p>

<p>Finally, my thanks to Christoph, Florian, Freddy and Nico who came here to climb! It was a pleasure to host you four and I’m looking forward to climb and boulder with you soon again. Also make sure to check our Nico’s photos on <a href="http://vertical-axis.de">Vertical Axis</a> as he’s a very talented photographer with a great eye &amp; vision and I certainly learned a thing or two from him.</p>

<p>As usually, you can see more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157647589227685">Åland Album on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15255431254" title="Enjoying the view on deck by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7482/15255431254_59734ee939_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Enjoying the view on deck" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pelago Bicycles Stavanger]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-24T16:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>New bike. New Adventures.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15242575763" title="Pelago Bicycles Stavanger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7554/15242575763_c58ed5e9a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Bicycles Stavanger" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Cycling. Bicycles. I always have loved bikes. And as someone without a driving license and being a household that has never owned a car bikes are our way to get around. In town, around town, in nature, in life. </p>

<p>I still remember my first bike. It was a hand-me-down from distant cousins that I fixed up with dad. Being a kid of the glorious 80s, it was a BMX, and my brother and me of course were proud like kids are of their bikes. Dad and I took the bikes apart, got new parts, cleaned everything and then put them together. The highlight for my brother and me was probably that we were allowed to choose the colours we wanted to spray paint our bikes in. We rode them forever - I at least. With the move to Finland I took along my Mom’s Holland bike, a 40 year old bike that still rides mighty fine. It’s just nice to sit in an upright position on a comfy saddle when you ride from A to B. </p>

<p>A couple of years ago then I got my first Mountain Bike. A 29er. <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/bikepacking/">Bikepacking</a> was all the rage and I did some nice tours on my own or with friends. I still ride that bike all the time, though with new work possibilities opening up in the future I looked for a new ride. A street ride. A bicycle that can accompany me on rides in town, to the supermarket, to the climbing gym, to the sea and beyond. A Multipurpose bike thus.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15860273491" title="Pelago Bicycles Emblem by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7517/15860273491_c813080961_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Bicycles Emblem" /></a></p>

<p>I’ve known <a href="http://pelagobicycles.com">Pelago Bicycles</a> for a quite some time, and always have loved their designs. <em>“Bicycles for daily transport and alternative travel”</em> as they say themselves. I’ve visited their <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11098456643">wonderful shop in Helsinki</a>. I interviewed the two brothers who started the company. I have been to their workshop and have seen their bikes being built. You get the picture, I like them. </p>

<p>So when that new work - more on that some other time - came along, I used the opportunity to justify a new bike for the urban and road adventures. One new family member. That family member arrived two weeks ago, and last weekend I finally had the time to put it together. The <a href="http://pelagobicycles.com/bicycles/advanced-multipurpose/stavanger-2014.html">Pelago Bicycles Stavanger</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15861617012" title="All thanks to the Shimano 105 5700 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7491/15861617012_f74ae43340_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="All thanks to the Shimano 105 5700" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15674725548" title="Love the clean cockpit on this semi-ergo drop bar by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7552/15674725548_b3186ae866_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Love the clean cockpit on this semi-ergo drop bar" /></a></p>

<p>A clean cockpit. A bike bell. A semi-ergo drop bar. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15860260081" title="Shimano 105 5700 Drivetrain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7513/15860260081_b98070c00a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shimano 105 5700 Drivetrain" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15862256265" title="The Avid BB-7 disc brakes are super powerful by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/15862256265_79b8555f9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Avid BB-7 disc brakes are super powerful" /></a></p>

<p>A Shimano 105 5700 Drivetrain with plenty of gears, one for each degree of uphill. Avid BB-7 disc brakes to stop me when I go too fast.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15676496547" title="Shimano PDA530 Pedals by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8667/15676496547_e2f520b163_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shimano PDA530 Pedals" /></a></p>

<p>Shimano PDA530 Pedals that can be ridden with normal or cycling shoes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15242579283" title="A Brooks B17 Saddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7581/15242579283_d71269167a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A Brooks B17 Saddle" /></a></p>

<p>A Brooks B17 Saddle, my second one. Comfortable, durable, beautiful, hand-made.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15860281631" title="Schwalbe Marathon Winter Tires by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/15860281631_edeb284094_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schwalbe Marathon Winter Tires" /></a></p>

<p>And because it’s winter, Schwalbe Marathon Winter Tires. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15242591953" title="A side view to fall in love with by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7490/15242591953_efbed9c7c1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A side view to fall in love with" /></a></p>

<p>It’s a beautiful bike, and I’m looking forward to further kit it out for the 2015 and onwards adventures it will accompany me on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review XCV]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/the-week-in-review-xcv.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-23T14:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/the-week-in-review-xcv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back from my Höga Kusten thru-hike in Sweden, which was just as cold &amp; wet as a November hike can be - but it was beautiful nevertheless!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15671072898" title="A view over the sea towards a moody sky over the Archipelago by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8614/15671072898_bd068d7c4d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A view over the sea towards a moody sky over the Archipelago" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/11/16/sports/clif-bar-drops-sponsorship-of-5-climbers-citing-risks-they-take.html?_r=3">A Sponsor Steps Away From the Edge</a>.</p>

<p>Can’t be at the Kendal Mountain Festival 2014? <a href="http://www.sidetracked.com/tv/kmf14-saturday/">Sidetracked has you covered</a> with their daily video updates!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kenilgunas.com/2014/11/the-art-of-keeping-warm.html">The Art of Keeping Warm</a>.</p>

<p>Nick ponders if <a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2014/11/17/its-all-about-the-number-8/">it’s All About the Number 8</a>?</p>

<p>Franz held a lecture at the University of Innsbruck in which he contemplates <a href="http://franzstraubinger.wordpress.com/2014/11/18/konnen-wir-von-tieren-sprechen/">if we can talk about animals</a>? [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://semi-rad.com/2014/11/how-to-be-a-writer-one-story/">How To Be A Writer: One Story</a>. Also useful for Bloggers ;)</p>

<p><a href="http://wickedoutdoorsy.blogspot.fi/2014/11/garlic-farts-and-all.html">Garlic, farts and all</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi/2014/11/lets-talk-about-advantages-of-being.html">The advantages of being a single female backpacker</a>.</p>

<p>Lots of cottages have special sales for the next few weeks: <a href="https://goosefeetgear.com">GooseFeet Gear</a> gives you 10% off ANY ORDER using the coupon code “THANKS” till the 1st of December while <a href="http://astucas.com/en/promotions/free-shipping-europe/">As Tucas</a> offers free shipping on orders to Europe. And <a href="http://locusgear.com/5th-anniversary-special">Locus Gear</a> celebrates its fifth birthday with some special items.</p>

<p>Backcountry.com lets you <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">take 20% Off One Full-Priced Item</a>, while the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/p/10-top-marken-im-angebot/">Bergfreunde have 25% off</a> on the gear from Haglöfs, Patagonia, Houdini, TNF, Vaude, Pyua, Icebreaker, Berghaus, ABK, and Monkee till Monday midnight!</p>

<p>And then there’s the <a href="http://www.outdoorblackfriday.de">Outdoor Black Friday</a> where close to 30 Outdoor Shops will offer interesting gear next Friday! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>I really love this <a href="http://velo-orange.blogspot.fi/2014/11/wine-crate-bike-basket-diy-bike-project.html">Wine Crate Bike Basket DIY Bike Project</a>.</p>

<p>Joe from ZPacks shows how to set up the new <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JFObVp43zgU&amp;feature=youtu.be">Altaplex Tent</a>.</p>

<p>Marc takes a look at the <a href="http://forgottentracks.blogspot.fi/2014/11/alpkit-brukit-review-part-1.html">Alpkit BruKit</a>.</p>

<p>Brian reviews the <a href="http://briangreen.net/2014/11/bushnell-solarwrap-mini-solar-charger.html">Bushnell SolarWrap Mini Solar Charger</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2014/11/gear-review-speed-cinch-stakes/">Speed Cinch Stakes Review</a>.</p>

<p>Chris reviews the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/five-ten-anasazi-verde-climbing-shoe-review/">Five Ten Anasazi Verde Lace-Up</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://indefinitelywild.gizmodo.com/outdoor-sleeping-pad-comparison-data-1659782011">Outdoor Sleeping Pad Comparison Data</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.scottishwinter.com/?p=4733">The Great Mountain Crags of Scotland</a> Book Review.</p>

<p>Chad presents his <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2014/11/22/butt-in-a-sling-bias-weight-weenie-micro-hammock-w-knotty-mod/">Butt In A Sling (BIAS) Weight Weenie Micro Hammock w/ Knotty Mod</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorwomensalliance.com/2014/11/review-ultimate-direction-ultra-vesta-running22.html">Ultimate Direction’s Ultra Vesta Running Vest</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15672818967" title="Natur Reservat by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/15672818967_bc83905b3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Natur Reservat" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Emily’s <a href="http://emilyroolearnstorun.blogspot.fi/2014/11/navlikin-or-kotur-expedition-kyrgy-mark.html">Navlikin (or Kotur!) Expedition</a>.</p>

<p>Chris Townsend tells what happened <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2014/11/after-pacific-crest-trail.html">after the Pacific Crest Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://tozantales.wordpress.com/2014/11/17/zao/">Mt. Zao – A final visit</a>.</p>

<p>Rick hikes the <a href="http://besthike.com/2014/11/18/langtang-trek-day-6/">Langtang Trek</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://desertcolors.blogspot.fi/2014/11/november-creek.html">November Creek</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/Phl82D57P58?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.americangrouch.com/2014/11/the-dry-run-part-ii_18.html">The Dry Run</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/2014/11/cape-to-cape-cycling-1000-km-across-japan.html">Cycling 1000 km Across Japan</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2014/11/rosvosektori.html">Rosvosektori</a> comes into ice climbing conditions! Time for a visit me thinks. [Finnish]</p>

<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/extemperaneousness/">Extemperaneousness</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seakayakingetc.blogspot.fi/2014/11/observing-nature-on-mount-laguna.html">Observing nature on Mount Laguna</a>.</p>

<p>John hikes <a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2014/11/el-pont-de-suert-circular-walk-no-2.html">El Pont de Suert - Circular Walk No 2</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=307857&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/307857/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 06/2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/trekking-magazin-06-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T14:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/trekking-magazin-06-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since last week available is the 06/2014 issue of the trekking Magazin!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15625818987" title="trekking Magazin 06/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5615/15625818987_f2c7bbd7e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 06/2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In the last issue of 2014 you will find in my Gear column a discussion of Hardshell Jackets for hiking. After discussing what a hardshell is made of and what it should have I review five different jackets which I have used this year. Elsewhere there is a company interview with ORTOVOX, tips on buying snowshoes and a visit to the island Elba in Tuscany.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15625820437" title="trekking Magazin 06/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7469/15625820437_4be22622dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 06/2014" /></a></p>

<p>There’s still plenty more in there, from fine hikes in Germany to gear news. Thus go pick up the last issue of 2014 at a Kiosk near you or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> to not miss any future issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review XCIV]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/the-week-in-review-xciv.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T14:21:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/the-week-in-review-xciv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m on a boat to Sweden to hike the Höga Kusten Trail right now, so follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> to see how the autumn-turns-winter hike will unfold!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15748496572" title="Frozen"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7480/15748496572_4c5f8206f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Frozen" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Davy organizes a <a href="http://walkers-anon.blogspot.fi/2014/11/roll-up-roll-up.html">Prize Draw in aid of Scottish Mountain Rescue and Mountain Rescue England &amp; Wales</a> - donate and wind sweet prizes from Ian Macloed Distillers, True Mountain and many more!</p>

<p><a href="http://jackgeldard.com/2014/10/24/blog-finding-your-limits-finding-yourself/">Finding your limits - finding yourself</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://news.coreyrich.com/2014/11/story-behind-image-best-time-photographer-right-now/">The Best Time to be a Photographer is Right Now</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-22-ab-hier-nur-konserven/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #22</a> is out.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.freitag.de/autoren/raffael-siegert/ueber-e-books-und-die-zukunft-der-verlage">E-Books and the future of publishing hosues</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.climax-magazine.com/alpinjournalimus/">Alpine Journalism</a>. [German]</p>

<p>The <a href="http://us1.campaign-archive1.com/?u=f52be6b77acbf695649694b8d&amp;id=c19e1bfc51&amp;e=aef4c16e04">PHD Winter Sale</a> is a go!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amersports.com/investors-and-media/media/news/news-article/2014/10/29/ski-touring-an-ever-growing-trend">Ski touring – an ever growing trend</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://themindunleashed.org/2014/10/12-things-taught-school-creative-thinking.html">12 Things you were not taught in school about Creative Thinking</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/bergfilm-und-outdoor-buch/reinhold-messner-ueber-leben/">Reinhold Messner – Über Leben</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Check out the new Wanderlust Equipment <a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/products/muon-pack-expedition/">MUON PACK EXPEDITION</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://anotherbirdblog.blogspot.fi/2014/11/anti-social-birding.html">Anti-Social Birding</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://popupbackpacker.com/technology-might-be-killing-wilderness/">Technology Might Be Killing Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>And some thoughts on our favourite form of backpacking: <a href="http://ulning.dk/is-ul-for-experts-only/">Is UL For Experts Only</a>? Or is it <a href="http://www.pmags.com/lightweight-backpacking-evolution-not-revolution">an evolution not revolution</a>? Ignore it all and go for the <a href="http://semi-rad.com/2014/11/introducing-the-heavy-backpack-workout/">The ‘Heavy Backpack Workout’</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://davemacleod.blogspot.fi/2014/10/bouldering-media-and-messners-castle.html">At Messner’s Castle</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://read.garagegrowngear.com/why-do-people-climb-mountains/">Why do people climb mountains? An Alaskan’s answer to this question</a>.</p>

<p>Get <a href="http://bit.ly/1tL4fzI">free hiking socks with your Icebreaker order at Bergfreunde_de</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Absolutely awesome: The <a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-494.html">G-Works Gas saver</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2014/11/bontrager-is-winning.html">Bontrager is winning</a>.</p>

<p>Dennis sleeps in the <a href="http://www.outdoor-blog.com/exped-scout-hammock-combi-ul/">Exped Scout Hammock Combi UL</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Book Review: <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/das-zen-des-gluecklichen-wanderns/">Das Zen des glücklichen Wanderns</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Basti ponders about <a href="http://www.beuteltiere.org/2014/11/der-perfekte-rucksack.html">the perfect Backpack</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2014/11/bushcraft-packrafting-survival.html">Bushcraft, Packrafting &amp; Survival</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.carryology.com/insights/specialist-carry/huayhuash-carry-joey-schusler-interview/">Huayhuash Carry</a> - the Joey Schusler Interview.</p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1x3bin7" title="Patagonia Kit Builder"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7541/15525319397_28459d7c0a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="604" alt="Patagonia Kit Builder" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://en.pzs.si/novice.php?pid=9693">Slovenian alpine climbers first to climb the north face of Hagshu</a>.</p>

<p>Early Snow: <a href="http://backcountrymagazine.com/photos/early-snow-earning-north-cascades/">Earning it in the North Cascades</a>.</p>

<p>When summer visits Norway - <a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/klettern-in-und-um-bergen/">climbing in and around Bergen</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Jeremie enjoys <a href="http://injuringeternity.net/2014/11/02/a-cabin-in-the-wood-2-latvia/">a cabin in the woods</a>.</p>

<p>Jill is <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2014/11/home-roaming.html">home roaming</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/109092069?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;badge=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1280" height="720" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The <a href="http://andyhouseman.blogspot.fi/2014/11/polishmichto-route-on-grades-jorasses.html">Polish/Michto route on the Grandes Jorasses</a>.</p>

<p>Hiking in the ALps with kids: <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.com/2014/11/wolkenstein-rundweg--Juac-Regensburger-huette-coll-raiser.html">Über die Regensburger Hütte zu Col Raiser</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Colin’s 2nd part of his <a href="http://www.tramplite.com/2014/11/arctic-trail-trip-report-part-2.html">Arctic Trail Trip</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pantilat.wordpress.com/2014/11/04/ericsson-genevra/">Ericsson &amp; Genevra</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2014/11/karlsruher-grat-panoramawanderung.html">Karlsruher Grat</a> in the Black Forest. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20354608/">火打山 2日目</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Toni reports from the <a href="http://www.tonilund.fi/2014/11/race-report-mammoth-march-impossible.html">Mammoth March Impossible 2014</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review XCIII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/the-week-in-review-xciii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-02T11:18:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/the-week-in-review-xciii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Imagination is more important than knowledge.”</em> - Albert Einstein</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445751220" title="Trebanna Sector by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5607/15445751220_96d616fe54_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trebanna Sector" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Happy first birthday, <a href="http://astucas.com/en/events/1-year/">As Tucas</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://ulning.dk/paradigm-change/">Paradigm Change</a>.</p>

<p>The Petzl technical insitute explains <a href="http://petzlsolutions.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/Zombie-Experience-Web.jpg">the basics of Zombie Escape</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/message/a-need-to-walk-ba8c06927e88">A need to walk</a>.</p>

<p>Wondering where to cycle next? <a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/10/29/european-bikepacking-routes/">European Bikepacking Routes</a> has you covered.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/win-stuff-online-competitions-hikers-november-2014/">Online Competitions for Hikers in November</a>.</p>

<p>The new <a href="http://www.alpackawhitewater.com">Alpacka White Water Raft</a> has a new (lame, imo) name.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.airfreshing.com/erfahrungsbericht-hoehenangst-coach-frank-uwe-reinhardt.html">How to get over your fear of heights</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.latvianalaskan.com/rants/">The Rants</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>John says <a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2014/10/farewell-to-osprey-exos-44-10000-km.html">farewell to the Osprey Exos 44 - a 10.000 km Backpack</a>.</p>

<p>Basti ponders about <a href="http://www.beuteltiere.org/2014/10/geteert-und-gefedert-in-der-ethisch.html">ethical and sustainable gear questions</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Jim takes a look at the <a href="http://adventuresinstoving.blogspot.fi/2014/10/the-kovea-supalite-upright-canister-gas.html">Kovea Supalite (KB-0707) Gas Stove</a>.</p>

<p>Knut tries <a href="http://offroute.ca/2014/10/31/chapeau-headgear-for-two-wheeled-adventures/">Headgear for Two-Wheeled Adventures</a>. </p>

<p>A review of the <a href="http://jwboutdoors.com/2014/11/borah-gear-down-jacket-review/">Borah Gear Down Jacket</a>.</p>

<p>Corinna tries the <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2014/10/erfahrungsbericht-wash-bag-scrubba.html">Wash Bag from Scrubba</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Helen shares her <a href="http://walkingwomad.blogspot.fi/2014/10/gear-review-haute-route.html">Gear Reviews Haute Route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/whats-best-climbing-chalk/">What’s the best climbing chalk</a>?</p>

<p>John has a chat with Evan about the new <a href="http://hikelighter.com/2014/11/02/interview-blackrockgear-the-blackrock-day-pack/">BlackRock Day Pack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=49337&amp;pw=73183">Check out ULA’s #1 Circuit Backpack, a 1.105 g pack with 69 l volume, Made in the USA</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445215308" title="Steve McLure on &quot;Power of the Night&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3941/15445215308_508e109f44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Steve McLure on &quot;Power of the Night&quot;" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Nick spends <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/?p=1509">Fall in the Spanish Peaks</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://thestonemind.com/2014/10/28/transient-power-travel/">The Transient Power of Travel</a>.</p>

<p>Heather Weidner reports from the road of the <a href="http://heatherclimbs.com/2014/10/27/on-the-road-with-petzl-turkey/">Petzl RocTrip Turkey</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20342579/">火打山 1日目</a>, a beautiful autumn hike in Japan. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Dave does a <a href="http://davesearle.me/2014/10/30/droites-north-face-solo/">Droites North Face Solo</a> while Charlie enjoys a <a href="http://chamconditions.blogspot.fi/2014/10/aiguilles-rouges-binge.html">Aiguilles Rouges Binge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.fi/2014/10/paria-canyon-40-miler.html">Paria Canyon 40 Miler</a>.</p>

<p>Fräulein Draussen visits the <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/wandern-auf-saaremaa-nationalpark-vilsandi/">Vilsandi National Park</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://glencoemountaineer.blogspot.fi/2014/10/ogof-y-daren-cilau-caving-in-south-wales.html">Caving in South Wales</a>.</p>

<p>It gets steep in Part 4 of Jörgen’s <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se/2014/10/brooks-range-vacation-iv-steep.html">Brooks Range Vacation</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cbjimtrip.blogspot.fi/2014/10/blog-post.html">気田川　川下り＆キャンプ</a>, a packrafting trip report from Japan. [Japanese]</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/110270168?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="1280" height="720" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://tozantales.wordpress.com/2014/10/30/togakushi/">Mt. Togakushi – The High Lands</a>.</p>

<p>Andy heads out to <a href="http://seatosummitultralight.blogspot.fi/2014/10/miter-basin-and-mt-langley-october-2014.html">Miter Basin and Mt. Langley</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2014/10/rollomixedin-jaaennuste-kaudelle-1415.html">Rollomixedin jääennuste kaudelle 14/15</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p>Jill is <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2014/10/ridin-range-once-more.html">ridin’ the range once more</a>.</p>

<p>Jeremie <a href="http://injuringeternity.net/2014/10/26/vasaloppsleden-the-day-i-went-stupid-light/">went stupid light on the Vasaloppsleden</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/10/26/a-greek-bike-odyssey/">A Greek Bike Odyssey</a>.</p>

<p>Greg goes up <a href="http://www.hikingfiasco.com/2014/10/mount-kooyoora-victoria-july-2014.html">Mount Kooyoora</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://dirtanddogs.blogspot.fi/2014/10/cliffs-by-any-other-name.html">Cliffs By Any Other Name</a>.</p>

<p>Mario went on his <a href="http://www.alpin-blog.com/1st-skitour-saison-201415-wildspitze/">first ski-tour of this season</a>. [German]</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.gif" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking Skills: Get The Most Out of Travelling to the Trail]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/hiking-skills-get-the-most-out-of-travelling-to-the-trail.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T09:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/hiking-skills-get-the-most-out-of-travelling-to-the-trail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’re not heading out on a S24O from your doorstep, chances are that you will be spending quite some time on your way to the trail. With these five tips you can already make the time travelling to your hike relaxing and fun instead of stressful &amp; tedious.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764088782" title="There&#x27;s the Sauna? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2836/9764088782_aa74826384_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="There&#x27;s the Sauna?" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Living in Scandinavia is awesome. You can start an Overnighter from your front door with your bike and can be in less than an hour in a wild place. But if you want to visit a National Park, Wilderness Area or a Long Distance Trail chances are that you will spend many hours travelling there - by bus, train, plane or car. The latter can be tedious and stress-inducing - the exact opposite of why you’re heading out. These five tips get you into the right mind set and help make the journey to the trail already part of the relaxing time you’re going to spend outdoors.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083811733" title="Road to Abisko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7443/13083811733_5834be0283_b.jpg" width="1024" height="541" alt="Road to Abisko" /></a></p>

<h2 id="choose-the-right-time--mode-to-travel">Choose the right time &amp; mode to travel</h2>

<p>Try to plan your travels to the trailhead always so that you still can walk without a hurry to a nice camp spot after having arrived. That means already planning the journey so that you arrive relaxed and at a good time at the trailhead. Several factors go into this and it’s usually best start backwards:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Try to estimate the time needed to reach the camp spot - I aim usually to be there by 20 o’clock. That means I subtract the walking time from the arrival time, which gives me the latest time I should arrive at the trailhead</li>
  <li>Look for the most convenient travel mode to arrive at the trailhead, be it plane, bus, train or taxi</li>
  <li>It’s smart to compare prices and travel-time between the transportation options - sometimes a flight can be just 20€ more expensive but several hours faster - and choose the one which suits you best</li>
  <li>Whenever possible I try to use night trains: They are environmentally friendly and allow me to travel while I sleep, which means I arrive early &amp; well-rested at the trailhead!</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9129336618" title="Calazo Maps Border by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5529/9129336618_a06884312e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Calazo Maps Border" /></a></p>

<h2 id="study-the-map">Study the map</h2>

<p>Sure, you were planning your route at home and have been pouring over this <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/maps/">map</a> already many evenings. But now you’re sitting in the daylight in the train and have another six hours of travelling in front of you - time enough to study the map anew, look if you can find an even better camp spot, consider bail-out options, see where to pick up fresh water and just simply get into the mind-set for the hike ahead. This also allows you to become more familiar with the terrain once you’re hiking, and you don’t need to get the map out every hundred meters to check for the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/grace_land/8681800072" title="Untitled by GraceOda, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8380/8681800072_7e82294800_b.jpg" width="1000" height="667" alt="Untitled" /></a></p>

<h2 id="charge-your-gadgets">Charge your gadgets</h2>

<p>If travelling by train, bus or plane in Scandinavia you often have the possibility to charge your gadgets while you’re travelling. This being the last chance to power up the batteries of your camera, GPS or smartphone it’s a good opportunity to make use of the free electricity. It also allows you to spend ample time on points 2 and 3!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14004820125" title="The Pictorial Guide to the Lakeland Fells by A. Wainwright by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2940/14004820125_91a7056da2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Pictorial Guide to the Lakeland Fells by A. Wainwright" /></a></p>

<h2 id="read-a-book">Read a book</h2>

<p>I’m old-fashioned and really like real <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">books</a>. While a <a href="http://amzn.to/1xyQgf1">Kindle</a> or similar would be lighter &amp; allow me to carry hundreds more books along on the trail, I usually have a paperback along for the hike. If you have a long journey ahead of you it might be worth it to even take two books - one for the journey, one for the hike! If you’re not deeply attached to your book you even can leave it at a railway station or a wilderness hut for a fellow traveler or hiker - and make your backpack lighter, too!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/infomastern/14567590309" title="Pastry with berries by Susanne Nilsson, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3926/14567590309_94b84d4326_b.jpg" width="1024" height="640" alt="Pastry with berries" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fuel-up-on-fresh-coffee-and-pastries">Fuel up on fresh coffee and pastries</h2>

<p>Coffee. Cake. Pastries. Bread. If the way to the trail head is long, make sure to have fuel breaks on the go, and have a cup of coffee and a piece of cake whenever you have a chance. On the trail it is difficult to get fresh cake &amp; coffee and usually involves getting your stove out, so while you travel make use of the Cafés along the road or in the train. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14855955819" title="Approach to Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5585/14855955819_2b5e7f275c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Approach to Mnich" /></a></p>

<p><strong>That’s it!</strong> These five tips help you get into the right mind set when you step out of your home and make the journey already part of your outdoor adventure, so that the door-to-wilderness-to-door experience is almost as relaxing as the hike itself. Happy trails!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review XCII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/the-week-in-review-xcii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-26T14:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/the-week-in-review-xcii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Live in each season as it passes; breathe the air, drink the drink, taste the fruit, and resign yourself to the influence of the earth.”</em> ― Henry David Thoreau, <a href="http://amzn.to/1nGQj8u">Walden</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15632190602" title="Kezban Camping, Main House by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3936/15632190602_3760215cbf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kezban Camping, Main House" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.dailycamera.com/boulder-business/ci_26750326/boulder-based-golite-files-chapter-11-bankruptcy-reorganization">GoLite</a> has filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection.</p>

<p><a href="http://greenlanddreams2015.fi">Lauri and Olli are dreaming of Greenland in 2015</a> - good luck on the crossing!</p>

<p>Dave helps you to figure out <a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2014/10/22/how-to-behave-on-the-internet/">How to behave on the internet</a>.</p>

<p>Angelica likes to hike on her own and shares <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2014/10/22/alleine-wandern-tipps-motivationshilfen/">tips on solo hiking and motivation</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Save up to 50% at the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Backcountry.com Winter Gear Sale</a> and get free shipping for your order over $50.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/">Bergzeit</a> has the latest gear from <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/ortovox/">Ortovox</a> online, well worth checking out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=271921&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10083/271921/55699/73183/image.gif" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://davesearle.me/2014/10/22/kyrgyzstan-september-2014/">Kyrgyzstan</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2014/10/camping-ellendalen-scrambling.html">Camping Ellendalen &amp; Scrambling Signaldalen</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p>Nico enjoys <a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/10/23/albanian-dirt/">Albanian Dirt</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/blogs/chamonix-conditions/15529785-the-first-ascent-of-the-colton-macintyre-on-the-grandes-jorasses">The First Ascent of the Colton-Macintyre on the Grandes Jorasses</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.limberlost.co/lost-idaho-4-4-return-south-through-eagles-nest/">Lost in Idaho</a>.</p>

<p>Erika goes up the <a href="http://ulligunde.com/2014/10/auf-die-hofats/">Höfats</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-490.html">北八ヶ岳ハイキング</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Skyler adds an <a href="http://offroute.ca/2014/10/21/coast-mountains-addendum/">Addendum to Bikepacking the Coast Mountains</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/107469289?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1280" height="720" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Christine shares her conclusion, tips and route alternatives for <a href="http://christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi/2014/10/paddling-across-southern-sweden.html">paddling across Southern Sweden</a>.</p>

<p>Ray Mears’ <a href="http://blog.raymears.com/2014/10/17/wabakimi-adventures-by-ray-mears/">Wabakimi Adventures</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://skyhighmw.exblog.jp/23627705/">Trail Session For Beginners</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Tyan at the <a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2014/10/the-start-of-west-highland-way.html">start of The West Highland Way</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blakeclimbs.blogspot.fi/2014/10/moonlight-buttress-free-beta-overload.html">Moonlight Buttress Free Beta Overload</a>.</p>

<p>Stefanie shares tips on <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/zehn-tipps-skifahren-lernen/">learning to ski if you’re 30+</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.twistingspokes.com/the-wakhan-valley-with-exciting-views-roads-and-people/">The Wakhan valley with exciting views, roads and people</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://indefinitelywild.gizmodo.com/hunting-alaskas-most-elusive-game-1649426313">Hunting Alaska’s Most Elusive Big Game</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15607640396" title="Trebanna Sector by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3950/15607640396_ef997616f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trebanna Sector" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Roger takes you down a walk on memory lane and shares <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/10/what-works-for-me-rucksacks-backpacks.html">which backpacks work for him</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2014/10/packrafting-zu-zweit-oder-packrafting.html">Packrafting goes Canoeing with the Alpacka Raft Gnu</a>.</p>

<p>How does the <a href="https://vimeo.com/109722405">Alpacka Raft Cargo Fly System</a> work?</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=379313&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/12135/379313/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard Interview]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T11:11:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An interview with Barry Blanchard, one of Canada’s most famous Alpinists, in which we chat about music, fear and his book “<a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">The Calling</a>”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15606594195" title="Barry Blanchard by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5608/15606594195_52bea0a1b6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Barry Blanchard" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Barry, thanks for taking the time to answer a few questions from an aspiring Alpinist in Finland. First things first: What song are you right now listening too?</strong></p>

<p><em>Snake Farm by Ray Wylie Hubbard. I’ve listen his music since I was teenager and had the pleasure of meeting the man, and his wife, Judy, yesterday at a concert in the park. Very, very cool.</em></p>

<p><strong>What’s your favourite medium: MP3, Vinyl or Cassettes?</strong></p>

<p><em>I listen to most music on my computer these days so I guess its MP3, although I still listen to CDs in my truck.</em></p>

<p><strong>If you would make a mixtape for a road trip, which songs would definitely be on there?</strong></p>

<p><em>On my road tripping mix there would definitely be: King of the Road by Roger Miller, Six Days on the Road by Dave Dudley and a cover by Steve Earle, Hurtin Albertan by Corb Lund and by Tim Hus, Running on Empty by Jackson Browne, Continental Trailways Blues by Steve Earle, Brand New Cadillac by the Clash, Cadillac Ranch by Bruce Springsteen, Born to Run by Bruce Springsteen … and the list goes on.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15421002960" title="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/15421002960_d3178af41a_b.jpg" width="678" height="1024" alt="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p><strong>I really enjoyed reading your book, by the way. It was raw, to the point and I had a few good laughs. It also had a Quentin Tarantino-esque feel to it at times: Good music, story lines that interweave and come together at the end. Did you plan it like that?</strong></p>

<p><em>My friend, Mark Twight, told me that my book would not end up being what I thought it would be, and that it would be more work than I thought it would be. He was right on both counts. I wanted to write a full 360 degree view of my life and climbing as I believe that much of the value in my writing is that which is common to all people: love, loss, desire, fear, hurt, joy. I believe I share the most that way and that is what writing is for me, a hope to share a little something about life with people.</em></p>

<p><strong>The weather this summer in Chamonix seems to have been much the same as you first visited the crucible of European Alpinism. Any idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer?</strong></p>

<p><em>I have no idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer. Mark Twight and I were pleased to see that our route, The Richard Cranium Memorial, had several repeats in the last couple years and that the ascensionists seemed to enjoy it.</em></p>

<p><strong>Reinhold Messner, another of your idols judging from your book, just got 70 in September. Did you send him a card or where even invited?</strong></p>

<p><em>Reinhold didn’t invite me to his birthday, but he might have invited my guiding mentor, Rudi Kranibitter, who took Reinhold out climbing in Reinhold’s early days and taught him some stuff. Rudi once told me “Ya, that guy was a fast learner!”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14985858864" title="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/14985858864_8c1c2399df_b.jpg" width="710" height="1024" alt="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You are well-read and have devoured a lot of books - from Heinrich Harrer’s “The White Spider” to Lionel Terray’s “Conquistadors of the Useless”. If you could recommend just three books to aspiring alpinists, which ones would that be?</strong></p>

<p><em>I would recommend: <a href="http://amzn.to/1xc7z5m">The Great Days</a> by Walter Bonatti, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vRe3bB">The Seventh Grade</a> by Reinhold Messner and <a href="http://amzn.to/12gRwtY">Feeding the Rat</a> by Al Alvarez.</em></p>

<p><strong>One of your colleagues, Andy Kirkpatrick from the UK, made in his essay “How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche” his first point to not have kids. You’re a father of two - do you feel you climbed harder pre-fatherhood or that you stayed on the same level?</strong></p>

<p><em>I definitely climbed harder before the birth of my daughters but I became a father at 45 and I was, by then, far past my physical prime that was, for me, between 25 and 35. I just can’t climb as hard now, especially at 55! as I could when I was younger. But! the inner journey up the easier mountain is still as challenging and rewarding, maybe more so on both counts.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15582918726" title="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3951/15582918726_29591133dd_b.jpg" width="672" height="1024" alt="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee" /></a></p>

<p><strong>As someone who likes to climb mountains myself it feels like the majority of climbers nowadays are rather enjoying themselves in gyms or bouldering. How would you try to get these people outside?</strong></p>

<p><em>I think that once gym climbers and boulders experience the added challenges of traditional climbing, especially dealing with risk, some of them will be called to the richness of alpinism, but it is a dangerous game so it is not for everyone.</em></p>

<p><strong>Is there a chapter of your climbing life that you wished would have made it in the book still?</strong></p>

<p><em>When I sat down to write The Calling I thought that it would cover my whole climbing life, but I’ve been cursed with a long memory and seemed to have a lot to write. I’d like to write a second book to cover the rest of my climbing life beyond 1988.</em></p>

<p><strong>Well Barry, many thanks again and have fun on the book tour!</strong></p>

<p><em>You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">read my Review of Barry’s book “The Calling” here</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review XCI]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/the-week-in-review-xci.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T16:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/the-week-in-review-xci</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back home from a busy yet unforgetable week in Turkey. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15406145637" title="Petzl RocTrip 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5614/15406145637_23e3eb4aec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl RocTrip 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?products_id=220">MLD 2015 APEX Balaclava</a> is ready to ship.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/featured-videos/adventure-videos/nature/Words-of-Wilderness.html">Words of Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>Pre-order Chris Townsend’s new book <a href="http://amzn.to/1vHvawC">Rattlesnakes and Bald Eagles: Hiking the Pacific Crest Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Backpacker’s choice of <a href="http://www.backpacker.com/view/photos/culture/35-awesome-outdoor-movies/#bp=0/img1">35 Outdoor Movies</a>. Or just watch <a href="http://www.servustv.com/de/Medien/Zurueck-ans-Licht">Into the Light</a> tomorrow.</p>

<p>Answer SparkMade’s 9 Questions on <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/s/PNLJM36">Why Independant (Cottage) Gear</a>?</p>

<p>Sven shares his thoughts on the <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2014/10/fazit-zur-e-o-f-t-1415-in-luxemburg/">E.O.F.T. 14/15 in Luxembourg</a>.</p>

<p>A goal of Zero: <a href="http://backcountrymagazine.com/stories/goal-zero-avalanche-industry-looks-change/?utm_source=8s11s&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=oct-3">The Avalanche Industry looks to change</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.fi/2014/10/avoiding-condensation-in-your-tarptent.html">How-to avoid condensation in your Single Wall Tent</a>.</p>

<p>A fine <a href="http://outdoorsmh.blogspot.fi/2014/10/myog-cuben-hybrid-pack-lid.html">MYOG Cuben Hybrid Pack Lid</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.rockandice.com/lates-news/tnb-clip-like-pro-5-tips-from-sasha-digiulian-and-sean-mccoll">Clip Like A Pro—5 Tips from Sasha DiGiulian and Sean McColl</a>.</p>

<p>Is the <a href="http://ivovanmontfort.blogspot.fi/2014/10/roclite-315-gewogen-te-licht-bevonden.html">RocLite 315</a> too light? [Dutch]</p>

<p><a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/the-zerogram-900-titanium-pot/">ZeroGram 900 Titanium Pot</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gearexposure.com/mammut-ultimate-light-hoody-review/">Mammut Ultimate Light Hoody review</a>.</p>

<p>An initial review of the <a href="http://overthehillsblog.com/2014/10/15/trekkertent-stealth-initial-review/">Trekkertent Stealth</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-491.html">Black Diamond Ion</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>The <a href="http://walkers-anon.blogspot.fi/2014/10/berghaus-freeflow-25-5-pack.html">Berghaus Freeflow 25 + 5 Pack</a> reviewed.</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/catch-hangboard-buzz/">Catch a Hangboard Buzz</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blackwoodspress.com/blog/20401/how-to-hike-15-to-30-miles-a-day/">How To Hike 15 to 30 Miles A Day</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/N6mb-VlY22o?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://sweepingthegarden.wordpress.com/2014/10/19/respite-angeles-national-forest-101814/">Respite</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://therepublicofdoom.blogspot.fi/2014/10/one-year.html">One year</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/10/15/return-to-albania-valbona-fierze-kukes/">Return to Albania: Valbonë, Fierzë, Kukës</a>.</p>

<p>The Deliverance Team’s movie <a href="http://youtu.be/uz_sRkKSyQo">The Venture</a> is out. </p>

<p><a href="http://benvironment.org.uk/post/99987726087/learning-to-scramble-day-1-fiacaill-ridge">Learning to Scramble</a>.</p>

<p>Christina catches the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/supermoon-catch-me-if-you-can/">Supermoon</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20285309/">裏銀座縦走, Day 4</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tramplite.com/2014/10/arctic-trail-trip-report-part-1.html">Arctic Trail Trip Report Part 1 - Nordkalottleden Trail</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/108679294?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;badge=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/bolivia/riding-the-railtrail-to-cusco">Fatbiking the Cusqueñan Railtrail</a>.</p>

<p>Above the clouds on the <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2014/10/13/ueber-den-wolken-rheinsteig-mix-im-siebengebirge/">Rheinsteig-Mix in the Siebengebirge</a>. [German]</p>

<p>The North Face of the <a href="http://biwak.blogspot.fi/2014/10/bluemlisalphorn-nordwand-3661m.html">Blüemlisalphorn</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://davesearle.me/2014/10/19/jottnar-aiguille-du-midi/">Jottnar, Aiguille du Midi</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bicyclenomad.com/2014/10/17/mt-arapiles-rock-climbing-the-family-way/">Mt Arapiles: rock climbing the family way</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se/2014/10/brooks-range-vacation-iii-rain-and-shine.html">Brooks Range Vacation III - Rain and Shine</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pinetflorence.blogspot.fi/2014/10/etape-4-les-meteores-en-grece.html">Les Météores en Grèce</a>. [French]</p>

<p><a href="http://mitsackundpackraft.wordpress.com/2014/10/12/packraften-in-finnisch-lappland-4/">Packrafting in Finnish Lapland</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2014/10/trip-report-west-coast-trail/">West Coast Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Derek and son are <a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2014/10/backpacking-sunset-trail-mount-elden/">backpacking the Sunset Trail on Mount Elden</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://howlingmist.blogspot.fi/2014/10/sneem-glorious-sneem.html">Sneem Glorious Sneem</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bencollinsoutdoors.com/2014/10/18/bikepacking-around-the-north-east-corner-of-the-us/">Bikepacking around the North East of the United States</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/" title="Ausrüstung für Klettern, Bergsport und Outdoor bei Bergfreunde.de kaufen" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><img src="http://www.bergfreunde-partner.de/banner/DE/AF_Banner_728x90_DE.jpg" alt="Ausrüstung für Klettern, Bergsport und Outdoor bei Bergfreunde.de kaufen" border="0" /></a><img src="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=30&amp;cpid=1&amp;prid=1&amp;view=1" height="1" width="1" border="0" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review XC]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/the-week-in-review-xc.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-12T14:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/the-week-in-review-xc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“I want to lead an important life. I want to do it because I was born a human being.”</em> ― Eiji Yoshikawa, <a href="http://amzn.to/119Lbjh">Musashi</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445679656" title="Sony A7R - Duckboard Riding by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5598/15445679656_4e76c924df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Duckboard Riding" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://backcountrymagazine.com/stories/mind-mountain-andreas-franssons-story/">Mind over Mountain: Andreas Fransson’s Story</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://backcountrymagazine.com/stories/remembering-liz-daley/">Remembering Liz Daley: 1985 - 2014</a>.</p>

<p>Paige ponders <a href="http://paigeclaassen.com/how-do-you-define-victory/">How Do You Define Victory?</a>.</p>

<p>Welcome to <a href="http://semi-rad.com/2014/10/utahlorado-an-idea-for-a-mega-state-of-awesomeness/">Utahlorado</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Sale:::35.html?refID=hif">trekking-lite-store.com Sale</a>.</p>

<p>Mountain Laurel Designs launches the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?products_id=218">M Quilt</a>.</p>

<p>Its <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/fleece-jacket/?_artperpage=96">Fleece Time</a> at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>!</p>

<p>For 72 Hours only you get <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=67763&amp;pw=73183">Free 2-Day Shipping on Orders Over $50 at Backcountry.com</a> till October 14th.</p>

<p>Chad on <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2014/10/05/why-do-i-hike/">why he hikes</a>.</p>

<p>And Amy visited <a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/2014/10/bonsai-cycle-works-tokyo.html">Bonsai Cycle Works in Tokyo</a>.</p>

<p>Stylish into the autumn with <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/chillaz/">Chillaz</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/patagonia/">Patagonia</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=197901&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/197901/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-489.html">Road to Yomogitouge</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://davesearle.me/2014/10/06/matterhorn-north-face-schmidt-route/">Matterhorn North Face, Schmidt Route</a>.</p>

<p>Uli visits the <a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/wandern/suedtirol/messner-mountain-museum-ripa-in-bruneck/">Messner Mountain Museum Ripa in Bruneck</a> [German]</p>

<p>Adam visits <a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2014/10/the-subcontinent-wrangellia.html">The Subcontinent Wrangellia</a>. </p>

<p>Rene goes up the <a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/durch-die-watzmann-ostwand/">Watzmann Ostwand</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Part 3 of the <a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2014/10/articulo-camino-del-agua-laponia.html">Planeta Packraft Packrafting Expedition</a> trip report is online.</p>

<p>Great crag report from Chris about <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/climbing-saint-leger-france/">Climbing in Saint Leger, France</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://fuusora.blogspot.fi/2014/10/fastpacking-shiranesanzan-in-2days_8.html">Fastpacking the Shiranesanzan in 2 days</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Angelica writes and gives tips from her <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2014/10/09/das-illertal-im-herbst-wanderurlaub-im-allgau/">Wanderurlaub im Allgäu</a>. [German]</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/108092536?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.skadinagrani.pl/2014/10/trekking-w-masywie-lagazuoi-16092014.html">Trekking in the Massif Lagazuoi</a>. [Polish]</p>

<p><a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2014/10/07/perseverance-of-fear/">Perseverance of fear</a>.</p>

<p>Jörgen enjoys the <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se/2014/10/brooks-range-vacation-ii-glory-days.html">Glory Days on his Brooks Range Vacation</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.downthetrail.com/hiking-backpacking-denali-national-park/tattler-creek-and-climbing-sable-mountain-unit-29/">Tattler Creek and Climbing Sable Mountain</a>.</p>

<p>With the packraft through the <a href="http://mitsackundpackraft.wordpress.com/2014/10/11/mit-dem-packraft-durch-die-entenlochklamm/">Entenlochklamm</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Chris on <a href="http://indefinitelywild.gizmodo.com/the-time-iceland-almost-killed-me-1642137050">the time Iceland almost killed him</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/10/05/eastern-enchantment-on-the-top-biking-trail-3-montenegro/">Eastern Enchantment on the Top Biking Trail 3, Montenegro</a>.</p>

<p>Roger hikes the <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/10/e6-korsr-to-hvals.html">E6 from Korsør to Hvalsø</a>.</p>

<p>Jonathan enjoys <a href="http://www.jstarinorbit.com/2014/10/new-england.html">New England</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20271543/">裏銀座縦走</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Willem is <a href="http://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2014/10/08/preparing-a-thru-hike-of-new-zealands-south-island/">preparing a hiking &amp; packrafting traverse of New Zealand’s South Island</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2014/10/10/into-the-wild-alone-in-sarek-and-padjelanta-part-four/">James climbs a mountain 200 km north of the Arctic Circle</a>.</p>

<p>John hikes around <a href="http://overthehillsblog.com/2014/10/10/around-martindale/">Martindale</a>.</p>

<p>Alex enjoys <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2014/10/the-gift-of-impermanent-permanence.html">the gift of impermanent permanence</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://skyhighmw.exblog.jp/23542815/">上高地ー立山室堂ファストパッキング</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html" title="Sony A7R - Back view with screen folded out by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15460478982_8e3b956b11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R - Back view with screen folded out" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Phil is <a href="http://philsorrell.com/2014/10/08/from-orange-survival-bag-to-hooped-bivvy-falling-in-love-with-bivvying/">falling in love with bivvying</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.coldfear.com/build-wall-ice-climbing-training/">Build A Wall For Ice Climbing Training</a>.</p>

<p>Amy reviews the <a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/2014/10/bullitt-electric-assist-cargo-bike-review.html">Bullitt Electric Assist Cargo Bike</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://koukidou.exblog.jp/23526877/">H.M.E system Pouch</a> looks like a smart stuff sack!</p>

<p>Jacob takes a look at the <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/small-things-the-solio-bolt/">Solio Bolt</a>.</p>

<p>Matthew on the <a href="http://hillplodder.com/2014/10/10/the-trouble-with-trailstars-or-a-brief-history-of-my-tents/">Trouble with TrailStars</a>.</p>

<p>Joe on <a href="http://thunderinthenight.blogspot.fi/2014/10/riding-tractor-road-gear-post.html">th gear used while riding the Tractor Road</a>.</p>

<p>Got a new <a href="http://bit.ly/1xS7sjj">GoPro</a>? The visit the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UClwg08ECyHnm_RzY1wnZC1A">GoPro Tutorial Channel</a> to learn how to get the best out of it!</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony A7R Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T06:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A 407 g Full Frame camera? Yes please. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15457679781" title="Sony A7R without lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3935/15457679781_9874095671_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R without lens" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Earlier in the year I had the pleasure of test-driving the latest creation from <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/kamerat">Sony</a>, their <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/jarjestelmakamerat/ilce-7r">A7R camera</a>. I’ve been a user of Sony cameras since over three years and while my Sony NEX-5n is still a trusty companion on many trips, I’m in the market for a new camera. So having being able to use the A7R in what I usually do was a superb opportunity that I wasn’t going to pass up, even if our love affair only was to last for several weeks and I knew saying good bye to it would hurt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460816735" title="Sony A7R and Sony NEX-5n by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15460816735_9cda8d1df7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R and Sony NEX-5n" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re looking for pixel-peeping and very detailed technical information, I’d like to send you to <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-alpha-a7r/">DP Review</a> who do a rather spectacular job with that sorts of things. If you’re an outdoor photographer, journalist or writer who wants to know how the A7R performs in the outdoors, I invite you to stay for a while and read my thoughts on this camera. I will delve first a (little) bit into the technical details and how the camera handles, and then discuss in detail how the camera works in the field.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274063999" title="Sony A7R - Back view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3934/15274063999_ae9d765df2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R - Back view" /></a></p>

<p>First off: At a suggested retail price of 2300€ for the body only and a good lens setting you back another 800€, the A7R is in my opinion a camera for people who earn a living with photos. Sure, if you have the spare change to buy a 3000€ camera you could get it, but chances are you either way don’t know how to use its full potential. And a lot of potential she has, the A7R.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15458998652" title="Sony A7R - Having a good grip on it by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15458998652_82cf23ce8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Having a good grip on it" /></a></p>

<p>The camera lays beautiful in the hand and it is easy to operate the different controls and functions with one hand. The sealed alloy and composite body is weatherproof and allows for a good, reassuring grip, even with gloves on. The 3-inch tilting LCD turns up and down and makes shooting e.g. Macros easier, although the XGA electronic viewfinder is where it’s at. The viewfinder eyepiece is large and comfortable, and far enough away so that you also can use it with (sun) glasses on. I have been sceptical of viewfinders in the past as (good) LCD screens are more than adequate in composing photos, but as my photographic needs evolve I come back to viewfinders and find them increasingly a necessity for my kind of shooting.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272647760" title="Sony A7R - View on top with thumb on the trigger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5601/15272647760_fddc5ae121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - View on top with thumb on the trigger" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272582069" title="Sony A7R - Thumb access to different buttons on the back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15272582069_311a4c0d93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Thumb access to different buttons on the back" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re a control freak you will love the possibilities the A7R offers: Three customizable buttons and four dials (front, rear, exposure compensation &amp; an additional rear dial around the four-way controller), and several buttons for accessing different settings (Menu, Trash, Playback, etc.). If you shot Manual the front and rear dials allow you to adjust shutter speed and aperture, while the directional controller lets you set the drive mode, white balance mode and what’s displayed on the screen. The shutter button sits above the On/ Off switch which I found comfortable in use - I could switch the camera on with my index finger and then have my thumb immediately on the shutter. The camera did need a moment to start up, something that might be better nowadays with an updated Firmware.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272723658" title="Sony A7R - Back view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3934/15272723658_9fc99380d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Back view" /></a></p>

<p>On the right side of the body you see in the above photo the dedicated movie recording button (red), which for my liking was a bit far in the back. The A7R has Full HD video recording capabilities which makes it a mighty fine video camera to produce super-sharp HD videos.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/QUHHBay1x14?list=UU927vE_KkPy6pFJboaJ9Lig" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>On the left side you have four ports behind two plastic doors: Micro, Headphones, Multi (allows you to charge the battery) and micro-HDMI. On the top there’s a Hotshoe which accepts an external flash or <a href="http://amzn.to/1yJHYWK">Microphone</a>. The A7R uses the NP-FW50 Lithium battery like the NEX-5n, which was very useful for me as I so could use my charger and spare batteries on tour. The default charging method is via the USB port which I think is a hassle, so I recommend getting the external charger or the battery grip.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274058359" title="Sony A7R - Side I/O ports with the Rode Video Pro on top &amp; connected by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3936/15274058359_b578a549e7_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Sony A7R - Side I/O ports with the Rode Video Pro on top &amp; connected" /></a></p>

<p>The A7R has an E-Mount like my NEX camera which means I can use E-Mount lenses - though they will crop the photo it’s useful if you already have a NEX camera - and with an <a href="http://amzn.to/1pMVoI0">adapter</a> also allows you to use Canon, Nikon, Pentax and other lenses. This could make it interesting for people who are switching from Nikon or Canon but want to keep to use their glass. With an adapter you’re also able to use other Sony A-mount lenses. To really get the most out this full frame sensor you’ll want to invest into a (few) Sony FE-series lenses. I used the <a href="http://amzn.to/1xl9bKL">35mm F2.8 Carl Zeiss</a> and found it a superb lens, though for outdoor photography I would have found a faster 16 mm or 20 mm lens even more useful.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460475032" title="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15460475032_be1fa0e188_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens" /></a></p>

<p>With 36 megapixels and a max resolution of 7360 x 4912 it are photos where the A7R really shines, so lets have a look how the camera handles in the field.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274057619" title="Sont A7R - Composing a photo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15274057619_9d2c7a6105_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sont A7R - Composing a photo" /></a></p>

<p>Together with the Carl Zeiss 35mm F2.8 lens (120 g) the A7R weighs 585 g (including battery, which is 58 g). With this lens it is a compact package that fits into large jacket pockets and comfortably under the jacket in bad weather. It’s also light enough to not bother you when wearing around your neck, though I would update the strap to one from <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/slide?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design</a> for more functionality. </p>

<p>The first time I used the camera was at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a>, which was a good test for it. Lots of white in different shades, colourful clothing, early dusks, northern lights. It performed well, and would have been outstanding if I would have had the functions dialled in better. With gloves on the camera was easy to use, but things like smaller buttons where more difficult to control. That meant either setting White Balance, ISO, Aperture et al. before hand or take the gloves off to fine adjust settings.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445682176" title="Sony A7R - Roadtrippin&#x27; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15445682176_9e35c9589d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Roadtrippin&#x27;" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15282159468" title="Sony A7R - Ice climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15282159468_f9a430f0c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Ice climbing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465648641" title="Sony A7R - Aurora Borealis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15465648641_46952da3d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p>In warm daylight the camera was a pleasure to use and produced almost perfect images without needing much post processing. Colours were bright and true to colour, and given that this can be a very hard environment for good photos, with all the snow and ice, I was very happy with the output. The LCD screen is great to review photos on the fly and it’s fast to delete bad shots, but also works well to compose a photo if you can not/ don’t want to use the Viewfinder. The Viewfinder is great in use, and helped in the bright and snowy environment of Northern Sweden to compose a few good shots.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15281893779" title="Sony A7R - All Smiles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15281893779_8c91a81b2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - All Smiles" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465644681" title="Sony A7R - Getting schooled by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15465644681_f1772308e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Getting schooled" /></a></p>

<p>The Magnesium Alloy Body didn’t get very cold, and bumps against the ice and rock didn’t bother it. Something that did bother me was the shutter sound, which I didn’t manage to silence. I like stealth photography and even if large landscapes aren’t scared away by the sound, animals are, and also during street photography it’s something that can give you away. The shutter also seemed to be slow, taking a good moment to make its <em>“Clack”</em> sound to take a picture. While I got used to it, it’s something I’d very much would like to be seen improved. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445745166" title="Sony A7R - Snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15445745166_75ff8416ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Snow" /></a></p>

<p>One of the big benefits of the A7R is obviously that it is a full frame. The detail you get from the camera is pretty amazing and  allows you to reduce the resolution in post or crop aggressively. The example of this lonely reed against a late March afternoon sky is a good example:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465621521" title="Sony A7R - Reed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5597/15465621521_cd0f005fa2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Reed" /></a></p>

<p>And now the crop of the above photo:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468757625" title="Sony A7R - Reed Crop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3932/15468757625_5293bd9a0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Sony A7R - Reed Crop" /></a></p>

<p>The amount of sharp detail you get is wonderful and gives you a lot more creative options when working with this camera. You can include a lot more of the subject’s environment and still capture plenty of detail which is highly useful if you decide to crop the photo later, which is great if you are in a hurry to capture a unique moment but can’t compose the image perfectly.</p>

<p>The A7R also has a good Auto Focus/ Facial Recognition, even if the subject isn’t 100% to be identified. Take this <em>“Portrait”</em> I shot of myself for a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/trekking-magazin/">trekking Magazin</a> article as an example:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445671636" title="Sony A7R - &quot;Portrait&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5598/15445671636_c449958015_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - &quot;Portrait&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>This photo has not been touched in post, but with a few easy adjustments was perfect for my article. However, I really loved how good the camera put the focus on me (and I wasn’t standing behind the Viewfinder, obviously =) and blurred out the background. The colours again are rich and lush out of the camera and details like the Ripstop pattern on the windjacket are clearly to be seen.</p>

<p>Night and low-light shooting is something that you really need to put an effort in to get it right, but with a good camera and a good lens things get easier. I think one could get some really nice illuminated-shelters-in-the-hills with the A7R + 35 mm lens, sadly I didn’t have time for such a test so this twilight shot from town needs to do. With focus peaking on it’s easy to get the stuff sharp that matter, and it’s something I highly recommend always using - also in daylight shots.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468453232" title="Sony A7R - Twilight by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15468453232_b2c0eedd0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Twilight" /></a>
ƒ/2.8, 2 seconds, ISO 800</p>

<p>The pine has a lot of detail and the stars that you can see are nice and crisp. I edited it lightly in <a href="http://amzn.to/1vL8VDP">Lightroom</a> to bring out some details and added a bit of clarity, but even in camera on the screen it looked already good. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468786525" title="Sony A7R - Waterdrops by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15468786525_8408833471_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Waterdrops" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15284760469" title="Sony A7R - Scarpa Rebel Ultra Gtx in the snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3941/15284760469_052c55e581_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Scarpa Rebel Ultra Gtx in the snow" /></a></p>

<p>Taking product shots is something I do quite a bit for the blog and the magazines, and also here the A7R performed very satisfying. On the top you see clearly that the focus is on the water drops on the pants, and in these you can see how they reflect their surroundings - the kitchen windows, in this case. Underneath we again have a difficult case: Patterned orange and snow. A combination which gives some of my other cameras a headache, but the A7R produced a perfect image.</p>

<p>Also indoors the A7R did very well, and I snapped some nice shots at the Art Museum here in Vaasa at an exhibition earlier in winter. Again colours and sharpness are outstanding and as the full frame sensor records so much detail it would have been easy to crop this composition if needed (but it wasn’t, I was quite happy with this shot).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468829345" title="Sony A7R - Art Museum by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2950/15468829345_b99c8ecb23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Art Museum" /></a></p>

<p>In conclusion I can say that my experiences with the Sony A7R were nothing but superb. Sure, it took a second longer to start up as I’d like, it took a moment between shots to be ready again, the shutter was a bit loud, there’s still just a fairly limited selection of FE lenses out, and yes, it’s pricey. But the plusses outweigh these small complaints for me. The biggest advantage is that with the 35 mm lens you have a Full Frame camera which is less than 600 g. In comparison: The Canon EOS 5D Mk III is 950 g for the body only, and the Nikon D800 still puts 900 g for the body only around your neck. </p>

<p>Then there’s the weatherproof body that withstood at least light impacts on ice and rock and had no problems operating in light minus temperatures this winter. The layout of the dials and buttons needs some getting used to, but once you have internalized the layout you’ll be able to use the camera with your eye to the viewfinder.  I loved that it had a regular sized Microphone port, and if I ever get a phone with NFC I’m happy to know that I can just touch it against the A7R and have the two linked, being able to send photos from the camera to the phone very easily. </p>

<p>A large plus is also that thanks to various adapters you’re able to use a massive variety of 35 mm lenses with no field-of-view crop, and if you’re already a Sony NEX camera user you will be able to use your E-Mount lenses on the A7R (with field-of-view crop, though). What’s nice about the 35 mm lens possibility is obviously that many of these lenses can be bought cheaply, and as I have used a few old lenses on my NEX-5n I know how wonderful it is to use a manual lens. Sony is set to release some more FE lenses in 2015, and also Zeiss just announced at the photokina a very nice pair of manual Full-Frame lenses for the A7R and its siblings. </p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline:</strong> The Sony A7R is a lightweight, compact camera that produces outstanding photos and video. If you’re an (outdoor) photographer, journalist or writer who needs high-quality photos with lots of details and the ability to crop the A7R will appeal as it’s such a portable camera and won’t weigh you down when you’re hiking and climbing far off the beaten track.</p>

<p>I recommend you go visit your local camera shop to have a look at the camera and the lenses. If you’re in Finland, <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/sony-ilce-7r-runko.html">Rajala</a> has the A7R right now on offer for 1600€ for the body only. </p>

<p>You can see <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157643203488075/">more photos of the Sony A7R and photos taken with it on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460817595" title="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15460817595_676a7bca38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard - The Calling]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T06:23:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What do Joy Division, The Rolling Stones, Les Droites, Nanga Parbet and the Cassin Ridge have in common?</em> They play a part in Barry Blanchard’s life, which is aptly re-told in his memoirs, “The Calling”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15451426995" title="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15451426995_53b9507d6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="675" alt="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge.of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Tune in to the soundtrack of Barry’s life with this Playlist, dutifully reconstructed from Chapter 2:</p>

<iframe src="https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify:user:skullmonkey:playlist:7qy8hUL8yIyABU8JFRfj3z" width="300" height="380" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true"></iframe>

<p>Alpinism and mountaineering books tend to often be of interest only to pursuers of these activities. But Barry manages to write his memoirs in such a compelling edge-of-your-seat style that also non-climbers will be eagerly turning each page to read how the stories unfold. And unfold they do. And if you haven’t heard of Barry before, that’s easily fixed: He is <em>one of North America’s top alpinists, noted for pushing the standards of highly technical, high-risk alpine climbing in the Canadian Rockies and the Himalayas.</em> But nobody is born an alpinist, even if it is their calling.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264859557" title="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15264859557_249539e96d_b.jpg" width="660" height="1024" alt="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the.exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never.been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p>In 20 chapters <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">The Calling</a> stops at important stations in Barry’s life, but does not take a linear approach. It’s more a Tarantino style, weaving stories together, jumping between different stations, different countries, different mountains, different climbing partners. It starts off with an Avalanche and only later on you learn more about how the four rope partners ended up in that situation on a high Himalaya peak. It’s followed two chapters on how Barry grew up and how he got into climbing (via the Canadian equivalent of the Boy Scouts), and that especially will be of interest to aspiring alpinists and climbers around the globe. From how he loaned books at the library on how to climb to saving up to buy his first climbing shoes, it shows that Barry is from a pre-Internet era where you couldn’t just order the latest gear and books online - but often head to search in shops across town to find what you wear looking for.</p>

<p>Really interesting are the personal stories and how Barry manages to illustrate his climbing partners: Kevin and Ward, Gregg and David, Mark and Phil and many more. If you climb, especially in the mountains, you know how important it is to be able to totally trust the person at the other end of the rope, and Barry is able to communicate that trust between climbing partners wonderfully. The story accompanies Barry and his partners as they learn to climb - from Trad at the Wasootch Slabs with Phil to alpine climbing the Calgary Route on Mt Yamnuska with Gray, all told in such a fun way that I couldn’t help but chuckle a few times. After a stop in Chamonix and taking Rebuffat’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1pECtyN">The Hundred Finest Routes</a> as a tick-list Barry travels a bit through Europe (and manages to lose his wallet and passport) before heading back to Canada and onwards to Yosemite. We see how Barry makes the decision to quit his salesman job to go more climbing and becoming a guide, all while repeating hard routes in Canada and the USA.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15448265551" title="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3929/15448265551_a50450ccbc_b.jpg" width="676" height="1024" alt="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p>And as the walls and routes keep getting bigger &amp; more committing we accompany Barry to the Karakoram &amp; Himalaya, to Peru and the Cassin Ridge and read captivating accounts of daring alpine ascents. Always interweaved are anecdotes from his time - be it books (I got away with a whole list of books to read) to music (see above) to relationships and how climbing gear has evolved. The writing is lively &amp; outspoken and I often was laughing out loud, and it was able to keep me on reading until I finished the book in a week, often reading in my lunch breaks and late till night. It were the personal connections with his rope partners that I found very fascinating and that kept me on reading past bedtime, how they pushed themselves on to become better climbers, train together, climb together, party together and go on expeditions together, all while trying to figure out how to be able to get out more to the mountains. If you have a longing for the mountains but can’t be in them as much as you like (and don’t want to quit your job just yet for them), I can warmly recommend you this fine book for your mountain fix. It’s captivating style with adventures from near &amp; far will keep you entertained for many days, and after you’re done you’ll go through the book again - to search out some of the books Barry mentioned, look up a song and re-read about the daring ascents.</p>

<p>Get your paper or digital copy today from <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">Patagonia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1rTGvIH">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vDx8O1">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1nTA8oO">Amazon.de</a> or your local book store.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264720600" title="The Calling Cover by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15264720600_920b3f8714_b.jpg" width="674" height="1024" alt="The Calling Cover" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review LXXXIX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/the-week-in-review-lxxxix.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-05T17:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/the-week-in-review-lxxxix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“My favourite things in life don’t cost any money. It’s really clear that the most precious resource we all have is time.”</em>
- Steve Jobs</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214282280" title="Onwards by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2943/15214282280_591f2c7dda_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Onwards" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/category/backpacks/">Katabatic Gear Backpacks</a> are a go! Choose from a 30 l alpine climbing pack or a 40 and 55 l backpacking pack. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/LAUFBURSCHE-gear/197297190298337">Laufbursche PACKraum - DxG</a> is coming in 2015 and looks swell!</p>

<p>Walk on the Wild Side introduces the <a href="http://www.walkon-blog.de/vihe-vaellus-laavujen-ja-loueiden-asiantuntija/">Vihe Vaellus</a> shelters they now offer.</p>

<p>Vote for Alex’s <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2014/10/the-atholl-expedition-shortlisted-for.html">The Atholl Expedition</a> as the Outdoor book of the Year (I did!).</p>

<p>Tasty: <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/exoprotein/exo-protein-bars-made-from-cricket-flour">Exo: Protein Bars Made from Cricket Flour</a> and the <a href="http://chapul.com">Chapul Cricket Bar</a>. Not convinced? Then red <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/08/dining/energy-bars-that-put-a-chirp-in-your-step.html?_r=2">Energy Bars That Put a Chirp in Your Step</a>.</p>

<p>It’s October. Pumpkin season. Tasty soups. And your cance to win VO stuff in the <a href="http://velo-orange.blogspot.fi/2014/10/pumpkin-contest-win-vo-stuff.html">Pumpkin Contest</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://amzn.to/1BGLYDu">Contour ROAM3</a> is now available, as is the <a href="http://bit.ly/1xS7sjj">GoPro HERO4</a>. If you get the latter, consider backing <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1702705519/jolt-worlds-first-wireless-charger-for-gopro-camer">Jolt: World’s first wireless charger for GoPro® cameras</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://onehundredmountains.blogspot.fi/2014/09/convergence-of-twain.html">Convergence of the twain</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2014/09/7-bergregeln.html">7 simple rules for the mountains</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=378787&amp;pw=73183">Spend $100 &amp; Get $20 in Credits at Backcountry.com</a></p>

<p>Neil helps you to win stuff with his <a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/win-stuff-online-competitions-hikers-october-2014/">Online Competitions for Hikers</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20248844/">裏銀座縦走</a>. A recommended read &amp; see. I always love the beautiful, thoughtful photos on the Japanese backpacking blogs. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2014/10/articulo-jose-mijares-la-laponia.html">Forgotten Lapland</a>. Another recommended read. [Spanish]</p>

<p>Skyler follows the call of the wild on his <a href="http://offroute.ca/2014/10/01/call-of-the-wild-part-2/">Bikepacking B.C.’s Coast Mountains – Part 2</a>. Which would be the third recommended read this week.</p>

<p>Alice has <a href="http://alicehikes.com/2014/09/i-finished-the-pct-but-it-hasnt-finished-with-me/">finished the PCT, but it hasn’t finished with her</a>.</p>

<p>Ellen hikes to <a href="http://spicebush.blogspot.fi/2014/09/the-baldfaces.html">The Baldfaces</a>. Pretty autumn colours in full effect.</p>

<p><a href="http://tozantales.wordpress.com/2014/10/03/gathering3/">The Gathering III</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/?p=1482">The Rut 50K 2014 race report</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://dirtanddogs.blogspot.fi/2014/09/strike-three.html">Strike Three</a>.</p>

<p>Casey is <a href="http://greenecasey.blogspot.fi/2014/10/floating-around-internet.html">floating around the Internet</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/ISagf2eCzKg?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Uli goes up on the <a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/wandern/suedtirol/pursteinwand-klettersteig/">Pursteinwand Via Ferrata</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Emma climbs <a href="http://emmaamerikassa.blogspot.fi/2014/09/needles-emmas-epic-tr-sessions.html">The Needles</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://tarmachan.blogspot.fi/2014/10/blog-post_4.html">First snow in the Cairngorms</a>.</p>

<p>Sven shares his experiences of the <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2014/10/samsung-fitness-camp-2014-tag-2-rafting-bergwanderung-kegeln/">Samsung Fitness Camp 2014</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://willsim.blogspot.fi/2014/10/the-north-face-of-mount-alberta.html">The North Face of Mount Alberta</a>.</p>

<p>Jens finishes his <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/touren/von-kueste-zu-kueste-auf-dem-nord-ostsee-wanderweg-westensee-kiel/">Coast to Coast hike</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Greg ponders whipping litterers on his <a href="http://www.hikingfiasco.com/2014/10/southern-gorge-walk-lerderderg-gorge.html">Southern Gorge Walk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://howlingmist.blogspot.fi/2014/09/the-domes-de-miage-thrice.html">The Domes de Miage</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wUb3JOw5SjE">Petzl RocTrip 2014 video from Bulgaria</a> is online.</p>

<p>Sean goes his <a href="http://gearjunkie.com/pnt-trip-report-pacific-ocean">Last Steps on the PNT</a>.</p>

<p>Linda hikes the <a href="http://photomomlinda.blogspot.fi/2014/10/the-obsidian-trail.html">Obsidian Trail</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/ixcFL8hOzGc?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Antti’s <a href="http://longdistancetrail.wordpress.com/2014/09/29/my-hiking-gear-overview-2014/">hiking gear overview 2014</a> is a nice visual presentation of the gear he uses.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.minimallyminimal.com/blog/leica-t-extended-review">Leica T extended review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://danceswithangiosperms.blogspot.fi/2014/09/hmg-windrider-4400-review.html">HMG Windrider 4400 Review</a>.</p>

<p>Jacob talks <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/pillow-talk/">Pillows</a>.</p>

<p>Matt is happy with his <a href="http://outdoorsmh.blogspot.fi/2014/10/As-Tucas.html">As Tucas Custom Gear</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://woodtrekker.blogspot.fi/2014/10/ultralight-fly-fishing-kit.html">Ultralight Fly Fishing Kit</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/equipment/montbell-u-l-trekking-umbrella-review/">Montbell U.L. Trekking Umbrella review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking &amp; Scrambling in the Polish Tatras - Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-03T10:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">climbing &amp; mountaineering in the Polish Tatras</a> to hiking and backpacking. In the rain &amp; sunshine, up high in the mountains and low in the valleys.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397717831" title="Focus on the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397717831_9014d3f632_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Focus on the rain" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rain--misery">Rain &amp; Misery</h2>

<p>As we wake up at the <a href="http://www.piecstawow.pl/en/">Przedni Staw Polski Refuge</a> and I look out from my window the mist hides the mountains and the rain drops leave little circles on the lake. Everything is wet. Marcin and I silently get out of bed and move to the big common room, give in our orders for breakfast and enjoy the tasty food that comes through the small window from the kitchen. Slowly it gets busy, people packing, but with the rain keeping up a constant drum on the roof none leave the hut. At ten we’re the first ones to venture outside, curious looks on us in our rain gear, and as Marcin tells where we headed people just look even more confused.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214238360" title="A look back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214238360_3bfa19dbfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin gave me a few options: Walk the easy trail through the valley to the Schronisko Murowaniec refuge, or the shorter but high route across a pass at the end Orla Perć. We had light packs, good gear and so it was easy to make the decision to go via the pass. I either way was a bit disappointed that we didn’t take my original route, but plans are plans: Drawn on paper, dreamed up looking over maps in the warm comfort of home. When the weather turns it’s best to adapt them and stay safe - something I can now say in hindsight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400893955" title="Crossing snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15400893955_db1585c08f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crossing snow" /></a></p>

<p>We walk by the mist-enshrouded lakes, cross the stream via the little bridge and hear the waterfall thunder down towards the valley while we slowly ascend. I carry my camera underneath my jacket so I can keep on making photos, but in the drizzle and thick mist there isn’t much to see. We cross small streams, old snow, and steadily keep on walking uphill. Once in a while the mist has a gap and we can see a bit further - the other side of the valley, further up, down the valley.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397714501" title="Slippery by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/15397714501_32e8d0e031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slippery" /></a></p>

<p>To be able to continue to take photos I left <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hestra/">my gloves</a> in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">my pack</a> - a decision I regret the higher and windier it gets. I also ponder why I decided to put on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1BD2sfW">Alpha Comp Jacket</a> instead of my <a href="http://bit.ly/1rRRHpb">Patagonia Alpine Houdini</a> rain jacket as I start the get wet inside - or then it’s the sweat from hiking and scrambling up? At least I’m warm and the jacket and pants keep the wind outside. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214147809" title="Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/15214147809_699c6e2391_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up" /></a></p>

<p>We scramble up steep passages, rain and small streams making things slippery - it’s a good thing I’m wearing my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a> boots, that way I have good grip on the wet rocks and half-way dry &amp; warm feet. Soaked we arrive at the pass and the wind howls past us. I shelter behind a big rock, but Marcin lets me know we should push on. So on we push.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14363720837" title="Wind. Rain. Honesty. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14363720837_7ac4627792_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wind. Rain. Honesty." /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400901985" title="At the top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/15400901985_9d8d44d8b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the top" /></a></p>

<p>On the way up I thought about how nice it will be to go down in the downwind side. But I must have misunderstood Marcin, as we hike down on wet talus fields on the upwind side. At a narrow stretch of path between the talus I finally decide to go search for my gloves in my pack, as my hands started to be just too damn cold in the strong wind. When I finally have managed to get my soaking wet &amp; cold hands in the gloves they need a moment to warm up, but then it’s infinitely more comfortable. The same time I pack away my camera, so I can concentrate on the path. We down climbing a few sections and then slowly are getting lower. </p>

<p>We hike over snowfields and I can believe it as down, out of the treacherous wind, we see a solitary figuring coming our way, wearing a Poncho. Marcin chats with him, and as we continue to walk I hear a similar story like the ones I have heard the days before: First time in the mountains, wants to continue to the hut we started out from. A bit later we meet a couple who also have the same plan and think that now they’re at least three if they catch up with the guy, which makes it a bit safer. We pass a high-alpine lake and low pines are starting to appear. <em>“Not long anymore”</em> Marcin tells me - he must see that I’m not feeling too great: By now I’m drenched. Soon we are walking through a pretty pine forest in the mist. After a final small uphill we stand in front of the massive <a href="http://www.murowaniec.e-tatry.pl">Schronisko Murowaniec refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214246510" title="Schronisko Murowaniec by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15214246510_1e268ebe57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schronisko Murowaniec" /></a></p>

<p>We head inside and it is full of people - some dressed in dry clothes, others looking just as wet &amp; miserable as we. Marcin shows me the drying wall, where I hang my wet gear after I slipped into my dry layers. Then it’s feasting time - I’m starving and munch away a soup and pancakes, a hot tea and coffee give more warmth. We sit for a while at the hut, with people coming and going. My clothes still moist but a bit drier I put them back on after almost two hours inside. Outside it’s still as misty as before, but the rain has become just the faintest drizzle. </p>

<p>Steadily we go down, soon the rain stops while the mist lingers on. We descend on paths that get broader and broader to a wide meadow. The mist mixes with the clouds and hangs above us while we walk towards Kuznice, a suburb of Zakopane and the start of a gondola up to Kasprowy Wierch.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214316898" title="Down by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15214316898_c764198aa9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Down" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214153899" title="Green under grey by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214153899_189ef3dfff_b.jpg" width="863" height="1024" alt="Green under grey" /></a></p>

<p>Here Marcin and I separate for a while - he needs to run an errand in town and hopes to catch a bus from here - we’ll meet up at the refuge later. After checking out the the small settlement with the gondola station and resisting buying some more food I hike up the broad cobblestone trail and take the first possibility into the forest.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400906185" title="Cobblestone by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15400906185_c9f9fbcb40_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cobblestone" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214397527" title="Fast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214397527_125435355d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fast" /></a></p>

<p>There’s several possibilities to visit shrines and monasteries along the trail, but I just want to reach the refuge to finally strip out of all the moist clothes, take a hot shower, dress in dry clothes and eat some good food. But the scenery is lovely on the way, and so I stop here and there to take photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400582682" title="Tranquility by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3915/15400582682_cba7c400f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tranquility" /></a></p>

<p>As the forest disappears another wide meadow comes into view, with the pretty <a href="http://schroniska.pttk.pl/kondratowa/pl">Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali refuge</a> sitting at its side. I go in and am welcomed by smiling faces in the common room. While I don’t speak a word of Polish I still am able to communicate with the wonderful owners of the refuge and she shows me the room I am staying in. I put down my pack, get rid of the wet clothes and then just am for a moment. Then the rest of the evening is just as I imagined it would be: Hot shower, dry, warm clothes, good food, early to bed. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214400107" title="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/15214400107_6ca4d4a074_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ridges-and-summits">Ridges and Summits</h2>

<p>I slept great after the day before, and as we get up at 6 in the morning the sky is blue and the sun is already shining across the summits opposite my window. Marcin and I head silently down, where the two ladies of the refuge have a breakfast waiting for us! We eat, pack, and are out of the hut by 7 and make our way to the pass.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214320388" title="Up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214320388_576117b4da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>The sky is blue with the occasional white cloud running across it and we quickly are hot from the sun and hiking. At the final spring we refill the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/platypus/?pid=81">Platypus</a> bottles with cold, clear water and then walk on. Soon we are at the pass where we drop our packs into the shrubbery and almost run up to Giewont, so light we are!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397733501" title="Further up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3866/15397733501_cb1086ff52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Further up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377897226" title="Final bit up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15377897226_c0ec8a1c1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Final bit up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214268900" title="Summit of Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3848/15214268900_d99bdd983e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit of Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400602172" title="Down from Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3853/15400602172_b9e263692a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Down from Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>It doesn’t take us long and we’re standing on the summit, underneath the massive iron cross which can be seen from Zakopane. The views are hazy but good nevertheless: Zakopane towards the north with the small villages surrounding the city towards east &amp; west, and you even can glimpse into Slovakia from here. On the way down we encounter a lonely, old chamois and then soon are back at our packs. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214337218" title="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/15214337218_b8187c6356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377902416" title="A look down at the valley by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/15377902416_901ef59a4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look down at the valley" /></a></p>

<p>The trail to Kondracka Kopa is a long, steady climb over a wide ridge. Clouds float over the ridge and surroundings summits, while alpine flowers are adding bright colours to the grey &amp; white of the sky. On my left I can see the lower hills of the Tatras and the meadow and refuge we slept in last night, and on the left zig-zags the trail down to the meadow from my original route. It does not take long and we’re on the summit of Kondracka Kopa, and now we will walk on the border of Poland and Slovakia while ticking off the next few summits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214340958" title="Along the border by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15214340958_71b3d109f2_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Along the border" /></a></p>

<p>We stay now almost all the time above 2000 m elevation while we hike in the clouds from Kondracka Kopa to Malolaczniak, Krzesanica, Ciemniak and then Twarda Kopa. Once in a while the clouds rip open and we can see the lower Tatras in Slovakia, narrow valleys, high walls, streams running towards the far off sea. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214423037" title="Towards Twarda Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3844/15214423037_2c456098d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Towards Twarda Kopa" /></a></p>

<p>From Twarda Kopa we can see Giemont in the distance, now in the clouds - but more worrisome is the helicopter which flies up to it from the valley. We don’t know what happened, but hope no one died.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400937025" title="A look back to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2943/15400937025_742b942b3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin waits for me at a large summit cairn and suggests we take the green trail down to the next refuge. It’s just around 11 and we have the whole day really in front of us still, so I agree and we take a turn from the big main path and walk on a very narrow path in a hanging meadow towards the Western Tatras.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214191449" title="Down 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3852/15214191449_334c07144a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="964" alt="Down 2" /></a></p>

<p>The views and the trail are spectacular. A narrow singletrack trail that’s demanding and exposed, but with gorgeous views on the lower-lying mountains, valleys, meadows - and in front of us, the Western Tatras. A pair of chamois give us a show as they are fighting in a couloir, but my view often just drifts to the horizon, where large mountains try to reach the sky with their summits. At a turn in the path we sit down and have a snack &amp; drink, while Marcin names the peaks and valleys and tells me anecdotes about geographical features. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377924676" title="A look back up the green trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2941/15377924676_45d34c6126_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="A look back up the green trail" /></a></p>

<p>Too soon we reach the tree line, but the path continues to be lovely. It gradually widens and Marcin tells me that it has been an old road for an iron ore mine, and I again wonder about how much work it must have been to clear the forests to create it. While we talk we reach the meadow and a group of fully loaded foreign backpackers pass us, just as amazed about the beautiful scenery around them as we are. The trail now runs next to a stream, and it does not take long until we reach the <a href="http://www.schronisko-ornak.pl">Schronisko Ornak refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397759651" title="Schronisko Ornak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397759651_65b41d3012_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Schronisko Ornak" /></a></p>

<p>It is busy outside and not even 13 o’clock. I check in with the help of Marcin and then accompany him down the valley - our hike ends here today, and I will be venturing on for the next two days on my own. The trail is now a wide dirt road and full of people, with plenty of trails going off on the right and left - trails which I will explore on my way back up to the refuge, I decide. And as Marcin tells me about the long caves up on the mountains which one can explore my afternoon suddenly looks like it will be filled with plenty of adventure!</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review LXXXVIII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxviii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-28T11:18:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxviii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“You can’t wait for inspiration. You have to go after it with a club.”</em> - Jack London</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15286935491" title="Seakayaking by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3868/15286935491_9e6b17ce63_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Seakayaking" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Help <a href="http://www.gofundme.com/ebhedc">find Cody Roman Dial</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://expedition-double8.dynafit.com/">Sebastian Haag dies during a speed ascent of Shisha Pangma</a>.</p>

<p>The first <a href="http://www.alpackawhitewater.com/">Alpacka Whitewater Packraft</a> has launched! Pre-order yours now.</p>

<p>And right on the heels of that is the <a href="http://www.bakraft.com/">BAKraft</a> from AIRE. It’s a self-bailing, whitewater-worthy, Dyneema shell and urethane bladders construction that weighs 6.5 pounds that costs around $1,200. It looks very nice and is a slight departure from traditional packraft designs. [<a href="http://forrestmccarthy.blogspot.fi/2014/09/bakraft-by-aire.html">Hat tip to Forrest</a>]</p>

<p>Mountain Laurel Design launched the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?products_id=217">DuoMid XL</a>, a new, asymmetrical DuoMid that is taller + wider. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.gearexposure.com/gopro-hero4-specs-leak-built-display-4k-30fps/">GoPro Hero4 specs leak</a> and it’s not a surprise as the HERO4 should come out within the next weeks. Which will make the <a href="http://bit.ly/1CxfHBc">HERO3</a> cheaper!</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://bit.ly/Yy21Xb">Patagonia Truth to Materials</a> line.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2014/09/25/africa-just-nature/">Africa is more than just nature</a>.</p>

<p>You can <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/">save 10% on HMG Gear</a> during the last week of September with the coupon code <em>follow10sep</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ukclimbing.com/articles/page.php?id=2298">How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/denniscaco/the-undress-change-clothes-in-public-without-getti">The Undress</a>.</p>

<p>Download the free <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/stand-here/id898186533?mt=8">Stand Here</a> app, an <em>app that provides you with everything you’ll need to know to get to the most stunning locations along the trail.</em></p>

<p>Bergfreunde have a lot of <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-bekleidung/fuer--kinder/">new gear for kids</a> - and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/p/icekid/">save 20% on Icebreaker garments</a> with the code <em>icekid</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=371165&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/371165/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://jolly-green-giant.blogspot.fi/2014/09/sili-dripper-lightweight-coffee-filter.html">Sili-Dripper - a Lightweight Coffee Filter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.backpackingengineer.com/falling-angels-7-days-gear-big-agnes-q-core-sl/">Big Agnes Q-core SL</a> reviewed.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-488.html">RMG Shoulder Pack Prototype</a> looks pretty awesome.</p>

<p><a href="http://geoffmallinson.com/2014/09/26/teaching-kids-how-to-navigate/">Teaching kids how to navigate</a>.</p>

<p>Jacob reviews the <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/western-mountaineering-alpinlite/">Western Mountaineering Alpinlite</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2014/09/paper-panniers-7-days-with-ortleib/">7 Days with Ortlieb</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/bergfilm-und-outdoor-buch/bene-benedikt-gebrauchsanweisung-fuer-die-alpen/">Gebrauchsanweisung für die Alpen</a> book review. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15229569551" title="Sunset by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3865/15229569551_be31061ddd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Chris is back! <a href="http://i-cjw.com/blog/2014/09/26/no-ifs-just-buttresses/">No Ifs, Just Buttresses</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cBJyo0tgLnw">Arctic Swell - Surfing the Ends of the Earth</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://vimeo.com/89458528">first attempt to cross Iceland on fixed gear bikes</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://stefanandcherry.com/2014/09/27/captain-kirk-and-the-one-day-enterprise/">Captain Kirk and the one day Enterprise</a>.</p>

<p>Nick is in <a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/09/24/albania-albania-albania/">Albania</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://offroute.ca/2014/09/25/call-of-the-wild-part1/">Bikepacking B.C.’s Coast Mountains</a>.</p>

<p>A great <a href="http://ivovanmontfort.blogspot.fi/2014/09/gort-droog-karst-en-sappige-bergweiden.html">9-day Pyrenees Trip report</a> from Ivo. [Dutch]</p>

<p>David enjoyed the <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2014/9/18/island-life">island life</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://willsim.blogspot.fi/2014/09/canada-part-1.html">Canada</a>.</p>

<p>Stefanie stand of top of <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/gipfelbuch-marmolata/">Marmolata</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Casey goes <a href="http://greenecasey.blogspot.fi/2014/09/bikepacking-yaaks-lookout-towers.html">Bikepacking Yaak’s Fire Lookout Towers</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seakayakingetc.blogspot.fi/2014/09/paddling-trip-on-san-juan-islands.html">Paddling trip on San Juan Islands</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/dHaNGTZWIxY?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://adelorenzo.exposure.co/aishihik-river">Aishihik River</a>, early season Yukon packrafting.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2014/05/building-patagonia-national-park-a-decade-long-partnership-with-patagonia-inc.html">Building Patagonia National Park: A decade-long partnership with Patagonia, Inc.</a>.</p>

<p>On the <a href="http://urskyburz.blogspot.fi/2014/09/sidelhorn.html">Sidelhorn</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Christine gives some tips about <a href="http://christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi/2014/09/paddling-gotakanal-conclusion-and-tipps.html">Paddling the Götakanal</a>.</p>

<p>John reviews the <a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2014/09/munich-to-venice-dream-way-review.html">Dream Way</a> from Munich to Venice.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://danceswithangiosperms.blogspot.fi/2014/09/the-last-days-day-129-141.html">The Last Days</a> on the PCT.</p>

<p><a href="http://howlingmist.blogspot.fi/2014/09/a-taste-of-chamonix-and-saas-grund-alps.html">A Taste Of Chamonix and Saas Grund</a>.</p>

<p>Steven &amp; Katrijn are <a href="http://patagoniandreams.com/2014/09/25/til-fots-i-fjellet-walking-in-the-mountains/">walking in the (Norwegian) mountains</a>.</p>

<p>Ryan starts at <a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2014/09/cape-wrath.html">Cape Wrath</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20228652/">燕岳</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://outdoorsmh.blogspot.fi/2014/09/two-days-in-northern-fells.html">Two Days in the Northern Fells</a>.</p>

<p>Steve tackles <a href="http://sdbwanderings.blogspot.fi/2014/07/crinkle-crags-bowfell-via-climbers.html">Crinkle Crags &amp; Bowfell via the climbers traverse</a>.</p>

<p>James heads <a href="http://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2014/09/27/into-the-wild-alone-in-sarek-and-padjelanta-part-two/">into the wild to Sarek and Padjelanta</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=42809&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/42809/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear Outtakes - Summer 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/09/gear-outtakes-summer-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-25T15:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/09/gear-outtakes-summer-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bite-sized gear reviews.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163660879" title="Gear Outtakes Summer 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3841/15163660879_2c170b6451_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gear Outtakes Summer 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I often get sent products or get asked to do reviews about gear though right now I’m short of time to do my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">in-depth reviews</a>. As I still use the kit quite a bit, Gear Outtakes is my solution to the problem - a seasonal collection of kit and what I think about it, inspired by <a href="http://www.minimallyminimal.com/">Minimally Minimal</a>.</p>

<p>★☆☆☆
Mediocre, I wouldn’t spend money on it.</p>

<p>★★☆☆
Good, but there are better options.</p>

<p>★★★☆
Great, worth your money.</p>

<p>★★★★
Outstanding, the benchmark of its category.</p>

<p>DISCLAIMER
<br />Some of these products have been sent to me for free by the manufacturer.</p>

<h2 id="phd-waferlite-shirt">PHD WaferLite Shirt</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15327351646" title="PHD WaferLite Shirt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3906/15327351646_183bfcdba7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD WaferLite Shirt" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />£150, available at <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/">PHD</a></p>

<p>A 137 g light down pullover (Size M). Between the 10X fabric is 900 cuin down and this sweet little pullover has been warm enough for summer adventures, when reaching the summit and there’s a small breeze, chilling at camp or taking a break between bouldering. It packs very small so easily fits in my backpack wherever I go, and is comfortable on the skin. While the material does feel filigrane it can take a bit of abuse, though I have used it strictly as a garment at camp/ resting/ when more warmth was needed. A long zipper helps with getting in and venting, there’s stretchy rims on the hem and cuffs and that’s about it. Really something for a SUL setup!</p>

<h2 id="field-notes-expedition-note-book--fn-19-space-pen">Field Notes EXPEDITION Note Book &amp; FN-19 Space Pen</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163680760" title="Field Notes EXPEDITION Note Book &amp; FN-19 Space Pen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3899/15163680760_0689dd6168_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Field Notes EXPEDITION Note Book &amp; FN-19 Space Pen" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />$9,95 for a 3-Pack of Note Books, $23,95 for the FN-19 Space Pen, available at <a href="http://fieldnotesbrand.com/colors/expedition/">Field Notes</a></p>

<p>I write it really down to remember it later. As I’m on over a dozen trips a year I sit down each evening at camp to write up how the day went. With the Expedition note books from Field Notes I can be sure that my notes will survive down pours and freezing cold temperatures. The FN-19 Space Pen packs small but is a real pen when in use, which I like. The ink won’t bleach, though it does have a bit of a tendency to smear when not 100% dry. / Pen 19 g, note book 30 g.</p>

<h2 id="patagonia-nano-puffy-hoody">Patagonia Nano-Puffy Hoody</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163622609" title="Patagonia Nano-Puff Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3928/15163622609_0e87a524a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Nano-Puff Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />From 209€, available at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-nano-puff-hoody-classic-navy-gr-s/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-nano-puff-hoody-kunstfaserjacke/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1peyjNY">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1DyvalK">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1u1LIi6">Patagonia</a></p>

<p>If it looks like it will get cool and wet on a spring, summer or autumn trip, the 331 g (Size S) light Nano-Puffy Hoody comes along, often even in conjunction with the PHD WaferLite Shirt. The Nano Puff Hoody is a classic piece and likely a staple in many outdoor mens &amp; womens wardrobe, and for a good reason. It’s a super warm hoody that keeps the wind outside and has a DWR finish that lets you wear it in a light drizzle. Even if it gets wet, it still keeps you warm. It packs in its own inside pocket. The hood keeps the ears and head warm. It looks nice. Yeps, with the Patagonia Nano-Puffy Hoody you’re warm &amp; well-dressed in the three warm seasons!</p>

<h2 id="houdini-thrill-twill-pants">Houdini Thrill Twill Pants</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163804978" title="Houdini Thrill Twill Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2950/15163804978_6b735d3d3a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Houdini Thrill Twill Pants" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />140€, available at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/houdini-thrill-twill-pants-kletterhose/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://moonlight-gear.com/?pid=59752392">Moonlight Gear</a></p>

<p>305 g in Size XS, the Houdini Thrill Twill Pants was along on lot of trips this year. The reason is simple: It’s a well-fitting pants with great freedom of movement. Hiking, scrambling, climbing, going to the pub or business meetings at the OutDoor, the Thrill Twill Pants does it all well while being comfortable. The biggest plus for me is probably that the size is so great, in XS I don’t need a belt and it fits perfectly. High heel hooks are no problem, and the pants dries fast when the get wet. Stretchy drawstring allow me to adjust the size of the trouser legs, very useful when climbing and wanting to see where that micro ledge for my next step is. A beautiful pair of trousers that’s durable and can be recycled at the end of its life.</p>

<h2 id="haglfs-triton-ii-hood">Haglöfs Triton II Hood</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163685740" title="Haglöfs Triton II Hood by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3911/15163685740_77186e7162_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs Triton II Hood" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />From 120€, available from <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorstore.com/en/miesten-vaatteet/miesten-alus-ja-valiasut/triton-II-hood/">Scandinavian Outdoor Store</a> and <a href="http://tinyurl.com/op2no7h">Cotswold</a></p>

<p>I have been using fleece jackets again for several years, and the Haglöfs Triton II Hood, a full-zip fleece jacket with thumbloops &amp; a hood, has been a staple in my layering system since I got it last year. The hood can be worn under a helmet, be it a cycle helmet or my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Petzl Sirocco</a>, while the thumbloops help on those first cool autumn days where I forgot to take a pair of gloves along for the bicycle ride. Three zippered pockets store stuff safely on the go, be it hiking, hill walking or climbing. It’s a comfy fleece jacket in a beautiful colour, and if I need a nice, cozy yet breathable midlayer or I’m cool in the mornings at home then the Triton II comes on. / 303 g in Size S.</p>

<h2 id="norrna-bitihorn-aero100-jacket">Norrøna bitihorn aero100 Jacket</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15347199481" title="Norrøna bitihorn aero100 Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3874/15347199481_2d57af6338_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Norrøna bitihorn aero100 Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />139€, available at <a href="https://www.norrona.com/en-GB/Products/4326-12/3440/bitihorn-aero100-jacket-m/">Norrøna</a></p>

<p>The Norrøna bitihorn aero100 Jacket (104 g in Size M) accompanies me since autumn 2013 already and has been a joy to use. It’s lightweight and can be packed in its own chest pocket, which is ideal when travelling. While I occasionally missed a hood I managed to life without it. The Size M was a alright fit despite me being a Size S - I needed to pull the hem drawstring pretty tight for it being a good fit. The jacket stays well in place also when in a cycling position and the material is durable enough to carry heavy grocery backpacks or light backpacking rucksacks. As its always windy on the coast here, the bitihorn aero100 is often along to keep the cool wind at bay.</p>

<h2 id="merrell-allout-rush">Merrell AllOut Rush</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15350072232" title="Merrell AllOut Rush by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2942/15350072232_2970494944_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Merrell AllOut Rush" /></a></p>

<p>★★☆☆
<br />From $71,95, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1reb500">Backcountry</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1ptL2M3">CampSaver.com</a></p>

<p>I’m not 100% happy with the Merrell AllOut Rush - the large drop is likely the reason for that. It’s not as minimal anymore as other shoes from Merrell and after wearing them for a while and switching into more minimalist shoes I realize how my stride has suffered. That said, if you’re new to the whole barefoot hiking &amp; walking movement you might find the AllOut Rush just perfect. It’s a nice shoe with good grip on many surfaces, from wet grass to muddy uphills. The toe box offers your toes plenty of space, and the heel cup also gives a good fit. / 556 g in Size 42.</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-carrier-duffle-50">Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle 50</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163678760" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Carrier Duffle 50 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2942/15163678760_a5bc6fc80f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Carrier Duffle 50" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />125€, available at <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;category=Packs&amp;subcat=Duffle_Bags&amp;model=Carrier-Duffle-50">Arc’teryx</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1ptPtX0">Backcountry</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1renam3">CampSaver.com</a></p>

<p>It was about time that I replaced the 60 l stuff sack I used for transporting my ultralight backpacks when flying abroad for a hike: It already had a few holes at it and somehow always arrived open in Vaasa’s airport at the baggage claim. That no longer happens with the Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle 50: It stays closed and also the occasional downpours the duffle needs to endure when it’s loaded in to the plane are no problem anymore: The Carrier Duffle is highly water resistant. It is just 538 g heavy, which is in comparison with other duffles almost SUL! I can wear it backpack style or over the shoulder and at the airport the straps can be pulled tight and stored out of the way. At the top and bottom there is a haul loop and on each side there’s a handle - so you or the friendly airport employee can carry the duffle as it was intended. A superb piece of kit that goes along on every trip abroad.</p>

<h2 id="rock-technologies-chalk-balls">Rock Technologies Chalk Balls</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15350381185" title="Rock Technologies Chalk Balls by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15350381185_01d38b17dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Technologies Chalk Balls" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />From £10, available at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/rock-technologies/">Bergzeit</a> and <a href="http://www.rocktechnologies.co.uk/order-online/">Rock Technologies</a></p>

<p>Using chalk is pretty much essential when climbing, even more so when bouldering. <em>“Chalk up correctly”</em> was something I heard quite a few times during the last weeks climbing &amp; bouldering, and I was happy to have pharmaceutical grade Magnesium Carbonate chalk from Rock Technologies in my chalk bag. A chalk ball reduces air born chalk dust and so is more healthy - if you ever visited the <a href="http://www.boulderwelt.de/">Boulderwelt in München</a> you will wish everyone would use chalkballs! Anyway, the chalkballs are easy to use and it’s fast &amp; efficient for chalking up. The chalk is good and helps you to stick to slopers and prevents sweaty hands &amp; fingers for a good while. / 60 g</p>

<h2 id="ocun-crack-gloves">Ocun Crack Gloves</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15350377295" title="Ocun Crack Gloves by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15350377295_170a5e853c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ocun Crack Gloves" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />29,95€, available at <a href="http://shop.boulderkeskus.com/en/shop/climbing_gear/tarvike/crackgloves.html">Boulderkeskus</a></p>

<p>Also known as <em>Cheater Gloves</em> these 48 g light gloves allow you to climb cracks like Spiderman without ripping open your knuckles and the back of your hand. Also sweaty hands are no longer responsible for slipping in a crack. Sure, you could just tape up your hands and be tough when you go up a crack, but I find the Crack Gloves much better, really. Easy to use - the most difficult thing is figuring out your size - the gloves close with a Velcro strap and the outside is made of a sticky rubber which gives a lot of friction. The side that’s to the back of your hand has a cushioned mesh lining which makes sharp, sharp cracks slightly more bearable. If you’re starting to get into crack climbing - get a pair. They’re cheaper than all the tape you’re bound to wrap around your hands, and a lot better.</p>

<h2 id="peak-design-leash">Peak Design Leash</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15350376445" title="Peak Design Leash by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15350376445_37989a0ae7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Peak Design Leash" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />34,95$, available at <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/leash?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design</a></p>

<p>The 47 g light Peak Design Leash I bought earlier this year as I realized that my Dyneema cord ain’t the best solution to carry my camera (<a href="http://youtu.be/wHUFWUGWKS4?list=UU927vE_KkPy6pFJboaJ9Lig">as explained here</a>). I’ve been very happy with the Leash, it’s worlds more comfortable than the Dyneema string and easy to use, too. If it’s not needed or could get into the way I can quickly take it off, and the many varied possibilities the Leash can be used make it a really versatile camera strap. It’s also compatible the the Peak Design Strap and the new systems, which I’m considering trying out next.</p>

<h2 id="hariyama-productions-coin-case">Hariyama Productions coin case</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163805668" title="Hariyama Productions coin case by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2941/15163805668_c2bc43673d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hariyama Productions coin case" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />1.800円, available at <a href="http://moonlight-gear.com/?pid=39819567">Moonlight Gear</a></p>

<p>A companion since well over a year, the Hariyama Productions coin case is a 4 g cuben wallet and all I need for carrying cash &amp; cards. It can get a bit tight when I have several business cards in there and need to carry cash, but in Finland I rarely need anything else than a Debit/ Credit Card either way so there’s no need to search for coins or bills. It has been water-resistant but after being daily pulled out of my pocket between a few times and a dozen times it look like I will need to get a new one. They come with differently coloured zippers and I think I will go for a orange one the next time! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review LXXXVII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxvii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-21T10:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxvii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The three weeks climbing &amp; bouldering roadtrip through Finland is finished. Time to enjoy being at home with the family and getting ready for the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/petzl-roctrip-2014-eastern-europe.html">Petzl RocTrip 2014</a> in Turkey in a few weeks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15301030592" title="Milky Way by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3886/15301030592_bb029c0f2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Milky Way" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.gq.com/news-politics/newsmakers/201409/the-last-true-hermit">The Strange &amp; Curious Tale of the Last True Hermit</a>.</p>

<p>PHD has launched their <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/sales-and-special-offers">Autumn Race Collection</a> which also will appeal to ultralight backpackers and alpinists who wanna go super-light!</p>

<p>Win a new <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/black-diamond-raffle/">Black Diamond Access LT Hybrid Hoody &amp; Speed 40 pack</a>. Or check out the New <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en/mens-jackets-shells-goretex.html">Black Diamond Gore-Tex line</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.walkonthewildside.eu/advanced_search_result.php?keywords=zeltsale">Walk on the Wild Side Tent Sale</a> is in full swing.</p>

<p>Dave wonders what <a href="http://davemacleod.blogspot.fi/2014/09/what-have-we-done.html">Scotland has done</a>.</p>

<p>LAUFBURSCHE has the <a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/trekker-ultra-004/">Nomadic Trekker stoves in stock</a> - but be quick to order one, they’re popular!</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2014/09/3-lessons-about-bicycle-tourism-from-rural-bike-advocates/">Three Lessons about Bicycle Tourism from Rural Bike Advocates</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-21-dia-abend-2-0/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #21</a> is out. [German]</p>

<p>Tourism: <a href="http://grapevine.is/mag/column-opinion/2014/09/04/tourism-the-destruction-of-iceland/">The Destruction Of Iceland</a>.</p>

<p>The FREELIGHT <a href="http://obakanahibi.blog31.fc2.com/blog-entry-1169.html">SpinNap Code Zero</a> pack is released in the coming week.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-adventure/exploration/The-Worlds-Toughest-Adventure-Addict.html">Swiss explorer Mike Horn looks to grind out a big first</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.spoon-tamago.com/2014/09/19/wasabi-the-hardest-plant-to-grow-in-the-world/">Wasabi is the hardest plant to grow in the world</a>.</p>

<p>You still have time to win some sweet <a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.com/2014/09/big-sky-gear-raffle.html">Big Sky Gear</a>.</p>

<p>Bergfreunde have the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/fjaellraeven/">Fjällräven</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/marmot/">Marmot</a> gear for the winter online!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.garagegrowngear.com/where-to-find-the-latest-trends-for-cool-new-gear/">Cairn</a> is a new way to discover new gear &amp; companies.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Jacob is <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/nutty-for-cococnut/">Nutty for Coconut</a>.</p>

<p>Jim sat down with Excel to ponder: <a href="http://adventuresinstoving.blogspot.fi/2014/09/which-is-lighter-alcohol-or-gas_14.html">Which is Lighter – Alcohol or Gas</a>?</p>

<p>Chris reviews the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/source-wlp-low-profile-hydration-system-review/">Source WLP Low Profile Hydration System</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-487.html">RMG Body Pocket Prototype</a> looks pretty good.</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/blue-steel-permadraw-solution/">Blue Steel: A Permadraw Solution</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=264573&amp;pw=73183">REI Outlet Days of Deals are a go</a>! Save an EXTRA 20% - 30% on a new deal every day - but be quick, it ends on the 23rd of September!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15046116028" title="Chalk on Rock by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5591/15046116028_f45ff540ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chalk on Rock" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Jean and John are enjoying <a href="http://www.panafoot.com/2014/09/best-of-both-worlds.html">the best of both worlds</a> since four and half years. </p>

<p><a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2014/09/ghost-towns-road-to-nabesna.html">The Road to Nabesna</a>.</p>

<p>Angelica takes a <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2014/09/19/die-landskrone-lohrsdorf-gipfelselfie-im-ahrtal/">Summit Selfie in the Ahrtal</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Ryan’s <a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2014/09/my-last-full-day-in-ireland.html">last full day in Ireland</a>.</p>

<p>Cass rolls into <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/bolivia/into-chile-and-out-to-la-paz">Chile</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://surfnslide.wordpress.com/2014/09/14/wild-camping-in-the-welsh-wilderness/">Wild Camping in the Welsh Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>Jill is <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2014/09/living-in-color-part-two.html">Living in color</a>.</p>

<p>Nick climbs the <a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2014/09/15/steves-wisdom-aka-humble-horse-diadem-north-face/">Diadem North Face</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/96945398?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A story narrated by <a href="http://around-scotland.blogspot.fi/2014/09/a-story-narrated-by-helvellyn.html">Helvellyn</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/himalaya-ice-climbing/">Himalaya Ice Climbing</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://shewiesworld.blogspot.fi/2014/09/cape-wrath-trail.html">Cape Wrath Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Don takes a ride in the <a href="http://lightpack.blogspot.fi/2014/09/dupont-national-forest.html">DuPont National Forest</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pinetflorence.blogspot.fi/2014/09/etape-1-la-roumanie.html">Florence reports from Romania</a>. [French]</p>

<p>Corinna hikes to the <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2014/09/wanderung-refugio-pedrotti.html">Refugio Pedrotti</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/09/20/around-shkoder-lake-montenegro/">Around Shkodër Lake, Montenegro</a>.</p>

<p>Roger hikes to <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/09/cuhcajavri-to-nikkaluokta-end.html">Nikkaluokta, the end of his trip</a>.</p>

<p>Watch the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kgb2G_IgvTw">Kongakut</a> video!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpin-blog.com/weisskugel/">Weisskugel</a>. [German]</p>

<p><strong>Follow along</strong> on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
