<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-03T13:08:44+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking &amp; Scrambling in the Polish Tatras - Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/go-east-hiking-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras-part-iii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-03T10:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/go-east-hiking-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras-part-iii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">climbing &amp; mountaineering in the Polish Tatras</a> to hiking and backpacking. In the rain &amp; sunshine, up high in the mountains and low in the valleys.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397717831" title="Focus on the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397717831_9014d3f632_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Focus on the rain" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rain--misery">Rain &amp; Misery</h2>

<p>As we wake up at the <a href="http://www.piecstawow.pl/en/">Przedni Staw Polski Refuge</a> and I look out from my window the mist hides the mountains and the rain drops leave little circles on the lake. Everything is wet. Marcin and I silently get out of bed and move to the big common room, give in our orders for breakfast and enjoy the tasty food that comes through the small window from the kitchen. Slowly it gets busy, people packing, but with the rain keeping up a constant drum on the roof none leave the hut. At ten we’re the first ones to venture outside, curious looks on us in our rain gear, and as Marcin tells where we headed people just look even more confused.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214238360" title="A look back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214238360_3bfa19dbfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin gave me a few options: Walk the easy trail through the valley to the Schronisko Murowaniec refuge, or the shorter but high route across a pass at the end Orla Perć. We had light packs, good gear and so it was easy to make the decision to go via the pass. I either way was a bit disappointed that we didn’t take my original route, but plans are plans: Drawn on paper, dreamed up looking over maps in the warm comfort of home. When the weather turns it’s best to adapt them and stay safe - something I can now say in hindsight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400893955" title="Crossing snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15400893955_db1585c08f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crossing snow" /></a></p>

<p>We walk by the mist-enshrouded lakes, cross the stream via the little bridge and hear the waterfall thunder down towards the valley while we slowly ascend. I carry my camera underneath my jacket so I can keep on making photos, but in the drizzle and thick mist there isn’t much to see. We cross small streams, old snow, and steadily keep on walking uphill. Once in a while the mist has a gap and we can see a bit further - the other side of the valley, further up, down the valley.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397714501" title="Slippery by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/15397714501_32e8d0e031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slippery" /></a></p>

<p>To be able to continue to take photos I left <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hestra/">my gloves</a> in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">my pack</a> - a decision I regret the higher and windier it gets. I also ponder why I decided to put on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1BD2sfW">Alpha Comp Jacket</a> instead of my <a href="http://bit.ly/1rRRHpb">Patagonia Alpine Houdini</a> rain jacket as I start the get wet inside - or then it’s the sweat from hiking and scrambling up? At least I’m warm and the jacket and pants keep the wind outside. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214147809" title="Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/15214147809_699c6e2391_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up" /></a></p>

<p>We scramble up steep passages, rain and small streams making things slippery - it’s a good thing I’m wearing my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a> boots, that way I have good grip on the wet rocks and half-way dry &amp; warm feet. Soaked we arrive at the pass and the wind howls past us. I shelter behind a big rock, but Marcin lets me know we should push on. So on we push.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14363720837" title="Wind. Rain. Honesty. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14363720837_7ac4627792_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wind. Rain. Honesty." /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400901985" title="At the top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/15400901985_9d8d44d8b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the top" /></a></p>

<p>On the way up I thought about how nice it will be to go down in the downwind side. But I must have misunderstood Marcin, as we hike down on wet talus fields on the upwind side. At a narrow stretch of path between the talus I finally decide to go search for my gloves in my pack, as my hands started to be just too damn cold in the strong wind. When I finally have managed to get my soaking wet &amp; cold hands in the gloves they need a moment to warm up, but then it’s infinitely more comfortable. The same time I pack away my camera, so I can concentrate on the path. We down climbing a few sections and then slowly are getting lower. </p>

<p>We hike over snowfields and I can believe it as down, out of the treacherous wind, we see a solitary figuring coming our way, wearing a Poncho. Marcin chats with him, and as we continue to walk I hear a similar story like the ones I have heard the days before: First time in the mountains, wants to continue to the hut we started out from. A bit later we meet a couple who also have the same plan and think that now they’re at least three if they catch up with the guy, which makes it a bit safer. We pass a high-alpine lake and low pines are starting to appear. <em>“Not long anymore”</em> Marcin tells me - he must see that I’m not feeling too great: By now I’m drenched. Soon we are walking through a pretty pine forest in the mist. After a final small uphill we stand in front of the massive <a href="http://www.murowaniec.e-tatry.pl">Schronisko Murowaniec refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214246510" title="Schronisko Murowaniec by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15214246510_1e268ebe57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schronisko Murowaniec" /></a></p>

<p>We head inside and it is full of people - some dressed in dry clothes, others looking just as wet &amp; miserable as we. Marcin shows me the drying wall, where I hang my wet gear after I slipped into my dry layers. Then it’s feasting time - I’m starving and munch away a soup and pancakes, a hot tea and coffee give more warmth. We sit for a while at the hut, with people coming and going. My clothes still moist but a bit drier I put them back on after almost two hours inside. Outside it’s still as misty as before, but the rain has become just the faintest drizzle. </p>

<p>Steadily we go down, soon the rain stops while the mist lingers on. We descend on paths that get broader and broader to a wide meadow. The mist mixes with the clouds and hangs above us while we walk towards Kuznice, a suburb of Zakopane and the start of a gondola up to Kasprowy Wierch.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214316898" title="Down by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15214316898_c764198aa9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Down" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214153899" title="Green under grey by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214153899_189ef3dfff_b.jpg" width="863" height="1024" alt="Green under grey" /></a></p>

<p>Here Marcin and I separate for a while - he needs to run an errand in town and hopes to catch a bus from here - we’ll meet up at the refuge later. After checking out the the small settlement with the gondola station and resisting buying some more food I hike up the broad cobblestone trail and take the first possibility into the forest.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400906185" title="Cobblestone by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15400906185_c9f9fbcb40_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cobblestone" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214397527" title="Fast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214397527_125435355d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fast" /></a></p>

<p>There’s several possibilities to visit shrines and monasteries along the trail, but I just want to reach the refuge to finally strip out of all the moist clothes, take a hot shower, dress in dry clothes and eat some good food. But the scenery is lovely on the way, and so I stop here and there to take photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400582682" title="Tranquility by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3915/15400582682_cba7c400f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tranquility" /></a></p>

<p>As the forest disappears another wide meadow comes into view, with the pretty <a href="http://schroniska.pttk.pl/kondratowa/pl">Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali refuge</a> sitting at its side. I go in and am welcomed by smiling faces in the common room. While I don’t speak a word of Polish I still am able to communicate with the wonderful owners of the refuge and she shows me the room I am staying in. I put down my pack, get rid of the wet clothes and then just am for a moment. Then the rest of the evening is just as I imagined it would be: Hot shower, dry, warm clothes, good food, early to bed. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214400107" title="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/15214400107_6ca4d4a074_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ridges-and-summits">Ridges and Summits</h2>

<p>I slept great after the day before, and as we get up at 6 in the morning the sky is blue and the sun is already shining across the summits opposite my window. Marcin and I head silently down, where the two ladies of the refuge have a breakfast waiting for us! We eat, pack, and are out of the hut by 7 and make our way to the pass.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214320388" title="Up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214320388_576117b4da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>The sky is blue with the occasional white cloud running across it and we quickly are hot from the sun and hiking. At the final spring we refill the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/platypus/?pid=81">Platypus</a> bottles with cold, clear water and then walk on. Soon we are at the pass where we drop our packs into the shrubbery and almost run up to Giewont, so light we are!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397733501" title="Further up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3866/15397733501_cb1086ff52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Further up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377897226" title="Final bit up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15377897226_c0ec8a1c1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Final bit up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214268900" title="Summit of Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3848/15214268900_d99bdd983e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit of Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400602172" title="Down from Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3853/15400602172_b9e263692a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Down from Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>It doesn’t take us long and we’re standing on the summit, underneath the massive iron cross which can be seen from Zakopane. The views are hazy but good nevertheless: Zakopane towards the north with the small villages surrounding the city towards east &amp; west, and you even can glimpse into Slovakia from here. On the way down we encounter a lonely, old chamois and then soon are back at our packs. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214337218" title="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/15214337218_b8187c6356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377902416" title="A look down at the valley by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/15377902416_901ef59a4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look down at the valley" /></a></p>

<p>The trail to Kondracka Kopa is a long, steady climb over a wide ridge. Clouds float over the ridge and surroundings summits, while alpine flowers are adding bright colours to the grey &amp; white of the sky. On my left I can see the lower hills of the Tatras and the meadow and refuge we slept in last night, and on the left zig-zags the trail down to the meadow from my original route. It does not take long and we’re on the summit of Kondracka Kopa, and now we will walk on the border of Poland and Slovakia while ticking off the next few summits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214340958" title="Along the border by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15214340958_71b3d109f2_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Along the border" /></a></p>

<p>We stay now almost all the time above 2000 m elevation while we hike in the clouds from Kondracka Kopa to Malolaczniak, Krzesanica, Ciemniak and then Twarda Kopa. Once in a while the clouds rip open and we can see the lower Tatras in Slovakia, narrow valleys, high walls, streams running towards the far off sea. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214423037" title="Towards Twarda Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3844/15214423037_2c456098d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Towards Twarda Kopa" /></a></p>

<p>From Twarda Kopa we can see Giemont in the distance, now in the clouds - but more worrisome is the helicopter which flies up to it from the valley. We don’t know what happened, but hope no one died.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400937025" title="A look back to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2943/15400937025_742b942b3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin waits for me at a large summit cairn and suggests we take the green trail down to the next refuge. It’s just around 11 and we have the whole day really in front of us still, so I agree and we take a turn from the big main path and walk on a very narrow path in a hanging meadow towards the Western Tatras.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214191449" title="Down 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3852/15214191449_334c07144a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="964" alt="Down 2" /></a></p>

<p>The views and the trail are spectacular. A narrow singletrack trail that’s demanding and exposed, but with gorgeous views on the lower-lying mountains, valleys, meadows - and in front of us, the Western Tatras. A pair of chamois give us a show as they are fighting in a couloir, but my view often just drifts to the horizon, where large mountains try to reach the sky with their summits. At a turn in the path we sit down and have a snack &amp; drink, while Marcin names the peaks and valleys and tells me anecdotes about geographical features. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377924676" title="A look back up the green trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2941/15377924676_45d34c6126_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="A look back up the green trail" /></a></p>

<p>Too soon we reach the tree line, but the path continues to be lovely. It gradually widens and Marcin tells me that it has been an old road for an iron ore mine, and I again wonder about how much work it must have been to clear the forests to create it. While we talk we reach the meadow and a group of fully loaded foreign backpackers pass us, just as amazed about the beautiful scenery around them as we are. The trail now runs next to a stream, and it does not take long until we reach the <a href="http://www.schronisko-ornak.pl">Schronisko Ornak refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397759651" title="Schronisko Ornak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397759651_65b41d3012_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Schronisko Ornak" /></a></p>

<p>It is busy outside and not even 13 o’clock. I check in with the help of Marcin and then accompany him down the valley - our hike ends here today, and I will be venturing on for the next two days on my own. The trail is now a wide dirt road and full of people, with plenty of trails going off on the right and left - trails which I will explore on my way back up to the refuge, I decide. And as Marcin tells me about the long caves up on the mountains which one can explore my afternoon suddenly looks like it will be filled with plenty of adventure!</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review LXXXVIII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxviii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-28T11:18:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxviii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“You can’t wait for inspiration. You have to go after it with a club.”</em> - Jack London</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15286935491" title="Seakayaking by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3868/15286935491_9e6b17ce63_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Seakayaking" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Help <a href="http://www.gofundme.com/ebhedc">find Cody Roman Dial</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://expedition-double8.dynafit.com/">Sebastian Haag dies during a speed ascent of Shisha Pangma</a>.</p>

<p>The first <a href="http://www.alpackawhitewater.com/">Alpacka Whitewater Packraft</a> has launched! Pre-order yours now.</p>

<p>And right on the heels of that is the <a href="http://www.bakraft.com/">BAKraft</a> from AIRE. It’s a self-bailing, whitewater-worthy, Dyneema shell and urethane bladders construction that weighs 6.5 pounds that costs around $1,200. It looks very nice and is a slight departure from traditional packraft designs. [<a href="http://forrestmccarthy.blogspot.fi/2014/09/bakraft-by-aire.html">Hat tip to Forrest</a>]</p>

<p>Mountain Laurel Design launched the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?products_id=217">DuoMid XL</a>, a new, asymmetrical DuoMid that is taller + wider. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.gearexposure.com/gopro-hero4-specs-leak-built-display-4k-30fps/">GoPro Hero4 specs leak</a> and it’s not a surprise as the HERO4 should come out within the next weeks. Which will make the <a href="http://bit.ly/1CxfHBc">HERO3</a> cheaper!</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://bit.ly/Yy21Xb">Patagonia Truth to Materials</a> line.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2014/09/25/africa-just-nature/">Africa is more than just nature</a>.</p>

<p>You can <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/">save 10% on HMG Gear</a> during the last week of September with the coupon code <em>follow10sep</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ukclimbing.com/articles/page.php?id=2298">How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/denniscaco/the-undress-change-clothes-in-public-without-getti">The Undress</a>.</p>

<p>Download the free <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/stand-here/id898186533?mt=8">Stand Here</a> app, an <em>app that provides you with everything you’ll need to know to get to the most stunning locations along the trail.</em></p>

<p>Bergfreunde have a lot of <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-bekleidung/fuer--kinder/">new gear for kids</a> - and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/p/icekid/">save 20% on Icebreaker garments</a> with the code <em>icekid</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=371165&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/371165/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://jolly-green-giant.blogspot.fi/2014/09/sili-dripper-lightweight-coffee-filter.html">Sili-Dripper - a Lightweight Coffee Filter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.backpackingengineer.com/falling-angels-7-days-gear-big-agnes-q-core-sl/">Big Agnes Q-core SL</a> reviewed.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-488.html">RMG Shoulder Pack Prototype</a> looks pretty awesome.</p>

<p><a href="http://geoffmallinson.com/2014/09/26/teaching-kids-how-to-navigate/">Teaching kids how to navigate</a>.</p>

<p>Jacob reviews the <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/western-mountaineering-alpinlite/">Western Mountaineering Alpinlite</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2014/09/paper-panniers-7-days-with-ortleib/">7 Days with Ortlieb</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/bergfilm-und-outdoor-buch/bene-benedikt-gebrauchsanweisung-fuer-die-alpen/">Gebrauchsanweisung für die Alpen</a> book review. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15229569551" title="Sunset by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3865/15229569551_be31061ddd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Chris is back! <a href="http://i-cjw.com/blog/2014/09/26/no-ifs-just-buttresses/">No Ifs, Just Buttresses</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cBJyo0tgLnw">Arctic Swell - Surfing the Ends of the Earth</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://vimeo.com/89458528">first attempt to cross Iceland on fixed gear bikes</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://stefanandcherry.com/2014/09/27/captain-kirk-and-the-one-day-enterprise/">Captain Kirk and the one day Enterprise</a>.</p>

<p>Nick is in <a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/09/24/albania-albania-albania/">Albania</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://offroute.ca/2014/09/25/call-of-the-wild-part1/">Bikepacking B.C.’s Coast Mountains</a>.</p>

<p>A great <a href="http://ivovanmontfort.blogspot.fi/2014/09/gort-droog-karst-en-sappige-bergweiden.html">9-day Pyrenees Trip report</a> from Ivo. [Dutch]</p>

<p>David enjoyed the <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2014/9/18/island-life">island life</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://willsim.blogspot.fi/2014/09/canada-part-1.html">Canada</a>.</p>

<p>Stefanie stand of top of <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/gipfelbuch-marmolata/">Marmolata</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Casey goes <a href="http://greenecasey.blogspot.fi/2014/09/bikepacking-yaaks-lookout-towers.html">Bikepacking Yaak’s Fire Lookout Towers</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seakayakingetc.blogspot.fi/2014/09/paddling-trip-on-san-juan-islands.html">Paddling trip on San Juan Islands</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/dHaNGTZWIxY?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://adelorenzo.exposure.co/aishihik-river">Aishihik River</a>, early season Yukon packrafting.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2014/05/building-patagonia-national-park-a-decade-long-partnership-with-patagonia-inc.html">Building Patagonia National Park: A decade-long partnership with Patagonia, Inc.</a>.</p>

<p>On the <a href="http://urskyburz.blogspot.fi/2014/09/sidelhorn.html">Sidelhorn</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Christine gives some tips about <a href="http://christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi/2014/09/paddling-gotakanal-conclusion-and-tipps.html">Paddling the Götakanal</a>.</p>

<p>John reviews the <a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2014/09/munich-to-venice-dream-way-review.html">Dream Way</a> from Munich to Venice.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://danceswithangiosperms.blogspot.fi/2014/09/the-last-days-day-129-141.html">The Last Days</a> on the PCT.</p>

<p><a href="http://howlingmist.blogspot.fi/2014/09/a-taste-of-chamonix-and-saas-grund-alps.html">A Taste Of Chamonix and Saas Grund</a>.</p>

<p>Steven &amp; Katrijn are <a href="http://patagoniandreams.com/2014/09/25/til-fots-i-fjellet-walking-in-the-mountains/">walking in the (Norwegian) mountains</a>.</p>

<p>Ryan starts at <a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2014/09/cape-wrath.html">Cape Wrath</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20228652/">燕岳</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://outdoorsmh.blogspot.fi/2014/09/two-days-in-northern-fells.html">Two Days in the Northern Fells</a>.</p>

<p>Steve tackles <a href="http://sdbwanderings.blogspot.fi/2014/07/crinkle-crags-bowfell-via-climbers.html">Crinkle Crags &amp; Bowfell via the climbers traverse</a>.</p>

<p>James heads <a href="http://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2014/09/27/into-the-wild-alone-in-sarek-and-padjelanta-part-two/">into the wild to Sarek and Padjelanta</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=42809&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/42809/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear Outtakes - Summer 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/gear-outtakes-summer-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-25T15:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/gear-outtakes-summer-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bite-sized gear reviews.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163660879" title="Gear Outtakes Summer 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3841/15163660879_2c170b6451_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gear Outtakes Summer 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I often get sent products or get asked to do reviews about gear though right now I’m short of time to do my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">in-depth reviews</a>. As I still use the kit quite a bit, Gear Outtakes is my solution to the problem - a seasonal collection of kit and what I think about it, inspired by <a href="http://www.minimallyminimal.com/">Minimally Minimal</a>.</p>

<p>★☆☆☆
Mediocre, I wouldn’t spend money on it.</p>

<p>★★☆☆
Good, but there are better options.</p>

<p>★★★☆
Great, worth your money.</p>

<p>★★★★
Outstanding, the benchmark of its category.</p>

<p>DISCLAIMER
<br />Some of these products have been sent to me for free by the manufacturer.</p>

<h2 id="phd-waferlite-shirt">PHD WaferLite Shirt</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15327351646" title="PHD WaferLite Shirt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3906/15327351646_183bfcdba7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD WaferLite Shirt" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />£150, available at <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/">PHD</a></p>

<p>A 137 g light down pullover (Size M). Between the 10X fabric is 900 cuin down and this sweet little pullover has been warm enough for summer adventures, when reaching the summit and there’s a small breeze, chilling at camp or taking a break between bouldering. It packs very small so easily fits in my backpack wherever I go, and is comfortable on the skin. While the material does feel filigrane it can take a bit of abuse, though I have used it strictly as a garment at camp/ resting/ when more warmth was needed. A long zipper helps with getting in and venting, there’s stretchy rims on the hem and cuffs and that’s about it. Really something for a SUL setup!</p>

<h2 id="field-notes-expedition-note-book--fn-19-space-pen">Field Notes EXPEDITION Note Book &amp; FN-19 Space Pen</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163680760" title="Field Notes EXPEDITION Note Book &amp; FN-19 Space Pen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3899/15163680760_0689dd6168_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Field Notes EXPEDITION Note Book &amp; FN-19 Space Pen" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />$9,95 for a 3-Pack of Note Books, $23,95 for the FN-19 Space Pen, available at <a href="http://fieldnotesbrand.com/colors/expedition/">Field Notes</a></p>

<p>I write it really down to remember it later. As I’m on over a dozen trips a year I sit down each evening at camp to write up how the day went. With the Expedition note books from Field Notes I can be sure that my notes will survive down pours and freezing cold temperatures. The FN-19 Space Pen packs small but is a real pen when in use, which I like. The ink won’t bleach, though it does have a bit of a tendency to smear when not 100% dry. / Pen 19 g, note book 30 g.</p>

<h2 id="patagonia-nano-puffy-hoody">Patagonia Nano-Puffy Hoody</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163622609" title="Patagonia Nano-Puff Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3928/15163622609_0e87a524a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Nano-Puff Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />From 209€, available at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-nano-puff-hoody-classic-navy-gr-s/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-nano-puff-hoody-kunstfaserjacke/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1peyjNY">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1DyvalK">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1u1LIi6">Patagonia</a></p>

<p>If it looks like it will get cool and wet on a spring, summer or autumn trip, the 331 g (Size S) light Nano-Puffy Hoody comes along, often even in conjunction with the PHD WaferLite Shirt. The Nano Puff Hoody is a classic piece and likely a staple in many outdoor mens &amp; womens wardrobe, and for a good reason. It’s a super warm hoody that keeps the wind outside and has a DWR finish that lets you wear it in a light drizzle. Even if it gets wet, it still keeps you warm. It packs in its own inside pocket. The hood keeps the ears and head warm. It looks nice. Yeps, with the Patagonia Nano-Puffy Hoody you’re warm &amp; well-dressed in the three warm seasons!</p>

<h2 id="houdini-thrill-twill-pants">Houdini Thrill Twill Pants</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163804978" title="Houdini Thrill Twill Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2950/15163804978_6b735d3d3a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Houdini Thrill Twill Pants" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />140€, available at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/houdini-thrill-twill-pants-kletterhose/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://moonlight-gear.com/?pid=59752392">Moonlight Gear</a></p>

<p>305 g in Size XS, the Houdini Thrill Twill Pants was along on lot of trips this year. The reason is simple: It’s a well-fitting pants with great freedom of movement. Hiking, scrambling, climbing, going to the pub or business meetings at the OutDoor, the Thrill Twill Pants does it all well while being comfortable. The biggest plus for me is probably that the size is so great, in XS I don’t need a belt and it fits perfectly. High heel hooks are no problem, and the pants dries fast when the get wet. Stretchy drawstring allow me to adjust the size of the trouser legs, very useful when climbing and wanting to see where that micro ledge for my next step is. A beautiful pair of trousers that’s durable and can be recycled at the end of its life.</p>

<h2 id="haglfs-triton-ii-hood">Haglöfs Triton II Hood</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163685740" title="Haglöfs Triton II Hood by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3911/15163685740_77186e7162_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs Triton II Hood" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />From 120€, available from <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorstore.com/en/miesten-vaatteet/miesten-alus-ja-valiasut/triton-II-hood/">Scandinavian Outdoor Store</a> and <a href="http://tinyurl.com/op2no7h">Cotswold</a></p>

<p>I have been using fleece jackets again for several years, and the Haglöfs Triton II Hood, a full-zip fleece jacket with thumbloops &amp; a hood, has been a staple in my layering system since I got it last year. The hood can be worn under a helmet, be it a cycle helmet or my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Petzl Sirocco</a>, while the thumbloops help on those first cool autumn days where I forgot to take a pair of gloves along for the bicycle ride. Three zippered pockets store stuff safely on the go, be it hiking, hill walking or climbing. It’s a comfy fleece jacket in a beautiful colour, and if I need a nice, cozy yet breathable midlayer or I’m cool in the mornings at home then the Triton II comes on. / 303 g in Size S.</p>

<h2 id="norrna-bitihorn-aero100-jacket">Norrøna bitihorn aero100 Jacket</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15347199481" title="Norrøna bitihorn aero100 Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3874/15347199481_2d57af6338_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Norrøna bitihorn aero100 Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />139€, available at <a href="https://www.norrona.com/en-GB/Products/4326-12/3440/bitihorn-aero100-jacket-m/">Norrøna</a></p>

<p>The Norrøna bitihorn aero100 Jacket (104 g in Size M) accompanies me since autumn 2013 already and has been a joy to use. It’s lightweight and can be packed in its own chest pocket, which is ideal when travelling. While I occasionally missed a hood I managed to life without it. The Size M was a alright fit despite me being a Size S - I needed to pull the hem drawstring pretty tight for it being a good fit. The jacket stays well in place also when in a cycling position and the material is durable enough to carry heavy grocery backpacks or light backpacking rucksacks. As its always windy on the coast here, the bitihorn aero100 is often along to keep the cool wind at bay.</p>

<h2 id="merrell-allout-rush">Merrell AllOut Rush</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15350072232" title="Merrell AllOut Rush by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2942/15350072232_2970494944_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Merrell AllOut Rush" /></a></p>

<p>★★☆☆
<br />From $71,95, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1reb500">Backcountry</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1ptL2M3">CampSaver.com</a></p>

<p>I’m not 100% happy with the Merrell AllOut Rush - the large drop is likely the reason for that. It’s not as minimal anymore as other shoes from Merrell and after wearing them for a while and switching into more minimalist shoes I realize how my stride has suffered. That said, if you’re new to the whole barefoot hiking &amp; walking movement you might find the AllOut Rush just perfect. It’s a nice shoe with good grip on many surfaces, from wet grass to muddy uphills. The toe box offers your toes plenty of space, and the heel cup also gives a good fit. / 556 g in Size 42.</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-carrier-duffle-50">Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle 50</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163678760" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Carrier Duffle 50 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2942/15163678760_a5bc6fc80f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Carrier Duffle 50" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />125€, available at <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;category=Packs&amp;subcat=Duffle_Bags&amp;model=Carrier-Duffle-50">Arc’teryx</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1ptPtX0">Backcountry</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1renam3">CampSaver.com</a></p>

<p>It was about time that I replaced the 60 l stuff sack I used for transporting my ultralight backpacks when flying abroad for a hike: It already had a few holes at it and somehow always arrived open in Vaasa’s airport at the baggage claim. That no longer happens with the Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle 50: It stays closed and also the occasional downpours the duffle needs to endure when it’s loaded in to the plane are no problem anymore: The Carrier Duffle is highly water resistant. It is just 538 g heavy, which is in comparison with other duffles almost SUL! I can wear it backpack style or over the shoulder and at the airport the straps can be pulled tight and stored out of the way. At the top and bottom there is a haul loop and on each side there’s a handle - so you or the friendly airport employee can carry the duffle as it was intended. A superb piece of kit that goes along on every trip abroad.</p>

<h2 id="rock-technologies-chalk-balls">Rock Technologies Chalk Balls</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15350381185" title="Rock Technologies Chalk Balls by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15350381185_01d38b17dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Technologies Chalk Balls" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />From £10, available at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/rock-technologies/">Bergzeit</a> and <a href="http://www.rocktechnologies.co.uk/order-online/">Rock Technologies</a></p>

<p>Using chalk is pretty much essential when climbing, even more so when bouldering. <em>“Chalk up correctly”</em> was something I heard quite a few times during the last weeks climbing &amp; bouldering, and I was happy to have pharmaceutical grade Magnesium Carbonate chalk from Rock Technologies in my chalk bag. A chalk ball reduces air born chalk dust and so is more healthy - if you ever visited the <a href="http://www.boulderwelt.de/">Boulderwelt in München</a> you will wish everyone would use chalkballs! Anyway, the chalkballs are easy to use and it’s fast &amp; efficient for chalking up. The chalk is good and helps you to stick to slopers and prevents sweaty hands &amp; fingers for a good while. / 60 g</p>

<h2 id="ocun-crack-gloves">Ocun Crack Gloves</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15350377295" title="Ocun Crack Gloves by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15350377295_170a5e853c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ocun Crack Gloves" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />29,95€, available at <a href="http://shop.boulderkeskus.com/en/shop/climbing_gear/tarvike/crackgloves.html">Boulderkeskus</a></p>

<p>Also known as <em>Cheater Gloves</em> these 48 g light gloves allow you to climb cracks like Spiderman without ripping open your knuckles and the back of your hand. Also sweaty hands are no longer responsible for slipping in a crack. Sure, you could just tape up your hands and be tough when you go up a crack, but I find the Crack Gloves much better, really. Easy to use - the most difficult thing is figuring out your size - the gloves close with a Velcro strap and the outside is made of a sticky rubber which gives a lot of friction. The side that’s to the back of your hand has a cushioned mesh lining which makes sharp, sharp cracks slightly more bearable. If you’re starting to get into crack climbing - get a pair. They’re cheaper than all the tape you’re bound to wrap around your hands, and a lot better.</p>

<h2 id="peak-design-leash">Peak Design Leash</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15350376445" title="Peak Design Leash by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15350376445_37989a0ae7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Peak Design Leash" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />34,95$, available at <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/leash?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design</a></p>

<p>The 47 g light Peak Design Leash I bought earlier this year as I realized that my Dyneema cord ain’t the best solution to carry my camera (<a href="http://youtu.be/wHUFWUGWKS4?list=UU927vE_KkPy6pFJboaJ9Lig">as explained here</a>). I’ve been very happy with the Leash, it’s worlds more comfortable than the Dyneema string and easy to use, too. If it’s not needed or could get into the way I can quickly take it off, and the many varied possibilities the Leash can be used make it a really versatile camera strap. It’s also compatible the the Peak Design Strap and the new systems, which I’m considering trying out next.</p>

<h2 id="hariyama-productions-coin-case">Hariyama Productions coin case</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15163805668" title="Hariyama Productions coin case by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2941/15163805668_c2bc43673d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hariyama Productions coin case" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />1.800円, available at <a href="http://moonlight-gear.com/?pid=39819567">Moonlight Gear</a></p>

<p>A companion since well over a year, the Hariyama Productions coin case is a 4 g cuben wallet and all I need for carrying cash &amp; cards. It can get a bit tight when I have several business cards in there and need to carry cash, but in Finland I rarely need anything else than a Debit/ Credit Card either way so there’s no need to search for coins or bills. It has been water-resistant but after being daily pulled out of my pocket between a few times and a dozen times it look like I will need to get a new one. They come with differently coloured zippers and I think I will go for a orange one the next time! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review LXXXVII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxvii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-21T10:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxvii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The three weeks climbing &amp; bouldering roadtrip through Finland is finished. Time to enjoy being at home with the family and getting ready for the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/petzl-roctrip-2014-eastern-europe.html">Petzl RocTrip 2014</a> in Turkey in a few weeks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15301030592" title="Milky Way by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3886/15301030592_bb029c0f2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Milky Way" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.gq.com/news-politics/newsmakers/201409/the-last-true-hermit">The Strange &amp; Curious Tale of the Last True Hermit</a>.</p>

<p>PHD has launched their <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/sales-and-special-offers">Autumn Race Collection</a> which also will appeal to ultralight backpackers and alpinists who wanna go super-light!</p>

<p>Win a new <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/black-diamond-raffle/">Black Diamond Access LT Hybrid Hoody &amp; Speed 40 pack</a>. Or check out the New <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en/mens-jackets-shells-goretex.html">Black Diamond Gore-Tex line</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.walkonthewildside.eu/advanced_search_result.php?keywords=zeltsale">Walk on the Wild Side Tent Sale</a> is in full swing.</p>

<p>Dave wonders what <a href="http://davemacleod.blogspot.fi/2014/09/what-have-we-done.html">Scotland has done</a>.</p>

<p>LAUFBURSCHE has the <a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/trekker-ultra-004/">Nomadic Trekker stoves in stock</a> - but be quick to order one, they’re popular!</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2014/09/3-lessons-about-bicycle-tourism-from-rural-bike-advocates/">Three Lessons about Bicycle Tourism from Rural Bike Advocates</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-21-dia-abend-2-0/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #21</a> is out. [German]</p>

<p>Tourism: <a href="http://grapevine.is/mag/column-opinion/2014/09/04/tourism-the-destruction-of-iceland/">The Destruction Of Iceland</a>.</p>

<p>The FREELIGHT <a href="http://obakanahibi.blog31.fc2.com/blog-entry-1169.html">SpinNap Code Zero</a> pack is released in the coming week.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-adventure/exploration/The-Worlds-Toughest-Adventure-Addict.html">Swiss explorer Mike Horn looks to grind out a big first</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.spoon-tamago.com/2014/09/19/wasabi-the-hardest-plant-to-grow-in-the-world/">Wasabi is the hardest plant to grow in the world</a>.</p>

<p>You still have time to win some sweet <a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.com/2014/09/big-sky-gear-raffle.html">Big Sky Gear</a>.</p>

<p>Bergfreunde have the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/fjaellraeven/">Fjällräven</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/marmot/">Marmot</a> gear for the winter online!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.garagegrowngear.com/where-to-find-the-latest-trends-for-cool-new-gear/">Cairn</a> is a new way to discover new gear &amp; companies.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Jacob is <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/nutty-for-cococnut/">Nutty for Coconut</a>.</p>

<p>Jim sat down with Excel to ponder: <a href="http://adventuresinstoving.blogspot.fi/2014/09/which-is-lighter-alcohol-or-gas_14.html">Which is Lighter – Alcohol or Gas</a>?</p>

<p>Chris reviews the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/source-wlp-low-profile-hydration-system-review/">Source WLP Low Profile Hydration System</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-487.html">RMG Body Pocket Prototype</a> looks pretty good.</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/blue-steel-permadraw-solution/">Blue Steel: A Permadraw Solution</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=264573&amp;pw=73183">REI Outlet Days of Deals are a go</a>! Save an EXTRA 20% - 30% on a new deal every day - but be quick, it ends on the 23rd of September!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15046116028" title="Chalk on Rock by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5591/15046116028_f45ff540ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chalk on Rock" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Jean and John are enjoying <a href="http://www.panafoot.com/2014/09/best-of-both-worlds.html">the best of both worlds</a> since four and half years. </p>

<p><a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2014/09/ghost-towns-road-to-nabesna.html">The Road to Nabesna</a>.</p>

<p>Angelica takes a <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2014/09/19/die-landskrone-lohrsdorf-gipfelselfie-im-ahrtal/">Summit Selfie in the Ahrtal</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Ryan’s <a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2014/09/my-last-full-day-in-ireland.html">last full day in Ireland</a>.</p>

<p>Cass rolls into <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/bolivia/into-chile-and-out-to-la-paz">Chile</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://surfnslide.wordpress.com/2014/09/14/wild-camping-in-the-welsh-wilderness/">Wild Camping in the Welsh Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>Jill is <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2014/09/living-in-color-part-two.html">Living in color</a>.</p>

<p>Nick climbs the <a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2014/09/15/steves-wisdom-aka-humble-horse-diadem-north-face/">Diadem North Face</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/96945398?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A story narrated by <a href="http://around-scotland.blogspot.fi/2014/09/a-story-narrated-by-helvellyn.html">Helvellyn</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/himalaya-ice-climbing/">Himalaya Ice Climbing</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://shewiesworld.blogspot.fi/2014/09/cape-wrath-trail.html">Cape Wrath Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Don takes a ride in the <a href="http://lightpack.blogspot.fi/2014/09/dupont-national-forest.html">DuPont National Forest</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pinetflorence.blogspot.fi/2014/09/etape-1-la-roumanie.html">Florence reports from Romania</a>. [French]</p>

<p>Corinna hikes to the <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2014/09/wanderung-refugio-pedrotti.html">Refugio Pedrotti</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/09/20/around-shkoder-lake-montenegro/">Around Shkodër Lake, Montenegro</a>.</p>

<p>Roger hikes to <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/09/cuhcajavri-to-nikkaluokta-end.html">Nikkaluokta, the end of his trip</a>.</p>

<p>Watch the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kgb2G_IgvTw">Kongakut</a> video!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpin-blog.com/weisskugel/">Weisskugel</a>. [German]</p>

<p><strong>Follow along</strong> on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review LXXXVI]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxvi.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-14T09:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxvi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>People who think they know everything are a great annoyance to those of us who do.</em> - Isaac Asimov</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15209576226" title="Åland Impressions by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5575/15209576226_6c68d0f5b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="256" alt="Åland Impressions" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Win some sweet <a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.com/2014/09/big-sky-gear-raffle.html">Big Sky Gear</a>.</p>

<p>Simon ponders about an <a href="http://simon-willis.blogspot.com/2014/09/an-independent-scotland.html">Independent Scotland</a>.</p>

<p>Sir Chris Bonington climbs <a href="http://community.berghaus.com/athletes/the-old-man-at-80/">The Old Man of Hoy on his 80th birthday</a>.</p>

<p>The newest <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/trekking-magazin-05-2014.html">trekking Magazin</a> is out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/bei-dauerregen-auf-einer-berghuette/">What to do when it rains on a mountain hut</a>? [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://johndburns.wordpress.com/2014/09/13/its-life-jim-but-not-as-we-know-it/">Climbing is changing</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/">Bergzeit.co.uk</a> has new winter gear from Mammut &amp; Norrona in stock. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=371165&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/371165/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.com/2014/09/notfallapotheke-wanderung-mit-kindern.html">What belongs into your FA Kit when hiking with kids</a>? [German]</p>

<p>Zack takes a <a href="http://dedpxl.com/fuji-x100t-first-look/">first look at the Fuji X100T</a>.</p>

<p>I conclude the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">One Stop Shop Series</a> with a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/multi-shop-stop.html">Multi-Shop Stop</a>.</p>

<p>Emily reports from <a href="http://emilyroolearnstorun.blogspot.com/2014/08/the-other-side-of-camera.html">the other side of the Camera</a>.</p>

<p>Niels spent 30 nights on the <a href="http://backpackinglightdk.blogspot.com/2014/09/30-ntter-pa-nemo-zor-20r-liggeunderlag.html">Nemo Zor 20R</a>.</p>

<p>Dave files the <a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2014/09/09/the-2014-shoe-report/">2014 shoe report</a>.</p>

<p>Mike ponders about <a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.com/2014/09/snowbike-geometry.html">Snowbike geometry</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://coastkid.blogspot.com/2014/09/surly-karate-monkey-drop-bar-29er.html">Surly Karate Monkey Drop bar 29er</a>.</p>

<p>Michael reviews the <a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/msr-hubba-nx">MSR Hubba NX</a>.</p>

<p>Chad takes a look at the <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2014/09/11/first-look-the-montbell-ex-light-anorak/">Montbell Ex Light Anorak</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://imaginegnat.com/2014/09/08/fatbike-ramblings/">Fatbike Ramblings</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/hmg-packs-100-waterproof/">Are HMG Packs 100% Waterproof</a>?</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/ausruestung/vorgestellt-das-modulare-sheltersystem-von-the-theory-works/">modular Shelter System from The Theory Works</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15232294192" title="Nico by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5558/15232294192_c9c0bc2d7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="668" alt="Nico" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/bolivia/cycling-on-the-salar">Eyes Wide Shut: Cycling on the Salar</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20187571/">鳳凰三山</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>A fine <a href="http://www.albertodegiuli.com/2014/09/alpinismo-e-alta-montagna-dente-del-gigante-biancograt-al-bernina-e-traversata-del-piz-palu/">mountaineering trip to the Piz Palu</a>. [Italian]</p>

<p>Planeta Packraft’s 2nd part of their <a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2014/09/articulo-camino-del-agua-laponia_12.html">Lapland Packrafting trip</a>. [Spanish]</p>

<p>Don shares some thoughts and wonderful photos from the <a href="http://talusfield.net/blog/2014/8/30/sierra-high-route-route-notes-thoughts-and-photos">Sierra High Route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jstarinorbit.com/2014/09/ten-days-in-idaho.html">Ten days in Idaho</a>.</p>

<p>Greg is <a href="http://cumbriafellraven.blogspot.com/2014/09/out-and-in-aiguestortes.html">Out and In the Aiguestortes</a>.</p>

<p>Nick takes a <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/?p=1462">short round on The Beaten Path</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/o86TpaSBcWw?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Joery packrafts the <a href="http://dzjow.com/2014/09/08/the-gorges-of-the-haut-allier-the-jewel-of-paddling-in-the-massif-central/">gorges of the Haut-Allier</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pantilat.wordpress.com/2014/09/11/mount-davis/">Mount Davis</a>.</p>

<p>Paul hikes to <a href="http://www.sharkeysdream.walkingplaces.co.uk/?p=22965">Raven Crag &amp; Castlerigg Stone Circle</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2014/09/rock-my-raft-packrafting-tour-am.html">“Röck my Raft” Packrafting-Tour</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://outtherekids.wordpress.com/2014/09/07/abisko-2014-high-altitude-valleys/">Kungsleden Family backpacking trip</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/wandern-schafe-schottland-irland/">An ode to the sheep</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Will shares memories from <a href="http://willsim.blogspot.com/2014/09/summer.html">Summer</a>.</p>

<p>Part 3 of Willem’s <a href="http://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2014/09/12/iceland-part-iii-kristinarstindar-and-other-bits-and-pieces/">Iceland hike</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://stefanandcherry.com/2014/09/14/heat-hydration-and-offset-nuts-on-triple-direct-el-capitan/">Heat, Hydration and Offset nuts on Triple Direct, El Capitan</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Follow along</strong> on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 05/2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/trekking-magazin-05-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-12T09:40:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/trekking-magazin-05-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today on the shelves is the latest issue of the trekking Magazin with three articles of your truly!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15213900425" title="trekking Magazin 05/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5579/15213900425_03da672782_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="trekking Magazin 05/2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In this issue I write about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> which I visited in June and give a lot of details about planning your own stay in Chamonix. In my columne I write about five great hiking pants from Houdini to Klättermusen, and then there’s a very long trip report in it about my hike on the Escapardenne Eisleck Trail in Luxembourg which I thru-hiked in May of this year. It’s a beautiful trail with lots to offer and is well suited for those that look for culture, nature and a well-marked trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15213900665" title="trekking Magazin 05/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3886/15213900665_eeed1d365b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="trekking Magazin 05/2014" /></a></p>

<p>And of course there’s still plenty more in there, from fine hikes in Germany to rambling through the hills of Tuscany. Thus go pick up the current issue at a Kiosk near you or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> to not miss any future issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multi-Shop Stop]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/multi-shop-stop.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-09T15:27:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/multi-shop-stop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the spring and summer of this year <a href="http://blog.fastpacking.de/">Carsten</a> started the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">One Stop Shop Series</a> and I added several international webshops to the list. Now I want to take an excursion into shopping NOT at one shop, but buying an Ultralight Gear List from several shops. Will it be lighter and cheaper than the average?</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3780/13239809123_951258df2d_b.jpg#tl-502427615970197505;1043138249" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>If you need to freshen up what this is all about, read the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/one-stop-shop-introduction.html">Introduction</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">browse the past entries</a>!</em></p>

<p>Carsten’s One Stop Shop Idea really was superb. It gave new and old backpackers an easy list of online shops with gear choices which allowed them to find the lightest and/ or cheapest gear to lighten up or get a complete backpacking kit. I tried to get a few big Retailers like <a href="http://bit.ly/UB20wn">REI.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/Wi4tZS">Backcountry.com</a> to join the series for even more options but wasn’t successful (well, maybe they join now ;). Anyway, with 13 shops from Europe, the USA and Japan budding lightweight backpackers have over a dozen of options to choose from and get inspiration for a lightweight kit. Here’s that list with weights &amp; prices for your convenience:</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/one-stop-shop-trekking-lite-store-dot-com.html">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a></td>
      <td>6.157 g</td>
      <td>2.288,80 €</td>
      <td>0,47 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/one-stop-shop-campsaver-dot-com.html">CampSaver.com</a></td>
      <td>5.316 g</td>
      <td> 1.993,80 €</td>
      <td>0,52 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/one-stop-shop-globetrotter.html">Globetrotter</a></td>
      <td>8.995 g</td>
      <td> 3.272,20 €</td>
      <td>0,36 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/one-stop-shop-partioaitta.html">Partioaitta</a></td>
      <td> 7.354 g</td>
      <td>2448,15 €</td>
      <td>0,33 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/one-stop-shop-bergfreunde.html">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> 4.657 g</td>
      <td>2.440,10 €</td>
      <td>0,52 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/one-stop-shop-walkonthewildside.html">Walkonthewildside.eu</a></td>
      <td> 6.143 g</td>
      <td> 2.349,45 €</td>
      <td>0,38 g per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/one-stop-shop-backpackinglight-dot-dk.html">Backpackinglight.dk</a></td>
      <td> 4.994 g</td>
      <td>2.464,35 €</td>
      <td>0,49 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/one-stop-shop-racelite-dot-de.html">Racelite.de</a></td>
      <td>5.884 g</td>
      <td> 2.145,05 €</td>
      <td>0,36 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/one-stop-shop-ultralight-outdoor-gear.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a></td>
      <td> 4.549 g</td>
      <td>2.796,69 €</td>
      <td>0,61 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/one-stop-shop-bergzeit.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> 5.559 g</td>
      <td>2.430,00 €</td>
      <td>0,44 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/one-stop-shop-outdoorline-dot-sk.html">Outdoorline.sk</a></td>
      <td> 5.392 g</td>
      <td> 2.056,70 €</td>
      <td> 0,38 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/one-stop-shop-aventure-nordique.html">Aventure Nordique</a></td>
      <td> 6.044 g</td>
      <td> 2.121,40 €</td>
      <td> 0,35 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/one-stop-shop-moonlight-gear.html">Moonlight Gear</a></td>
      <td> 2.630 g</td>
      <td>1.735,36 €</td>
      <td>0,66 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>AVERAGE</strong></td>
      <td> 5.667 g</td>
      <td>2.349,39 €</td>
      <td>0,45 € per gram</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br />The thing is with the One Stop Shop: What if you really want a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/05/packing-your-frameless-backpack-laufbursche-huckepack.html">Laufbursche huckePACK</a> as your backpack? Or a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mpv4kAtN_DQ">Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar</a> as your shelter? An <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/the-2nd-renaissance-of-esbit.html">Esbit Stove setup</a>? You always could adapt your shopping at the one shop you want to buy - they do, after all, often offer a lot more options than the ones they suggested. But what if another webshop has a better price on the kit you want? What if the shop <em>doesn’t have</em> the item you really want?</p>

<p>Then you’ll need to buy from several shops. While this will add extra costs in form of shipping costs (and import taxes if you order from outside Europe) it still might be cheaper - the € is still relatively strong which makes buying abroad more affordable. Thus my experiment is simple: I want to buy a few items I really want but try to keep the list as cheap &amp; light as possible. Here we go:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Item</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Name</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">Weight in gram</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">Price in €</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Backpack</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/huckepack">Laufbursche huckePACK incl. Airbeam</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">525</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">348,00 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Sleeping bag</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/">PHD Minix Down Bag</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">590</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">199,00 £</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mattress</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html">Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">353</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">149,95 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Shelter</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">499</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">675,00 $</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pot</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="">-</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: right"> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> Stove</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Kueche/Trail-Designs-Caldera-GVP-Kochsystem::533.html?refID=hif">Trail Designs Caldera GVP</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">91</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">53,90 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Cutlery</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Kueche/Sea-to-Summit-Alpha-Light-Loeffel-lang::349.html?refID=hif">Sea to Summit Alpha Light</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">12</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">7,95 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Knife</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Kueche/Deejo-Leichtgewichtsmesser-27-g::748.html?refID=hif">Deejo Light Knife</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">27</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">24,95 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Lamp</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-eplus-lite-stirnlampe/?pid=81">Petzl e+ Lite</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">27</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">29,95 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trekking Poles</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles.html">Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">264</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">129,95 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Shoes</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals OSO</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">412</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">125,00 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Fleece</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-delta-lt-jacke-anvil-grey-gr-s/?pid=81">Arc’teryx Delta LT Jacket</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">285</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">99,95 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Insulation</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-atom-lt-hoody-kaktos-gr-s/?pid=81">Arc’teryx Atom LT Hoody</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">375</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">139,00 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Rain pants</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/marmot-precip-full-zip-pant-black-gr-xl-short-brg/?pid=81">Marmot PreCip Full Zip Pant</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">377</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">89,95 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Rain jacket</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/marmot-precip-jacke-green-lime-gr-s/?pid=81">Marmot PreCip Jacket</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">372</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">80,00 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Boxers</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/super-natural-base-boxer-175-dark-blue-gr-s/?pid=81">Super.Natural Base Boxer 175</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">50</td>
      <td style="text-align: right"> 18,00 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>T-Shirt</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/icebreaker-tech-t-lite-ss-climb-on-heat-gr-m/?pid=81">Icebreaker Tech T Lite SS</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">138</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">45,00 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Longsleeve</td>
      <td style="text-align: center"><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/ortovox-rock-039-n-039-wool-longsleeve-crazy-orange-gr-l/?pid=81">Ortovox Rock’n’Wool Longsleeve</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: right">250</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">84,95 €</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>TOTAL</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">-</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">4.647</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">2.200,00 €</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br />In this list I ordered from five different parties and this are the shipping costs to Finland: HMG 50 $, Laufbursche 17 €, PHD 24,90 £, Trekking-Lite-Store.com 13,50 €, Bergzeit 9,95 €. In the above total these are not included (currencies have been converted today via <a href="http://www.xe.com/">xe.com</a>) but would add 110,45€ to the total. I also only ordered the HMG UltaMid from outside Europe so only would need to pay import duties for it (or not with some luck!). I looked for bargains in the different shops, and thus with a total of 2.310,45 € I would get the exact kit I want from several different shops. My list still is cheaper than over half of the above shops, and only two shops offered a lighter list. </p>

<p><em>The conclusion?</em> If you’re starting out with backpacking and want to do it right (thus, light) from the start, buying all your gear from one shop is very convenient. However, if you want a special piece of gear that the shop doesn’t carry, it only minimally increases the costs to order it from somewhere else (and this is especially true in the USA, where lots of online retailers offer free shipping above a certain amount). Also, mixing it up and supporting small cottages like Laufbursche Gear, highly specialized companies like PHD, niche retailers like Treking-Lite-Store.com and large online shops like Bergzeit makes sense, as this way you can look for the best offers across them &amp; still save, and what the one doesn’t have the other can offer. </p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">One Stop Shop Series</a> was <a href="http://blog.fastpacking.de/">Carsten</a>’s idea and he gave me permission to translate his posts to English and contact a few more shops around the world. If you can read German, you can head over to his blog and read the posts in German.</em></p>

<p><em>Liked this? Follow along for more of that on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review LXXXV]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxv.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-07T11:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“When I feel well and in a good humour, or when I am taking a drive or walking after a good meal, or in the night when I cannot sleep, thoughts crowd into my mind as easily as you could wish.”</em> ― Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14978534228" title="Olhava by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5590/14978534228_23ae154568_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Olhava" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Read the free <a href="http://www.edelrid.de/en/Rope-Book/">Edelrid Rope book</a> to learn more about ropes.</p>

<p>Get the new <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/norrona/?_artperpage=96&amp;sort=3">Norrøna Lofoten line at Bergzeit.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p>Why <a href="http://davemacleod.blogspot.fi/2014/09/scotland-what-to-decide-starting-place.html">Dave MacLeeod votes Yes on an independent Scotland</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://twitter.com/TrekkingLite">Trekking-Lite-Store.com is now on Twitter</a>.</p>

<p>There are <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=4050&amp;pw=73183">rebates available at REI</a> and you can get <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3853&amp;pw=73183">free shipping using the REI Store Pickup</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/s/*/kategorie--klettern/?listorderby=oxinsert&amp;listorder=desc&amp;log=intern&amp;">Bergfreunde have a lot of new climbing gear just in</a>.</p>

<p>I have updated the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/rock-climbing-for-beginners.html">Beginner’s Guide to Rock Climbing</a> and added several more instructional videos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15142058046" title="Jetboil Joule by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3835/15142058046_12a99b4510_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Joule" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Roger compares the <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/09/what-works-for-me-shelters.html">Tarptent Stratospire and Notch</a>.</p>

<p>Phil takes a look at the <a href="http://philsorrell.com/2014/09/01/mountain-warehouse-microlite-700-sleeping-bag-initial-thoughts/">Mountain Warehouse Microlite 700 Sleeping Bag</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bah.cocolog-nifty.com/blog/2014/09/20130515-aki-sa.html">Jaki Sandals a.k.a huarache sandals</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Derek reviews the <a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2014/09/therm-a-rest-slacker-hammock-single-review/">Therm-a-Rest Slacker Hammock Single</a>.</p>

<p><a title="Bergzeit.co.uk" href="http://apps.bergzeit.de/seo/ldyn?pid=81&amp;bid=13&amp;cat=9&amp;lang=en" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><img alt="Bergzeit.co.uk" title="Bergzeit.co.uk" src="http://apps.bergzeit.de/seo/bdyn?pid=81&amp;bid=13&amp;cat=9&amp;lang=en" width="728" height="90" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>The Planeta Packraft Team  is back from Lapland and writes about the <a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2014/09/articulo-camino-del-agua-laponia.html">Camino del Agua</a>. [Spanish]</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2014/09/baugen-pieni-retrospektiivi.html">small retroperspective on Baugen</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.abenteuersuechtig.de/index.php/spaghetti-tour-light-fuenf-viertausender-einem-tag/">Five 4000 m peaks in a day</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/09/05/romanian-rail-serbian-sun-montenegran-mountains/">Romanian rail, Serbian sun, Montenegran mountains</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://injuringeternity.net/2014/08/16/climbing-and-packrafting-in-ardeche-and-vercors-france/">Climbing and packrafting in Ardeche and Vercors, France</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seakayakingetc.blogspot.fi/2014/09/hiking-trip-on-yosemite-national-park.html">Hiking Trip on Yosemite National Park</a>.</p>

<p>Nick does the <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/?p=1431">Teton Crest Trail in a day</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://outlivingblog.wordpress.com/2014/09/03/late-summer-in-wet-canyons-2/">Late summer in wet canyons</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bah.cocolog-nifty.com/blog/2014/09/2013051112-hike.html">Okutama hike</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://dirtyteeth.wordpress.com/2014/09/02/white-mountain-peak-ride-silver-canyon-to-the-summit/">White Mountain Peak Ride – Silver Canyon to the Summit</a>.</p>

<p>Cass appeases <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/bolivia/appeasing-papa-uturuncu-and-pedalling-to-5777m">Papa Uturuncu and pedals to 5777 m</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-484.html">立山縦走 Day3</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/103160832?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Adam visits the <a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2014/09/walrus-lakes.html">Walrus Lakes</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://imaginegnat.com/2014/09/03/touring-the-root-river-trail-with-kids/">Touring the Root River trail with Kids</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.farawayvisions.com/mud-and-biryani-netley-to-amberley/">Mud and Biryani – Netley to Amberley</a>.</p>

<p>Willem found <a href="http://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2014/09/06/iceland-part-ii-a-special-spot-above-heinabergsjokull/">a special spot above Heinabergsjökull</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.guthookhikes.com/2014/09/baxter-backpacking-day-5-the-traveler.html">Baxter Backpacking, Day 5</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://lifeinthevertical.co.uk/blogs/blog/2014/09/north-wales-climbs-episode-2/">North Wales Climbs</a>.</p>

<p>Mark spent <a href="http://markswalkingblog.wordpress.com/2014/09/01/5-days-in-the-lakes-part-1/">five days in the Lakes</a>.</p>

<p>James goes into the <a href="http://glencoemountaineer.blogspot.fi/2014/09/hagg-gill-pot.html">Hagg Gill Pot</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cumbriafellraven.blogspot.fi/2014/09/backpacking-in-and-out-of-aiguestortes.html">Backpacking in and out of the Aiguestortes</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want to stay up-to-date?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review LXXXIV]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxiv.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-01T08:07:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/the-week-in-review-lxxxiv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“If you don’t have expectations, you don’t have disappointment.”</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15079626126" title="Florian on Lenina-T, Redpoint. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/15079626126_2dafb00695_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Florian on Lenina-T, Redpoint." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Neil lets you know where to <a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/win-stuff-online-competitions-hikers-september-2014/">win outdoor gear</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/tipps/wettervorhersage-in-der-natur/">1 x 1 of outdoor weather prediction</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Chris Townsend votes Yes on the <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2014/08/scottish-independence-referendum-why-im.html">Scottish Independence Referendum</a>.</p>

<p>Win a <a href="http://www.appalachiantrials.com/gear-giveaway-renegade-pro-series-quilt/">RENEGADE Pro Series Quilt by UGQ Outdoor Equipment</a>.</p>

<p>A new <a href="http://simon-willis.blogspot.fi/2014/09/new-podcast-double-ditch.html">Sea kayak podcast</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.trailgroove.com/">TrailGroove Issue 17 is out</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://misscristascott.blogspot.fi/2014/08/10-reasons-to-run-50k-instead-of.html">10 Reasons to run a 50k instead of a Marathon</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2014/08/29/news-termine-september-2014/">News &amp; Dates for September 2014</a>. [German]</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/">Bergfreunde</a> move and have a massive sale on sleeping bags, tents, backpacks, climbing gear and clothes. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28933&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28933/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="468" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20146111/">日陰名栗山</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.abenteuersuechtig.de/index.php/auf-messers-schneide-die-liskamm-ueberschreitung/">The Liskamm Traverse</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2014/08/still-too-dumb-to-quit.html">Still too dumb to quit</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.williswall.com/willis-wall-blog/2014/8/31/8-days-in-the-pasayten-wilderness-aug2014.html">8 Days in the Pasayten Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>John hikes from Munich to Venice and spends <a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2014/08/day-15-munich-to-venice-passo-pordoi.html">Day 15 on the Passo Pordoi</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://danceswithangiosperms.blogspot.fi/2014/08/day-109-128.html">Days 109 - 128</a> on the PCT.</p>

<p><a href="http://biwak.blogspot.fi/2014/08/piz-surgonda-3196m.html">Piz Surgonda</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://chamconditions.blogspot.fi/2014/08/arete-du-doigt-pointe-percee.html">Arete du Doigt, Pointe Percee</a>.</p>

<p>Krister &amp; Anna climb the <a href="http://mountainpassion.blogspot.fi/2014/08/aiguille-moine-arete-sud-classique-3412m.html">Arete Sud Classique on the Aiguille Moine</a>. </p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/qd0tuOZPdzY?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://alanrayneroutdoors.blogspot.fi/2014/08/all-around-broom-and-heather.html">All around the Broom and Heather</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cumbriafellraven.blogspot.fi/2014/08/backpacking-in-and-out-of-aiguestortes.html">Backpacking in and out of the Aiguestortes</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seattlebackpackersmagazine.com/adventure-sciences-100-miles-of-wild-expedition-tsingy-de-bemaraha-madagascar-part-i/">100 Miles of Wild Expedition to the Tsingy de Bemaraha</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2014/08/24/the-underground-mountain-soundtrack/">The Underground Mountain Soundtrack</a>.</p>

<p>Nick shares some <a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/08/31/western-ukrainian-snapshots-august-2014/">Western Ukrainian snapshots</a>.</p>

<p>Leor’s <a href="http://www.irunfar.com/2014/08/leor-pantilats-supported-john-muir-trail-fkt-report.html">Supported John Muir Trail FKT Report</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://tv.thebmc.co.uk/video/arcteryx-lakeland-revival">Arc’teryx Lakeland Revival</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.barefootjake.com/2014/08/bailey-range-stephen-basin.html">Bailey Range: Stephen Basin</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2014/08/cross-mountain-gorge.html">Cross Mountain Gorge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi/2014/08/cycling-baltic-states-and-finland.html">Cycling Baltic States and Finland: Conclusion and lessons learned</a>.</p>

<p>Corinne turns around on the way up the <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2014/08/pic-d-estats-pyrenaeen.html">Pic d’Estats</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-482.html">立山縦走</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14915974590" title="Hands-free belaying. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5590/14915974590_f9987f00df_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hands-free belaying." /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.fi/2014/08/lightweight-gear-finds-from-outdoor-and.html">Lightweight Gear Finds from the OutDoor and Outdoor Retailer</a>.</p>

<p>Jörgen ponders in detail about the <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se/2014/08/brooks-range-vacation-gear-reflections.html">Big 3</a> and his <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se/2014/08/brooks-range-gear-reflections-on-stove.html">stove &amp; footwear</a> that he used in the Brooks Range.</p>

<p><a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/testbericht-roejk-tvister-helmet-hood/">Röjk Tvister Helmet Hood for Women</a> reviewed.</p>

<p>Bjarke’s <a href="http://www.gearcatalyst.com/one-great-little-piece-gear-fall/">favourite piece of autumn gear</a>. </p>

<p>Planeta Packraft shows you <a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2014/08/como-empaquetar-tu-packraft-folding.html">how to fold your packraft</a>.</p>

<p>Rogers eats <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/08/what-works-for-me-freeze-dried-meals.html">Freeze Dried Meals</a> and shares his experiences.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoors.org/publications/outdoors/2014/equipped/how-to-destroy-your-gear.cfm">How to Destroy Your Gear</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/narrative-clip/">Narrative Clip</a>, a small five megapixel camera you clip to somewhere on your body and record your hiking adventures.</p>

<p>Derek reviews the <a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2014/08/hummingbird-hammock-single-review/">Hummingbird Hammock Single</a>.</p>

<p>Stevie helps you <a href="http://steviehaston.blogspot.fi/2014/08/choosing-and-fitting-climbing-boots-by.html">choosing and fitting climbing boots</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://woodtrekker.blogspot.fi/2014/08/tenkara-vs-western-fly-fishing.html">Tenkara vs. Western Fly Fishing – A Beginner’s Perspective</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.com/2014/08/test-wanderhose-montura-kids-zip-off.html">Montura Kids Zip-off</a> reviewed.</p>

<p><strong>Want to stay up-to-date?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3409&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/3409/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review LXXXIII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/the-week-in-review-lxxxiii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-24T11:10:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/the-week-in-review-lxxxiii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Beauty is everywhere a welcome guest.</em> - Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14810925460" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5555/14810925460_9de39c2981_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://jensholsten.blogspot.fi/2014/08/chad-and-i.html">Chad and I</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ustream.tv/recorded/51592845">Alex Honnold: Relativity of Risk</a>.</p>

<p>Yosemite Valley, where <a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-adventure/media/film/Yosemites-History-of-Criminal-Fun.html">the outlaw spirit is alive and well</a>.</p>

<p>Pics.io, a browser-based Raw editor built on Google Drive, goes into <a href="http://pics.io/">Beta</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com/introducing-mr-fusion-2/">Mr. Fusion</a> is the new modular, user-friendly, and stupidly-stable seat system from Porcelain Rocket. Goes well with a <a href="http://velo-orange.blogspot.fi/2014/08/six-pack-rack-arrives.html">Six-Pack Rack</a>, too.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Zelte/Big-Sky-International-Wisp-Tent-1P::796.html?refID=hif">Big Sky International Wisp Tent 1P</a> is now available from the Trekking-Lite-Store.com - a 476 g enclosed shelter!</p>

<p>$50.000 are up for grabs via the <a href="http://expeditiongranted.nationalgeographic.com/">National Geographic Expedition Granted</a> competition.</p>

<p>LAUFBURSCHE-gear now sells <a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/toaks-titanium-pot-1000/">Toaks Titanium pots</a> and their sweet Esbit setup in his shop as Evernew has left the European market and will be increasingly difficult (and expensive!) to get in the future.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2014/08/op-ed-climbing-accidents-dealing-disaster/">Climbing Rescue and Dealing with disaster</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://yle.fi/uutiset/three_national_parks_lead_the_pack_in_finland/7428843">Three national parks lead the pack in Finland</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.fi/2014/08/lightweight-packing-for-lake-district.html">Lightweight packing for the Lake District</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://jwboutdoors.com/2014/08/enlightened-equipment-enigma/">Enlightened Equipment Enigma</a> review.</p>

<p>And I reviewed the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals OSO</a>, one of my favourite pieces of gear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14726775089" title="Nice views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/14726775089_9bbf1de51c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Nice views" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://davesearle.me/2014/08/22/rebuffat-gully-tour-ronde/">Rebuffat Gully, Tour Ronde</a>. Or a mighty fine day in the mountains.</p>

<p>Equally awesome is the Expedition Frumplestiltskin up the <a href="http://maxneale.blogspot.fi/2014/08/expedition-frumplestiltskin-cassin.html">Cassin Ridge of Denali</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://downthecolorado.org/">Down the Colorado</a>, a five Episodes series of paddling down the Colorado River system.</p>

<p>Paulina recaps her <a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/lassen-volcanic-national-park-trip-recap/">Lassen Volcanic National Park Trip</a>.</p>

<p>Linda heads up the <a href="http://photomomlinda.blogspot.fi/2014/08/cooper-spur.html">Cooper Spur</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://urskyburz.blogspot.fi/2014/08/klettern-gerstenegg.html">Climbing (almost) like in the past</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://dmmclimbing.com/knowledge/big-wall-dreaming/">Big Wall Dreaming</a>.</p>

<p>Ute and daughter enjoy a few hikes around the <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.com/2014/08/kindertaugliche-touren-freiburger-huette.html">Freiburger Hut</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Roger hikes <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/08/back-to-sweden-cuhnojaka-to-cuhcajavri.html">back to Sweden</a>.</p>

<p>Jotaro and Barefoot Jake were <a href="http://www.barefootjake.com/2014/08/backpack-japan-to-olympic-mountains.html">backpacking in the Olympic Mountains</a>.</p>

<p>And a <a href="http://maxneale.blogspot.fi/2014/08/olympic-peninsula-traverse-again.html">Olympic Peninsula Traverse</a> on foot and packraft is also a sweet way to explore that area.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/98904694?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A mountaineering life at the <a href="http://www.wusaonthemountain.at/2014/08/expedition-pik-lenin-7134m.html">Pik Lenin and Pik Razdelnaya</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://universalklister.blogspot.fi/2014/08/blood-sweat-and-fish-fries-in-bwca-with.html">Blood, sweat and fish fries in the BWCA</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://teleturn.blogspot.fi/2014/08/alaska-mountain-wilderness-classic-2014.html">Alaska Mountain Wilderness Classic 2014 Ice route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2014/08/19/seventeen-year-hiatus-on-the-grand-pilier-d-angle/">Seventeen Year Hiatus on The Grand Pilier d’ Angle</a>.</p>

<p>Marko was <a href="http://www.flickriver.com/photos/m3t/sets/72157646656117845/">Packsailing In Tammisaari Archipelago</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2014/08/tincan-and-kickstep-glaciers.html">Tincan and Kickstep Glaciers</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://chamconditions.blogspot.fi/2014/08/august-skiing-on-le-tour-glacier.html">August skiing on the Le Tour Glacier</a>.</p>

<p>Darren <a href="http://djm74.blogspot.fi/2014/08/kiandra-to-kosciuszko-splitboarding.html">splitboards from Kiandra to Kosciuszko</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cyclocaust.blogspot.fi/2014/08/road-touring-cambridge-leeds-geneva.html">Road Touring from Cambridge to Paris</a>.</p>

<p>A Women’s only <a href="http://kidproject.org/2014/08/19/lens-cirque-towers-girls-trip/">Cirque of the Tours Trip</a>.</p>

<p>And finally, Mark shares a view photos and words from <a href="http://www.backpackingnorth.com/blog/2014/8/18/views-from-sarek">Sarek</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want to stay up-to-date?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=365721&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/365721/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Karwendel by Heinz Zak]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/karwendel-by-heinz-zak.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-22T16:36:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/karwendel-by-heinz-zak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.tyrolia.at/list?back=de0e51d6a2668c2896f6ca67e63d39c1&amp;xid=3626313">Karwendel</a> is a beautiful mountain range in the Alps between Munich and Innsbruck. In his book Heinz Zak shows his home mountains and its inhabitants in all seasons, and gives tips on hiking, mountaineering, climbing, canyoning and paddling. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14975984496" title="Karwendel by Heinz Zak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3908/14975984496_0f5a1d1a39_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Karwendel by Heinz Zak" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>750 km² large is the Karwendel and with that the largest nature park in Austria. It’s home to Chamois, Ibex, Eagles, and more, and also you can find the pretty Edelweiss and Gentian growing on the alpine pastures of this beautiful region. But not only nature is highlightesd in this book, also the people of this unique area are portrayed and the mountains themselves.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14812270409" title="Karwendel by Heinz Zak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5557/14812270409_1d674db674_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Karwendel by Heinz Zak" /></a></p>

<p>The over 200 photos in this 284 page thick coffee-table book will make you fall in love with the region and will have you plan your next holiday to this part of the Alps. The photos from all seasons are accompanied by stories and anecdotes of the author, but he also gives tips for your own ski-touring trips and hikes. Small stories with local people, from Mountainbikers to Mountaineers, loosen up the book and give other viewpoints on this range. </p>

<p>At close to 2 kg it’s not really a book you want to carry into the Karwendel (unless you’re training) but it makes a fine coffee-table book to read while you’re stuck at home. It’s a gorgeous book and <em>the</em> photo book about the Karwendel. You can get your copy from your local bookstore, <a href="http://www.tyrolia.at/list?back=de0e51d6a2668c2896f6ca67e63d39c1&amp;xid=3626313">Tyrolia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1llioS9">Amazon.de</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1tsdWRy">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1llixFb">Amazon.com</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Luna Sandals OSO]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-19T15:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Do you have a favourite piece of gear?</em> Vincent asked me. I thought for a moment and then answered <em>“Yes, I really like my <a href="https://lunasandals.refersion.com/c/8168e">Luna Sandals</a>.”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14958208275" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5566/14958208275_cd4e868c0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I picked up my pair of <a href="https://lunasandals.refersion.com/c/8168e">OSO sandals</a> in Munich as I was visiting the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/ispo-news-2014.html">ISPO</a> and have worn them on the trail in Luxembourg and Poland, on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor 2014</a> and pretty much the last three months every day in Finland.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14957856322" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5565/14957856322_89afe61dd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>They’re sandals, so they’re, like, made for having cool feet. Minimal walking. Protecting your soft feet from sharp bits and stuff.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14771534800" title="Luna Sandals OSO in the Snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5566/14771534800_9f2c283d8e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Luna Sandals OSO in the Snow" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The OSO</p>

<ul>
  <li>Has a non-slip MGT (Monkey Grip Technology) footbed</li>
  <li>ATS (All Terrain Strapping) laces with a non-stretch, cushioned heel strap</li>
  <li>Optional Tech Straps</li>
  <li>A grippy Vibram® sole</li>
  <li>Is 11 mm thick</li>
  <li>The HEAVIEST Luna Sandal there is :D</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14847755314" title="Lunas&#x27;n&#x27;Hail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/14847755314_6f9381dc9d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lunas&#x27;n&#x27;Hail" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Sandals and innovations, right? Right. If you saw the features above you quickly will see some things which you likely haven’t read before. The MGT footbed, the ATS laces and the Tech Straps are all innovations when it comes to sandals, or then Barefoot Ted just paid close attention to how the Tarahumara indians made their sandals, and improved a bit on those with modern materials. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14780608779" title="Luna Sandals OSO Sole by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5561/14780608779_16cf7ceddd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Luna Sandals OSO Sole" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>These sandals are hand-made by monkeys in Seattle, USA. I couldn’t find any fault with them, and I looked close. And walked a lot in them. They’re high-quality sandals. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14944316186" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3870/14944316186_5c1816b038_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The OSO is the heaviest Luna Sandal available and my pair in Size 43,5 weighs 412 g or 206 g for one sandal. The Tech Straps (two) add 18 g to the pair.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14780605729" title="Luna Sandals OSO and Tech Strap by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/14780605729_6d146ba843_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Luna Sandals OSO and Tech Strap" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Ah well, sandals are shoes. Here in Finland they go into the rubbish bin nowadays and are burned for energy. If the sole is still good you could probably just try to order a new ATS system and rig it yourself, if that was what was broken. And if the sole is walked through, maybe get your shoe maker apply a new one? Or then you really could just put them in the trash and start to walk barefoot.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I settled on the OSO because both <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">Benjamin</a> and <a href="http://www.infiniteoutdoors.blogspot.de/">Marius</a> had them and liked them. And if those young men can walk in a pair of sandals in the mountains then the strapping young lad that is the author of this website most surely also could walk in them. Should. Would. And thus walking in the mountains with sandals he did.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14957855962" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5572/14957855962_5c0eb7db3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<p>In the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/lake-district/">Lake District</a> I wished I would have taken the OSOs along. On the Escapardenne Trail I did and hiked 85 km of it in them. And in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/back-from-the-polish-tatras.html">Poland</a> I hiked five out of seven days in them, much to the surprise of the Mountain Guide I was walking with. Minimal footwear is still an unusual view in the mountains and hills, and a pair of sandals at 2000+ m most certainly has people turn their heads. Which might be dangerous for them if they’re walking on a narrow ridge.</p>

<p>First you will need to learn to walk in them correctly. Walk wrong in these sandals - with your heel first as you might have learned by using high drop, thickly cushioned shoes - and you will get pain. Pain in the heel, knees and your back. The strap will pull uncomfortably into the front of your foot and hurt the top of it. After having used some cushioned shoes I switched into the OSO and walked wrong for a while and quickly experienced that pain. I realized that I walked wrong, and by walking as nature intended the human body to walk - the front first - the pain eased and walking became a pleasure. So much that I have barely used any other shoe in the past three months. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14550172205" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/14550172205_4436dd8d70_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<p>Lets talk a bit about the construction of the OSO. The toe webbing is soft and comfortable and will mould to the space between your toes after a few days of wearing them. At the beginning it was something to get used to, but nowadays I don’t even realize that I have the sandal on and that there’s some webbing between my toes. Much of that has to do with the ATS strap which really is what makes a Luna Sandal a Luna Sandal in my opinion. This is a super-smart system. When they’re new you once need to sit down, fiddle around with the buckle and strap to get it to fit your foot just right, and then that was that. Unlike other Luna Sandals the ATS in the OSO is not elastic so you need to pull it a bit to slip it over your heel, but then it sits there. There’s a MGT rubber lining on the inside of the heel part which helps to keep the strap in place. The same MGT material is on the top webbing before the buckle, with the same comfortable effect. By the way: The whole strap really is just one piece of webbing with a buckle &amp; the plug, which are threaded through the sole and buckle to keep it connected to your foot.</p>

<p>If you go running in the OSO, and it’s perfectly capable of that, then I found the Tech Strap a good Add-on. It is included with the OSO and really is just a Velcro strap that helps to keep your heel strap and ankle secure. While this might sound trivial, it makes the OSO a completely different sandal. With the Tech Strap on the sandal is glued to your foot, no slipping, nothing. It’s just as easy to put the sandal on - it’s still slip-on-and-off-able - as the Tech Strap is just a Velcro strap but makes a world of difference. If you run and like the sandal to be glued to your foot, then you’ll love the Tech Strap.</p>

<p>So running. Trailrunning, really, because running on asphalt still sucks in my opinion. During the winter I ran in a different pair of shoes each day, and I looked forward to the Luna Sandals days. Sure, running on snow at -5°C is a bit fresh, but with a pair of <a href="http://bit.ly/VBOBYP">Injinji Toesocks</a> it’s just fine. You generate a lot of heat when running, so the feet were never cold. The OSO had superb grip on the snow and ice, which surprised me. The OSO kept on surprising me as I was hiking in Luxembourg on the Escapardenne Eisleck Trail, where it rained every day and I was hiking up some slippery, muddy hills. But like a bear the OSO just had grip and didn’t slip. Neither did my foot, thanks to the really grippy MGT footbed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14955105781" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5572/14955105781_9bd2a982e0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<p>While my feet got wet and a bit dirty when it rained, they got a nice tan from the sunshine which we had in Finland the last months, including an ATS mark =) I already mentioned the Injinji Toesocks, which are nice on cool evenings or if it’s very windy &amp; rainy or you’re running on snow.</p>

<p>So yeah. The Luna Sandals are my de-facto everyday shoes since about May. Foodshopping. Going to the crag. Travelling. Visiting Fairs. Going to eat ice at the beach. Even now that it gets cooler I still slip into my OSOs when I go out, be it to pick up the Newspaper or going somewhere. Cycling. In the rain. Sunshine. On sand. Gravel. Asphalt. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14781579849" title="Cycling with Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3892/14781579849_7ecc2c6eef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cycling with Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>If we look at Minimalistic Sandals I’m only aware of <a href="http://bedrocksandals.com/">Bedrock Sandals</a> which have a slight variation on the toe webbing but otherwise are fairly similar to Luna Sandals. There’s a bunch of “traditional” <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-sandalen/fuer--maenner/">hiking sandals</a> but honestly, these can not compare with Luna Sandals and are pretty heavy.</p>

<h2 id="what-could-be-better">What Could Be Better</h2>

<p>As they’re hand-made there can be bits of yarn standing over where things were sewn together, and that was what I had with my sandals. I called to Luna Sandals and asked what to do, and the solution to this was to singe the yarns briefly with a lighter to burn off the over-standing yarn or fabric. Done and never had a problem again.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14957855372" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5564/14957855372_4e0b2a6310_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>To get back to the intro and elaborate a bit further, as I did to <a href="http://www.vincentkleine.com/">Vincent</a>: The Luna Sandals are one of my favourite bits of kit because they’re simple. They’re comfy. They’re light. They communicate to anyone who see me in them that I like it minimalistic. Going back to nature. Feeling the ground, the air, the mud &amp; rain on my feet. But also the sunshine. Cool breezes on hot summer days. </p>

<p>Sweaty feet are a thing of the past if you wear Luna Sandals. At the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy 2014</a> I was wearing another favourite pair of shoes which are awesome up high and when it’s cold (more on those soon), but down in the summery 35°C of Chamonix they were too hot. Way too hot. And I was happy indeed that I had my Luna Sandals along. Comfy, cool feet down in the valley.</p>

<p>To conclude this wee review: If you want to take the next step in terms of minimal footwear for hiking, backpacking, packrafting and everyday-life and you have a healthy, natural fore-foot stride, get a pair of Luna Sandals. The OSO, which by the way means bear in Español, is a superb, hand-crafted sandal that allows you to experience the nature much closer than in a closed trail running shoe, or God forbid, a boot. It’s a beautiful sandal that once you’ve put it on you will forget is there, and you can concentrate just on the trail ahead, and the hiking, wherever it may lead you.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-your-sandals">Where to buy your Sandals</h2>

<p>You can buy your Luna Sandals from <a href="http://luna-sandals.de/">Luna-Sandals.de</a> and <a href="http://www.racelite.de/luna-oso.html">Racelite</a> in Germany, <a href="http://www.fastway.fi/category/8/luna-sandals">Fastway</a> in Finland, <a href="http://moonlight-gear.com/?pid=44256135">Moonlight Gear</a> in Japan and of course at <a href="https://lunasandals.refersion.com/c/8168e">Luna Sandals</a> in the USA and else where on this globe. Be sure to read up on the sizing on their website and print out the template to find the right size!</p>

<p>The accompanying book is “<a href="http://amzn.to/1pEbB5d">Born to Run</a>” and you might want to order that at the same time to get into the mood &amp; mind-set. If you are unsure about hiking barefoot but want to give these sandals a try, order a pair of <a href="http://bit.ly/1thAkNq">Injinji</a> <a href="http://bit.ly/1BwIrKM">Toesocks</a> which help to protect your feet a bit more.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then gives us a thumbs up on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> or a + on <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. Heck, you even could follow along on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> if you’re so inclined =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14780635760" title="Luna Sandals OSO &amp; Born to Run by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3862/14780635760_b35fe4e01d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Luna Sandals OSO &amp; Born to Run" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review LXXXII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/the-week-in-review-lxxxii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-17T13:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/the-week-in-review-lxxxii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Clouds come floating into my life, no longer to carry rain or usher storm, but to add color to my sunset sky.</em>
- Rabindranath Tagore</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14923989211" title="Alpacka Yukon Yak Packraft by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3886/14923989211_d32cf62e71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alpacka Yukon Yak Packraft" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2014/08/before-it-gets-dark.html">Before it gets dark</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://lifeinthevertical.co.uk/blogs/blog/2014/08/its-official-snowdon-is-broken/">Snowdon is broken</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2014/08/planetapackraft-pone-rumbo-laponia.html">Planeta Packraft Team is on tour in Finnish Lapland</a> - Hyvää matka! [Spanish]</p>

<p>Anna &amp; Chris got <a href="http://wanderingthewild.com/2014/08/15/married-at-maroon-bells/">Married at Maroon Bells</a> - Congratulations!</p>

<p><a href="http://gearcommons.com/">GearCommons</a> is another website that lets you rent your gear that sits idle in your closet.</p>

<p><a href="http://freedirtmonger.blogspot.fi/2014/08/definitions.html">Definition(s)</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/3-latest-gear-trends-climbing/">3 Climbing Gear Trends Worth a Look</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://dedpxl.com/an-ambitious-lazy-procrastinator/">An ambitious, lazy Procrastinator</a>. </p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.eoft.eu/">E.O.F.T.</a> starts on the 11th of October, are you ready for it?</p>

<p>M$ launched a <a href="http://www.diyphotography.net/microsofts-hyperlapse-technology-will-make-all-your-gopro-footage-look-amazing/">Hyperlapse technology</a> which might make the average Joe’s POV videos worth viewing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.thebmc.co.uk/how-dangerous-are-climbing-and-hill-walking">How dangerous are climbing and hill walking</a>?</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/238053029/father-nature-outdoors-integrated-camping-blanket">Father Nature Outdoors Integrated Camping Blanket</a> is on Kickstarter.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/2014/08/untapped-sport-packaged-maple-syrup.html">UnTapped</a> is a Sport Packaged Maple Syrup. </p>

<p>Ross ponders about <a href="http://woodtrekker.blogspot.fi/2014/08/trapping-and-modern-woodsman.html">Trapping and The Modern Woodsman</a>.</p>

<p>The big <a href="http://tinyurl.com/mrtjewr">Cotswold Sale</a> has just kicked off and is full of gear for little prices from Rab, Haglöfs, Mountain Equipment and more. At Backcountry.com backpacks get the sale treatment and you can <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=364813&amp;pw=73183">save at least 30% on Packs from Osprey, The North Face &amp; others</a>. GearTrade.com lest you <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=328429&amp;pw=73183">save up to 64% on Marmot, Big Agnes, Black Diamond &amp; Co. tents</a>! The <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Sale:::35.html?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com Outlet</a> also just was filled up with sweet down sleeping bags from Montane, Terra Nova and Cumulus. If you still need a jacket, pants or shirt then the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/outdoor-bekleidung/">Bergfreunde Clothing Sale</a> might be worth checking out, whereas if you want the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx/?_artperpage=96&amp;sort=3">newest Arc’teryx gear for winter</a> see what Bergzeit has on offer.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.minimallyminimal.com/blog/leica-t">Leica T</a>.</p>

<p>Adrian’s Tour on the <a href="http://velo-orange.blogspot.fi/2014/08/adrians-tour-on-26-campeur.html">26” Campeur</a>.</p>

<p>I reviewed the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/klymit-x-pillow.html">Klymit Pillow X</a> and the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html">Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite</a> which are my essentials for good sleep on the trail.</p>

<p>John talks about the <a href="http://hikelighter.com/2014/08/11/six-moon-designs-flight-30/">Six Moon Designs Flight 30 Pack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14913070312" title="Along the Ourthe by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5581/14913070312_0004e63c75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Along the Ourthe" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://pinetflorence.blogspot.fi/2014/08/majorque.html">Majorque</a>. [French]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpinestyle.ca/2014/08/14/east_creek_0">East Creek</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-481.html">立山縦走</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jeepermtj.com/2014/08/mont-chaberton-3136m.html">Mont Chaberton, 3136 m</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://fuusora.blogspot.fi/2014/08/sawwer-jam-meets-rod.html">Sawwer Jam meets ROD</a>! [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.appalachiantrials.com/hikers-guide-bike-touring/">A Hiker’s Guide to Bike Touring</a>.</p>

<p>Dawn &amp; Jim have a couple of <a href="http://hikerdawn.blogspot.fi/2014/08/back-to-back-long-distance-flights-in.html">Back-To-Back Long-Distance Flights in Austria</a>.</p>

<p>Ryan spent he <a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2014/08/last-day-on-blackwater-way.html">last day on Blackwater Way</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.packgofind.com/iceland">Iceland by (Fat-) Bike</a>, a recommended read &amp; see.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/102759765?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2014/08/14/reigniting-memories-the-tournier-spur-north-face-of-the-midi/">The Tournier Spur, North Face of the Midi</a>.</p>

<p>Luc about the <a href="http://thingstolucat.com/2014-summer-classic/">2014 Alaska Mountain Wilderness Classic</a> &amp; Rob Kehrer.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2014/08/the-dream-path-munich-to-venice.html">‘The Dream Path’ - Munich to Venice</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2014/08/11/der-wilde-kaiser-und-die-drei-hexen/">Der Wilde Kaiser &amp; die drei Hexen</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Roger hiked from <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/08/katterjakk-sweden-to-cuhnojaka-norway.html">Katterjåkk to Čuhnojåka</a>.</p>

<p>Don &amp; Karen go on thin ice up to <a href="http://talusfield.net/blog/2014/8/3/mount-lyell-yosemite-national-park">Mount Lyell</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://biwak.blogspot.co.at/2014/07/rosengarten-normalweg-2999m.html">Rosengarten</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/hiking/nishizawa-gorge/">Nishizawa Gorge</a>.</p>

<p>Cass rides <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/bolivia/madmax">to Ayuni</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2014/08/bugaboo-essentials/">Bugaboos Essentials</a>.</p>

<p>Pik Lenin (7134 m) - <a href="http://www.wusaonthemountain.at/2014/08/expedition-pik-lenin-7134m-anreise-bis.html">Travel to Base Camp Achik Tash</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Want to stay up-to-date? Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a> or subscribe to our <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3409&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/3409/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Klymit Pillow X]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/klymit-x-pillow.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-15T23:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/klymit-x-pillow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not only a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/sleeping-pads/">sleeping pad</a> is needed for a good night’s sleep on the trail, also a pillow is what many of us want for sweet dreams under the stars. After trying several pillows and fussing around with spare clothes I found the Klymit Pillow X and don’t go backpacking without it anymore.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732148989" title="75% of the sleep system deployed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5554/14732148989_77b4b1a3af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="75% of the sleep system deployed" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Another 56 g that’s added to the sleep system. If it looks like there’s a gear-increase, that well may be possible. But after years of fussing around with rolled-up clothing or stuff sacks to act as a pillow, trying some other <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kissen/">backpacking pillows</a> and trying to learn to sleep without one I pulled the trigger on the <a href="http://bit.ly/1BiBQ6m">Klymit Pillow X</a> as I saw it over at <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=42&amp;products_id=207">Mountain Laurel Designs</a>. I didn’t bother reading reviews (there were none) but felt this would be a winning purchase just by a look at the design.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14923923062" title="Klymit Pillow X Packed Size by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3854/14923923062_c4b0718a72_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klymit Pillow X Packed Size" /></a></p>

<p>That X is where the magic happens, design-wise. It centres your head in the middle, cradles it a bit, and works great for side and back sleepers. I turn a lot in my sleep, from side to belly to side to back and onwards, and the Pillow X is comfortable in any of these positions. I even can prop my arm up underneath it, almost as home. I have used it on all long hikes this year, from winter camping in the north to hillwalking in the Lake District and backpacking on the Eisleck Trail and the result is: It’s a winner. It gets packed always, because I value good sleep on the trail. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918461392" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5579/14918461392_fca784d892_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow" /></a></p>

<p>Two puffs to inflate. It takes longer to deflate and roll up the Pillow X, around a minute or two, as the X construction likes to trap air here and there. But hey, that’s OK, there’s usually no hurry in the mornings. When the vlave looks big: It is. But it ain’t in the way for me, in a pinch you can even turn the pillow around and don’t have the valve on top. Maybe Klymit will at some point use a smaller vlave which would save some weight and not stand out that much, but even like this it works well.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918807565" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5574/14918807565_ee3f52704a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow" /></a></p>

<p>The bottomline is pretty straight forward: When I pack along with the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html">XLite</a> or <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">Xtherm</a> the Pillow X always comes along. It are 56 g that I’m happy to carry for a comfy pillow that works. If you feel the same and want to get a good night’s sleep order your Pillow X from <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=42&amp;products_id=207">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> or directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1BiBQ6m">Klymit</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732204528" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5564/14732204528_9318db644b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-14T12:37:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/ie/therm-a-rest/mattresses/fast-and-light/neoair-xlite/product">Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite</a> lets you sleep comfortable &amp; warm all night long and won’t slow you down or take up a lot of space in your pack while you’re hiking. After over a year of use on different trails the verdict is out: This is one of the best 3-Season sleeping pads on the market. <em>Read all about it in my in-depth review.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376802441" title="Bed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5515/14376802441_7b2115dea3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bed" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I’m sleeping on the NeoAir XLite Regular since August 2013 when it’s the season. It was along in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho-Kekkonen National Park</a>, on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/koli-national-park.html">2013 UL Summit</a> and every hike of 2014. I slept over 50 nights on this mat and it still works superb.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14915727601" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3883/14915727601_8491b07928_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>Like the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">NeoAir XTherm</a> the XLite’s function is to provide you with a warm and comfortable bed at camp while being small &amp; light when being carried in your pack. The mattress is insulating you towards the ground so you can sleep warm.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732150280" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, inflated by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5552/14732150280_caed27a91e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, inflated" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>My Regular length XLite has the following specs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>R-Value 3,2</li>
  <li>183 cm long, 6 cm thick, tapers from 49 cm to 38 cm (that’s the real inflated width)</li>
  <li>Reflective ThermaCapture™ technology traps radiant heat </li>
  <li>Triangular Core Matrix™ construction minimizes convective heat loss</li>
  <li>Made in Ireland</li>
</ul>

<p>The XLite is available in three sizes (S = 119 cm long, 230 g/ Regular = 183 cm long, 353 g/ L = 196 cm, 460 g) and a Women’s Version (168 cm, 340 g) which has a higher R-Value.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732146959" title="Sleep &amp; shelter system by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/14732146959_1ed65c71de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sleep &amp; shelter system" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The Reflective ThermaCapture™ technology is an innovation. It are reflective layers inside the NeoAir mattress that reflect radiant heat back to your body, and so amplifys the warmth without the bulk, weight or durability issues of down and synthetic fills. Also the Triangular Core Matrix™ construction is an innovation, this construction combines two layers of triangular baffles to create over a hundred insulating cells in the mattress and so slowing down convective heat loss as well as delivering very good stability for maximum comfort.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918803885" title="75% of the sleep system deployed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5563/14918803885_16ef248408_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="75% of the sleep system deployed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After over 50 nights on thee mattress it still works and looks great and shows no signs of weaknesses. It’s a durable mat and can take the abuse of what you encounter when you’re backpacking.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Regular length XLite is 353 g.</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>The XLite is made in Ireland of oil based materials and has a coating on the inside, so shouldn’t be thrown in the garbage like ordinary rubbish. You could try to either recycle it via your local outdoor shop or inquire from Therm-A-Rest how to recycle the mat at the end of its life cycle.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918814195" title="Valve by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3906/14918814195_4dd814de57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Valve" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>15 large breaths, that’s how often a non-smoker will need to inhale and exhale to make out of the small, rolled up package a fully inflated, comfy mat. If you like it softer, maybe 13 or 14 are enough, and if you have a small lunge volume it might be more, but 15 breaths is what it takes me to inflate this mat. If that seems too much for you then Therm-A-Rest has a a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-neoair-mini-pump/">Mini Pump</a> for you which will add 65 g to your pack or an <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-neo-air-pumpsack/">Pump Sack</a> that adds 77 g to your packed weight and make life on the trail slightly easier. Of course then you just also could take a self-inflating mat or a closed cell foam mat and be done and never inflate a mattress again. </p>

<p>But those mats are quite a bit larger in packed size and often also quite a bit more heavy. So with a mat like the XLite you get a light mat that packs up small - about 1 l rolled up is what it will take of the space in you pack. Speaking of the rolled up mat, deflating is just as easy as inflating. Open the valve and it will largely empty itself, but to speed things up you can kneel on it. When it’s fully deflated I lay it out flat, fold it twice into the middle and then roll it up, that way I get an approximately 23 cm long package that’s about 9 cm in diameter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732244997" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, folded by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3904/14732244997_e1fbff813e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, folded" /></a></p>

<p>One of the reasons you will consider the XLite is Comfort. At six cm thick the XLite is fully inflated a very comfy mattress, and if you like more cushy/ soft mattresses just open the valve to adjust it to your liking. It also makes camping fairly flexible as you’re less dependent on 100% even surfaces - if theres a root protruding from the spot you want to camp the XLite is able to comfortably lay on top of it and you’d have never known. Similarly it’s great for camping on the rocks, for example if you want to bivy on a summit. While it’s a durable mat I do carry a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/exped-doublemat-evazote-sleeping-mat.html">very thin Exped CCF pad</a> along which I lay underneath the XLite to protect it a bit from sharp, small rocks or stuff I might have not seen. It’s also a good back-up and adds a bit of extra warmth.</p>

<p>Warmth is one of the other things where the XLite shines. It’s a warm mattress - I had it down to around -5°C and was toasty on it and never knew I’m on a 3-Season pad. Which means you’re good to go till late autumn with this mattress, and if you like to use a CCF pad in winter as a back-up either way you even might be able to use the XLite in mild winters. For serious cold winters I’d still use the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">XTherm</a>, though.</p>

<p>Finally, the XLite fits well into my different bivys. While in SUL bivys which are not very high you might run into trouble, my tyvek, Pertx and Cuben bivys are all wide and spacious enough to accommodate this inflated mattress. If you use a thin mattress right now and your bivy is a bit tight already it might be useful to get a more spacious bivy at the same time that you’re getting the XLite. If you don’t use a bivy this obviously will be of no concern =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13982574636" title="Good night! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7203/13982574636_c7f96370bb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Good night!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a few mattresses that fill the same niche as the XLite: There’s the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/exped-synmat-7-isolierte-isomatte-kunstfaserfuellung/">Exped SynMat 7</a>, the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-light-pump-mat-ul-isomatte/">Mammut Light Pump Mat UL</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/vaude-norrsken-primaloft-isomatte/">Vaude Norrsken</a> and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/trangoworld-micro-air-isomatte/">Trangoworld Micro Air</a> which all have a similar pack size and warmth rating but most of these are heavier. </p>

<h2 id="what-could-be-better">What Could Be Better</h2>

<p>I have no complains about the XLite. Sure, at some point in time it’d be nice to get the same warmth &amp; comfort for less weight, but for now I’m happy. Those that always thought the XLite and XTherm were to loud, Therm-A-Rest has heard you and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html">from 2015 on the mats will be more silent</a>. And those that would like to not have to inflate their XLite but still want a 5 cm thick pad should get the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html">EvoLite</a> in 2015.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>After many years of backpacking and sleeping outside it’s pretty straight forward for me when I pack the sleep system: Spring till autumn it’s the XLite, winter and high-altitude it’s the XTherm. The XLite packs small in my pack when on the trail and is lightweight with just 353 g for the 183 cm long mattress. After 15 puffs of air at camp I have a comfy mat to chill and sleep on that keeps me well insulated against the ground. It makes finding a 100% perfect camp spots less of a hassle as I can lay comfortable above roots and round rocks on this 6 cm thick pad. Most important, I get a great nights sleep on it every time and am ready for another good day on the trail, where the small packed mattress again disappears in my pack. If you want comfort &amp; warmth paired with a light weight and small pack size, look no further than the Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Buy your XLite at <a href="http://bit.ly/Vpj8J3">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-neo-air-xlite-small-isomatte/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite-isomatte/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1bcnz0i">Campsaver</a>, <a href="http://tinyurl.com/pacvgwc">Cotswold</a>, <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite-200118/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Globetrotter</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/VmUMQt">REI</a> or the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Isomatten/Therm-A-Rest-NeoAir-XLite::458.html?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732238277" title="Day-Dreaming by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3867/14732238277_8e75eeaf30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Day-Dreaming" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review LXXXI]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/the-week-in-review-lxxxi.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-10T13:08:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/the-week-in-review-lxxxi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“An early morning walk is a blessing for the whole day.”</em> -Henry David Thoreau</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14847137861" title="Locus Gear Khufu eVent II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3892/14847137861_5a372ef639_b.jpg" width="1024" height="544" alt="Locus Gear Khufu eVent II" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Have you heard of the <a href="http://www.hcn.org/issues/46.12/the-death-of-backpacking">death of backpacking</a>? It has splashed some waves in the blogsphere. A <a href="http://popupbackpacker.com/is-backpacking-dying/">good reply came from Nick</a> and <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/07/18/how-taking-a-hike-can-mak_n_5584809.html?ncid=fcbklnkushpmg00000044&amp;ir=Green">proof that hiking makes you happier and healthier</a> maybe will motivate some people (me, at least) to go outdoors &amp; sleep under the stars. Also Roger reflects on his <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/08/reflecting-on-my-walk-from-kebnekaise.html">walk from Kebnekaise Fjällstation to Nikkaluokta</a> and ponders if the dying of backpacking is a culturally dependent phenomenon.</p>

<p>Starbuck VIA Addicts: Get your fix at the <a href="http://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/marken/weitere-produkte-food/starbucks-via-ready-brew-veranda-blend-12x23g.php#.U-djOdOSwtx">Outdoor Food Shop</a> and choose from three different tastes in 12 Sachet packs!</p>

<p>An <a href="http://theusualmontauk.com/don-of-the-dirtbags-an-interview-with-yvon-chouinard/">interview with Yvon Chouinard</a>.</p>

<p>My <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/outdoor-2014-wrap-up-and-conclusions.html">OutDoor 2014 conclusions</a> look into the future.</p>

<p>David shares a list of his favourite <a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/musings/10-best-outdoor-and-adventure-blogs/">Outdoor and Adventure Blogs</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2014/08/08/3-jahre-wandernbonn-bloggeburtstag-verlosung/">WandernBonn celebrates its 3rd birthday</a> and raffles some nice kit off.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody.html">Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody</a> is on <a href="http://bit.ly/OcTdRJ">sale at CampSaver.com</a>, as is the <a href="http://bit.ly/1kTfnIn">Integral Designs Chock 2 Mountain Tent</a>, while at the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1328&amp;pw=73183">Backcountry Men’s Clothing Outlet</a> you can save up to 70%. In the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-outdoor-outlet/?pid=81">Bergzeit Arc’teryx Outlet</a> you can save up to 50% on the great Canadian gear and at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/p/top-gear-im-angebot/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc&amp;&amp;">Bergfreunde</a> you can save 40% on selected climbing gear. Also the big <a href="http://tinyurl.com/mrtjewr">Cotswold Sale</a> has just kicked off and is full of great gear for little prices.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=216231&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/12135/216231/55699/73183/image.gif" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Geoff thinks that <a href="http://geoffmallinson.com/2014/08/05/trail-runners-will-revolutionise-your-hiking/">trail runners will revolutionise your hiking</a>. Right on!</p>

<p>Jacob likes the <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/borah-gear-cuben-bivy/">Borah Gear Cuben Bivy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/climbing-gear-for-kids.html">Climbing gear for kids</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14663572079" title="Wald by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/14663572079_7041623386_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wald" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Hana retires: <a href="http://hana2009.wordpress.com/2014/08/10/the-end-of-an-era/">The end of an era</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://offroute.ca/2014/08/05/shaqsha/">Nevado Shaqsha and other escapades in the Cordillera Blanca</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seatosummitultralight.blogspot.fi/2014/08/thru-hiking-trans-catalina-trail.html">Thru-Hiking the Trans Catalina Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Nick and Lael check in from <a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/08/08/ukraine-so-far/">Ukraine</a> and <a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/08/04/across-slovakia-up-high/">Slovakia</a>, both recommended reads.</p>

<p>A re-acquaintance with <a href="http://northernwalker.wordpress.com/2014/08/08/glenfinnan-to-inverie-a-re-acquaintance/">Glenfinnan to Inverie</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://imaginegnat.com/2014/08/03/friday-morning-river-ramble/">Friday Morning River Ramble</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://yukonfrolics.blogspot.fi/2014/08/continental-divide-to-morley-river.html">Continental Divide to Morley River</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://ajliikala.blogspot.fi/2014/08/via-ferrata-loen-norway.html">Via Ferrata in Norway</a>.</p>

<p>Rob entered the <a href="http://robgreenwoodclimbing.com/2014/08/09/welcome-to-the-8th-grade/">8th Grade</a> - congratulations!</p>

<p><a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/wandern-fuer-anfaenger-riessersee-kochelbergalm-partnachklamm/">Hiking for beginners to the Partnachklamm</a>, an amusing trip report. [German]</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/101096882?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://dailey7779.blogspot.fi/2014/08/sphinx-trail-work.html">Sphinx Trail Work</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://alicehikes.com/2014/08/holy-shit-i-walked-to-oregon/">Alice walked to Oregon</a>.</p>

<p>Leor visits the <a href="http://pantilat.wordpress.com/2014/08/05/arrow-peak-bench-lake/">northeast Ridge of Arrow Peak &amp; Bench Lake</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2014/08/trailrunning-auf-der-extra-tour-b-des-mullerthal-trails/">Trailrunning on the Extra Tour B of the Mullerthal Trail</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://bencollinsoutdoors.com/2014/08/06/industrial-landscapes-back-to-the-country-brake-troubles-thunderstorms-and-a-great-lake/">Industrial landscapes, back to the country, brake troubles, thunderstorms, and a Great Lake</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://alptraeume-suedtirol.blogspot.fi/2014/08/hintergrat-ortler-normalweg.html">Ortler Summit</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Dave heads out on <a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2014/08/07/the-farewell-tour/">The farewell Tour</a>. </p>

<p>Andy is <a href="http://andyhouseman.blogspot.fi/2014/08/getting-miles-in.html">getting the miles in</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://besthike.com/2014/08/06/inca-trail-to-machu-picchu/">Inca Trail to Machu Picchu</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2014/08/bellingham-to-baker-and-back.html">Bellingham to Baker and back</a>.</p>

<p>Jamie hikes the <a href="http://www.downthetrail.com/hiking-backpacking-denali-national-park/the-savage-river-loop-trail/">Savage River Loop Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2014/08/trip-report-shivering-cold-dark-mt-louis/">Shivering in the cold &amp; dark on Mt. Louis</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=310481&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/12313/310481/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Climbing Gear for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/climbing-gear-for-kids.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-09T13:39:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/climbing-gear-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Climbing is fun, and it’s even more fun to have your children along. In this article I share some thoughts on climbing with litte kids &amp; highlight some kids climbing gear that has worked well for us.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14863252951" title="Kids Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3865/14863252951_76a691f99f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kids Climbing" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Our son always has climbed: First on chairs and the sofa, up stairs and even on top of the table when no-one was looking. Taking him along to the climbing gym and outside bouldering and rock climbing, he quickly also wanted to climb like dad. As normal shoes are fairly inadequate for climbing and I want to encourage him to climb &amp; have fun, I did quite a bit on research on kids climbing gear: Interviewing friends who go climbing with their little ones, comparing at online shops and reading the handful of reviews on blogs. So that you have an easier time picking good gear for your little one to come along and climb safely &amp; have fun, here’s our gear recommendations.</p>

<h2 id="shoes">Shoes</h2>

<p>As children grow fast almost all <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kletterschuhe/fuer--kinder/">kids climbing shoes</a> are available in adjustable sizes. It hurts in the wallet if you need to buy a new pair each four to six months and at a regular price of around 50€ <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/kletterschuhe-kinder/">climbing shoes for kids</a> ain’t cheap. We bought the <a href="http://bit.ly/1A2essj">Climb X Monkey</a> in EU Size 29 (16 cm inside length). The Monkey print on them is a nice touch for kids, and parents will appreciate the large Velcro closure which makes it super easy to put on. In the heel there is a 2nd Velcro strap which lets you adjust the size. It has a flat, grippy rubber sole, a rubber toe bumper and the rubber goes up in the heel, too - ideal for heel hooks. The toe box is wide if I compare them to my shoes so you won’t damage your kids feet. The rubber sole is thick but still lets the little ones climb very precise - I’m often surprised by how well he can stand on narrow ledges with the shoes. </p>

<p>I usually buy his shoes a number larger and adjust the size then via the Velcro strap, that way we get more usage out of them. As it’s now summer sale in most shops it’s a good decision to check out what they have on offer - at least at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kletterschuhe/fuer--kinder/">Bergfreunde</a> all kids climbing shoes are almost 15 or more % reduced in price right now, so a good opportunity to pick up a pair. If you only go bouldering then a pair of shoes is pretty much all you’ll need for the start, but if you also do a lot of rock climbing you also might want to pick up a kids harness.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14864052894" title="Climb X Monkey Kids climbing shoe by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5568/14864052894_5cfb04c66a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Climb X Monkey Kids climbing shoe" /></a></p>

<h2 id="harness">Harness</h2>

<p>Our son started climbing before he was two years old and since then has been climbing indoors &amp; outdoors and often comes along bouldering with me. As I really like rock climbing I decided to buy him a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/klettergurte/fuer--kinder/">Kids harness</a> so he can come along to the gym and crag once and a while. After some research I quickly settled on the <a href="http://bit.ly/1h4WCge">Edelrid Fraggle</a> - it’s a full-body harness, affordable and easy to use. We use the XXS Size since January 2014 and I expect we’ll get another year or one and half out of this harness. The XXS size goes from a Torso length of 50 to 70 cm and the leg loops go till 37 cm in diameter and can carry a child up to 40 kg. </p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/1olaR65">Edelrid Fraggle</a> is easy to put on: Two leg loops and two arm loops with two buckles to adjust the size - one in the front, one on the backside. A Buckle closes the harness below the tie-in loop. It’s padded &amp; comfy and my son wears it often the whole time we’re at the crag until we go home. What’s special about it is that in the back it has a 2nd loop, which is ideal for kids that already can climb on their own but are too light and tend to get stuck when you lower them. In this back loop you can tie in a 2nd rope, wicht which you can gently pull the child down when it is stuck again. If your child is already a bit older and can already sit upright in a harness by itself then a normal harness like the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/edelrid-finn-kinderklettergurt/">Edelrid Finn</a> would be a good solution. For more safety you can add the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/edelrid-kermit-brustgurt/">Edelrid Kermit Chest Harness</a> which is compatible with any (normal) harness. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14679865078" title="Edelrid Fraggle - Back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5571/14679865078_e58cf79c49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Edelrid Fraggle - Back" /></a></p>

<h2 id="helmet">Helmet</h2>

<p>There are dedicated kids climbing helmets, like the <a href="http://bit.ly/1A2eFM4">Petzl Picchu</a>. While safety is of the utmost importance for us if we go climbing with our son we thus far have used my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Petzl Sirocco</a> for my son as with a thin beanie underneath it can be cinched down to a good fit for him. When he will be older &amp; we’ll be more regularly rock climbing he will get his own helmet (maybe the new <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-1.html">Edelrid Kids helmet</a>) but for now we use the Sirocco. If you’re child already has a bicycle helmet, that’d be an option that could work in a pinch, too.</p>

<h2 id="clothes">Clothes</h2>

<p>Clothes for climbing should be durable and give freedom of movement. It’s astounding how fast kids learn just by seeing what mom and dad do: We once were bouldering and I heel hooked, and the next time it was my sons turn to climb he started to also heel hook - without me having told him so! It’s a case of monkey see, monkey do =) So pants and shirts should not inhibite movement and should be robust: The little ones will often lean against the rock to take a break or slide down on it, so unless you want to buy new clothes after each climbing trip it’s well worth it to buy durable garments that have reinforcements in the seat and knees.</p>

<p>We like <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/">Isbjörn of Sweden</a> and so does our son, too. The <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.13.841/trapper-pant-cordura">Trapper Pant Cordura</a> has the afore-mentined reinfocements in the knee and seat area, made of Cordura these pants take any abuse my son throws at them. To keep mosquitos and UV rays at bay he wears the very cool <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.13.1339/mountain-longsleeve">MOUNTAIN Longsleeve</a> which has a topographic print of the Kebnekaise on it. Made from Tencel it’s soft on the skin and his favourite piece to wear when we go outdoors. If there’s a chance of rain then the <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.16.776/light-weight-jacket">Light Weight Jacket</a> comes into the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/fjaellraeven-kanken-mini-daypack/">backpack</a>. Made from a wind- and waterproof fabric with a high collar and removable hood, it’s a nice jacket that keeps him dry &amp; warm in bad weather. Finally, to keep the ears warm and make the helmet fit better we have the soft merino wool <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.18.878/beanie-extended">Isbjörn Beanie</a> along. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14680213960" title="Isbjörn of Sweden Kids clothing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5562/14680213960_fab69a0d94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="760" alt="Isbjörn of Sweden Kids clothing" /></a></p>

<h2 id="good-mood-snacks-and-toys">Good mood, snacks and toys</h2>

<p>Probably most important when we go to the crag is that there’s a good atmosphere and setting no objectives &amp; high expectations. When my son doesn’t want to climb but rather play with his toys or eat some fruit - that’s a decision I happily accept. Forcing kids likely will result in the opposite so he only climbs when he likes to do it. So one, two toys and snacks (We carry apples, water melon, sandwiches and nuts along &amp; go pick raspberries &amp; blueberries where available) are important to have along so he can be entertained. Often he likes to sit and watch what mom &amp; dad are doing and cheers us on. A couple more things are important to have along:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A full <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/klean-kanteen/">water bottle</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/mawaii/">Sunscreen</a></li>
  <li>A sun hat</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/julbo-looping-ii-spectron-4-baby-sonnenbrille/">Sunglasses</a></li>
  <li>The rain jacket in case the weather turns</li>
  <li>Something comfy to sit on (I use some segments of a <a href="http://bit.ly/1yguVGx">ZLite</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p>The last time we were at the crag I walked up to the top of the cliff with my son and we wanted to try to rappel down, so he can see how to “<em>walk down</em>”. We were almost over the lip as I realized that he didn’t seem to like it, so we made the two steps back up to the cliff and saved the rappel experience for another time. I think as a parent it is important in these situations to be <strong>a)</strong> Aware if the little one is doing fine and <strong>b)</strong> If one’s owns plans are feasible &amp; safe. If either of these questions is answered with “No” it’s a smart solution to just walk back down.</p>

<p><strong>That’s it. A pair of shoes, a harness and helmet along with comfy clothes, snacks and some toys and you’re ready to take you daughter or son along for a safe, fun climbing trip =)</strong></p>

<p><em>Here’s the small print: Climbing is dangerous and as a responsible adult you should know what you’re doing. Don’t do dangerous stuff when the health of your child is at risk, don’t force them to do things, and most of all, have fun. You’re a hero for them already, no matter if you manage to top out or not. Be wise &amp; be a good example.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14121989044" title="Kids Bouldering &amp; Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5221/14121989044_4ed8072ff0_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Kids Bouldering &amp; Climbing" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review LXXX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/the-week-in-review-lxxx.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-03T19:12:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/the-week-in-review-lxxx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Happiness is neither virtue nor pleasure nor this thing nor that but simply growth, we are happy when we are growing.</em>
- William Butler Yeats</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14632821859" title="Finnish countryside. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3911/14632821859_06350d86df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Finnish countryside." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3032980/work-smart/why-the-last-five-years-of-your-life-have-disappeared">Why the last five years of your life have disappeared</a>. Or why it’s smart to go outdoors.</p>

<p>Jacob reflects <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/footprints-in-the-paella/">on Backpacking, Trail Running, and Stereotypes</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://dedpxl.com/crop-or-crap-math-or-moment/">CROP OR CRAP : MATH OR MOMENT</a>.</p>

<p>Corinna ponders if it always needs to be <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2014/07/der-reiz-der-superlative-warum-muss-es.html">the furthest, fastest or highest</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Neil helps you to win stuff with his <a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/competitions-for-hikers-august-2014/">Online Competitions for Hikers</a> overview.</p>

<p><a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2014/07/29/the-democratic-wild/">The democratic wild</a>.</p>

<p>I’m <a href="https://m.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=827776367252697&amp;id=499777346719269">selling a bunch of gear</a>. PM or EMail me if you need something. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=358361&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/358361/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://ajliikala.blogspot.fi/2014/07/vuorilla-vihdoin.html">Vuorilla, vihdoin!</a> [Finnish]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/bolivia/lagunas-route">Fat Bike Heaven; the Lagunas Route, Bolivia</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.walkingwithwired.com/2014/08/day-107-unexpected-long-day.html">Day 107: The Unexpected Long Day</a>.</p>

<p>Chad was out on a AT Section Hike from <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2014/08/01/july-2014-at-section-hike-winding-stair-gap-to-the-noc/">Winding Stair Gap to the NOC</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.hikingfiasco.com/2014/08/five-mile-beach-to-tin-mine-cove.html">Five Mile Beach to Tin Mine Cove</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikelighter.blogspot.fi/2014/07/an-overnighter-on-eisleck-trail.html">An overnighter on the Eisleck Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/07/29/to-slovakia-nothing-not-to-like/">To Slovakia!</a>.</p>

<p>Peter and friends are <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2014/07/kayaking-in-archipelago-sea.html">kayaking in the Archipelago Sea</a>.</p>

<p>Do yourself a favour: <a href="http://universalklister.blogspot.fi/2014/07/do-yourself-favor-take-your-kid-into.html">Take your kid into the Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://steviehaston.blogspot.fi/2014/07/kids-in-mountains-by-stevie-big-kid.html">Kids in the mountains</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2014/07/first-day-on-kerry-way-trail.html">First Day on the Kerry Way Trail</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/100694882?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://geoffmallinson.com/2014/07/28/a2k-hiking-all-australian-peaks-over-2000m-in-one-go/">A2K – Hiking All Australian Peaks over 2000m in one go</a>.</p>

<p>Paul spends a <a href="http://www.sharkeysdream.walkingplaces.co.uk/?p=22549">late afternoon on Dow Crag via the South Rake</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pantilat.wordpress.com/2014/07/29/the-roof-of-yosemite-loop/">The Roof of Yosemite Loop</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://photomomlinda.blogspot.fi/2014/07/silver-star-mountain.html">Silver Star Mountain</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://outlivingblog.wordpress.com/2014/07/28/the-first-of-many/">The first of many</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://glencoemountaineer.blogspot.fi/2014/07/a-solo-round-trip-of-giants-hole.html">A solo Round Trip of Giant’s Hole</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi/2014/07/cycling-in-finland-conclusion-and-tips.html">Cycling in Finland: Conclusion and tips</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14623999908" title="Luna Sandals OSO at the Beach. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5586/14623999908_29ba87c0b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Luna Sandals OSO at the Beach." /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://fuusora.blogspot.fi/2014/07/omm.html">OMM race packing account</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/7/30/5949913/lytro-illum-review">Lytro Illum review</a>: This is the camera of the future.</p>

<p><a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-478.html">Sanpo’s Alumisheet Cozy</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.minimallyminimal.com/blog/coteciel-nile-rucksack">Côte&amp;Ciel Nile Rucksack</a> review.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/your-labor-day-escape/">Your Labor Day Escape?</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/the-north-face-cinder-pack-40l-review/">The North Face Cinder Pack 40l review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2014/07/goal-zero-lighthouse-250-led-laterne-im-test/">GOAL ZERO Lighthouse 250</a> review.</p>

<p><a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2014/08/first-look-two-person-clark-vertex-hammock/">First Look: The Two-Person Clark Vertex Hammock</a>.</p>

<p>Where Roger goes and <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/07/heading-up-north-what-am-i-doing-where.html">what he takes</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://yeahyeahyeahyeah-yeah.blogspot.fi/2014/08/stooge-cycles-progressive-29er.html">Stooge Cycles - Progressive 29er</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://jwboutdoors.com/comfortable-xul-backpacking-gear-list/">“Comfortable” XUL Backpacking Gear List</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://woodtrekker.blogspot.fi/2014/07/diy-ultralight-white-gas-stove.html">DIY Ultralight White Gas Stove</a>.</p>

<p>And yes, Summer Sale time is still on here and there: <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/laufschuhe/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a> has over 50% off on trailrunning shoes, the Bergfreunde have up to 60% off on <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/rucksaecke/">backpacks</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/zelte/">shelters</a>, at Klymit you can get 20% off on the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=212735&amp;pw=73183">Static V, X Frame, and XL Sleeping Pads</a> and <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=355989&amp;pw=73183">Sierra Designs</a> has all their backpacks on sale.</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2014 - 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-4.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-29T19:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good beats and good moods on the final day of the 2014 OutDoor fair. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14484700469" title="Impressions by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5567/14484700469_019ddec51c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Impressions" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="supernatural">super.natural</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.supern8ural.com/en/about.htm">super.natural</a> hails from München and they like to combine Merino wool with durable polyamide fibres. The result are yarns that offer the best of both materials and these are then sewn into some very nice garments. They have a Women’s Yoga range which looked super comfy while being very stylish - garments that could be used for climbing &amp; hiking in the blink of an eye. But really any of their garments from the Base, Training and Superfly ranges could do well outdoors while still looking good when returning to the city. I tried some garments on and really liked them - good fit, freedom of movement, soft on the skin and they let light.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476789409" title="super.natural by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3915/14476789409_0af1b06133_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="super.natural" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476971517" title="super.natural by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3873/14476971517_abf8babd9f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="super.natural" /></a></p>

<h2 id="true-mountain">True Mountain</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.true-mountain.com/">True Mountain</a> makes gear in the UK from European and British materials. It’s a good effort, helping to re-establish the skills needed to sew and build high-quality kit in the UK, creating jobs and being - thanks to shorter transports - more environmentally friendly. Their gear goes on sale this autumn and will start with functional boxers which will be followed later on by tops, wind jackets and more. You can <a href="https://www.facebook.com/TrueMountainUK">follow their progress on FB</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773741624" title="True Mountain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3898/14773741624_6701cda2e4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="True Mountain" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14772926641" title="True Mountain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3890/14772926641_37d7c8160d_b.jpg" width="870" height="1024" alt="True Mountain" /></a></p>

<h2 id="aarn-packs">Aarn Packs</h2>

<p>All <a href="http://www.aarnpacks.com/">Aarn Packs</a> get a more streamlined, clean look. They’ve been optimized in several ways, and should now be even more suitable to runners, backpackers and hikers alike. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773742274" title="Aarn Packs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3926/14773742274_a78c57a72d_b.jpg" width="796" height="1024" alt="Aarn Packs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589379840" title="Aarn Packs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2930/14589379840_3219995230_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Aarn Packs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589447718" title="Aarn Packs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5579/14589447718_c60712c6e3_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Aarn Packs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773741884" title="Aarn Packs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5582/14773741884_7925be6541_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Aarn Packs" /></a></p>

<h2 id="mountain-network">Mountain Network</h2>

<p>Now something for the climbing gym owners and climbing clubs: <a href="http://www.mountain-network.eu/">Mountain Network</a> has created a climbing wall system that is self-bearing and that can be used indoors &amp; outdoors. Prefabricated elements allow you to build a tower like the one underneath in a day which makes them not just ideal for events, but also for hotels and other places which want to have a climbing wall e.g. over the summer outside and then store it away when the winter comes. It’s not just ideal to build climbing walls but also for bouldering walls. <a href="http://www.mountain-network.eu/klimwanden/klimwanden/driehoek-klimwanden/algemene-informatie/">Check out the video and photos on their site</a>, it’s pretty cool - so cool that it won an OutDoor Award!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773740874" title="Mountain Network by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3866/14773740874_ce1cca0d38_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Network" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589378780" title="Mountain Network by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5595/14589378780_3b1976bf2a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Network" /></a></p>

<h2 id="mountain-hardwear">Mountain Hardwear</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com/">Mountain Hardwear</a> Stretch Ozonic jacket is a 276 g 2.5-layer shell with good stretch. It’s made from the Dry.Q® Active fabric which has a ‘soft shell’ feel with the benefits and light weight of a hard-shell. It felt nice and Mountain Hardwear claims this is a great wet weather hiking jacket, so it could be interesting for those that prefer to walk in the rain and not this hot weather!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589426959" title="Mountain Hardwear Stretch Ozonic™ jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3843/14589426959_cc9d15efc3_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear Stretch Ozonic™ jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Quasar™ Lite Jacket is 340 g light and uses another Mountain Hardwear fabric, Dry.Q™ Elite. It’s also a 2.5 layer shell but has two harness/ hipbelt compatible pockets with a mesh lining that help with venting. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589448528" title="Mountain Hardwear Quasar™ Lite Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3856/14589448528_8cd312f7d4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear Quasar™ Lite Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>Mountain Hardwear uses OutDry in some of their packs, and the newest addition is the Scrambler 30. OutDry makes this pack’s main compartment completely waterproof. It has a 30 l volume and weighs 770 g and can carry between four and 11 kg. The waistbelt is stowable and you can carry your skis, ice tools or trekking poles. A versatile pack that should keep your gear dry in any situation.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589380770" title="Mountain Hardwear Scrambler™ 30 OutDry® by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5559/14589380770_c46164af2c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear Scrambler™ 30 OutDry®" /></a></p>

<p>The Mountain Hardwear Optic tent series gives you grand vistas through the possibility to open two adjacent doors for 180° views. The Optic 6 gives this possibility now to your next family camping trip. Not a lightweight shelter by any means at almost 7 kg, it does offer plenty of space - six adults could sleep in there, but please don’t move much in your sleep then. I think it’d be good for a family with two to three kids. At 500€ it’s certainly cheaper than many other camping tents where you can stand in, and divided between a family it is even lightweight when hiking. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776099795" title="Mountain Hardwear Optic™ 6 Tent by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3884/14776099795_a79fdff3a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Mountain Hardwear Optic™ 6 Tent" /></a></p>

<h2 id="tenaya">Tenaya</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.tenaya.net/index.php">Tenaya</a> makes climbing shoes. I decided to swing by and see what this company from Spain has to offer to us climbers and tried their <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/tenaya-oasi-kletterschuhe/?pid=81">Oasi</a> on. Wow. It’s hands down the most comfy climbing shoe I have worn - and that while also allowing for precision on small holds and hooking. <a href="https://www.facebook.com/AlexanderMegosSportler">Alex Megos</a> wears them, and he certainly knows a thing to two about climbing and shoes. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776098195" title="Tenayah Oasi by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3839/14776098195_1ec22697e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tenayah Oasi" /></a></p>

<p>But the Oasi isn’t new. The Tarifa is. It is a laced shoe and is designed for versatile performance and comfort on rock. It has a Vibram XS Grip 3.5 mm sole and is similarly constructed like the Oasi - I’d say it’s the Oasi with laces instead of the Velcro closure system. Definitely a shoe to try on if you have a chance, as its comfy with great performance. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589600097" title="Tenaya Tarifa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/14589600097_33ea0e0821_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tenaya Tarifa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776098075" title="Tenaya Tarifa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3906/14776098075_999775c4fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tenaya Tarifa" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rock-technologies">Rock Technologies</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.rocktechnologies.co.uk/">Rock Technologies</a> is the UK’s largest manufacturer of loose chalk and chalk balls, as well as several other climbing-related gear. They’re in business since 2001 and Richard, the owner started in his mother’s garage until the business was getting to big and dusty! Now they produce their high-quality chalk products in the UK and Austria, and they use only medical grade magnesium carbonate which minimizes health risks. Other products are a power putty for training and finger tape - I got some of the gear here on test and will report back after use.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14772928251" title="Rock Technologies Sterevive by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3886/14772928251_2bc594715a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Rock Technologies Sterevive" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14799510443" title="Rock Technologies Chalk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5594/14799510443_c9cca7e001_b.jpg" width="960" height="790" alt="Rock Technologies Chalk" /></a></p>

<h2 id="goal-zero">Goal Zero</h2>

<p>Power on the go - with <a href="http://bit.ly/1rXAMAH">Goal Zero</a> no problem. The Rock Out2 Solar Speaker is well suited for those backpacking parties where you don’t have a guitar along but need some tunes. The speaker hooks up via Bluetooth or a audio jack to your phone and gives an adequate sound for your next beach or outdoor party - 20 hours long or as long as the sun shines.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14663080042" title="Goalzero Rock Out2 Solar Speaker by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3854/14663080042_8539a3684b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Goalzero Rock Out2 Solar Speaker" /></a></p>

<p>The Torch 250 is a torch that can be powered via the solar panel or the crank. It has a between 70 and 180 Lumen depending on the mode you choose, and also has a red light. I wouldn’t carry it on a backpacking trip, but if you need a torch in your house or car for emergencies and don’t want to also have many batteries to power it, this would be the best alternative.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476811188" title="Goalzero Torch 250 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5594/14476811188_190f7a35ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Goalzero Torch 250" /></a></p>

<p>A piece of gear that certainly is something for backpackers is the Switch 10 Set. It consists of the Nomad 7 Solar Panel, Goal Zero Switch 10 Recharger and three add-on for the latter: A Ventilator (made from silicone so folds up), a USB to Mini-USB converter and a torch. These connect to the Switch 10 (which packs some more power than the current Switch 8). Weight will be probably a bit over 500 g all included, but if you only take what you need that goes down. The panel itself can store all the gear in a mesh pocket on the back and be strapped to your pack so you can power up while you hike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476815358" title="Goal Zero Switch 10 Set by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5494/14476815358_a17417670f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Goal Zero Switch 10 Set" /></a></p>

<h2 id="pramo">Páramo</h2>

<p><a href="http://paramo.co.uk/en-gb/index.php">Páramo</a> introduced three fleece/ windproof duos that use their innovative combination of Nikwax® Fleece with Nikwax® Windproof fabrics to create a versatile system. On their own both the fleeces and windproofs are water-repellent and able to hold off a rain shower. However, when worn together they provide the equivalent protection to a Páramo Analogy® Waterproof. And all of that PFC-free! Interesting for mountaineers and climbers is the Men’s Enduro &amp; Ladies’ Ventura Fleece/ Windproof Systems, these have an athletic fit, are harness, helmet and glove compatible and both have (aligned) hoods. The Men’s Bora &amp; Ladies’ Zonda duos are for hill walkers and backpackers, while the Men’s Bentu is for the everyday walker. Nice garments, made by a company that takes environmental and social matters serious and makes good efforts to make the (outdoor) world a better place.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589599957" title="Páramo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3870/14589599957_442af65f57_b.jpg" width="862" height="1024" alt="Páramo" /></a></p>

<p>The company also launched an Active Travel Collection, made of cool, protective and lightweight garments. They’re made of the Nikwax fabrics Parameta A and Cotton+ which keep you cool and provide protection against UV rays and biting insects. I imagine this would work well for backpacking in hot regions or just as casual garments in the office and town. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776141234" title="Páramo Men&#x27;s Maui II Cargo Trousers Sedge Cotton+ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5574/14776141234_a1c145483f_b.jpg" width="506" height="1024" alt="Páramo Men&#x27;s Maui II Cargo Trousers Sedge Cotton+" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14591991357" title="Páramo Men&#x27;s Katmai Light Shirt Woodland Check by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3846/14591991357_6483695440_b.jpg" width="986" height="1024" alt="Páramo Men&#x27;s Katmai Light Shirt Woodland Check" /></a></p>

<h2 id="scandinavian-outdoor-group">Scandinavian Outdoor Group</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorgroup.com/">Scandinavian Outdoor Group</a> not just has the tastiest coffee on the fair at the SOG Bar, but also unites the best outdoor brands from the north. The SOG Press Conference was an interesting event to attend, where 13 companies presented themselves and their newest creations. The SOG also heads out before each fair and tests kit that has been submitted for consideration for the prestigious SOG Award, which this time went again to Röjk and their PrimaLoft Zippen Hood. There were lots of great presentations with heaps of humour, which shows that the North not just builds some high-quality gear but also can have a laugh about themselves =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776101165" title="SOG Haglöfs Presentation by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5570/14776101165_afd96efe36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="SOG Haglöfs Presentation" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773743944" title="Peak Performance Cuben Suit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3874/14773743944_3e6a346289_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Peak Performance Cuben Suit" /></a></p>

<h2 id="big-agnes">Big Agnes</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.bigagnes.com/">Big Agnes</a> is still pretty hard to get in Europe so it was nice to check out their gear and meet the team. The Fly Creek UL 2 looked pretty cool and also won a OutDoor Award, and at packed weight of 1.050 g for the 2 Person version it’s a pretty impressive looking shelter. If you are hiking with a tablet or Kindle, install the Entertainment Center Loft inside and you can read or view a movie while lying down or sitting in the tent.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476728320" title="Big Agnes Fly Creek UL 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2900/14476728320_c3dc5d9a36_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Big Agnes Fly Creek UL 2" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14660188781" title="Big Agnes Fly Creek UL 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3891/14660188781_4d7c8e2ba4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Big Agnes Fly Creek UL 2" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14660188691" title="Big Agnes Entertainment Center Loft by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5523/14660188691_aa0fe2bfc7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Big Agnes Entertainment Center Loft" /></a></p>

<p>The Double Z Air Pad will be available as an Insulated version and should keep you warm when it gets cold. Pack size looked good, as did the thickness and size of the pad. It’s gonna be 595 g light in the 183 x 51 cm size and uses PrimaLoft Silver Hi-Loft as an insulation material to achieve an R-Value of 4.5.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14661141894" title="Big Agnes Insulated Double Z Air Pad by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3896/14661141894_49fc01c9fa_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Big Agnes Insulated Double Z Air Pad" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, mtnGlo™ is a really smart way to illuminate your shelter at night. Flexible LEDs are sewn into several of the Big Agnes models available, like the Copper Spur UL2 and UL3, Rattlesnake SL1 - SL4, Ripple Creek UL2+ and several more. But Big Agnes also thought about those tent users who don’t want to buy a new tent but would like to enjoy mtnGlo™ light inside, and that’s where the mtnGlo™ Tent Light Accessory Kit comes in handy. It’s a 254 cm long LED strand with Power pack that you can easily clip into the ceiling of your tent or shelter and <em>Voilá</em> - it’s light! Clips are included, the whole package is 84 g and is powered by three AAA batteries. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476781198" title="Big Agnes mtnGlo™ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3852/14476781198_def1fe84e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Big Agnes mtnGlo™" /></a></p>

<h2 id="salomon">Salomon</h2>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1qffpI5">Salomon</a> presented a sub 400 g, crampon compatible mountaineering boot, the Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX. It uses a carbon fibre midsole that is laterally stable but otherwise flexible. A Contragrip sole, a Sensifit upper with GTX lining &amp; Quicklace closure, this is the shoe for all those that like to run mountains up. I’m generally not a boot type, but this is a boot I’m excited about.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589445398" title="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3843/14589445398_8ec27437af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14753133576" title="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX Sole by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5588/14753133576_dc60394031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="725" alt="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX Sole" /></a></p>

<p>Flowtech is Salomon’s idea of venting on strenuous ascents where you don’t want to take the jacket off. Just open the zippers, roll the front up and keep it in place with the bungee cord. Good idea, but how will it work in the field?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14640394336" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5570/14640394336_bc32c5c9d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>The Ellipse Sport W is Salomon’s Women-only shoe. It has a women’s last and design and is from their hiking/ sports line, so could be a suitable hiking shoe for the ladies. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14663377945" title="Salomon Ellipse Sport W by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5544/14663377945_3c5b68268c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon Ellipse Sport W" /></a></p>

<p>The S-Lab Sense 4 Ultra SG goes into round four. The rubber on the sole has been made a bit more durable, so you might now get two Ultras out of one pair ;) It’s still as grippy and light as the ones before it - a fine shoe, slightly better.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14683282353" title="Salomon S-Lab Sense 4 Ultra SG by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3880/14683282353_9ef22fe79d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon S-Lab Sense 4 Ultra SG" /></a></p>

<p>The Speedcross 3 continues to be one of Salomon’s most popular shoes and now get updated colours for 2015, including Camo, which means finally hunters and Bushcrafters can wear them. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476758988" title="Salomon Speedcross 3 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5157/14476758988_afd596acc8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon Speedcross 3" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sealskinz">Sealskinz</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.sealskinz.com/UK/?skip_welcome_popup">Sealskinz</a> is also a company which I have read about a lot but have never tried their gear, so it was nice to put on some of their socks and gloves. The socks felt comfy warm and I can imagine them working well in wet weather or in winter when skiing, snow shoeing or ice climbing. The gloves had a good fit and the different models I tried on gave me quickly warm hands! There were a couple of models which I think could work well for winter mountaineering/ hiking and ice climbing, though for me they might be too warm to use in summer. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14775741742" title="SealSkinz by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5573/14775741742_896b5f198f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="SealSkinz" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14772928081" title="SealSkinz by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3871/14772928081_4ea8a75c04_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="SealSkinz" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. More photos you can find on the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157645582553771/">Flickr OutDoor 2014</a> set. </p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review LXXIX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/the-week-in-review-lxxix.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-27T14:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/the-week-in-review-lxxix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“The way out is through the door. Why is it that no one will use this method?”</em> ― Confucius</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14547032420" title="Valle Blanche by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2913/14547032420_eb765d013c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Valle Blanche" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.thebmc.co.uk/zoomtopo-crags-like-youve-never-seen-them-before">ZoomTopo: crags like you’ve never seen them before</a>.</p>

<p>Part 3 of my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-3.html">OutDoor News 2014</a> is out.</p>

<p><a href="http://semi-rad.com/2014/07/the-benefits-of-discomfort/">The Benefits Of Discomfort</a>.</p>

<p>David shares some tips on <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/news/outdoors-photography-at-night/0011240/">outdoors photography at night</a>.</p>

<p>It’s still summer sale time! At <a href="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=cc&amp;cpid=1&amp;target=http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/outdoor-bekleidung/">Bergfreunde</a> you can save up to 30% on garments, at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/outdoor-outlet/?_artperpage=96&amp;sort=4">Bergzeit</a> you’ll find gear that’s up to 90% reduced, and at the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=358273&amp;pw=73183">Patagonia’s July Sale</a> till 7/29/14 you can save up to 40% on selected gear. At <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/capturepro?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Designs</a> you can  get 10% off, and at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=247&amp;pw=73183">CampSaver.com there’s free shipping for orders over $50</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Jill shares some <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2014/07/one-more-for-road-gear-and-training-post.html">gear insights</a> - recommended for cyclists.</p>

<p><a href="http://bencollinsoutdoors.com/2014/07/26/evolution-of-a-lightweight-bike-touring-rig/">Evolution of a lightweight bike touring rig</a>.</p>

<p>Corinna reviews two <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2014/07/zuverlassig-in-der-handhabung-und.html">Klean Kanteen</a> bottles. [German]</p>

<p>Joslyn takes a look at the <a href="http://ulborbust.wordpress.com/2014/07/26/first-look-zpacks-custom-flat-tarp-my-birthday-presents/">Zpacks Custom Flat Tarp</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2014/07/articulo-la-sportiva-raptor-buena.html">La Sportiva RAPTOR</a> as a packrafting shoe.</p>

<p><a href="http://dedpxl.com/fuji-x-t1-review-yep-its-a-fuji/">FUJI X-T1 Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://steviehaston.blogspot.fi/2014/07/scarpa-booster-s-by-stevie-haston.html">Scarpa Booster S</a> review.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/icebreaker-aero-tank/">Icebreaker Aero Tank</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/edelrid-shark-crampon-review">Edelrid Shark Crampon review</a>.</p>

<p>John helped design the <a href="http://hikelighter.com/2014/07/22/zpacks-arc-zip-backpack/">ZPacks “Arc Zip” Backpack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-gear/gear-shed/pro-shop/The-Best-Coffee-Accessories-for-Backpackers.html">The Best Coffee Tools for Backpackers</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14604399775" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX &amp; Grivel Air-Tech crampons by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3863/14604399775_16e2e604d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX &amp; Grivel Air-Tech crampons" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Even non-vertical-enthusiasts will enjoy this post: <a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2014/07/bermudan-kolmio.html">Norway. Climbing.</a> [Finnish]</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.letsbewild.com/coast-to-coast-madagascar-expedition/">Madagascar Coast to Coast expedition</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://adventureblog.nationalgeographic.com/2014/07/24/a-grand-adventure-skiing-and-climbing-the-grand-teton/">Skiing and Climbing the Grand Teton</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2014/07/the-beara-peninsula.html">The Beara Peninsula</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://thunderinthenight.exposure.co/yellow-rope">Yellow Rope</a>.</p>

<p>Jules visits the <a href="http://amblesandrambles.blogspot.fi/2014/07/peaks-of-balkans-albania-montenegro_25.html">Peaks of the Balkans</a>.</p>

<p>Minna reaches <a href="https://ppyoralla.wordpress.com/2014/07/26/pva-22-26-1856-km-sveitsi/">Switzerland</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p>Angelica enjoys blue skies and sunshine on the <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2014/07/26/wanderflow-auf-dem-wiesensteig-dem-schwarzwaldsteig/">Wiesensteig &amp; Schwarzwaldsteig</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.schroll.at/blog/archives/4219">Oregon in photos</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2014/07/26/alaska-smorgasbord-last-chance-ak/">Alaska Smorgasbord</a>.</p>

<p>Roger &amp; his brother make <a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2014/07/tin-mine-cove-to-five-mile-beach-wander.html">a wander across the northern Wilsons Promontory</a>. </p>

<p>Chris hikes to the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/tegernseer-hutte-ross-und-buchstein/">Tegernseer Hütte</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seakayakingetc.blogspot.fi/2014/07/hiking-trip-to-tahquitz-peak.html">Overnight hiking trip to Tahquitz Peak</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2014/07/23/july-22-oh-those-sisters/">Horseshoe Lake to Sawyer Bar – Three Sisters Wilderness</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/101817145?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://alptraeume-suedtirol.blogspot.fi/2014/07/isihuette-kugeljoch-schwarzhorn.html">Schwarzhorn</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Chris spends a <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2014/07/a-night-on-creag-meagaidh.html">Night On Creag Meagaidh</a>.</p>

<p>Christine enjoys the <a href="http://christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi/2014/07/endless-summer-in-finland.html">endless summer in Finland</a>.</p>

<p>James goes into the <a href="http://glencoemountaineer.blogspot.fi/2014/07/giants-hole.html">Giant’s Hole</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://joecruz.wordpress.com/2014/07/25/fat-bike-south-africa/">Fat Bike South Africa</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://walkingwomad.blogspot.fi/2014/07/le-haute-route-chamonix-zermatt-or-how.html">Le Haute Route: Chamonix - Zermatt</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/almighty-dolomites/">Almighty Dolomites</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=358361&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/358361/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
