<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-01T23:04:41+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/bikepacking-on-the-wild-trails-of-britain.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/bikepacking-on-the-wild-trails-of-britain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html">Ireland</a> to Britain: Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain takes you &amp; your bike on the most beautiful multi-day rides in Wales, Scotland and England. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101282/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7252/27183101282_48e647f3ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Bikepacking is a big trend these days (check the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html">The Bikepacking Framebag Manufacturer List</a> to see how to transform your bike into a bikepacking rig) so it was a nice surprise as I was contacted by Wild Things Publishing and a question if they could use one of my photos in the book. Sure they could! As a wee thank you they sent me a copy of the book, and as I love alternative travel guide books <em>Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain</em> was right up my alley.</p>

<p>It is another beautiful book that will inspire you to pack up your bike and head to Britain in order to ride one (<em>or more!</em>) of the presented trips. From Epic Wilderness Rides over Family Rides to Technical &amp; Coastal Trails, the book presents 30 trips which range from a night to a week or riding in the countryside of Britain. The book starts off with an introduction to bikepacking and some history, some stories to get you in the mood, tips on gear - including a cool short chapter on tarps! - and how to plan a ride. In short: All you need to get on your bike and head out for a night or more in the wild. After the introduction it takes you on the different rides, which make up the majority of the book. These are sorted by regions in the UK - from the South East to the South West of England to the Midlands, Scotland and Wales. A map of the UK in the beginning highlights where these trips are to be found (good for planning) and a table on the next page gives  quick overview of relevant data about the rides - including distance, ascent and how many percent of the ride are off-road. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101142/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7326/27183101142_3113691725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I loved the very well designed info boxes which had all needed information ready with one look, a small map which gave a good idea of the ride (though you’ll need a real map for your adventure) and the beautiful photos. The trip descriptions are entertaining little trip reports in their own which will make you anticipate your own ride even more. All in all a unique book that is beautifully designed &amp; presented. If you’re into bikepacking and want to go to Britain for a wee adventure or more, this book is a recommended read!</p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://www.wildthingspublishing.com/product/bikepacking-book/">Wild Things Publishing</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i3Sr">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUYI3">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5hJmE">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Ireland's Wild Atlantic Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T22:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is the Wild Atlantic Way on your bucket list? Then you want to grab this travel guide to Ireland’s wild west coast!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183102302/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Cover"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7074/27183102302_ee6f87d84a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Cover" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last year I was lucky enough to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">explore Ireland</a>, hike the IAT and go sea stack climbing. What caught my interest and brought me to the Green Isle, however, was the Wild Atlantic Way: The world’s longest coastal touring route which goes from south to north along the west coast and is over 2.500 km long. There’s all kind of adventures to be had along the WAW, from visits in picturesque Irish villages and their pubs to bigger towns and their cultural offerings. However, <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</a> helps you find the off-the-beaten-track gems and takes you outdoors into the fresh, Irish air (and occasional rain shower!). </p>

<p>On 224 pages <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> takes you from the south in Kinsale to the far north of Malin Head along the coast. In seven chapters - divided by county - you can start to explore the Wild Atlantic Way. Do you fancy surfing, sea stack climbing and lots of remote wilderness? Then head to Donegal in the north. Do you prefer a cable car ride to an island, trying your luck fishing or going cycling? Then Cork in the south is a good place to start your adventures! Wherever you decide to go, <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> will have an insider tip ready for you. The seven county chapters are further divided into sections, each coming with their own little overview map to give you a feel of the land. Hundreds of gorgeous photos will get you in the mood to explore, while the detailed introduction chapter gives tips on when to come, what to bring and any other question you may have.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101542/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Inside"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7529/27183101542_ffe5d299bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Ireland is beautiful, and <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> helps you discover the green isle beyond the hustle and bustle of Dublin and the other big towns. Jam-packed with beautiful photos that inspire to visit the described places on Ireland’s west coast this book helps you plan your ultimate outdoor adventure itinerary. Three Rocks Books has created another stunning book which showcases some of the best scenery, sights and places in Ireland, and no matter if you plan to explore the Wild Atlantic Way on a roadtrip, by bike or public transportation, it will make sure you will see the true Wild Atlantic Way. <em>My tip: Book a flight to Ireland the same time you order this book!</em></p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Three Rocks Books</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/25pjt1d">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i48S">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUK3G">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yosemite in the Fifties]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/yosemite-in-the-fifties.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T20:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/yosemite-in-the-fifties</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Big walls, inspiring stories, epic climbing photos - that’s <a href="http://bit.ly/1RvKL98">Yosemite in the Fifties</a> in a nutshell.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101812/in/dateposted/" title="Yosemite in the Fifties Cover"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7095/27183101812_79dc07e245_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yosemite in the Fifties Cover" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>“Show me a climber who doesn’t know Yosemite and I show you someone who doesn’t climb.”</em> OK, I made that up, but there’s a hint of truth in that: Climbers from across the globe know the view down the valley on El Cap, heard about the epic Dawn Wall climb of Tommy Caldwell and Kevin Jorgeson in 2015, and just long to stand underneath the towering granite walls of El Capitain before also they will start to scale it. Yosemite in the Fifties transportes you back in time to the iron age of climbing history in the valley, when climbers where pushing the envelope of what had been thought possible and established the routes we still climb today.</p>

<p>The book is a collection of beautiful photos of the valley, the protagonists and their climbs, all taken with cameras that relied on the skill &amp; knowledge of the operator. In between these inspiring photos are four chapters with over a dozen essays. These essays are from original source material - first-person narratives and anecdotes of the climbers and their friends, interspersed with archive photos and shots of memorabilia from back in the day. Stories range from a history of climbing tools over portraits to historic climbing routes. With over 200 pages and twenty essays <em>Yosemite in the Fifties</em> is captivating for a long time and a book one can go back to time &amp; again to let the imagination wander off once more while looking at the old photos or reading one of the adventurous stories.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183102042/in/dateposted/" title="Yosemite in the Fifties Inside"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7301/27183102042_88924e20aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yosemite in the Fifties Inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Climbing in Yosemite is high on my bucket list so <em>Yosemite in the Fifties</em> is a book I enjoyed immensely. It’s a tasteful combination of visuals and stories, many written by John Long, one of climbing’s best writers. If climbing in Yosemite is something you also aspire to, I think you should pick up this beautiful coffee table book and immerse yourself into the history of the Iron Age of climbing in the valley. The stories and little anecdotes will surely be something that will make your wish to go to Yosemite even stronger, and once you’re standing on a ledge on El Cap Tower you will remember this book, it stories, and smile - because now you are there, and become part of its history! </p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1RvKL98">Patagonia</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/25pkA0R">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5ilsg">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUhP2">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 236]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/twir-236.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-23T23:51:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/twir-236</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“You learn a lot when you’re barefoot. The first thing is every step you take is different.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/25hpw82">Michael Franti</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27109586945/in/photostream/" title="Luna Sandals Mono"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7520/27109586945_8163019e61_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Luna Sandals Mono" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>It’s spring, lakes and rivers are open and you are pondering <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/images/content/CC_EN.pdf">which packraft to get</a>? I know the feeling. Good thing the Packrafting Store has created the most awesome fully-interactive <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/images/content/CC_EN.pdf">comparison chart</a> which lists all their packrafts from super-ultralight to cargo carriers for the whole family. Use it to find the right packraft for your needs, sorted by size, weight and best use, rated from robustness to Whitewater capability and see what the different accessories weigh. After you made up your mind click the packraft and get directly to the prduct page and find out even more about your chosen raft. I know I’d wish there’d been something like this when I started packrafting years ago!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/images/content/CC_EN.pdf" title="Packrafting Store Comparison Chart"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7087/27095298972_5b66db7cb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="488" alt="Packrafting Store Comparison Chart" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Help LAUFBURSCHE and win a SUL <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2016/05/cuben-fiber-huckepackchen-laufbursche/">Cuben Fiber huckePÄCKchen</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/@kellycatchpole/i-am-a-cyclist-and-i-am-here-to-fuck-you-up-a2fb97b1ea16#.2i98yjjzi">I am a cyclist. I am here to fuck you up</a>.</p>

<p>Share your favourite <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/weekend-bikepacking-routes/">Weekend Bikepacking Route</a> and win some sweet prizes.</p>

<p><a href="http://publications.americanalpineclub.org/articles/13201213644/Dean-Potter-19722015">Dean Potter, 1972–2015</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/galleys/how-chris-mccandless-died-992e6ce49410#.ionapl5ff">How Chris McCandless Died</a>.</p>

<p>Alex Lowe’s Son Reflects on <a href="http://adventureblog.nationalgeographic.com/2016/05/11/a-son-remembers-his-dad-alex-lowe-whose-body-was-discovered-in-tibet/">Finding Closure</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FMqADdsVmwQ">Candide Thovex skis in spring conditions</a>.</p>

<p>The Enormocast with <a href="http://enormocast.com/episode-104-ines-papert-walking-the-the-beautiful-line/">Ines Papert</a>.</p>

<p>A good <a href="http://seawildearth.com/motion-timelapse-tutorial/">Motion Timelapse Tutorial</a>.</p>

<p>Check out these <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/vivobarefoot/the-original-san-dal">hand-made leather sandals from VIVOBAREFOOT</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/05/adjustments-on-and-off-the-trail.html">Adjustments on and off the trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kenilgunas.com/2016/05/books-for-21st-century-environmentalist.html">Books for the 21st Century Environmentalist</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bunyanvelo.com">Bunyan Velo Issue 6</a> is out!</p>

<p>How Neuroscientists Explain the <a href="http://nymag.com/scienceofus/2016/04/how-neuroscientists-explain-the-mind-clearing-magic-of-running.html">Mind-Clearing Magic of Running</a>.</p>

<p>Get $30 Off the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=243989&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR236">Fre Power Case From LifeProof</a> which gives your iPhone 6 complete protection plus 2X Battery Life. Oh, and there’s Free Shipping, too!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> finally got a responsive website! Go check it out on your tablet and smartphone and also check out their big <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/10-jahre-bergfreunde-gewinnspielpreise/?pid=10239">10th Anniversary Raffle</a>!</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3638&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR236">Backcountry.com Outlet</a> has up to 70% off on your favourite outdoor gear and gives you free 2-day shipping on orders over $50.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=462077&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR236"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/13582/462077/55699/73183/image.jpg?ctc=TWIR236" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Check out Hikeminded’s <a href="https://hikeminded.wordpress.com/tag/serratramuntana/">Serra de Tramuntana</a> posts from the GR21! [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2016/05/el-otro-peru-la-travesia-de-los-lagos.html">“La travesía de los lagos”</a>.</p>

<p>Nick visits <a href="http://tms.nickbramhall.com/blog/2016/05/conachcraig-lochnagar/">Conachcraig and Lochnagar</a>.</p>

<p>Ute &amp; kids enter the realm of the Dragon, the <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/im-reich-des-drachens-die-kundler-klamm/">Kundler Klamm</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.goout.hk/2016/05/17/summer_camping/">夏至・遊の營</a>. [Chinese]</p>

<p><a href="https://emmakarjalainen.com/2016/05/17/the-ladies-climbing-trip-to-yosemite/">The Ladies’ Climbing trip to Yosemite</a>.</p>

<p>Cool trip report from the <a href="https://mbguiding.ca/2016/05/coast-trail-east-sooke-regional-park/">Coast Trail – East Sooke Regional Park</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/22990491?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.oooyeah.de/nord-norwegen/">Oh, how beautiful is…</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://create.adobe.com/2016/4/8/somewhere_in_new_zealand_chapter_one.html">Somewhere in New Zealand</a>.</p>

<p>Heather’s <a href="https://heatherclimbs.com/2016/05/18/wake-up-fall/">Wake Up Fall</a>.</p>

<p>Gerald finishes his exploration of the <a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2016/05/die-vergessene-welt-des-huanchaca_20.html">Huanchaca Plateau</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A <a href="https://surfnslide.wordpress.com/2016/05/21/a-spring-wild-camp-in-mid-wales/">spring wild camp in Mid Wales</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://niksbikingblog.blogspot.fi/2016/05/highland-trail-2016-recce.html">Highland Trail 2016 Recce</a>.</p>

<p>David takes a hike up <a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/hiking/mt-kawanori/">Mt. Kawanori</a>.</p>

<p>Rode Trip: <a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2016/05/rode-trip-bikefishing-the-salmonfly-hatch-in-maupin/">Bikefishing the Salmonfly Hatch in Maupin</a>.</p>

<p>Check out Rick’s <a href="https://besthike.com/2016/05/17/sunshine-coast-trail-day-4/">Sunshine Coast Trail Trip Reports</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://outlivingblog.wordpress.com/2016/05/14/whats-left/">What’s left</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26505574003/in/dateposted/" title="Enjoying the view"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7264/26505574003_dc926838ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Enjoying the view" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plan/smartphone-as-a-gps/">Using your Smartphone as a GPS</a>.</p>

<p>Derek reviews the <a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2016/05/hennessy-deep-jungle-asym-hammock-review/">Hennessy Deep Jungle Asym Hammock</a>.</p>

<p>Raf takes a look at the <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2016/05/first-look-arcteryx-acrux-boot/">Arc’teryx Acrux AR Boot</a>.</p>

<p>Keith reviews the <a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/straight-jacket-syndrome-zpacks-sleeping-bag-review/">ZPacks Sleeping Bag</a>.</p>

<p>Jens tests the <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/bekleidung/praxistest-adidas-terrex-skyclimb-top/">Adidas Terrex Skyclimb Top</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Ivo made a <a href="http://ivovanmontfort.blogspot.fi/2016/05/shelter-in-tramplite-style.html">DIY Tramplite-Style Shelter</a> from Silnylon.</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=526209&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR236"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10921/526209/55699/73183/image.gif?ctc=TWIR236" width="468" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Additionally the Packrafting Store supported this post, too. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Leg for LAUFBURSCHE]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/a-leg-for-laufbursche.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-23T23:26:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/a-leg-for-laufbursche</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mateusz, backpacker and manufacturer of the ultralight <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">LAUFBURSCHE</a> backpacks, lost a leg in his battle against cancer. With this fundraiser I want to help him pay his medical bills and hopefully get a prosthesis that allows him to go hiking again. [<strong>Updated with winner!</strong>]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/" title="ILoveLAUFBURSCHE.com"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7176/26188616394_48ddfab21e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="615" alt="ILoveLAUFBURSCHE.com" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Mateusz and I met the first time six years ago when he joined a group of ultralight backpackers who followed my invite for an <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/02/tufwt-1-0-trip-report.html">Ultralight Winter trip</a>. We hiked, laughed, camped in the snow, went to Sauna and jumped into the ice hole together, and have been in contact ever since. I was lucky enough to get one of the very first 40D black Silnylon huckePACKs, a design which was back then and still today is revolutionary. As an Architect Mateusz has a great eye for functional design, and his backpacks are considered far and wide works of art. My “Packing your framless backpack - LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK” video is probably my most-watched video on Youtube, and it is that backpack which I today will to raffle off in support of Mateusz. </p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MDF26eJ2sqU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>As a fellow entrepreneuer I know that should sickness strike then shit hits the fan, and it’s sadly not different for Mateusz. Many other’s have written about his condition so I do not want to concentrate on it here, but instead send good vibes and support his way and a one-of-a-kind LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK your way. The pack is in great condition without any damage, is made of black 40d Silynlon with an XPAC floor, is Size L (which fits me at 175 cm very well) and weighs with all the straps attached 343 g. I guesstimate the volume at around 35 to 45 l, so it’s a great size for a week long trip in the mountains or woods.</p>

<p><em>So, how do you get a chance on winning this backpack AND help Mateusz?</em> </p>

<ul>
  <li>One lottery ticket costs 5€, and you can buy as many as you’d like. More tickets obviously increase your chances to win this unique pack and help Mateusz more!</li>
  <li>You Donate for each lottery ticket you’d like to buy 5€ to Mateusz via <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">this website</a> (<em>you can donate via PayPal or bank transfer, please follow the simple instructions given over there for your donation</em>)</li>
  <li>You send an Email with a screenshot of the confirmed donation to <em>laufbursche[ät]hikinginfinland.com</em> with your name and the amount of lottery tickets you purchased</li>
  <li>If you like, comment underneath to let others know how many tickets you have bought =)</li>
  <li>You can buy lottery tickets till the 22nd of May, Midnight Finnish time</li>
  <li>On the 23rd of May I will put all tickets in a hat and my son will pull out one lucky winner who gets the backpack!</li>
</ul>

<p>If you just like to help and have already enough huckePACKs, just head over to <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">I Love LAUFBURSCHE</a> and donate. Every donation is appreciated and helps Mateusz on the long trail of rehabilitation and getting back outdoors. <em>To read more about Mateusz condition head over to <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2016/04/crowdfunding-laufbursche.html">Outdoormädchen</a>, <a href="https://limitcamper.wordpress.com/2016/04/27/i-love-laufbursche/">Limitcamper</a> or the <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3737-ein-laufbursche-für-den-laufburschen/">various</a> <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3626-die-gute-tat-für-laufbursche-frühling/">threads</a> on <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3495-laufbursche-genesungswünsche/">Ultraleicht</a> <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3504-schulterschluss-für-mateusz/">Trekking</a>.</em></p>

<h2 id="update-23052016">Update 23.05.2016</h2>

<p>Wow, what a great effort! There were donations for a total of 201 lottery tickets, with some donations which didn’t want to enter, which raised a grand total of 1.295 € for Mateusz! I imagine that helps him with getting a ultralight carbon or titanium part for his prosthesis! The winner of the huckePACK has already been contacted and I hope she will enjoy hiking with the pack =)</p>

<p>Of course we don’t need to stop now - Mateusz is still battling with the complications of his sickness, and you can still <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">donate</a> to support him. Every small donation helps, so just drink one less fancy coffee and donate that sum instead =)</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I have no financial benefit in this campaign. Mateusz is a friend of mine and I want to help him pay his medical bills &amp; hike again in the future.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Writing II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/spring-writing-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-19T23:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/spring-writing-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Spring is in the air and new magazines are on the newsstand!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26501342664/in/dateposted/" title="Spring Writing II"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7555/26501342664_8be767dbc3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="872" alt="Spring Writing II" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="walden">WALDEN</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.walden-magazin.de">WALDEN</a> is a new German magazine which not only has a fantastic layout &amp; design, the content and stories in it also are top-notch. Thus it was a nice surprise to be asked if I’d like to contribute a short piece to the third issue - and now I’m part of the WALDEN family. Read my and other outdoor blogger’s spring tips in issue three which you can <a href="http://shop.geo.de/einzelhefte/walden/walden-01-2016.html">order here</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26501343264/in/dateposted/" title="WALDEN"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/26501343264_b02fcf2273_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="WALDEN" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-enthusiast">Outdoor Enthusiast</h2>

<p>I already mentioned my online piece about <a href="http://www.oe-mag.co.uk/imag/oemarchapril2016/files/36.html">Via Ferratas</a> in the Outdoor Enthusiast Magazine a month or two ago, but the article is also in the print magazine. It’s free and includes some great stories &amp; photos, so if you see it in your local outdoor shop grab a copy and enjoy it with a glass of beer the next time you’re needing an outdoor fix!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27038557421/in/dateposted/" title="outdoor Enthusiast"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7107/27038557421_c4a2b39e7b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="outdoor Enthusiast" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bike--travel-and-trekking-magazin">Bike &amp; Travel and trekking Magazin</h2>

<p>For both the <a href="http://www.biketravel-magazin.com">Bike &amp; Travel Magazine</a> and <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com">trekking Magazin</a> I have been writing a company portrait of Thule, the Swedish company that’s well-known for their innovative transport solutions for bikes &amp; skis. Both pieces are slightly different, so if you want to know more about Thule’s backpack line make sure to grab a copy of the trekking Magazin while if you’re a cyclist and want to know about their panniers and child transporters grab the Bike &amp; Travel Magazin!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26503271273/in/dateposted/" title="Bike &amp; Travel and trekking Magazin"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7388/26503271273_aa949d3323_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Bike &amp; Travel and trekking Magazin" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laufen. Essen. Schlafen.]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/laufen-essen-schlafen.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-06T09:22:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/laufen-essen-schlafen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Planning on hiking the PCT, CDT or AT? Then you can’t get around not reading German Tourist’s book <em>“Laufen. Essen. Schlafen.”</em>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26846528165/in/dateposted/" title="Laufen. Essen. Schlafen."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7688/26846528165_87e238d3c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Laufen. Essen. Schlafen." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I met <a href="http://www.christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi">Christine</a> two years ago as she was cycling through Finland, and we spent a nice afternoon eating cake and sushi in Vaasa. Of course I knew her much longer digitally, but it was really nice to finally met her and hear more about her stories from hiking, paddling and cycling around the globe. If you’re not so lucky to meet German Tourist (her Trailname) then you should pick up a copy of her book <em>Laufen. Essen. Schlafen.</em> which was published just a month ago. It’s in German, though, so I hope your Deutsch skills are up to scratch. The book chronicles GT’s decision from first hiking one long-distance trail in the US to all three and abandoning a <em>normal</em> 9-to-5 life. </p>

<p>The book starts out with Christine as a successful business women who is on holiday in the US, to losing her job and a good friend which in turn make her decide to go hiking the Pacific Crest Trail. The hiking story reminded me in parts of Keith’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1XbLlQl">The Last Englishman</a>, a book about Keith’s PCT hike. It’s a mix of trail description, <em>trail talk</em> (gossip) and Chrisitine’s experiences on the PCT. The PCT chapter is also the longest of the 288 page long book, with each subsequent chapter getting shorter. </p>

<p>The CDT chapter then starts again with Christine the successful business woman, a romance that’s doomed from the start, and the hard hiking life on the CDT. No rest days for three and a half months! During the CDT chapter German Tourist meets friends from the PCT again, loses her job while hiking the CDT and subsequently decides to quite the 9-to-5 rat race life. The AT chapter, which is a mere fifty something pages, then feels hurried. There’s the misery at the start, the realization that she does not need to hurry anymore, more meetings with old friends from the PCT and pretty autumn hiking through the green jungle. </p>

<p>I read the book in a day and overall found it an enjoyable read. There were a few sections that made me thoughtful, sad, laugh and anticipate what would happen next. The book is entertaining, but I felt that in the CDT and AT chapter Christine was just in a hurry to finish the book and get outdoors again - I would have wished for similar insights &amp; details from her about these two trails, too. Despite this I think it is a great read for anyone who is interested in hiking and long-distance backpacking, as Christine writes eloquently about the life on the trail and what it entails. The sections about her conversations with fellow thru-hikers and trail angels where my favourites by far, and made me want to pack my backpack and fly over to the USA! Get your copy from <a href="https://www.piper.de/buecher/laufen-essen-schlafen-isbn-978-3-89029-471-1">Piper</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1rwC7BW">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1rwCgp9">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lyngen]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/lyngen.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-02T23:53:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/lyngen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ski-touring in late April: Daylight from 4 am till 10 pm, great powder or spring crust, wall-to-wall sunshine &amp; all topped off with that breath-taking fjord &amp; mountain view of the Lyngen Alps.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26741128546/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1508/26741128546_756a100b4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Together with Henryk from <a href="http://www.oooyeah.de">Out of Office</a> I spent a fantastic week in the Lyngen Alps. Here’s a wee teaser so you can book your flight tickets and accommodation there for next spring, because it most certainly is a place you want to be. It all starts in Tromsø, where already the approach by plane is breath-taking. Then you go for a walk in the old town and pick up your Van from <a href="http://www.takemeaway.no">Take me Away Camping</a> to head north-west to the Lyngen Alps and their surroundings.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160875484/in/dateposted/" title="Tromsø Main street"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1508/26160875484_ce73ae3654_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tromsø Main street" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>You probably want to stop to take in the view once in a while.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160875184/in/dateposted/" title="Our Adventure Van"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1462/26160875184_b35e059705_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our Adventure Van" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160874894/in/dateposted/" title="Endless roads"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1490/26160874894_47fb2c1c77_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Endless roads" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>When your bindings decides to break you go for a walk along the coast of Arnøya and make a stop in a lovely little cabin.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160874544/in/dateposted/" title="Centuries in layers"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1508/26160874544_183b341431_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Centuries in layers" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160875804/in/dateposted/" title="A view to love"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1461/26160875804_1080a5c426_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A view to love" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>You take the ferry and enjoy the smell of the sea on deck.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26741113346/in/dateposted/" title="On a ferry"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1610/26741113346_46c00d88e5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On a ferry" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And what’s wrong with sitting down in the sun and have a beer (after a day of skiing, obviously!)?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160876694/in/dateposted/" title="After-Ski beers"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1538/26160876694_c5b83977c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="After-Ski beers" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the summit you snap a selfie with that big grin because the view is so amazing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160876794/in/dateposted/" title="Summit Selfie"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1504/26160876794_3853aab70b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit Selfie" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And while the tide is low you go for a walk along the beach.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26741128296/in/dateposted/" title="Evening Sunset"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1464/26741128296_d26a5e3531_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Evening Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Or you go skiing while the sun sets.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26741129446/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset skiing"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1719/26741129446_117610d8ae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset skiing" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On blue-bird days the summits can be busy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160876444/in/dateposted/" title="Busy summit"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1462/26160876444_69cf794b5c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Busy summit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But there’s enough fjords so you can have one for yourself to enjoy the sunset.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160876304/in/dateposted/" title="Fjord sunset"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1489/26160876304_454bd5c53c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fjord sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So, book those tickets to Norway now, reserve your adventure van, and then check back in autumn to get the full low-down on our roadtrip ski-touring adventure.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Thanks to <a href="http://www.visit-lyngenfjord.com/en">Visit Lyngenfjord</a> and their partners who invited us up north. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 235]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/twir-235.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-01T23:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/twir-235</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Spring is nature’s way of saying, ‘Let’s party!’</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1Y1br6V">Robin Williams</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148754883/in/dateposted/" title="What a view!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1694/26148754883_8441890563_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="What a view!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Mateusz, the owner of the German cottage <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">LAUFBURSCHE</a> has cancer. He needs your help so please donate whatever you can. Tobias also wrote <a href="https://limitcamper.wordpress.com/2016/04/27/i-love-laufbursche/">a few words about the situation</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.npr.org/2016/04/08/473513620/what-happens-when-fashion-becomes-fast-disposable-and-cheap">What Happens When Fashion Becomes Fast, Disposable And Cheap</a>?</p>

<p>A Fashion Revolution: <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/dana-geffner/trading-fast-fashion-for-_b_9705654.html">Trading Fast Fashion for Fair Fashion</a>! </p>

<p><a href="http://trucedesigns.com">Truce</a> makes backpacks, duffles and totes from recycled materials.</p>

<p>Discover innovative gear from outdoor startups at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=489297&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR235">Garage Grown Gear</a>.</p>

<p>Check out this <a href="http://www.suluk46.com/products%20%20-%20P25%20Miksa%20Pot%20Lifter.html">6 g Miniature Pot Lifter from Suluk46</a>.</p>

<p>In much of Europe, walking wherever you want is perfectly legal. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/04/24/opinion/sunday/this-is-our-country-lets-walk-it.html?_r=1">Not in America</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/velorution-cycles-bed-rock-bags-unique-partnership/">Velorution Cycles and Bedrock Bags</a>: A Unique Partnership.</p>

<p><a href="http://thatemilychappell.com/2016/04/the-adventure-syndicate/">The Adventure Syndicate</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/bricks-bikepacking-moots/">Moots</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://enormocast.com/episode-103-stacy-bare-all-we-need-is-love-climbing/">All We Need is Love, Climbing</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://walkingwomad.com/2016/04/29/more-or-less-or-just-enough/">More or Less or Just Enough</a>.</p>

<p>David explains <a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/musings/what-to-expect-when-camping-in-japan/">what to expect when camping in Japan</a>.</p>

<p>Grab the <a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/free-kindle-download-journey-starts-soon/">FREE Kindle Download of The Journey in Between</a>.</p>

<p>And Torjus has a <a href="http://amzn.to/1Y1aiwb">E-book Version of his Fishing Book</a> now available.</p>

<p>Love Scandinavia? Then check out <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/brands/2117-of-sweden/?bfc-brand[0]=66-north&amp;bfc-brand[1]=norroena-bf&amp;bfc-brand[2]=bergans&amp;bfc-brand[3]=fjaellraeven&amp;bfc-brand[4]=lundhags&amp;bfc-brand[5]=devold&amp;bfc-brand[6]=peak-performance&amp;bfc-brand[7]=houdini&amp;bfc-brand[8]=hagloefs&amp;bfc-brand[9]=aclima&amp;listorderby=oxinsert&amp;listorder=desc&amp;?pid=10239">Scandinavian Outdoor Brands at Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p>Save up to <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3482&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR235">30% off Black Diamond at Backcountry</a> and get Free 2-Day Shipping.</p>

<p>Get <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=49341&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR235">FREE US Shipping on ALL Orders at ULA Equipment Backpacks</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR235"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg?ctc=TWIR235" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/2070446/county-donegal-hidden-irish-paradise-vertigo-inducing-fun">A hidden Irish Paradise of Vertigo-Inducing Fun</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://injuringeternity.net/2016/04/30/snow-rain-and-bikes/">Snow, Rain &amp; Bikes</a> on Gotland.</p>

<p>Joe’s <a href="http://alpine-works.com/2016/04/arizona-trail-race-part-2/">Arizona Trail Race</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mikesee.exposure.co/river-of-dreams">Traversing Oregon’s Kalmiopsis Wilderness</a> by bike &amp; packraft.</p>

<p>Jill’s <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2016/04/the-first-week.html">first week in Colorado</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://mitsackundpackraft.wordpress.com/2016/04/30/winterreise-nach-groenland8-spaziergang-auf-dem-meer/">walk on Greenland’s ice</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://racewithwind.blogspot.fi/2016/04/varia-kevaaseen.html">Spring colours</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p>Matthias’ <a href="http://photo.matthiaskodym.com/wordpress3/blog/2016/04/24/100-miles-of-istria-2016-race-report/">100 Miles of Istria 2016 Race Report</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RW_mZVJ1Xr4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Stephen visited <a href="http://howlingmist.blogspot.fi/2016/04/snowdoniaamphitheatre-buttress-and.html">Amphitheatre Buttress and Atlantic Slab</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://quasiout.blogspot.fi/2016/05/rennsteig-uber-ostern-bikepacking-zu.html">Bikepacking on the Rennsteig</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Gilad <a href="http://www.outdoorsfather.com/2016/04/why-i-failed-finish-cape-wrath-trail/">failed to finish the Cape Wrath Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.shinimichi.com/2016/04/winter-camping-in-norwegian-snow-you.html">Winter camping in the Norwegian snow</a>.</p>

<p>Check out Ryan’s <a href="http://freedirtmonger.blogspot.fi/2016/04/sky-island-traverse.html">Sky Island Traverse</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148754403/in/dateposted/" title="At the summit"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1681/26148754403_5dff0ce1e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the summit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2016/battle-of-the-bars-round-3/">Battle of the Bars, Round 3</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pmags.com/gear-review-deuce-of-spades">Deuce of Spades</a> Review.</p>

<p>Kristian checks if <a href="https://freieberge.wordpress.com/2016/04/29/schneehoehenmessung-der-zamg/">Snowgrid</a> works. [German]</p>

<p>Climbing Guide Review for the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/climbing-frankische-schweiz-frankenjura-band-2/">Fränkische Schweiz</a>.</p>

<p>Zena tests the <a href="http://www.timoanttalainen.com/2016/04/ruffwear-palisades-koiran-reppu.html">Ruffwear Palisade Dog backpack</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/kozikidz-stockholm-jacket-review/">Kozikidz Stockholm jacket</a> Review.</p>

<p>Alan’s <a href="http://alanrayneroutdoors.blogspot.fi/2016/04/custom-cone-windshield-for-meths-stoves.html">Custom Cone Windshield for his Meths stoves</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://hikeminded.wordpress.com/2016/04/23/the-ultralight-dilemma/">The Ultralight Dilemma</a>.</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=462153&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR235"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/13582/462153/55699/73183/image.jpg?ctc=TWIR235" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ski-Touring Pack List]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-18T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Travelling with your skis and packing for a week of ski-touring in the mountains seems daunting? No worries, with my packlist you’re ready to fly and ski a Haute Route without any packing problems!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26458154986/in/dateposted/" title="Packing for a ski-tour"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1512/26458154986_a0a9acf22a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packing for a ski-tour" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Before my first ski-touring trip to Canada last year I was worried: How should I transport my skis, boots and everything else in a way that it arrives in one piece and that it is easy for me to carry? What do I all need to take? After much research, reading gear reviews, making my own experienced guesses and adapting my ultralight packing strategy for ski-touring I have arrived at a pack list &amp; travel setup that works very well. </p>

<p>My pack list does cut no corners and allows me to either ski in comfort from a base camp or can be adapted for a Haute-Route-style ski-tour where I sleep each night in a different hut. With changing the backpack I even can take camping equipment and pitch the tent on the top of a summit! For the travelling part this pack list allows me to take a variety of gear but still not feel like I’m an over-loaded donkey. Besides a dedicated ski bag I rely again on the awesome <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/one-duffle-to-rule-them-all-the-arcteryx-carrier-duffle.html">Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle</a> to transport gear via bus, train, plane and car, while on tour I’m carrying all I need outdoors in one backpack. It’s a versatile, light and durable list that’s equally suitable for a week of ski-touring in Lyngen or the Alps. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25686718380/in/dateposted/" title="Will and Anselm discussing our run"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1690/25686718380_3134f5b330_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Will and Anselm discussing our run" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="when-skis-travel">When Skis Travel</h2>

<p>Travelling with skis can be easy, comfortable and fun - if you have a <a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/douchebag-the-douchebag-ski-bag/?pid=81">Douchebag</a> to transport your skis. If you look past the name - which is fun in my opinion! - you get a ski bag which transports skis, boots, backpack, poles, avalanche kit and clothes in comfort. My 184 cm long DPS Wailer Tour1 skis fit perfectly into it with room to spare, and the Ribcage construction of the Douchebag ensures the skis and everything else inside stay safe. I have flown thousands of kilometers with the Douchebag, travlled hundreds of kilometers by train and car and the Douchebag has never let me down. Thanks to the two large wheels it is easy to pull the ski bag through airports and streets, and best of all: If not needed it can be rolled up into a compact little package which takes up little space. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25897550964/in/dateposted/" title="The Douchebag rolled up"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1492/25897550964_a09fd56363_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Douchebag rolled up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If I travel inside the Douchebag I put:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1paqW0r">DPS Wailer Tour1 Skis</a> with <a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/g3-ion-12-touring-binding/?pid=81">G3 Ion 12 Binding</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/contour-hybrid-variocut-universal-cutting-skin/?pid=81">Contour Hybrid Skins</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/komperdell-carbon-c2-ultralight-ski-touring-poles/?pid=81">Komperdell Carbon C2 Ultralight Ski-Touring Poles</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/la-sportiva-spectre.html">La Sportiva Spectre boots</a></li>
  <li>As well as a variety of gear from the clothing and backpack section</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26476496496/in/dateposted/" title="Douchebag packed"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1556/26476496496_97588442f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Douchebag packed" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-backpack">The Backpack</h2>

<p><em>Airbag or normal ski-touring bag</em>, that was the question I asked myself as I set out to add yet another backpack to the collection. While I’d love to have an <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/arcteryx-voltair-avalanche-airbag.html">Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag</a> I settled for the lighter <a href="http://bit.ly/1pari78">Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 25 Pack</a> with the <a href="http://bit.ly/23GxUgv">Black Diamond Avalung Element</a>. It’s a reasonably light pack with an avy pocket in the front, a spacious google pocket and a large main compartment that’s opened via a zipper in the back panel - this keeps gear out of the snow. I also can carry my helmet at the front of the pack, and also the skis or a snowboard attach to the Dawn Patrol 25. If I travel I usually take this backpack also as a carry-on, and it fits my 15” MBP nicely into the main compartment with room to spare for cables, a book and more. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26410127142/in/dateposted/" title="Ski-touring Pack"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1583/26410127142_3dd4f2d4ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski-touring Pack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Inside the <a href="http://bit.ly/1pari78">Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 25 Pack</a> are</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1U1toDf">G3 AviTECH T-grip Shovel</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1SfUOkh">G3 240 SpeedTECH Probe</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">0,7 l Thermos bottle</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/montane-softflask-trinkflasche/">0,5 l Softflask Water bottle</a></li>
  <li>Snacks</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/hestra-merino-wool-liner-active-5-finger-handschuhe/">Hestra Merino Wool Liner Active Gloves</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/23Gymvd">Hestra Moon Mitten</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1TedIu9">Arc’teryx Cerium SV Hooded Down Jacket</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/salewa-vert-helmet-skihelm/">Salewa Vert Helmet</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1qSr0mJ">POC Lid Googles</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1U1wk2I">Petzl Tikka RXP Headlamp</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/269ZcL7">CAMP XLC 390 Crampons</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/23GwQsU">CAMP Corsa Ice axe</a></li>
  <li>Multitool</li>
  <li>Mesh covers for the skins</li>
  <li>Minimalistic 1st Aid &amp; Repair Kit</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/26a57zG">G3 Ski crampons</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/petzl-sitta-harness-orange-l/?pid=81">Petzl Sitta Harness</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/23Gz7nX">Petzl RAD System</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-laser-speed-light-eisschraube/">Petzl Laser Speed ice screws</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod.html">Velbon V-Pod Tripod</a></li>
  <li>Two spare <a href="http://amzn.to/1VcUSHm">batteries for the camera</a> and two <a href="http://amzn.to/1Tek0Kg">SanDisk Extreme 64GB SDXC</a> Memory Cards</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26436513541/in/dateposted/" title="Boot-packing up"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1490/26436513541_8e1264ac4b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Boot-packing up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Getting that all in can be a real Tetris-like experience, especially if the Hut-to-Hut stuff comes in, too! And of course, depending on where I am out, also a map, compass and a watch with GPS &amp; Altimeter are along.</p>

<h2 id="layering-for-ski-touring">Layering for ski-touring</h2>

<p>Layering for ski-touring is much like <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">layering for winter</a>. I wear a thin baselayer, thin midlayers, if it is cold an insulation vest, and depending on the weather either a softshell or a hardshell top &amp; bottom. I try to only take either shell layer along to save weight &amp; space, but depending on the weather forecast can be a bit risky. The underneath garments have proven themselves and work very well for me and I can recommend each piece. Besides that they also are comfortabl and look cool on photos.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26410122282/in/dateposted/" title="Norrøna Lyngen Softshell Combo + Alpha Vest"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1531/26410122282_da2b778669_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Norrøna Lyngen Softshell Combo + Alpha Vest" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I wear the following layers:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/icebreaker-anatomica-boxers-merinounterwaesche/">Icebreaker Anatomica Boxers</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1Qh7wNa">Icebreaker Ski+ Compression Light Socks</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/ortovox-merino-ultra-105-long-sleeve-merinounterwaesche/">Ortovox Merino Ultra 105 Long Sleeve</a> and <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/ortovox-merino-ultra-105-short-pants-merinounterwaesche/">Ortovox Merino Ultra 105 Short Pants</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/northern-playground-ziplongs-3-4-aktiv/">Northern Playground Ziplongs 3/4</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1MCKvd1">Arc’teryx Konseal 3/4-Zip Fleece Hoodie</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/norrona-lyngen-alpha-weste-cool-black-xl/?pid=81">Norrøna Lyngen Alpha Vest</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1TeiTdD">Norrøna Lyngen Driflex3 Jacket</a> &amp; <a href="http://bit.ly/1Smofn1">Norrøna Lyngen Driflex3 Pant</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/26a6Rcd">Arc’teryx Tantalus Jacket</a> &amp; <a href="http://bit.ly/1Ni09KQ">Arc’teryx Stinger Pants</a></li>
  <li>G3 Beanie, <a href="http://amzn.to/20PwNWC">Merino Buff</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1S4XRPx">Scott Obsess ACS Sunglasses</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1Smpdzw">PIEPS DPS Pro Ice</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/hestra-army-leather-heli-ski-3-finger-handschuhe/">Hestra Army Leather Heli Ski 3 Finger Gloves</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/20PvcAj">Sony RX 100 IV</a></li>
  <li>Spare <a href="http://amzn.to/1VcUSHm">battery for the camera</a>, a spare <a href="http://amzn.to/1Tek0Kg">SanDisk Extreme 64GB SDXC</a> &amp; a small cloth to clean the camera lens &amp; sunglasses</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26476494246/in/dateposted/" title="Merino Baselayers &lt;3"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1632/26476494246_ab30b87172_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Merino Baselayers &lt;3" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26410127562/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Hardshell Combo, PIEPS and accessories"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1443/26410127562_7e955d451b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Hardshell Combo, PIEPS and accessories" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-hut-to-hut-extras">The Hut-to-Hut Extras</h2>

<p>My Hut-to-Hut Extras include a silk inlet which I bought many years ago, as it is more hygienic and is wished for by hut owners, and some spare clothes. While I maintain the principle that I’m on a ski-tour and not on a fashion show it is nice to switch into dry and non-smelly clothes after a day on the mountain. I usually switch into dry underwear, socks and put on the shirt, while wearing the Northern Playground Ziplongs. I pack it all in an <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/eagle-creek-pack-it-specter-quarter-cube-white-strobe/?pid=81">Eagle Creek Pack-It Specter Quarter Cube</a> which fits well into my pack, right between the ION ski crampons.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/cocoon-inlett-ripstop-seide-101399?utm_source=PTID13002584">Cocoon Ripstop-Silk Inlet</a></li>
  <li>Minimalist Hygiene Set</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/icebreaker-tech-lite-ss-crewe-in-session-cyan-m/?pid=81">Icebreaker Tech Lite SS Crewe T-Shirt</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/icebreaker-anatomica-boxers-rocket-lunar-s/?pid=81">Icebraker Anatomica Boxers</a> &amp; <a href="http://bit.ly/20PGYdQ">Smartwool Hike Ultra Light Crew socks</a></li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26436340911/in/dateposted/" title="The Minimalist Hut-to-Hut Kit"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1565/26436340911_2f697920ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Minimalist Hut-to-Hut Kit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-camping-extras">The Camping Extras</h2>

<p>Sometimes you just want to pitch the tent on the summit, take the stove out and watch the stars and Northern Lights. Depending on the need of the tent it can be <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">lighter</a> or heavier, but what’s sure is that I need a larger backpack to carry it and the other kit! We’re having this planned for next week up north in Lyngen, so stay tuned on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> for a <em>“tent on summit under Northern Lights”</em> shot. </p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/helsport-reinsfjell-x-trem-2-2-personenzelt/">Helsport Reinsfjell X-Trem 2</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">Therm-A-Rest XTherm</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/01/katabatic-gear-sawatch-quilt.html">Katabatic Gear Sawatch quilt</a> or lighter</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.campsaver.com/windburner-1-0l-stove-system">MSR Windburner Stove</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/primus-winter-gas.html">Primus Winter Gas</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.outdoorfoodshop.de">Food</a>, cacao and a <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/Kueche/Sea-to-Summit-Alpha-Light-Spork-lang::967.html">long spoon</a></li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25897550004/in/dateposted/" title="The Bombproof Winter Summit Camp"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1583/25897550004_9764322026_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Bombproof Winter Summit Camp" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="at-basecamp">At Basecamp</h2>

<p>Often my ski-touring trips also involve staying in a town, which means after a day on the mountain I can jump into the Sauna, eat some tasty food and drink a beer. I usually have an extra nice-looking shirt along (the <a href="https://www.norrona.com/en-GB/Products/3360-14/1011/falketind-long-sleeve-shirt-m/">Norrøna falketind Longsleeve</a> is a favourite), but otherwise I wear the clothes I am also travelling in (usually an <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/houdini-thrill-twill-pants-jeans/">Houdini Thrill Twill Pants</a> or the <a href="http://amzn.to/1SpbZoV">Icebreaker Seeker Pants</a> and the awesome <a href="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=cc&amp;cpid=1&amp;subid=SkiPackList&amp;target=https://www.bergfreunde.de/ortovox-rnw-cool-double-check-shirt-long-sleeve-hemd/?_$ja=tsid:52154">Ortovox R’N’W Cool Double Check Shirt</a>). If you’re into Aprés skiing you probably wanna take more, I myself am happy to read a book and go to sleep reasonably early!</p>

<p>So, that’s my ski-touring packing list. A versatile list that uses only two pieces of check-in luggage - with some packing magic I also can get everything into the DOuchebag, but then it can get close to the 23 kg weight limit on most flights. The Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle also packs nicely down over the wheels of the Douchebag which means I can pull both bags, and the BD pack comes along as a carry-on. <strong>Happy travelling &amp; skiing!</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26436341961/in/dateposted/" title="Douchebag Fully packed"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1541/26436341961_f9caa28084_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Douchebag Fully packed" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I bought some of the gear in this article while other itmes were sent for free for testing to me. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 234]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/twir-234.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-17T23:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/twir-234</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Why buy two pieces of gear when one will do the work of both?”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1W9ww06">Yvon Chouinard</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26114793580/in/dateposted/" title="Please Leave Gate As Found"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1465/26114793580_d57a3662c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Please Leave Gate As Found" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://builtbyswift.com/swiftcampout/">Swift Campout 2016</a> is coming in the end of June - start planning an adventure with your bike!</p>

<p>Help <a href="http://www.ilovebialowieza.com">protect the Białowieża Forest in Poland</a>.</p>

<p>The new <a href="http://www.mountainpromag.com/imag/mproapril2016/">Mountain Pro Mag</a> is out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.patagonia.com/eu/deLU/worn-wear">Patagonia Worn Wear</a> comes to Europe this spring.</p>

<p>No more hippies and explorers: <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/bike-blog/2016/apr/12/no-more-hippies-and-explorers-lament-for-the-changed-world-of-cycling">a lament for the changed world of cycling</a>. Or has <a href="http://singletrackworld.com/columns/2016/04/technical-difficulties-has-cycling-lost-its-wild-side/">cycling lost its wild side</a>?</p>

<p>Hiking in Finland has made the <a href="http://www.happytosurvive.com/camping/best-backpacking-hiking-websites-of-all-time/">Top 40 of the 151 Best Backpacking &amp; Hiking Blogs</a>. Yay!</p>

<p>Have you seen the <a href="http://bit.ly/1VtoWOP">Hyperlight Mountain Gear Kits</a> yet? They’re great to get started on the ultralight path!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/2064481/david-morton-and-ghosts-everest">Dave Morton Is Quitting Everest. Maybe.</a></p>

<p>Try <a href="http://www.jpegmini.com/pro">JPEGmini</a> for free and minimize the sizes of your photos without decreasing their quality.</p>

<p><a href="https://gearjunkie.com/eastern-mountain-sports-bankruptcy">Eastern Mountain Sports may be headed for bankruptcy</a>.</p>

<p>Want to <a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2016/04/packrafting-testfahrten-in-dresden-der.html">test-paddle a packraft before buying</a>? That’s possible at the Packrafting shop in Dresden!</p>

<p><a href="http://enormocast.com/episode102-rebecca-rusch-once-a-climber-always-a-climber/">Once a Climber, Always a Climber</a>.</p>

<p>Campsaver has up to <a href="http://bit.ly/1VasRjt">30% off on selected tents</a>.</p>

<p>And at Backcountry you can get up to <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3482&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR234">30% off on Black Diamond and Free 2-Day Shipping</a>.</p>

<p>Need a <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/p/merinowolle/kategorie--outdoor-bekleidung/?pid=10239">new Merino shirt</a>? Bergfreunde have you covered with cool new styles &amp; colours.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR234"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg?ctc=TWIR234" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>James hikes from <a href="http://jmbarlow.com/blog/cape-wrath-trail-part-3/">Shiel Bridge to Craig</a> on the Cape Wrath Trail.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2016/04/pre-empting-springtime-slump.html">Pre-empting the springtime slump</a>.</p>

<p>Brian enjoys the <a href="http://www.skimolife.com/journal/2016/4/11/alaska-spring-and-type-ii-fun.html">Alaska Spring and Type II Fun</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://climbinghouse.com/2016/04/colors-of-the-red-river-gorge.html">Colors of the Red River Gorge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://andyhouseman.blogspot.fi/2016/04/link-sar-better-late-than-never.html">Link Sar</a>.</p>

<p>Traversing the <a href="http://sehn-suchtberge.blogspot.fi/2016/03/skitour-martelltal-butzenspitze.html">Butzenspitze</a>. [German]</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/llufipzI8_k" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2016/04/the-dirtbags-guide-to-squamish/">Dirtbag Guide to Squamish</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://runrideandsleepoutside.wordpress.com/2016/04/10/whatever-floats-your-boat/">Whatever floats your boat</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://tarmachan.blogspot.fi/2016/04/blog-post_11.html">Alpine conditions in Scotland</a> - looks like winter is still in some places!</p>

<p>A visit to the <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/griessbachklamm-klammwanderung-mit-kindern/">Grießbachklamm</a>. [German]</p>

<p>And Eric reports from the <a href="http://epiceric.blogspot.fi/2016/04/2016-winter-wilderness-ski-classic.html">2016 Winter Wilderness Ski Classic</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GD6dLzsNPh4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Isko shows how the <a href="http://iskosalminen.com/2016/3/16/hmg-ultamid-size-comparison">HMG UltaMid 2 and UltaMid 4</a> compare in size.</p>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/la-sportiva-spectre.html">La Sportiva Spectre Review</a>.</p>

<p>Alex’s <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/04/gear-list-west-highland-way-alder-trail-skye-trail.html">Scotland 2016 gear list</a>.</p>

<p>Ortlieb <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/gear/ortlieb-seat-pack-review/">Seat-Pack Review</a>.</p>

<p>Helen reviews the <a href="http://helenstakeon.com/gear/review-cumulus-lite-line-200-down-sleeping-bag/">Cumulus Lite Line 200 Down Sleeping Bag</a>.</p>

<p>An <a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/arizona-trail-bikepacking-rig/">Arizona Trail Bikepacking Rig</a>.</p>

<p>Chris reviews the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/the-vertical-life-climbing-app-2-0-reviewed/">Vertical-Life Climbing App</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2016/04/the-pleasure-of-maps.html">The Pleasure of Maps</a>.</p>

<p>Roger is <a href="https://nielsenbrown.com/2016/04/14/rethinking-navigation/">rethinking navigation</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plan/traveling-tubeless-guide/">Guide to travelling Tubeless</a>.</p>

<p>Long-term review of the <a href="http://www.outdoorsfather.com/2016/04/elemental-horizons-kalais/">Elemental Horizons Kalais Backpack</a>.</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183&amp;ctc=TWIR234"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg?ctc=TWIR234" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[La Sportiva Spectre]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/la-sportiva-spectre.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-14T23:51:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/la-sportiva-spectre</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ski-touring, that’s walking - skinning in skiing terms - the mountain up and then skiing it down. It’s a great way to enjoy the mountains in winter and has similarities to hiking. But much unlike the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">light trailrunners</a> I use from spring till autumn, in winter you need a ski boot. Happily I found after much research &amp; pondering a boot which is light and performs great on the way up &amp; down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26149591360/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="La Sportiva Spectre, ready for skiing"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1447/26149591360_9f3fcceb75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="La Sportiva Spectre, ready for skiing" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I bought the Spectre after much research last November from the Bergfreunde, and have used it ski-touring in Canada, Finland, Austria, Switzerland and South Tyrol since, all in all over 20 days. It coming along to Lyngen next week, too!</p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>A ski-touring boot has two modes: A Walk mode for skinning up the mountain and a ski-mode to come down again. The walk mode gives you freedom of movement for sliding the ski forward while you skin up, and the ski mode makes the boot stiff so you can transfer your power onto the binding and ski.  Normal Alpine Skiing boots miss the walk feature, and while you might be able to skin up short sections for serious ascents you want a <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/tourenskischuhe/">ski boot</a> with a walk mode. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25184029286/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="At the start of the ski-tour"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1495/25184029286_5212fe5fdc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the start of the ski-tour" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>As told by La Sportiva, the Spectre comes with these features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>4 Buckles plus optional Power Strap</li>
  <li>60° Range of Motion</li>
  <li>120 Flex</li>
  <li>3 preset Forward Lean options: 10°, 14° and 18°</li>
  <li>Tech and AT Bindings compatible</li>
  <li>Dynafit inserts</li>
  <li>Rockered Vibram Sole</li>
  <li>Carbon Reinforced Grilamid Vertebra</li>
  <li>Marfram Spoiler</li>
  <li>Pebax Cuff</li>
  <li>Grilamid Shell</li>
  <li>Sole length xxx mm in MP 26.5</li>
  <li>Dual Density EZ Thermo liner</li>
  <li>And it is Made in Italy</li>
</ul>

<p>In the box you’ll find besides the boots two optional laces which allow you to get a tighter fit of the liner on your foot, two insoles, a few patches and tools.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26149575060/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="The La Sportiva Spectres"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1549/26149575060_5387ff101d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="776" alt="The La Sportiva Spectres" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The Pegasus Buckles, which are flat when open which means they don’t snag on stuff close to your feet, and can comfortably be worn underneath your pants, are great. The buckles on my other ski-touring boot don’t lay flat so these are definitely more convenient in use. Additionally you can Micro-adjust the buckles for a perfect fit. The very low weight for a four-buckle boot is also a great achievement by La Sportiva.</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>I haven’t been easy on the boots, and they have flown several thousands of miles across the globe in my <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/douchebag-the-douchebag-skitasche-pitch-black/?pid=81">Douchebag</a>, skied and skinned thousands of meters, climbed ice in them and walked through town in them, and they still look good and only have minor scratches.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25892325271/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Anselm leading the way"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1596/25892325271_eaa15fdc8c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Anselm leading the way" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Size 26.5 Spectres weigh with liner 1374 g, that’s 240 g for the liner boot and 1134 g for the shell. The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/arcteryx-procline-carbon-lite-ski-boot.html">Arc’teryx Procline Carbon Lite Ski Boot</a> is lighter, but I haven’t used it yet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25105375706/in/album-72157664672954972/" title="I like crust, but I only like it on Crème brûlée"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1676/25105375706_0f539523c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I like crust, but I only like it on Crème brûlée" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p><em>My experience is based on skiing the Spectre with <a href="http://bit.ly/22PDNaU">DPS Wailer 99 Tour1 Skis</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/20DPCfk">G3 ION 12 Bindings</a>.</em></p>

<p>There’s plenty of opinions on the Spectre - from people that really dislike the boot to ones that love it, and everything in between. There’s two things why I don’t love the boot outright: And that are the two blisters on my feet. After hiking in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/inov-8-trailroc-235.html">Trailrunners</a> for over seven years, climbing in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx.html">Mountaineering boots</a> for four and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">XC skiing</a> in good boots since six years I haven’t had blisters anymore. But on my second ski-touring trip this year to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/ski-touring-south-tyrol-and-salzburger-lungau.html">South Tyrol</a> and Salzburger Lungau, on the second day blisters appeared on the inside of my ankles. Compeed helped in allowing me to ski the next few weeks, but even after the blister healed they were there again after a day of skiing on the next trip. Blisters are no fun, and while I happily bite my teeth together and continue to wear the boots I think I either will need to go with them to a good boot fitter (which, sadly, we don’t have in Vaasa) or try my hand at modifying the boot on my own; and as it is made from Grilamid which tends to hold its shape once punched (unlike Pebax, another plastic which is often used in the construction of ski boots) that might be a good option too. These problems came after moulding the liner twice and the shell once, by the way. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26149572410/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Liner &amp; insole"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1650/26149572410_5f4caf3e9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Liner &amp; insole" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Getting into the boot is easy for me, I have narrow feet and wear medium-thickness to thin skiing socks, and the shell has a medium to narrow heel fit, a narrow instep and has a medium forefoot last. The top buckles can be moved out of the way for easily getting in (and out) of the boot. After a day of touring getting out of the boot needs a bit of pulling - nothing difficult, though, and if I open all buckles it’s super-simple to get out. It’s recommended to play around with the boot and find the right adjustments for your style of skiing, and as the Spectre allows a host of possibilities to adjust it to your foot &amp; style - take the time to do it, you will have more fun in the long-run. Stepping in to the pin-binding of your choice is easy thanks to the two indicators on each side of the boot, these make it easy to align the boot with the pins and then push down so they snap into the fittings.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26422447775/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Aligned"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1553/26422447775_1186807e11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Aligned" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Other reviewers seem to take issues with the buckles. Yes, they’re different: You can micro-adjust them to your needs via the screw, and it takes some learning to get the hole placed over the stud - and it won’t snap over it unless you get the alignment correctly. I didn’t have any issues with them and found the system easy, and you can even adjust the buckles when you’re in the boot. I really liked the low profile buckle design which fits perfectly under the ski pants and does provide a cleaner profile &amp; prevents trees, rocks and stuff from catching the buckles, which protects them from being damaged and makes them last longer.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25817622514/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Open buckle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1518/25817622514_29135f20d5_n.jpg" width="320" height="213" alt="Open buckle" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25819650923/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Putting the buckle in place"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1446/25819650923_a4756db229_n.jpg" width="320" height="213" alt="Putting the buckle in place" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26422432205/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="And closed"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1495/26422432205_8f4a45879b_n.jpg" width="320" height="213" alt="And closed" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Liner is warm and I never had cold feet in them. I needed to add the included lacing for them to move less on my foot while touring. It has a flex zone that helps in touring mode. The two loops at the front and back make it easy to pull the boot on. The liner keeps your sweaty feet smell well, so if you’re a connoisseur of such things you’re in luck. Otherwise you might want to dry and air them well before taking them in. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25819639613/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Liner, inside"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1450/25819639613_a69bbc59f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Liner, inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The sticky rubber sole is great and allows for great grip when scrambling or walking in town and slippery ski stations. The yellow areas at the toe and heel are more durable, and the higher arch minimizes snow-build-up in my experience. The Spectre is crampons compatible and my <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-xlc-470-steigeisen/">CAMP XLC Crampons</a> are a great companion with them and make for an ultralight ski-mountaineering setup.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26396490096/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Spectre Sole"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1559/26396490096_22cc45afd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Spectre Sole" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26330101312/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="With Crampons, Side view"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1546/26330101312_97fe6ee3ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="With Crampons, Side view" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Alright, so getting in the boot is all swell, skinning up is great because the boot is light with a great range of motion, but what about switching into ski mode at the wind-blasted summit and the descent? I’m happy to report that it takes only a minute, it at all, to close all buckles and switch the boot into ski mode and if you have a wide ski pants you can even do it while the pants and snow-gaiter are down over the buckles (I have been using a <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/norroena-lyngen-driflex3-pants-hardshellhose/">Norrøna Lyngen softshell pants</a> and a <a href="http://www.arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;collection=Whiteline&amp;model=Stinger-Pant">Arc’teryx Stinger Pants</a> which both allowed to do this). Fussing around with boots at a windy &amp; cold summit is no fun, even less if you need to take the gloves off, and with the Spectre I was quickly ready to ski down. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26330086312/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Walk"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1560/26330086312_3bf75c533d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Walk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26149582890/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Lean back"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1467/26149582890_7fb38ed8d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lean back" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I found the Spectre a stiff boot when tightly buckled down for the descent, and find it has good control and power transmission that could easily control my fat DPS Wailers on almost all snow conditions (hard, icy slopes in resorts are tough and my skis started flutter, but that’s another story). Buckled down the boot still had plenty of room in the toe box for warm toes, I haven’t experienced any shin bang which I thank the Booster Strap for, and the black EZ Flex area on the tongue gives a nice flex in downhill mode. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25817614954/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Open!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1592/25817614954_1d2f98d371_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Open!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Some 20+ days are not really yet enough to give a comment on durability, so I will save that for a later time. But what’s worth discussing is the price of the Spectre. If you have read till here you might think that such a lightweight, innovative boot probably must cost a little fortune. Well, it does not. The regular, recommended price is around 490€ - but thanks to never-ending sales you can pick up the Spectre for as little as 370€. Even at the recommended price it’s an affordable ski boot, and if you can get it with a discount it is a lot cheaper than many other boots.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26396493176/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Outside"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1600/26396493176_9a9a38a9e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>La Sportiva decided to update the Spectre for 2016/ 2017, which should address some of the issues described above and allow for even more customization. Even if I try hard, I can not imagine something to complain about this boot - I think the blisters are something that just happened and because I want to keep these boot it is something I need to find a way to solve &amp; life with.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a wide variety of <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/tourenskischuhe/">ski-touring boot</a> available, I myself also own the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/scarpa/tourenskischuhe/">Scarpa Maestrale RS</a>, and many people like the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/dynafit-tlt-6-mountain-cr-tourenskischuhe/">Dynafit TLT 6</a>. In the end you should follow my final advice in the bottomline when it comes to buying boots.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26356257591/in/album-72157666988623142/" title="Spectre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1505/26356257591_719db2aea1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Spectre" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I decided the buy the Spectre because it is the lightest four buckle boot and would allow me an easier time on the way up - where I’d need to move the 1374 g per foot hundreds of times - and great control on the way down. So far it has performed great, and aside from the blisters which I hope to solve with some punches on the shell I imagine the boot will accompany for the next few ski-touring seasons. The Spectre is comfortable &amp; light on the way up and performs great on the way down, especially in powder. I love the low buckle design as they fit very well under my ski pants, the comfortable walking in town, and the cool look of the boot is also something I don’t get tired of. The light weight also make them good for climbing, be it rock or ice. Add in the amazing price and you have a boot which I am very happy with!</p>

<p><em>But the ultimate Bottomline for ski-boots is simple: If the boot fits and is comfortable, buy it. You might have the luck that your feet fit the Spectre out of the box, or they might not suit you at all - the general wisdom for ski boots is to buy a boot that fits you well, because everything else might end up in pain.</em></p>

<p>Check the over 40 detailed photos of the boot from all angles on the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157666988623142">La Sportiva Spectre Album</a>. </p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>As most shops are getting ready for summer you can get the La Sportiva Spectre currently with some good discounts. The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/la-sportiva-spectre-touring-ski-boots/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a> have them 25% reduced right now, and at <a href="http://bit.ly/1SxWcR7">Backcountry.com</a> they’re 35% off.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25210335485/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="Looking down"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1591/25210335485_b733a6734c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Looking down" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I bought the La Sportiva Spectre with my own money but got a wee discount from Bergfreunde. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 233]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/twir-233.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-10T23:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/twir-233</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Do not seek pleasure for its own sake.”</em>  ― <a href="http://amzn.to/221BFHo">Miyamoto Musashi</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25736343534/in/dateposted/" title="Albert ripping it!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1584/25736343534_f07a20c1bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert ripping it!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/business/currency/in-the-future-we-will-photograph-everything-and-look-at-nothing">In the future we photograph everything and look at nothing</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.fi/2016/04/funf-ultraleicht-tips-fur-anfanger.html">Five Ultralight Tips for Beginners</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.snewsnet.com/news/editors-note-in-celebration-of-outdoor-women/">In celebration of outdoor women</a>.</p>

<p>Alex reviews <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/04/review-life-of-a-mountain-blencathra-by-terry-abraham.html">Life of a Mountain: Blencathra</a>.</p>

<p>Why <a href="http://bunterwegs.com/warum-bunterwegs-sich-an-frauen-richtet/">Bunterwegs for women is</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Win the <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/news-and-media/mother-of-bikepacking-kits/">Mother of all Bikepacking Kits</a>.</p>

<p>On the <a href="http://www.shanecycles.com/how-a-lchf-lifestyle-changed-my-life/">merits of a Low Carb Healthy Fat diet for cycle touring</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/setting-and-revising-the-record-in-climbing/">Setting and Revising the Record in Climbing</a>.</p>

<p>Backcountry has a <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Big Brands Sale with up to 30% Off on Patagonia, Marmot &amp; Black Diamond</a> and Free 2-Day Shipping.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/info/kooperationen/skandinavische-wochen-2016/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Scandinavian weeks at Globetrotter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://unclippedadventure.com/wp/the-next-big-bicycle-adventure-begins/">The Announcement</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mcalisterium.wordpress.com/2016/04/07/annoyed-art/">Annoyed Art</a>.</p>

<p>Mike is <a href="https://mikesee.exposure.co/fat-n-happy">Fat ‘N Happy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">Winter Adventures in Finnish Lapland</a>.</p>

<p>Phil starts his <a href="http://philsorrell.com/2016/04/04/sun-sea-storm-katie-and-a-massive-mis-calculation-the-start-to-countycastlecaper/">#CountyCastleCaper</a> Tour.</p>

<p>Pieta was <a href="http://racewithwind.blogspot.fi/2016/04/viikko-gotlannissa-2016.html">a week on Gotland</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p>A beautiful weekend on <a href="https://beatingthebounds.wordpress.com/2016/04/04/meall-a-choire-leith-and-meall-corranaich/">Meall a’Choire Leith and Meall Corranaich</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/158773447?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;badge=0" width="500" height="208" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Michelle is <a href="http://www.shinimichi.com/2015/08/high-coast-hike-in-sweden-day-i.html">setting off into Skuleskogen National Park</a> on the High Coast Hike.</p>

<p>Same place, two days, two different worlds: <a href="http://www.oooyeah.de/suedtirol-schnalstal/">A Weekend in the Schnalstal</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/trans-uganda/">The Trans-Uganda</a>.</p>

<p>David was <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2016/4/4/a-winter-round-in-spring">out in spring and encountered winter</a>.</p>

<p>A cool ski-tour on the <a href="http://www.alpin-blog.com/skihochtour-aletschhorn/">Aletsch­horn</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Kathrin gets ready for <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/regentage-schlafsacknaechte/">her biggest adventure yet</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.twistingspokes.com/tribal-jungles-to-himalayan-hillstations/">Tribal jungles to Himalayan hillstations</a>.</p>

<p>Skitouring to the <a href="http://sehn-suchtberge.blogspot.fi/2016/03/skitour-martelltal-vertainspitze.html">Plattenspitze and Vertainspitze</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.williswall.com/willis-wall-blog/2016/4/3/how-to-sample-mt-rainier-np-in-short-segments">How to Experience Mt. Rainier NP in Short Segments</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25738443973/in/dateposted/" title="Tools of joy!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1598/25738443973_d7b1af966a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tools of joy!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="https://hikeminded.wordpress.com/2016/04/06/gear-review-camp-shoes/">Ultralight Camp Shoes</a>.</p>

<p>Andy reviews the <a href="http://www.andyhowell.info/trek-blog/2016/04/05/long-term-review-tarptent-stratospire-2/">Tarptent Stratospire 2</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/porcelain-rocket-mr-fusion-review/">Porcelain Rocket Mr. Fusion Review</a>.</p>

<p>Kevin reviews the <a href="https://climbinggearreviewsuk.wordpress.com/2016/04/06/jottnar-vanir-lt-pants/">Jöttnar Vanir LT Pants</a>.</p>

<p>A look at the <a href="https://ulgearblog.com/2016/04/04/featured-gear-dutchware-gear-sit-pad/">Dutchware Gear Sit Pad</a>.</p>

<p>Sven tests the <a href="http://www.aufundab.eu/test/schweizer-design-trifft-laufschuh-trifft-performance-cloudflyer">ON Cloudflyer</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://lesserplaces.wordpress.com/2016/04/05/the-arcteryx-bora-mid-one-million-step-review-514061-step-update/">The Arc’teryx Bora Mid One Million Step Review: 514,061 Step Update</a>.</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=462153&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/13582/462153/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Off The Road]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/off-the-road.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-08T23:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/off-the-road</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You like to go outdoors and love a tricked out van or off-road vehicle to get there? Then <em>Off the Road</em> is the book for you - but careful, you might want to sell your house and move into a van!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26210796662/in/dateposted/" title="Off the Road Cover"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1665/26210796662_6361a93f26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Off the Road Cover" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I don’t have a driving license. We don’t own a car. And yet I like the idea of living in a van or tricked-out off-road vehicle. Hence <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/off-the-road.html">Off the Road</a> is such an appealing book. On over 250 pages and even more photos you get inspiration for your own #VanLife. Are you an BMW Enduro kind of guy, or an VW T4 aficionado? Does your heart beat for adventure off the beaten track in a Toyota Land Cruiser or do you prefer to have an adventure-ready trailer behind your car? This book illuminates people from all these roads &amp; more, with inspiring stories of people who rode from the most southern point in Florida to the most northerly point in Alaska or who crossed Russia from the west to the east. </p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/144480827?byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>But it has not only such adventurous expeditions in it, also more achievable #VanLife stories are in the book - things you can realize at the weekend or during your summer holidays. Like going to the beach with your trailer for a lonely weekend at the sea, or taking your van with the surfboards on top for a trip to search the best waves. There’s a bunch of vans, cars, trailers, motorcycles and off-road vehicle depicted in the book, complete with technical information and how to make them even more off-road worthy for your next big (or small) trip. Inspiration for how to renovate the interior of your van, why an Unimog still is one of the greatest All-terrain vehicles, and how you can transform your van into a mobile office which allows you from anywhere. </p>

<p>And the appeal also comes through to me, who is generally opposed to motorized outdoor activities. I could imagine trading the house for a small van, drive around the world and have a new view to wake up to each morning. Where I can sit in front of the car and drink a coffee, sit by the camp fire and watch the stars before going laying down on a comfortable bed, and which would allow me to just put on the skis in the morning and skin up a mountain. Of course I’d first need to get a driving license to do that =) But if you have one, and it sounds like a good life to you, pick up this book and be inspired by what is possible. Great photos and stories most likely will make you think if you really need a house, or if a nice off-road vehicle or van wouldn’t suffice for a life off the road!</p>

<p>You can support me and buy this book at one of the following affiliate links - at no extra costs for you. <a href="http://amzn.to/1qbfFgW">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1S6UkSB">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1S6WEZL">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26210796292/in/dateposted/" title="Off the Road Inside"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1708/26210796292_ac7aee5ac8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Off the Road Inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Gestalten sent me the book for review. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hetta: Winter Adventures in Finnish Lapland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-04T23:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friendly, calm and lots to do: Hetta in Finnish Lapland is an ideal place if you want to enjoy winter holidays without hustle &amp; bustle. <em>A Winter Trip Report.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26057151772/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Pyhäkero in blue &amp; white 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1528/26057151772_de1f89e375_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pyhäkero in blue &amp; white 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="hetta">Hetta</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi">Hetta</a> is in the far, far north of Finland and that means: Lots of snow, crispy cold temperatures, Northern Lights and beautiful sunny days in spring. Last year we spent our winter holiday in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Pyhä</a> and this year we decided to visit another small and family-friendly town: Hetta. Right in the heart of Lapland it is located at the top of the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/pallas-yllastunturinp">Pallas-Yllästunturi National Park</a> and the starting point of the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/hettapallashikingtrail">Hetta-Pallas Trail</a> which you can ski in winter or hike in the summer. <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/poyrisjarvi">Pöyrisjärvi Wilderness Area</a> and <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/tarvantovaara">Tarvantovaara Wilderness Area</a> are right around the corner, and it isn’t far to Norway, either - which makes it an ideal base camp for outdoor and nature lovers in summer &amp; winter.</p>

<p>It has all that a winter enthusiast needs: Cafés &amp; <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/services/restaurants/">Restaurants</a>, various <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/accommodation/">accommodation options</a>, a supermarket and various other shops, the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/felllaplandvisitorcentre">Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</a> and lots of stuff to do, from skiing on the local hill to enjoying the silence on a Husky Sled ride. With six days in Hetta we had plenty of time to try various <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/things-to-do/winter/">activities</a> and experience what the town has to offer.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546943983/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Sunshine!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1646/25546943983_f5b7a882b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunshine!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outside-with-hetta-huskies">Outside with Hetta Huskies</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.hettahuskies.com/en">Hetta Huskies</a> are probably one of the most well-known companies from Hetta, and if you meet the dogs, owners and Guides it is clear why: The dogs are lovely and will make your trip unforgettable, while the owners Pasi &amp; Anna with their friendly, international staff of Guides will ensure you have a great experience - be it just a few hours or a week!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26122490546/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hetta Huskies"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1550/26122490546_2d432ac709_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hetta Huskies" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We were with the whole family - my four year old son, baby, wife and me - on the <a href="http://www.hettahuskies.com/en/activities/single-day-safaris">Silent Landscapes</a> Safari, in which you get a tour of the Farm, meet the dogs, get instructed on how to ride the sleigh and then are off into the winter wonderland for around 45 minutes. It’s was a great and interesting experience that we all enjoyed, especially our son thought it was a lot of fun (the baby slept!). We were accompanied by a guide who stayed mostly away but helped when the need arose - we had a small change in the configuration of dogs, for example. After I got instructed in riding the sleigh the family sat down and then we were off to the mires. I always love to explore swamps in winter, their vast area and wide views are beautiful to behold and in winter you can explore them without mosquitos and wet feet. We could see the distant fjells of the National Park, rode through the forest and loved the silence of nature. We could have gone much longer - and the dogs, too! - but after 45 minutes we were back at the farm where we helped bringing the dogs back to their compounds and said thanks for their great service!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25545774183/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hi there!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1624/25545774183_6423523d01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hi there!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148429495/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1490/26148429495_885653ee53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875556930/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Through the forest"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1490/25875556930_ccd9bde31b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Through the forest" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875557260/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hi there again!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1646/25875557260_aa5aa4d111_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hi there again!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="a-visit-to-the-hetta-snow-castle">A visit to the Hetta Snow Castle</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nakkala.com">Näkkälä Eräpalvelut</a> offers visits to their Snow Castle which is a short 20 minute snowmobile ride over the frozen lake away from Hetta. The castle is open from the end of November and still stands there in the end of June and with walls several meters thick that’s no surprise! The kids loved it and it is easy to understand why they were fascinated by the ice castle: Consisting of three domed rooms they were adorned with ice sculptures, an ice bar and tables as well as a frozen bed! You can sleep in the ice castle, too! After exploring the snow castle for a while we had hot juice and then it was again back to Hetta in the sleigh. A great activity for the morning or afternoon after which you might find yourself again outside trying to build your own snow igloo!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082084491/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Entering the Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1588/26082084491_3c4f638e8e_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Entering the Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082084791/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="At the Bar in the Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1466/26082084791_1836e001fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the Bar in the Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25543654324/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Cold as ice!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1512/25543654324_9b04cb2c86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cold as ice!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082086091/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="The Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1539/26082086091_c298c5a23f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875554680/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Back to Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1566/25875554680_fbdf050119_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back to Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="skiing-at-hetta-hiihtomaa">Skiing at Hetta Hiihtomaa</h2>

<p>If you <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">follow me on Instagram</a> you probably have realized that I have been ski-touring a lot this winter. <a href="http://www.hettahiihtomaa.fi">Hetta Hiihtomaa</a> is the local skiing hill and we took the chance for our son to learn a bit of skiing and I too took a ride in the lift up to go down through the snow-covered forest. The service at Hetta Hiihtomaa was superb, the two Gentlemen were super-friendly and helpful with <a href="http://www.hettahiihtomaa.fi/p/valinevuokraus.html">loaning the gear</a> and sharing local knowledge. Besides the lift and ski-rental there’s also a Café, a big sledding hill and a illuminated XC Loipe. The prizes are very affordable when compared to the large ski areas, and the people and kids all had a lot of fun on the slopes or off-piste. Hetta Hiihtomaa has also a small beginner’s hill which is excellent for learning to ski, and I can totally recommend the sledding hill, too! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25486428803/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Learning to ski at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1654/25486428803_d47754d6f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to ski at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25816133670/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Backcountry fun on Jyppyrä, Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1675/25816133670_564e5094cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Backcountry fun on Jyppyrä, Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26022665581/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Sledding fun at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1526/26022665581_f882f141b8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Sledding fun at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="ski-touring-into-the-white--out-at-nkklvaara">Ski-touring into the White (-Out) at Näkkälävaara</h2>

<p>What I like more than skiing at a resort is going into the backcountry, and I was fortunate enough to go out for a morning with Riikka from <a href="http://www.wildriver.fi">Wild River Nature Adventures</a>. We decided it’d be a good idea to go to Näkkälä, a tiny village some 30 minutes from Hetta, where we’d tour up to the local fjell, Näkkälävaara. It’s an easy tour with a really cool descent through a birch forest and I had a huge smile on my face after the cool run down! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546895203/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Yay!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1464/25546895203_30c25d623d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yay!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25544790224/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Snowhare vs Skis"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1593/25544790224_06566ed3f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowhare vs Skis" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546918523/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Never trust the weather forecast"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1605/25546918523_63fb03b0c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Never trust the weather forecast" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We started next to one of the few houses and then toured over a narrow lake to the foot of the fjell. It was a cold day and a mist was hanging in the air, which would before long engulf us as we started the climb up the hill. The visibility was soon just a couple dozen metre, and first as we were starting the descent the weather cleared a bit to give a few views price. Nevertheless it was beautiful to tour through the white landscape, with trees hidden under thick covers of snow &amp; ice, arctic hare tracks running across the hill and the wind being the only sound wide &amp; far. At the summit we waited for half an hour for the weather to clear, as you could see till Pyhäkero to the south and the mountains in Norway to the north, as well as the large Pöyrisjärvi lake. Alas, they stayed all hidden! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546929473/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Winter birch forest"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1520/25546929473_13dc3a1b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Winter birch forest" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26057122202/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Fun, fun, fun!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1564/26057122202_1e546f6369_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Fun, fun, fun!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the superb descent we skied along the lake, past the rental cabins of <a href="http://www.nakkala.com/kampat/">Näkkälä Eräpalvelut</a> and to a sacred rock of the Sami, which showed ancient reindeer paintings. Too soon we were back at the car and on our way back to Hetta, where we encountered many reindeer next to the road - and the sun also came out! There’s plenty of great ski-touring around Hetta, from the majestic Pyhäkero to smaller fjells in the area. Grab a map and go out explore!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26083255541/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Drawings"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1601/26083255541_e5e4bc0b53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Drawings" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26123653876/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Reindeers"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1482/26123653876_3da37f61cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reindeers" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="tasty-lappish-food">Tasty Lappish food</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.hetan-majatalo.fi/en">Hotel Hetan Majatalo</a> has every Friday a Lappish Buffet which is super-tasty. Reindeer, salmon, mashed potatoes and a tasty dessert along with a great home-brewed beer it is something you should treat yourself to. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26205517916/in/dateposted/" title="Lappish Buffet at Hetan Majatalo"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1535/26205517916_286bf7a114_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lappish Buffet at Hetan Majatalo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25626691604/in/dateposted/" title="Dessert at Hetan Majatalo"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1460/25626691604_e84413b6a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dessert at Hetan Majatalo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also the buffet at the Lapland Hotel Hetta was very tasty, with a wide variety of salads for startes, wish and meat mains and several sweet desserts. Add in a good selection of wines and beers with great service and you have a great evening!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063083516/in/dateposted/" title="Salad buffet at Lapland Hotel Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1497/26063083516_065d21ef59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salad buffet at Lapland Hotel Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484255534/in/photostream/" title="Main course at Lapland Hotel Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1609/25484255534_00e25051e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Main course at Lapland Hotel Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="enjoying-the-silence-of-xc-skiing">Enjoying the silence of XC skiing</h2>

<p>As we stayed in a cottage next to the lake and there’s around 100 km of skiing tracks (here’s the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/wp-content/uploads/Hetan-alueen-latukartta.pdf">map</a>) going XC skiing is something that you can do any time of the day - even at night, as there’s illuminated tracks, too! I took my son in a Pulka for a few hours of skiing along, which is a great way to be outdoors. XC skiing is relatively easy, you go at a low speed and thus still can experience the nature around you but it’s fast enough to feel good after a few hours outside. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26165151521/in/dateposted/" title="XC Skiing with kids"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1570/26165151521_0a3b0f0504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC Skiing with kids" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25628771613/in/dateposted/" title="Skiing to Hetta across the lake"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1493/25628771613_48dbeaf9c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skiing to Hetta across the lake" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="learning-about-sami-culture-at-the-fell-lapland-visitor-centre">Learning about Sami Culture at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</h2>

<p>If the weather is so bad that you don’t want to be outside, head to the wonderful <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/felllaplandvisitorcentre">Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</a>. It’s open every day of the week, has also a Café with tasty cakes and pastries and the exhibitions are free of charge - hence an ideal way to spend an afternoon. There’s even a very nice children’s corner which our son enjoyed playing at! The main exhibition shows the eight seasons of the Sámi and how their life has changed over the time. To take it all in a couple of hours would be needed I reckon, though it is easy to spend even more time there to also explore the small library and the two other exhibitions.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25996473812/in/dateposted/" title="Tunturi-Lappi Luontokeskus"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1709/25996473812_9c603c6ec6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tunturi-Lappi Luontokeskus" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26089003635/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1704/26089003635_69d533bf44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484241564/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1540/25484241564_7906a223df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484242434/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 3"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1552/25484242434_6eaf72deff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 3" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063074576/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 7"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1624/26063074576_635461a3cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 7" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="more-things-to-see--do">More things to see &amp; do</h2>

<p>Hetta has many other things to offer, from festivals like the Nordic Ice &amp; Snow Sculpture competition at the end of February over regular Nature evenings in the Museum to the <a href="http://saamiskirace.fi">Saami Ski Race</a> in April. You can view the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/events/">events</a> here. There’s also two silver smiths in Hetta which are worth checking out and a church which is architecturally interesting. It’s not far to Kilpisjärvi, either, or you could go for a day trip over to Alta in Norway. If you’re looking for a few days in nature you could ski from Pallas to Hetta through the fjells (or vice versa) and you even can ski onwards to Näkkälä. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25816138370/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Swan snow sculpture in Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1582/25816138370_0439531fd8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swan snow sculpture in Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p>More photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157665518007630">Hetta Photo Album</a>. </p>

<p><strong>Where to stay?</strong></p>

<p>We stayed at the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/ounistieva-en/">Ounistieva Cottage</a> which is a nice cottage a bit out of town right next to the lake. It’s a self-service cottage with a nice wood-heated sauna, a warm wood stove and you can go XC skiing from the doorstep, which is awesome. Cottages are great for families as you can be as loud as you want, the kids can play safely outside in the snow and there’s plenty of space inside. If you prefer something more central then we can recommend the <a href="http://www.hetan-majatalo.fi">Hotel Hetan Majatalo</a> and the <a href="https://www.laplandhotels.com/EN/hotels-in-lapland/hetta/lapland-hotel-hetta.html">Lapland Hotel Hetta</a> which are close to the centre of town and also have their own Restaurants with great food. Their rooms, especially in the Hetan Majatalo, are very cozy and it’s nice to have breakfast &amp; dinner served each evening. There’s several more <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/accommodation/">accommodation options in Hetta</a> for every budget, so have a look around and find what suits you!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26205520136/in/dateposted/" title="Ounistieva Cottage"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1617/26205520136_1638186cfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ounistieva Cottage" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How to get there?</strong></p>

<p>We travelled with a combination of <a href="https://www.vr.fi/cs/vr/fi/etusivu">train</a> and <a href="https://www.sixt.fi">car</a> instead of driving all the way up north, with a night in Rovaniemi on the way up and down - if you have small kids it is more comfortable this way, for everyone really. In the train the kids can play, nap and go easily to the toilet, and the ride from Rovaniemi to Hetta takes only around four hours by car - much better than the 12+ hours of driving it would take from Vaasa! And if you come from abroad - just fly straight to <a href="https://www.finavia.fi/en/enontekio/">Enontekiö Airport</a>! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063067296/in/dateposted/" title="Rush-hour in Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1467/26063067296_97c0b28cc2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rush-hour in Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Thanks to the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi">Enontekiö Region</a> who invited us up north. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 232]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/twir-232.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-03T23:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/twir-232</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“You must understand that there is more than one path to the top of the mountain”</em> ― <a href="http://amzn.to/221BFHo">Miyamoto Musashi</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25876680090/in/dateposted/" title="Snow-laden trees 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1531/25876680090_0dfb54759f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow-laden trees 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1pWrVlq">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Pack Pods</a> are coming soon and make packing your pack more tidy.</p>

<p>Martin looks back on the <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/weitwander-rueckblick-maerz-2016/">long-distance hikes of the last month</a>. [German]</p>

<p>An <a href="http://cruxcrush.com/2016/03/17/women-on-lead-katie-ives-editor-in-chief-of-alpinist-magazine/">interview with Katie Ives</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/2062221/new-science-creative-brain-nature">The New Science of the Creative Brain on Nature</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/film/2016/mar/30/sherpa-norbu-tenzing-on-the-everest-circus-and-the-inevitability-of-another-disaster">Norbu Tenzing on the Everest ‘circus’ and the inevitability of another disaster</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ddhammocks.com">DD Hammocks</a> updated their website!</p>

<p>Cyclists, check out <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/hexlox/hexlox-anti-theft-for-saddles-wheels-and-more-made">HEXLOX: Anti Theft for saddles, wheels and more</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://create.adobe.com/2015/10/29/control_your_lines_to_make_stronger_photos.html">Control your lines for better photos</a>.</p>

<p>There are still good offers to be found in the <a href="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=cc&amp;cpid=1&amp;target=http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/?_$ja=tsid:52154">Bergfreunde Outlet</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Mikkel was <a href="http://backwoodbikepacking.com/2016/03/29/riding-the-femundlopet-dogsled-trail/">riding the Femundløpet dogsled trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/stepping-out-10-reasons-to-climbing-outdoors/">10 reasons to climb outdoors</a>.</p>

<p>Peter went <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2016/04/early-spring-kayaking.html">spring kayaking</a>.</p>

<p>James went <a href="https://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2016/03/30/micro-wild-vanping-in-the-carsphairn-hills-part-one/">Micro wild vanping in the Carsphairn hills</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://surfnslide.wordpress.com/2016/04/01/short-blast-up-the-sugar-loaf/">short blast up the Sugar Loaf</a>.</p>

<p>Karin hikes the <a href="http://hikekarin.com/2016/02/06/bluestack-way-in-donegal/">Bluestack Way in Irland</a>. [German]</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oPv8PepssRo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Simon hikes the <a href="http://gipfelfieber.com/2016/03/29/via-ferrata-che-guevara-im-bann-des-despoten/">Via Ferrata Che Guevara</a>. [German]</p>

<p>John was <a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2016/03/8-days-on-lycian-way.html">8 Days on the Lycian Way</a>.</p>

<p>Jill was <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2016/03/lingering-at-end.html">lingering at the end</a>.</p>

<p>Leor visits <a href="https://pantilat.wordpress.com/2016/04/01/stone-ridge-aerial-falls/">Stone Ridge &amp; Aerial Falls</a> and brought back some great photos.</p>

<p><a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2016/03/31/hayduke-recon-recap-gear/">Hayduke Recon, Recap and Gear</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4OSFQoOFq44" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Dave’s <a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2016/04/01/bd-alpine-start-hoody-the-final-word/">final word on the BD ALpine Hoody</a>.</p>

<p>Neil reviews the <a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/45nrth-wolvhammer-boots/">45NRTH Wolvhammer Boots</a>.</p>

<p>Jens tests the <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/technik/vorgestellt-activeon-cx-gold-action-kamera/">Activeon CX Gold Action-Camera</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Gnat’s <a href="http://imaginegnat.com/2016/03/28/fragments-my-1st-month-with-the-fuji-x-pro-2/">1st Month with the Fuji X Pro 2</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2016/03/hennessy-hammock-monsoon-tarp-review/">Hennessy Hammock Monsoon Tarp Review</a>.</p>

<p>Matt’s <a href="http://outdoorsmh.blogspot.fi/2016/03/diet-jetboil.html">Diet Jetboil</a>.</p>

<p>And Erika reviews the <a href="http://ulligunde.com/2016/03/illuminator-sensor-handschuhe-von-or-im-test-outdoor-research/">Outdoor Research Illuminator Sensor Gloves</a>.</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/marmot-space-walk-jacket-and-edge-insulated-pants-review.html"/>
    <updated>2016-03-29T23:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/marmot-space-walk-jacket-and-edge-insulated-pants-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Skiing, sledding, hiking and building an igloo: Winter is a great time for kids to be outside &amp; enjoy the snow. So that he does not get cold, our son wore the Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants - which we review here.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108799805/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1583/26108799805_df4fb92f57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Winter, also known to parents as the time where you need to get ready 15 minutes before you plan to leave - because your little ones need help dressing up in the multitude of layers we make them wear so they do not get cold. Because only when they’re not cold they actually enjoy being outdoors (much like adults, really). We tested the <a href="https://marmot.com/products/details/boys-space-walk-jacket">Marmot Space Walk Jacket</a> and <a href="https://marmot.com/products/details/boys-edge-insulated-pant">Edge Insulated Pants</a> during the last four months outside while alpine skiing, sledding, building snowmen and XC skiing, and here are our thoughts about them.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484248574/in/dateposted/" title="Sledding at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1538/25484248574_b0fe932edf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sledding at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25835958970/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1488/25835958970_4ab4a4766b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25506181673/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1536/25506181673_6ef459c4a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="space-walk-jacket">Space Walk Jacket</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.marmot.de/content/de/collection_26&amp;c=643&amp;show=5778">Space Walk Jacket</a> in Size XS equals size 110 and weighs 512 g. Our son loved the colour combination of orange and reds, and we too really liked it. Outside a waterproof &amp; breathable Marmot MemBrain® Fabric keeps snow and moisture at bay, while on the inside a Thermal R 100 g insulation ensures generated warmth stays inside. The hood is removable, and a really good fit, even over a bobble hat. The Powder Skirt keeps the snow out and is extremely useful for little skiers and playing in the snow. It has a silicone band on the inside which keeps it in place and has two levels of tightness. In the back, chin and neck a fleece lining makes it comfortable against the skin and likely helps with breathability, too. What we found overkill were the six pockets, we could have done easily with only the one large mesh pocket on the inside (which is great to store beanie, neck warmer and gloves!) and one of the outside pockets. Our son never used the Velcro hand pockets nor the other two pockets on the outside. The hem is adjustable, though with the toggles in the pockets it is difficult to do so - happily we never needed it. The sleeves have Velcro closures and also can be adjusted, and most importantly are wide enough so gloves can be worn underneath the sleeves to keep the snow out. The jacket closes high and our son found the area in the front of the face constricting, something we solved by leaving the zipper always a couple of centimetre open.</p>

<p>In terms of warmth, we feel the jacket (and pants for that matter) are warm till -10°C with a thin midlayer on (plus normal clothes), probably more with a thicker midlayer. The jacket has plenty of space underneath for layering, and our son never was cold in a variety of activities and weather conditions. It gives little skiers and climbers great freedom of movement, and the Powder Skirt ensures no cold and wet snow comes inside. After four months of use and a couple of washes the jacket also still looks like new, also at high-stress areas like the cuffs and back. Overall our son really liked his Space Walk Jacket - it is warm, has nice colours and is easy for him to put on and off on his own. </p>

<p>Get the Marmot Space Walk Jacket right now with great discounts at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/marmot-boys-space-walk-jacket-ski-jacket/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1Uq4bDm">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1Sh9qz1">Campsaver</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1ogTV1S">evo</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1Uq5jqD">REI.com</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108801235/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1637/26108801235_cfc707f7e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25506181033/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1478/25506181033_1c7630e710_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25504057124/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1685/25504057124_34e4c202fc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="edge-insulated-pants">Edge Insulated Pants</h2>

<p>In size XS the <a href="http://www.marmot.de/content/de/collection_26&amp;c=647&amp;show=5792">Edge Insulated Pants</a> weighs 444 g. They are, as the name suggests, insulated pants, made of the proprietary Marmot MemBrain® fabric on the outside which makes the pants water-resistant, while on the inside a Thermal R™ insulation keeps little winter lovers warm. We found the internal flex boot gaiters great to keep shoes &amp; socks dry from the inside, and the reinforced inside leg is useful for skiing as well as scrambling on rocks. The waist is adjustable via Velcros on the inside, but sadly the adjustment is only minimal - we feel a bit more adjustment in width or a stretchy waist could have been better and would possibly make it possible to use the pants two winter seasons. The removable suspenders are great, and the soft inside lining makes it easy to put the pants on over other pants. We never used the three pockets on the pants, so maybe it’d make sense to get rid of at least the two zippered pockets. </p>

<p>Putting the pants on is easy thanks to the smooth lining and it stays well in place with the adjustable suspenders and button closure. After four months of daily use outside the Edge Insulated Pants still looks like new after a couple of washes. The Marmot MemBrain® fabric kept the snow &amp; wetness always reliable outside and it was easy to brush dirt off the pants. They allow for great freedom of movement, be it scrambling up the snow hills along the streets, climbing on the playground or Alpine and XC skiing. The sizing is good for kids between 108 and 112 cm, though if your child is wearing more than one baselayer the waist might get tight (we just left the button open). Asides from these little things from us parents our son simply liked his Edge Insulated Pants a lot: They were toasty, allowed him to go sledding on his pants down steep snow hills and also looked cool!</p>

<p>Buy the Marmot Edge Insulated Pants at <a href="http://bit.ly/1URthuB">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/marmot-boys-edge-insulated-pant-ski-pant/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1RnGIAh">Campsaver</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1UxaV2z">evo</a> - all of them have great offers on the pants thanks to their winter sales!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108802745/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1705/26108802745_6e2c8c20c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26016281992/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1582/26016281992_7a9bd6e1ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The jacket and pants have been provided by Marmot for review. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 231]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/twir-231.html"/>
    <updated>2016-03-27T23:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/twir-231</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“I wonder if the snow loves the trees and fields, that it kisses them so gently? And then it covers them up snug, you know, with a white quilt; and perhaps it says “Go to sleep, darlings, till the summer comes again.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1UQwIlj">Lewis Carroll</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25333253494/in/dateposted/" title="Powder turns on Kesänki"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1649/25333253494_d679a86349_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Powder turns on Kesänki" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Outdoor Blogger friends, do <a href="https://partner.bergfreunde.de/html.cgi?filename=anmelden.htm&amp;ref=10239">join the Bergfreunde Affiliate Programme</a> and earn some money with your reviews! It’s easy and a great way to help you cover the costs of running your blog.</p>

<p>Enjoy a weekend at the <a href="http://adventure-journal.com/2016/03/the-starlight-room/">Starlight Room</a> in the Dolomites.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.iambassador.net/2016/03/the-social-travel-summit-2016-inverness/">The Social Travel Summit 2016 goes to Inverness</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.climbingbusinessjournal.com/shaping-an-industry/">Shaping an industry</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/">Outdoorline.sk</a> has a great looking new webshop! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.oooyeah.de/gewinnspiel-mammut-xeron-courier/">Win a Mammut Daypack</a>.</p>

<p>The latest <a href="http://mountainpodcast.com">Mountain Podcast</a> is out!</p>

<p><a href="http://ulligunde.com/2016/03/zum-umgang-mit-bloggern-teil-1-offtopic/">How to cooprtate with bloggers</a>. [German]</p>

<p>You know you want to: <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Take 20% Off One Full-Price Item at Backcountry.com</a> with the Coupon Code: MAR20.</p>

<p>Head to the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=436797&amp;pw=73183">REI OUTLET</a> to save on Top Brand Outdoor Closeouts!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Still in the mode for ski-touring? Check out the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/teaser-graubunden-haute-route.html">Graubünden Haute Route</a>.</p>

<p>Erik, Jakke &amp; Tuomas’ <a href="http://www.packgofind.com/pallas">Pallas</a> adventure is also sublime.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/27/travel/camping-southern-california-desert.html">In California’s Desert Father and Daughter Find the Sublime</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cedricbernardini.com/2016/03/22/la-grave/">La Grave</a>.</p>

<p>Bikepacking from <a href="https://limitcamper.wordpress.com/2016/03/21/bikepacking-berlin-cologne/">Berlin to Cologne</a>.</p>

<p>Martin enjoys a <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/schneeweisser-fruehlingsbeginn-am-krummbachstein/">white spring begin on the Krummbachstein</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://climbinghouse.com/2016/03/the-illusion-of-control.html">The Illusion of Control</a>.</p>

<p>A ski-tour to <a href="http://www.alpin-blog.com/piz-beverin-skitour/">Piz Beve­rin</a>. [German]</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/159759743?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Scott Secco’s <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/video/scott-secco-raw-100/">Raw 100</a>.</p>

<p>Forrest <a href="http://forrestmccarthy.blogspot.fi/2016/03/crossing-southern-alps-new-zealand.html">crosses the Southern Alps in New Zealand</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://davesearle.me/2016/03/21/mont-dolent-traverse/">Mont Dolent Traverse</a>.</p>

<p>Very cool: <a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/alpine-huts-australia/">10 Australian alpine huts you should visit</a>! </p>

<p>Bikepacking the <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/altravesur-bikepacking-route/">Altravesur</a> in Southern Spain.</p>

<p>Tour Aotearoa 2016 - <a href="http://jeffsbike.blogspot.fi/2016/03/tour-aotearoa-2016-bikepacking-length.html">bikepacking the length of New Zealand</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2016/03/packrafting-in-marokko.html">Packrafting in Marocco</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A week of <a href="http://www.oooyeah.de/davos-freeride-safari/">freeriding in Davos</a>. [German]</p>

<p>David explores <a href="http://mountaincoastriver.blogspot.fi/2016/03/interlude-culture-of-nature-in-upland.html">the Culture of Nature in Upland Japan</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seatosummitultralight.blogspot.fi/2016/03/bishop-pass-march-2016.html">Bishop Pass</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22477361062/in/album-72157659948633968/" title="The Arc&#x27;teryx Carrier Duffle 100 is a Monster that swallows massive loads"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/594/22477361062_c547de058a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The Arc&#x27;teryx Carrier Duffle 100 is a Monster that swallows massive loads" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Rob Greenfield’s <a href="http://robgreenfield.tv/possessions/">111 Possessions</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2016/03/bakpocket-deluxe-adventurers-hammock-review/">Bakpocket Deluxe Adventurers Hammock Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/patagonia-merino-daily-review/">Patagonia Merino Daily T-Shirt</a> Review.</p>

<p><a href="http://chasingmailboxes.com/2016/03/20/traveling-light-and-self-contained-jerrys-cross-country-bike-tour-secrets/">Traveling light and self-contained by bike</a>.</p>

<p>Alex reviews the <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/03/gear-review-grivel-g1-new-classic-crampons.html">Grivel G1 New Classic crampons</a>.</p>

<p>Testing the new <a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2016/03/neues-wildwasser-packraft-testtour-der.html">MRS Alligator 2S</a> on the Ardèche in France. [German]</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=462077&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/13582/462077/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaser Graubünden Haute Route]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/teaser-graubunden-haute-route.html"/>
    <updated>2016-03-22T23:09:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/teaser-graubunden-haute-route</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In late February and early March I made a visit to Switzerland to attempt the Graubünden Haute Route. Sadly the high avalanche danger and changing weather cut us short - here’s a first taste of four days ski-touring in Graubünden.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25455047716/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Going down."><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1445/25455047716_5a5b16aa20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Going down." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The <a href="http://www.hauteroute-graubuenden.ch">Graubünden Haute Route</a> is a five days/ four nights ski-touring trip where you visit four beautiful huts, ski great powder, test your mountaineering skills while climbing some beautiful peaks and enjoy great scenary. Well, that’s at least the normal plan, but because of not really good weather and high avalanche danger our trip was cut a wee bit short. Stay tuned for a full day-to-day account of my Haute Route experience, but for now enjoy these fine selection of photos! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25283933403/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Madulain Railway Station"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1589/25283933403_f69055afe7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Madulain Railway Station" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25886747936/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Summit Cairn"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1518/25886747936_6f80f77374_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit Cairn" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25886734586/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="D&#x27;Es-Cha Hut"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1450/25886734586_dd1167a46f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="D&#x27;Es-Cha Hut" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Day one we skied from Madulain to the D’Es-Cha Hut, where we spent in the end two nights because we didn’t want to risk our lives in highly dangerous avalanche terrain. It’s a beautiful hut with great wardens, a wide selection of board and card games as well as interesting magazines - so we didn’t get bored while waiting for better weather.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25892325271/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Anselm leading the way"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1596/25892325271_eaa15fdc8c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Anselm leading the way" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25686718380/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Will and Anselm discussing our run"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1690/25686718380_3134f5b330_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Will and Anselm discussing our run" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25987279595/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="On the way to the railway station in Madulain"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1632/25987279595_e5cb3a3e25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="On the way to the railway station in Madulain" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the end we skied back to Madulain, took the loveley UNESCO World Heritage train to Bergün and took the long way up to the Kesch Hut.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25354582624/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="To the Kesch Hut, the long way."><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1638/25354582624_ba4b4c4b45_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="To the Kesch Hut, the long way." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25987285185/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Finally at the Kesch Hut."><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1719/25987285185_056018f76b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Finally at the Kesch Hut." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25866491312/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Tasty meats and cheese as starter!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1545/25866491312_065cce596e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty meats and cheese as starter!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Reto, the warden, welcomed us in heinous winds to his hut with a very taste cup of hot, sweet tea. His wife Ursina cooked us a delicious dinner and we slept great - ready for our fourth day, with high hopes of better weather yet again.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25686733060/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Up!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1478/25686733060_06a214e1b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25892341991/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Down through the powder"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1578/25892341991_90cce48c02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Down through the powder" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But the better weather never came, so we skied back down to Bergün through sweet powder forests! Take a peek at the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157665020355632">Flickr Album</a> and keep your eyes on this blog as the full story will come this month!</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: This trip was made possible with the support of <a href="http://en.graubuenden.ch">Graubünden</a> and <a href="http://www.myswitzerland.com/">Switzerland</a>. As usual I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 230]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/twir-230.html"/>
    <updated>2016-03-20T22:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/twir-230</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Set wide the window. Let me drink the day.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1LvLxXV">Edith Wharton</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25890904525/in/dateposted/" title="Snow window"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1558/25890904525_4c60804240_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow window" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Save the Blue Heart of Europe: <a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2016/03/save-the-blue-heart-of-europe-the-balkan-rivers-story.html">The Balkan Rivers Story</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/early-lead/wp/2016/03/02/why-this-record-breaking-pro-climber-is-devoting-himself-to-solar-energy/">Why this record-breaking pro climber is devoting himself to solar energy</a>.</p>

<p>An <a href="http://www.20min.ch/finance/news/story/Sportladen-verlangt-von-Kunden-Geld-fuer-Beratung-23664429">Outdoor Shop in Switzerland demands money from clients for consultancy</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.backpacker.com/trips/falling-in-love-on-the-trail/">Falling in Love on the Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Outdoor Blogger friends, do <a href="https://partner.bergfreunde.de/html.cgi?filename=anmelden.htm&amp;ref=10239">join the Bergfreunde Affiliate Programme</a> and earn some money with your reviews! It’s easy and a great way to help you cover the costs of running your blog.</p>

<p>Alastair Humphreys has a new book coming out: <a href="http://amzn.to/25bEji5">Grand Adventures</a>. You can <a href="http://amzn.to/25bEji5">pre-order it now</a> as a Paperback or eBook.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/2051821/123-mountain-infuriating-gear-retailer">The Husband-and-Wife Team behind the Internet’s most infuriating Outdoor Retailer</a>.</p>

<p>How to <a href="http://www.backpacker.com/skills/photo-skills/photo-school-tent-at-night/">shoot your tent at Night</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/outdoor-bekleidung/?pid=10239">60% off on Garments and Shoes at Bergfreunde</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=5729&amp;pw=73183">Last Chair Sale at evo.com</a> with up to 40% off 2016 Skis, Snowboards and Outerwear!</p>

<p>Take an additional <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">20% off selected Sale Items at Backcountry.com</a>.</p>

<p>ULA Equipment Backpacks has <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=49341&amp;pw=73183">FREE US Shipping on ALL Orders</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=462133&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/13582/462133/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Corinna enters the <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2016/02/xanderklinge-schwarzwald-schluchtenwanderung.html">Xanderklinge</a> in Germany’s Black Forest. [German]</p>

<p>Chris and Mark enjoyed a <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2016/03/sunshine-stars-snow-high-camp-in.html">Winter High Camp in the Cairngorms</a>.</p>

<p>Cycling through <a href="http://www.twistingspokes.com/arunachal-pradesh-zero-cycling/">Arunachal Pradesh</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://davesearle.me/2016/03/19/a-fine-link/">A Fine Link</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/157596292?byline=0" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Colin Haleys <a href="http://adventureblog.nationalgeographic.com/2016/02/10/how-a-longtime-patagonia-climber-just-had-his-best-season-ever/">had his best Patagonia season, ever</a>.</p>

<p>An interview with two <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/te-araroa-trail-neuseeland-interview/">Te Araroa Trail thru-hikers</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Alex finished a long-time objective, the <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/03/the-lochaber-traverse-in-winter.html">Lochaber Traverse in winter</a>.</p>

<p>Stefanie’s <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/skifahren-lernen-lofer/">fourth ski day of 2016</a> brings snow and fog - and big smiles nevertheless. [German]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25786900671/in/dateposted/" title="Sunrise"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1613/25786900671_158609cf36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Peter reviews the <a href="http://www.petesy.co.uk/haglofs-skarn-winter-pant-review/">Haglöfs Skarn Winter Pant</a>.</p>

<p>Review of the <a href="https://climbinggearreviewsuk.wordpress.com/2016/03/19/the-gr1-spains-sendero-historico/">GR1-Spain’s Sendero Historico Guide Book</a>.</p>

<p>A look at the <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2016/03/field-tested-g3-stinger-skis/">G3 Stinger Skis</a>.</p>

<p>Jens wrote down his thoughts on the <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/ausruestung/messertest-gerber-survivalmesser-lmf-ii-infantry-black/">Gerber Survivalmesser LMF II Infantry Black</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.atlasandboots.com/best-hiking-apps/">13 hiking apps</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://ulgearblog.com/2016/03/19/merit-of-the-often-ignored-4g-esbit-tab/">The Merit of the 4 g Esbit Tab</a>.</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you smile? Great! Smile more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more fun updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
