<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-19T20:29:11+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2015 - II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T23:29:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More new kit for trailrunners, lightweight backpackers, mountaineers, climbers and outdoor lovers from the world’s biggest outdoor fair!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686321301/in/dateposted/" title="Always bring the Houdini"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5715/20686321301_c0847978f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Always bring the Houdini" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>These posts do take a lot of time to write so I am happy if you’d <a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">get me a coffee</a> as a payment for my work =)</em></p>

<h2 id="marmot">Marmot</h2>

<p><a href="http://marmot.de">Marmot</a> had a wide range of new kit on the show so lets dive straight in. The Red Star Jacket for Men/ Starfire Jacket for Women is the first 3-layer jacket to incorporate the exceptionally breathable, very robust and waterproof NanoPro™ membrane. It’s very stretchy, 100% seam taped, has a fully adjustable hood with a laminated brim to keep your sight dry, and will weigh 425 g. The Red Star Pants has 3/4 Length Water-Resistant Side Zippers and will tip the scales at 470 g and should make for a breathable &amp; waterproof combo which keeps you dry in heavy rain.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679565205/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Star Jacket"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5620/20679565205_85257c0dea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Star Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056996144/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot NanoPro 3-layer"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/608/20056996144_ce232512a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot NanoPro 3-layer" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Graviton 38 backpack weighs 1.080 g and comes with a ventilated suspension (carrying) system. The series - there’s four different sizes in total - features a single-piece aluminum uniframe which should have good load stability and features soft pads in the shoulder and waist areas for improved carry comfort. Compression
straps on the sides and base, trekking pole attachment and several easily accessible pockets round out this pack. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491534738/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Graviton 38 backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/638/20491534738_b95bf1624d_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Marmot Graviton 38 backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Helium Sleeping Bag tips the scales at 935 g in Regular length and is filled with 560 g of hydrophobic, RDS certified down, which should keep you toasty till around -9°C Comfort. Really cool was the “Fold-Down” second zipper on the right which provides more ventilation and easy access. The Full Length Locking YKK Two Way Zipper has a Zip-Guard Slider which prevents the lining from getting stuck in the zipper, which solves a common problem in (sleeping bag) zippers. Overall a nice looking sleeping bag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653304776/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Helium &amp; Ion Sleeping Bags"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5715/20653304776_de7ae465b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Helium &amp; Ion Sleeping Bags" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491568270/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Helium Sleeping Bag Zipper"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/715/20491568270_b1baf24d69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Helium Sleeping Bag Zipper" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Vapor FC 2P is a 2.520 g 2 Person tent with a size of 107 x 137 x 224 cm and a spacey vestibule. The doors got bigger for easy access, a lamp shade pocket in the roof lets you read at night without a headlamp on and the color-coded pole clip system makes it easy to pitch. It looked like a nice 3-season tent for couples, but there’s also 3 and 4 Person tents available of the Vapor for families and small groups.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056994454/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Vapor FC 2P Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/724/20056994454_177aab81d7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Vapor FC 2P Tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the climbing garments corner there were lots of clothes for your favourite pastime. Cool designs in combination with functional &amp; stretchy materials make for sweet shirts, pants and hoodies to hit the crag in. Add in a new climbing pack called the <em>Gear Hauler</em> and you have all you need for a fun day climbing. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491536718/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/730/20491536718_690fde99ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="scarpa">Scarpa</h2>

<p>Wow, I really was surprised by all the new shoes from <a href="http://scarpa.it">Scarpa</a>! Lots of trailrunning/ ultralight backpacking shoes from them, and I found they actually looked good! The Proton is a shoe made for heel strikers which gives you good support on long runs. Will weigh around 360 g per shoe and has a Vibram® Genesis sole and lots of cushioning in the heel.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491564180/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Proton"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5726/20491564180_8969bb3378_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Proton" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Atom certainly was the most interesting shoe in the line, and at 260 g per shoe it was also rather light. Colour &amp; sole-wise it gets big thumbs up from me, the Vibram®  Genetic Lite reminds me of a trailrunning shoe I have used a lot. Scarpa says it <em>“Created for athletes with a perfect running style who weigh less than 70 kg, they will find this shoe is very reactive and it suits the athlete who favors a running style based on the toes”</em>. Well, if that doesn’t sound like a great shoe for me, I don’t know! Add in a breathable mesh upper and you will have a shoe which could become very popular.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653292466/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Atom"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5634/20653292466_a275b465eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Atom" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Neutron weighs 295 g and has a Vibram® Genetic sole that should give good grip on any kind of wet or dry terrain. It’s available as a fabric version, a special Women’s version and for Winter runs even as a Gore-Tex lined shoe. Still light enough for UL backpackers, but with more support and cushioning. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057014404/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Neutron"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5740/20057014404_560df31ac3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Neutron" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Scarpa Mountaineering boots aka the Phantom Line is awesome. It’s designed by Ueli Steck which means this are the boots that Ueli designed and uses himself - be it climbing Annapurna or on his 82 Summits project. There’s three new boots and they all feature the new zipper which runs around the shoe. It looks cool but I am a bit wondering how practical it will be in use when you need to pull a zipper behind your leg, and of course such a long zipper also adds weight and complexity aka a place where it can fail. Scarpa writes that the <em>“innovative “orange peel-like” closure with Flexseal® Waterproof zip avoids any inconvenience to the ankle movements”</em> so I guess it will have a benefit. Anyway. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20058614443/in/photostream/" title="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/611/20058614443_2482540e7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There’s three new boots - the Phantom 8000, the Phantom 6000 and the Phantom Tech. All have a gaiter made from KCN-Tech Fabric, S-Tech Fabric and an Outdry® membrane , which I like as I find OutDry better working as Gore-Tex. All three boots also have a Carbon insole and a Vibram® Gravity sole. The Phantom Tech is the lightest boot at 830 g per boot and also the least warm, but as it has a Primaloft® insulation layer I have no doubt that it will be a great alpine climbing/ ice climbing boot (in the photo underneath is the Tech on the right and the 6000 on the left).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679570315/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5827/20679570315_29ac835ee9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Phantom 6000 and 8000 come with a removable liner boot that has a Primaloft® lining and a 4 mm thermo-insulating EVA sole. The 6000 is made for peaks up to 6000 m and weighs 995 g per boot while the Phantom 8000 is made for the highest summits of the globe and weighs 1310 g per boot. The hole line looked sweet, curious to try out the Phantom 6000 in the Karakoram in the future!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20670328742/in/photostream/" title="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5687/20670328742_fe268302e1_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Phantom Mountaineering Boots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s Drago, the new climbing shoe. Made for bouldering, hard sports climbing indoors and outdoors the Drago is close in design to the Furia but has a Velcro strap for a good fit. The rubber on the upper goes really high for sticky toe hooks. The shoe is soft and gives you good control on small ledges and difficult placements.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057007954/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Drago Climbing Shoe"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/676/20057007954_6eb66f1fcb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Drago Climbing Shoe" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="haglfs">Haglöfs</h2>

<p>Haglöfs is a big company with many lines so it’s always a bit difficult to grasp all the new gear, especially as there’s so much new interesting kit. The Roc Helios 25 backpack is an OutDoor Award winner that’s made from XPac and has a back opening to access your gear. It’s made for mountaineering so has all the details you want from a rucksack for the mountains, but should do well when abused for backpacking, too. No info on weight, sorry.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461137721/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Roc Helios 25 backpack"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3814/20461137721_acafbdf705_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs Roc Helios 25 backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Herakles Jacket is 455 g in Size L and made from a 3-layer Gore-tex with the new CKnit backer. It’s a mountain jacket with a helmet-compatible hood, an articulated design for freedom of movement and high pockets. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20268246879/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Herakles Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/415/20268246879_e39a6fb420_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haglöfs Herakles Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Gram Pulse trailrunners - the Women’s model is in the photo - will weigh 215 g for a Women’s shoe and 260 g for a Men’s shoe. The sole pattern looks familiar and thus should be good, and on top there’s non-absorbing fabrics which should maintain a low weight in wet conditions. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461140421/in/dateposted/" title="Haglöfs Gram Pulse Shoe"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/458/20461140421_b578c49369_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haglöfs Gram Pulse Shoe" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s another backpack, the LIM Strive Backpack. Can’t give the weight on this pack either, but it felt light for being a 50 l pack. The front zipper makes for easy access to gear, the lid can be removed for more weight saving. The hipbelt pockets were pretty big, made from a stretchy mesh and looked great, and the material is bluesign certified 100HT Robic™, which also some cottages use for making their packs. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20454898805/in/dateposted/" title="LIM Strive Backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/439/20454898805_f9e2a1f04c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="LIM Strive Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="vaude">Vaude</h2>

<p>I’m pretty psyched about the biggest news for backpackers from <a href="http://www.vaude.com">Vaude</a>, and that’s the Alpstein 450 DWN quilt. Why? Well, I’m pretty proud that <a href="http://blog.fastpacking.de">Carsten</a> and me helped during the development of this quilt. We both have tested early prototypes and gave the designer a lot of feedback on what we liked and what could be better. I think I’ll give some insights on this quilt further down the road in a separate post, but the cool things are: 450 g of RDS certified down in the Alpstein 450 DWN (200 g in the Alpstein 200 DWN), total weight 750 g (550 g), and a unique attachment system which allows you to attach the quilt pretty easily to any sleeping pad. Oh, and it’s pretty cool that the quilt won a OutDoor Gold OutDoor Award, too! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20516026200/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Alpstein 450 DWN quilt"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/723/20516026200_795ffbd627_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Alpstein 450 DWN quilt" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then there’s the Citus 24 LW Backpack, a 500 g 24 l Volume pack that’s made from a siliconizied 40 D Rip-Stop. Special is that is has a Aeroflex back panel which should keep you dries aka less sweaty on your summer hikes. It has a zippered lid pocket, mesh side stretch pockets and a compression system that also lets you carry wet gear on the front. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20516112978/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Citus 24 LW Backpack"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5643/20516112978_a85234b05f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Citus 24 LW Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Pro Windshell Jacket weighs less than 80 g and is a cycling windjacket which packs tiny when not needed. Reflective details, long back, stretch inserts on the sides for freedom of movement and breathability and a PFC-free Eco Finish water repellency treatment that makes it water-resistant, its a wind jacket you can wear cycling or when out on the hills.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20710926061/in/dateposted/" title="Pro Windshell LW"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5652/20710926061_7afc5fae6a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Pro Windshell LW" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And as we’re already talking cycling the Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes are environmentally friendly made flat pedal cycling shoes. The Moab Low AM and Moab Mid STX AM fulfil the strict Vaude <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQgt80pO0YM">Green Shape</a> criteria and still will perform great on the trail. A great move to get a difficult product likes shoes fulfil this standard, and I hope we’ll see more of this in the future, also from other manufacturers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20694848822/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/762/20694848822_079c2a46ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Moab Low &amp; Mid Flatpedal shoes" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="norrna">Norrøna</h2>

<p>The news from <a href="https://www.norrona.com">Norrøna</a> included the bitihorn alpha60 Jacket which is a 250 g insulation piece that’s filled with Polartec Alpha. The shell is wind and water resistant so it also can be worn on its own, but it should be a good midlayer, too. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261529486/in/dateposted/" title="Norrøna bitihorn alpha60 Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/395/20261529486_55568dd61a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna bitihorn alpha60 Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now available is the fjørå line for Women (Men’s have been available for a while already). These are really great for riding on single track trails or shredding down hills, made from good materials and give good wind protection but also keep you cool on the uphill.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101181829/in/dateposted/" title="Norrøna fjøra line"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/456/20101181829_5747a8e82c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna fjøra line" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Lifestyle lines were a big trend at the OutDoor, and it’s understandable. Norrøna’s 29 line is very stylish and a mix of technical and functional fabrics. There’s a cool limited edition Denim Anorak which will make you stand out at the camp fire or in the office. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261544666/in/photostream/" title="Norrøna Lifestyle 29 Line"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3678/20261544666_2f1e05181a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna Lifestyle 29 Line" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="montane">Montane</h2>

<p>I only had a brief visit at <a href="Montane">Montane</a> so can’t give all the details on the lightweight new kit from them - which is a shame, as they had a very cool looking cuben fibre pack on display! But what I saw and tried were the new Ultra Tour packs, which did remind me design-wise from a now bankrupt lightweight company from the USA. Which isn’t bad, as that pack has been super popular. The Ultra Tour is available as a 22, 40 and 55 l volume pack, which will weigh 540 g, 725 g and 840 g respectively. There’s a roll-top closure, large stretch side pockets, a Comfort Vent Back Pad and Contact Air Mesh shoulder straps which will keep you cooler on long hikes with heavy loads, hip pockets and a front pocket/ compartment. These looked very good and if priced right (= affordable) these could become great entry-level UL packs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679558375/in/dateposted/" title="Montane Ultra Tour backpacks"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/693/20679558375_815277e522_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Ultra Tour backpacks" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Minimus 777 Pull-On is a 134 g hardshell that packs tiny and should be very breathable. The construction is of a very high quality that’s made to last, and in orange it also looks really sweet. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20670323222/in/dateposted/" title="Montane Minimus 777 Pull-On"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5693/20670323222_a126f9bded_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Minimus 777 Pull-On" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As I said, a shame I didn’t snap photos of the other new kit, as with the <em>ultra alpine 38 + 5</em> (a 547 g alpine climbing pack with a sweet design), the <em>hyper tour 38</em> (a 639 g cuben fibre hiking pack that can be stripped to 478 g) and several great garments there would have been plenty of interesting kit for lightweight backpackers, Alpinists and trailrunners!</p>

<h2 id="nikwax">Nikwax</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.nikwax.com/en-gb/">Nikwax</a> Down Wash Direct is an aftercare product which lets you clean and improve the performance of regular and hydrophobic garments/ quilts/ sleeping bags alike. What’s really cool is not just that Down Wash Direct is environmentally friendly but that it makes your down kit hydrophobic, even if it hasn’t been hydrophobic down to begin with. That’s a great way to make your favourite down jacket hydrophobic - both the down and the DWR of the shell. An exciting product that I’m curious to test with some of my down kit and see how it improves performance.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20056991504/in/dateposted/" title="Nikwax Down Wash Direct"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5689/20056991504_3456b34bee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nikwax Down Wash Direct" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="omm">OMM</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.theomm.com">OMM</a> makes sweet kit that makes ultralight backpackers and fell runners alike happy. The Phantom 25CL was the highlight, a great pack that would be ideal for a fast &amp; light weekend in the hills or an OMM event. It has a integrated sleeping mat and a carbon suspension system. The back length can be adjusted via an easy system, the stretchy side pockets were super easy to reach and the compression system could be adjusted with the pack on. Tipping the scales at just 400 g the Phantom 25CL is a great pack that works a charm if you go fast.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686315741/in/photostream/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/718/20686315741_c65a6a6a53_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686306421/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5670/20686306421_5c125f020c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20491570540/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Phantom 25CL"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/750/20491570540_d77bb3e1f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Phantom 25CL" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Ultra 8 is a new pack that will be super affordable and great for training or a SUL overnighter. Mesh side pockets, a good carrying system and a 8 l main compartment let you carry all you need for a day out running in the hills.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057013414/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Ultra 8"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/757/20057013414_c51cbdd786_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Ultra 8" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you need some more space on your existing pack, take a look at the Compressor Pod. It can work as a UL pack on its own, but it’s designed to be attached to a OMM pack or another pack and gives you more protected carrying space. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653312566/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Compressor Pod"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/629/20653312566_f41a8c4c0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OMM Compressor Pod" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, the Grid Longsleeve is simply a functional &amp; good-looking longsleeve for runners &amp; outdoor enthusiasts alike. The cool contour lines on the sleeves are a nice detail.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20057005354/in/dateposted/" title="OMM Grid Longsleeve"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/663/20057005354_d9447135b5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="OMM Grid Longsleeve" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="jetboil">Jetboil</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jetboil.com">Jetboil</a> had two interesting news on the show: A Basecamp stove and the MicroMo - the successor to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti.html">Sol Ti</a>. Lets take a look at the MicroMo first. It weighs 340 g all in and the pot has a volume of 0,8 l. You can store a 100 g cartridge inside the pot with the burner unit and on the outside a cozy lets you handle the pot with its hot content. Burning time for half a litre is supposed to be 2:15 min and it should be less ideal for cooking/ simmering than the MiniMo. The pot et al. is now made from Aluminium, so there should hopefully not be any melting fluxrings anymore.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653299766/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Micro Mo"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5787/20653299766_ffd9bf075d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Micro Mo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Genesis on the other hand is found at the opposite side of the spectrum of the MicroMo and weighs 4.100 g. I don’t know how light that is for a basecamp stove, but it sounds pretty good. A 5 l pot lets you cook for the team and the pan is ideal for bacon and eggs in the morning. The 2-Burner stove fits inside of the pot with the pan on top. I can see this coming in handy for car camping, glamping and canoe trips, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686316111/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/626/20686316111_3a0afa0678_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20686313981/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/772/20686313981_f49269f40a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20679567065/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil Genesis Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/588/20679567065_a3e3181c92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jetboil Genesis Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="stay-tuned-for-the-next-part-coming-soon">Stay tuned for the next part, Coming Soon™!</h2>

<p>You can see a lot more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157656356655229">OutDoor 2015 Flickr Album</a>. And if you liked this follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for more gear &amp; outdoor updates.</p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love the Dolomites Tour]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/love-the-dolomites-tour.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-17T23:53:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/love-the-dolomites-tour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friends. Good food. Wine. Three Guidebooks. No plan. Equals a fantastic time in the Dolomites.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19872954152/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19872954152_05a10af0d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In March I let you in on a well-kept secret: That I will be going to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html">Dolomites</a> in July. With four friends. A rental car. An obscene amount of climbing, camping, Via ferrata and backpacking gear. So obscene that I needed to ditch one of my twin-topes on my mate Stu, with whom I was flying out of Helsinki way to early on a Sunday morning. A good thing that a sweltering heat was welcoming us in Venice, as well as our three companions and a rental car. Packed to the brim with only a dim idea how to get to Cortina we directed our vehicle North. And somehow I was able to navigate us securely to the <a href="http://www.dolomiti.org/ita/cortina/laga5torri/ospitalita/CinqueTorri/index.html">Rifugio Cinque Torri</a>. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19259485003/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Cinque Torri Refugio in the morning"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/350/19259485003_a0a9541eef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cinque Torri Refugio in the morning" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Gorgeous, stunning, breath-taking, <em>I love it</em>, where words that were uttered after the engine was switched off. We lost no time and shouldered ropes and climbing kit and hit the first crag, Torre Quarta Bassa. An easy 6a/ 5 Multi-Pitch route was picked for warm-up by Stu and me, as well as popping our Multi-Pitch Cherries. Our vocabulary soon was enhanced by meaningful phrases like <em>Where’s the next bolt?</em> and <em>That’s not a 5a!</em> As the sun was making the five beautiful towers of the Cinque Torri draw long shadows on the meadows we were rappelling down, walking back to the Rifugio. Dinner was calling, and so was the wine. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692381198/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Abseil"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/365/19692381198_dfdebbbb20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Abseil" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20660448541/in/dateposted/" title="Cinque Torri"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/730/20660448541_7fb341c5b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cinque Torri" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It’s common for climbers to get up early, and so we decided on a 6 o’clock start to climb a route on Cima Grande’s Southwest Face, which gets backed in the sun during the day. Rosamunde was climbed by Sam, Stu and me, and then breakfast was calling us back. Yes, half-board at the Rifugios is mandatory and highly recommended. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19257749664/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Morning Session on Rosamund"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/19257749664_f16b5152cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Morning Session on Rosamund" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stu and me were the Multi-Pitch team, and as we were in the company of a battalion of Italian soldiers it was the Via Normale on Torre Inglese which we climbed. There was exposure, sweaty palms, smiles, running it out, more smiles, squeezes and a hard-earned summit with trad gear. More smiles, two abseils and then some Apfelstrudel and Cappuccino. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19885405791/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Stu at the summit of Torre Inglese"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/524/19885405791_0e4b6fb8af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stu at the summit of Torre Inglese" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A few easy climbs at the School of Rock sector on the way back to a hot shower and a slab attempt that ended with the rain. Doesn’t matter, because there’s wine, dinner, card games, laughter, sitting outside and taking in the view. The next morning it was up before sunrise at 5 o’clock and another attempt on the slab. Stu on-sighted it, I failed, and so it was back to breakfast, packing up and heading onwards.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692379838/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Stu in the early morning light after having topped out on the Trephor Slab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/386/19692379838_e315f1fc7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stu in the early morning light after having topped out on the Trephor Slab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A resupply in Cortina and we drove onwards. The Sorapiss Circuit was <em>The Plan™</em>. Car parked, backpacks with bivy gear shouldered and onwards we went. A coffee at the Rifugio on the way and up that lovely scree field in the 30°C heat. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19257748424/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="On the approach to the Sorapiss Circuit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/452/19257748424_cfb90f08d2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On the approach to the Sorapiss Circuit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20660450391/in/dateposted/" title="Lago di Sorapiss and a wonderful scree field"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5692/20660450391_04f879eb54_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Lago di Sorapiss and a wonderful scree field" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It was getting late, the clouds were closing in, and so we stayed put at the end of the world. A un-secured hike 1000 m over a valley on narrow ledges was to be done fresh &amp; full of energy. The thunderstorms hitting us shortly after the bivies were rolled out made us congratulate ourselves for our smart decision. It was early to bed, sleep in, lightning storms all night. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692405060/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="A break between Thunderstorms"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/309/19692405060_906ac422e5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="A break between Thunderstorms" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As the sky cleared in the morning we decided against the sketchy approach, strolled back and drove to mountains with fairer weather. We found it in the Val Gardena, where we rolled out our sleeping bags on the Parking lot, shared wine with other campers and were looking forward to the Via Ferrata Brigata Tridentina.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19693765169/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="After the rain on the Gardena Pass"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/545/19693765169_d3bb7e6da4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="After the rain on the Gardena Pass" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19854193206/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="The Bridge on the Brigata Tridentina Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3736/19854193206_49e12f1c1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The Bridge on the Brigata Tridentina Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning a cloud inversion in the valley (<em>yeps, the opening photo</em>) made us dally around, but we were still in good time on the Via Ferrata and topped out happy at the top. A Kaiserschmarn later Matt, Sam, Stu and me explored the high plateau before it was back to the valley, which involved more scree, steel cables, snow fields and the urge to run it all down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653770955/in/dateposted/" title="&quot;Easy&quot; Downclimb"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5717/20653770955_0e4089c4d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;Easy&quot; Downclimb" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I rolled out my bivy under a Boulder Problem called Sella benath Sassolunga that night, taking in the fine view of a star-filled sky. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19885410521/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Sassolunga at night"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3834/19885410521_a0c2b49e98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sassolunga at night" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Easy climbs ensued the next morning after breakfast, followed by a check in to the fine <a href="http://www.dolomitesrefugeandhut.it">Rifugio Carlo Valentini</a>. A private bunk room, warm showers and more climbing followed by more showers followed, topped by a delicious dinner which had us wonder if we understood the quoted price right. The next morning saw us drive our car to the start of the Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata, the <em>most difficult</em> Via ferrata yet. An inexperienced Via Ferrata-ist before us had us wondering if we weren’t pokering too high, but as climbers we dispatched the first difficult bit in no time and hence enjoyed in peace the rest of the Via Ferrata. Suspension bridges, views on the Marmolada, ridge walks and caves made for an atmospheric hike. Just the long, steep walk back, we could have done without it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20466763028/in/dateposted/" title="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/610/20466763028_99e525a09a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20645582602/in/dateposted/" title="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/639/20645582602_a3565a0977_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And that was it. A long, or rather short night later I was on my way to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-soa-jury-meeting.html">SOA Jury Meeting</a> and the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i.html">OutDoor 2015</a>, while my good friends travelled on to other parts of the world. But we were sure of one thing: That we loved the Dolomites, and that we will be back. And if you like mountains, good food &amp; wine, great climbing and fun Via Ferratas, you too should pay the Dolomits a visit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20465766490/in/dateposted/" title="At the End of the World, there is happiness"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5670/20465766490_422c576db0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="At the End of the World, there is happiness" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 209]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/twir-209.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-16T23:51:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/twir-209</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Thousands of tired, nerve-shaken, over-civilized people are beginning to find out that going to the mountains is going home; that wildness is a necessity.”</em> ― <a href="http://amzn.to/1Le0bl1">John Muir</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692402170/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Via della Trincee Sign"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3815/19692402170_4f02e99095_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Via della Trincee Sign" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/1998166/plastics">The Invisible Nightmare in your Fleece</a>, making you think about the plastic garments we wear when outdoors.</p>

<p>But is wool any better? Read Patagonia’s reply to <a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2015/08/petas-wool-video.html?sf11902806=1">PETA’s Wool Video</a>.</p>

<p>And then you realize that <a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/1998221/youths">the Outdoor Industry has a Millennial Problem</a>. </p>

<p>Maybe we should just think about <a href="https://www.freitag.de/autoren/sandro-abbate/von-einem-der-auszog-um-zu-leben?">this guy who went out to life</a>? [German]</p>

<p>Or have a browse of the new <a href="http://www.trailgroove.com/issue23.html">Trail Groove Magazine</a>?</p>

<p>You also could climb the Eiger with <a href="http://project360.mammut.ch/#home">Mammut’s Project 360°</a>.</p>

<p>Then just turn around <a href="http://dirtbagdiaries.com/the-shorts-the-hourglass/">The Hourglass</a> again.</p>

<p>Forrest and friends <a href="http://www.mountainonline.com/who-speaks-for-rivers-yellowstone-paddling-controversy/">speak for rivers</a>.</p>

<p>In Finland you’re sadly <a href="https://liveinfinland.wordpress.com/2015/08/14/cycling-sometimes-at-your-own-risk/">cycling mostly on your own risk</a>.</p>

<p>The Value of Content aka “<a href="https://medium.com/i-m-h-o/the-value-of-content-a30bbe8b54a5">Tab Closed; Didn’t Read</a>”, a recommended read for bloggers.</p>

<p><a href="http://enormocast.com/episode-86-mikey-schaefer-the-force-is-strong/">Mikey Schaefer – The Force is Strong</a>.</p>

<p>Take a <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=436094&amp;pw=73183">first look at the new fall arrivals from your favorite outdoor brands</a> at Backcountry and get free 2-Day Shipping - or <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3638&amp;pw=73183">save up to 70% at the Backcountry.com Outlet</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=355989&amp;pw=73183">Save Up To 50% On Men’s &amp; Women’s Technical Jackets, Pants &amp; Shirts At SierraDesigns.com</a> and get free shipping on order over $49 with the coupon code AFFSHIP49.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Erika climbs the <a href="http://ulligunde.com/2015/08/crashkurs-im-klettern-fur-grose-cassin-westliche-zinne/">Cassin</a> on Cima Ovest. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://revontulia.com/2015/08/15/alpenglow/">Alpenglow</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p>Joe’s <a href="https://joecruz.wordpress.com/2015/08/11/norway-journal-pt-1/">Norway Journal, Part 1</a>.</p>

<p>Fabian hikes &amp; scrambles up the <a href="http://www.aufundab.eu/tour/hoch-hinaus-matterhorn">Matterhorn</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2015/08/09/the-lone-star-express-lael-vs-lael/">The Lone Star Express: Lael vs. Lael</a>.</p>

<p>Rich is <a href="https://runrideandsleepoutside.wordpress.com/2015/08/09/travelling-light/">travelling light</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://stefanandcherry.com/2015/08/12/flugger-farg/">FLÜGGER FÄRG</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.shanecycles.com/48-hour-ride-eat-sleep-challenge/">48 hour Ride eat sleep challenge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://adventureblog.nationalgeographic.com/2015/07/30/exploring-the-birthplace-of-sport-climbing-in-europes-grandest-canyon/?">Exploring the Birthplace of Sport Climbing in Europe’s Grandest Canyon</a>.</p>

<p>Rick reports fromthe <a href="http://besthike.com/2015/08/11/colorado-trail-silverton-to-durango-day-3/">Colorado Trail</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/34414313?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://one9638.blog79.fc2.com/blog-entry-518.html">双六小屋まで</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Jill is <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2015/08/getting-my-lungs-back.html">getting her lungs back</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://sbrtrfr.blogspot.co.uk/2015/08/shoe-selfys.html">Shoe selfies</a>.</p>

<p>James is <a href="https://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2015/08/15/slackpacking-north-peak-grit/">Slackpacking North Peak Grit</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://tomripleyclimbing.blogspot.fi/2015/08/freezing-cold-soaked-through-and-scared.html">Freezing cold, soaked through and scared out of your tree</a> aka when light, fast and high goes wrong.</p>

<p><a href="http://thegoatthatwrote.net/2015/08/12/boulder-hopping-in-wildflower-heaven/">Boulder-Hopping in Wildflower Heaven</a>.</p>

<p>A nice dayhike in <a href="http://wanderingthewild.com/2015/08/13/tent-rocks-national-monument-day-hike/">Tent Rocks National Monument</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://freedirtmonger.blogspot.fi/2015/08/great-basin-traverse-ruby-crest-part-2.html">Great Basin Traverse: Ruby Crest Part 2</a>.</p>

<p>Going down the <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/zentralalpenweg-02-abstieg-pfaelzer-huette-nenzinger-himmel-nenzing/">Zentralalpenweg 02</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://www.bergzeit.de/primus-spider-stove-set/?pid=81" title="Primus Eta Spider Stove"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/283/20038351478_08e60b1522_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Primus Eta Spider Stove" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A first look at the new gear from the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i.html">OutDoor 2015</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/2003146/birth-boots">The Birthplace of your Boots</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://fstoppers.com/education/cheap-camera-versus-expensive-camera-part-2-prints-73187">Cheap Camera Versus Expensive Camera</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.albertdros.com/#!1-week-with-the-Zeiss-Batis-25mm-f2/cyck/559525b80cf20881704255d8">One week with the Zeiss Batis 25mm f2</a>.</p>

<p>Tookie reviews the <a href="http://walkwithtookie.com/high-uv-buff-with-insect-shield/">High UV Buff with Insect Shield</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2015/08/shameless-smoothies-die-smoothies-zum-anruehren-fuer-unterwegs/">Shameless Smoothies</a>, the smoothies for the trail.</p>

<p><a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/helium-600-mountain-equipment-test/">Mountain Equipment Helium 600 Review</a>. [German]</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for On-The-Trail updates! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em> </p>

<form action="https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr" method="post" target="_top">
<input type="hidden" name="cmd" value="_s-xclick" />
<input type="hidden" name="hosted_button_id" value="NTMRRLNGUHQ22" />
<table>
<tr><td><input type="hidden" name="on0" value="" /></td></tr><tr><td><select name="os0">
	<option value="TWIR Subscriber">TWIR Subscriber : €8.00 EUR - monthly</option>
	<option value="HiF Enthusiast">HiF Enthusiast : €19.00 EUR - monthly</option>
</select> </td></tr>
</table>
<input type="hidden" name="currency_code" value="EUR" />
<input type="image" src="https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_subscribeCC_LG.gif" border="0" name="submit" alt="PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!" />
<img alt="" border="0" src="https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif" width="1" height="1" />
</form>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

<p><a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/?utm_source=PTID13002584"><img src="http://ad.globetrotter-partnerprogramm.de/1-globetrotter-728x90.gif" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Icebreaker MerinoLOFT Helix Zip Jacket]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/icebreaker-ws-helix-jacket.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-11T23:47:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/icebreaker-ws-helix-jacket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Toasty AND Stylish? It must be the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/icebreaker-helix-ls-zip-hood-wolljacke/">Icebreaker W’s MerinoLOFT Helix Zip Jacket</a>, filled with Merino Loft Insulation. A look at this unique insulation layer for women.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20291209068/in/dateposted/" title="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/426/20291209068_7269e4a20e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/icebreaker/">Icebreaker</a> MerinoLOFT Helix Zip Jacket for Women arrived in the beginning of the year here at the Hiking in Finland HQ and has seen daily use over the winter, spring and rather cool summer months since. It’s designed as an insulation garment that works on its own or under a shell layer, and is filled with 100% Merino wool as insulation, what Icebreaker calls <em>Merino Loft</em>. What’s special about this insulation is that it it is recycled icebreaker Merino wool on the inside, while the outside is made from recycled polyester, which makes this also a more environmentally friendly choice than other insulation layers (wool is degradable and a natural fibre, whereas synthetic insulation materials are not). The shell also has a light DWR treatment and sheds light rain. On the inside a soft wool heather lining makes for a comfortable feeling.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20292582069/in/dateposted/" title="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/419/20292582069_feefb22bfc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That’s the materials, but also the cut is functional, not to mention the details. The jacket has good freedom of movement, with stretchy side panels that also help with breathability. Thumbloops keep wrists warm and the sleeves in place, zippered pockets on the outside warm up hands or store small items, and the zippered inside pocket has also a cable exit for listening music on the go. The collar keeps cold wind from your neck and the hem has a drawstring so the generated warmth can not escape.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20479254575/in/dateposted/" title="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/323/20479254575_01212e27f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19856583194/in/dateposted/" title="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/475/19856583194_73c41b125e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20292581679/in/dateposted/" title="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3698/20292581679_34179331e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The jacket was been worn outdoors from March till now, and has seen lots &amp; lots of use - and still looks great. It’s not as warm as other insulation materials like down so you’ll need to move (a bit, like light hiking) to be warm in it, but on the positive side once you for example enter a hut you don’t need to immediately need to take the jacket off or overheat like in a down jacket. If you’re mostly static in really, really cold weather then the jacket might not be the best, but if you move a lot in cold temperatures then you’ll love it. The side panels tend to have a minimum amount of pilling, especially on the inside. This does not bother in use and is to be expected from the material. </p>

<p>All in all the jacket has made the wearer very happy. The MerinoLOFT Helix Zip Jacket is stylish and warm, with useful details for hiking &amp; everyday use. You can wear it without problems in town and don’t look like you’re just coming from the Karakorum, but also stay warm in -8°C in winter when you’re building a snow castle. If it gets colder or snows/ rains a lot it feels good under a hardshell, but woks best when worn on its own. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19856585294/in/dateposted/" title="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/323/19856585294_a92eef19ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Icebreaker W&#x27;s Helix Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Still not convinced? <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157654757210864">View more photos on Flickr</a>, read Corinna’s <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2015/03/review-icebreaker-womens-helix-jacket.html">Review</a> or Rene’s take on the <a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/die-icebreaker-helix-ls-zip-wolljacke-im-test/">Men’s Helix Jacket</a>, then get the Helix Jacket at <a href="http://bit.ly/1NmXQBv">Backcountry</a> or <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/icebreaker-helix-ls-zip-hood-wolljacke/">Bergfreunde</a>, available as a Men’s and Women’s version. </p>

<p><em>Thanks to Bergfreunde for the free supply of the jacket.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2015 - I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-10T23:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What new gear is coming in 2016 for lightweight backpackers, mountaineers, climbers and outdoor lovers? </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665148874/in/dateposted/" title="OutDoor Award Showcase"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/559/19665148874_502f67dd93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OutDoor Award Showcase" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-research">Outdoor Research</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com">Outdoor Research</a>’s big news was that they now have a new investor on board, which allows them to invest more into R&amp;D and tap into the knowledge of the new partner. The first result is the <strong>Precipice Jacket™</strong> which uses the new AscentShell™ fabric technology, a 308 g (Size L) hardshell that’s made of 100% nylon 20D mechanical stretch ripstop face with a 100% Polyester 12D backer. The jacket is fully seam-taped and has a laminated construction with Dynamic Reach™ Underarm Panels which allow great freedom of movement. A helmet compatible Wire-Brimmed Halo-Hood™ keeps the head dry and one of the internal pockets doubles as a stuff sack. An interesting jacket with a new technology, curious to see if it performs better than existing hardshell fabrics.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279450652/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/376/20279450652_26a25f52f2_b.jpg" width="694" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Next up was the <strong>Ferrosi Summit Hooded Jacket™</strong> which adds a more durable, rugged jacket to the Ferrosi family that is still highly breathable while offering protection  for full mountain conditions. It is 526 g in Size 34 and has all the bells &amp; whistles you need from a mountain jacket: A helmet-compatible Wire-Brimmed Halo-Hood™, zippered chest &amp; hand pockets, Dynamic Reach™ Underarm Panels and being of course water-, wind-, and abrasion-resistant. Also new to the Ferrosi family is the <strong>Ferrosi Crag Pants™</strong> which will tip the scales at 314 g in Size 34 and comes with articulated knees, a gusseted crotch and a low-profile waist with Knit Stretch Panels for freedom of movement in the mountains.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665150104/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/393/19665150104_302f925916_b.jpg" width="597" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I really loved the look of the <strong>Women’s Ferrosi Knickers™</strong> which had a great orange (that was slightly difficult to photograph). It’s a rock climbing pants that has stretch knit panels at the waist which allows you to easily wear a harness over it. The lightweight stretch-woven construction is highly durable, for fun days at the crag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666841233/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Women’s  Ferrosi  Knickers™"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/487/19666841233_2bcc39743d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Women’s  Ferrosi  Knickers™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Already available are the <strong>Splitter Gloves™</strong>, OR’s take on crack gloves. These were very comfortable thanks to the synthetic suede on the inside and a non-slip  synthetic leather on the outside gives you grip in cracks and protects your hands. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099785740/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Splitter Gloves™"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/20099785740_b33bc64944_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Splitter Gloves™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Completely new is also the <strong>Sensor Dry Series</strong> which come in Premium &amp; Standard versions. Both are waterproof according to the IPX-8 Standard, fully touchscreen (and camera!) functional, have welded seams and are fairly lightweight. The Premium versions come with waterproof pins for your headphones and can swim when dropped into the water. Available for normal sized smartphone, massive smartphones and tablets.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101180819/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3709/20101180819_8489a1fa22_b.jpg" width="735" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099794998/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/327/20099794998_0cf1f64428_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And finally there were plenty of new hats, like the <strong>Helium Rain Bucket™</strong>, a waterproof hat; the <strong>Mesa Verde Sun Hat™</strong>, a 78 g light sun hat for the ladies; and the <strong>Springboard Cap</strong> I am sporting there, a lightweight cap for your trail adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101172829/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Helium Rain Bucket™"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/465/20101172829_070b5efe52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Helium Rain Bucket™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099780118/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Mesa Verde Sun Hat™"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3717/20099780118_b0cba6e0cf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Mesa Verde Sun Hat™" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287808785/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Outdoor Research Springboard Cap"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/507/20287808785_b89171d0e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research Springboard Cap" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="cilogear">CiloGear</h2>

<p><em>“Have you seen anything new &amp; interesting yet?”</em> is the standard conversation opener at the fair. In years past my reply was usually <em>“Nope”</em> but this year I passed Graham from <a href="http://www.cilogear.com">CiloGear</a> as I had some time to spare and walked with him to his booth where he showed me something. What I saw then was not new, but it was for me the coolest thing on the fair which I told everyone who asked me the opening question then. Graham had a pack along - the first preproduction <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/30wwo.html">3030</a> ever made - which had seen roughly 900 (!) days outdoors, including two expeditions to Pakistan and was along establishing a new route on K7, a 6,934 m peak near the Charakusa Valley in the Karakoram. The owner sent it in to get the extension collar renewed, but the rest of the pack - seams and material - were still in great shape (albeit a tad dirty, but what do you expect after over two years in the mountains!). For me the most interesting thing in the show, not just because it shows that small manufacturers produce superb gear that lasts, but also because of the stories this pack would tell. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261525866/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/517/20261525866_0308c0f8e0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293723261/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/337/20293723261_cba928572c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099796360/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="CiloGear"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/496/20099796360_40b3658e5d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="CiloGear" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx">Arc’teryx</h2>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> was their <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-acrux-ar-alpine-boot.html">2016 Footwear</a> which I already have presented to you in June. The next big news was the <strong>Atom SL Hoody</strong>, an ultralight summer insulation piece that will weigh 285 g for a Men’s Medium. The Coreloft 40g/m² insulation is quilted to the liner while on the side and arm panels a soft fleece material helps with ventilation. Really interesting is the No-Slip-Zip™ front zipper which works like a series of speed bumps that keep the zipper from self-opening. It packs tiny and so can always be along in your backpack on your mountain adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099806578/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Atom SL Hoody"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20099806578_9a436d4504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Atom SL Hoody" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That backpack could be one of the new <strong>Cierzo Packs</strong>, Arc’teryx’s updated alpine climbing pack (in the centre of the photo underneath). Available as a Cierzo 18 (375 g) and a Cierzo 28 (550 g) they open via a pull to open, pull to close drawcord system like the Alpha FL packs, but also feature a SwiftCord™ drawstring compression system which is versatile in use and can be stored away when not needed. You can carry ice tools with them, and the Cierzo 28 has a padded back panel that can be removed to save more weight. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665147454/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx 2016 Backpacks"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3796/19665147454_f7b2ba9550_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx 2016 Backpacks" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Interesting for hiking &amp; backpacking was also the <strong>Pelon Comp SS</strong> which is made from core-spun Merino wool and has durable nylon inserts in high wear areas as the shoulders. They weigh 145 g in Size M and have a Regular fit and should be pretty good for long trips in the outdoors thanks to the properties of Merino wool.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287804825/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Pelon Comp SS"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/458/20287804825_9135589edc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Pelon Comp SS" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="petzl">Petzl</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a> had a lot of new gear on their booth, and they were also celebrating 25 years of the GriGri, probably the most popular belay device amongst all sorts of climbers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287806355/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl 25 years GriGri"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20287806355_da5ee93c48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl 25 years GriGri" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But the new gear! All of the IRVIS, VASAK, SARKEN, LYNX, DARTWIN and DART crampons get technical upgrades, making them even more effective, durable and practical. Effective: the horizontal structure of the frame brings the boot sole as close to the crampon as possible for increased sensitivity and precision. Durable: a special steel, chosen by Petzl for its rigidity and strength, allows a reduction in thickness to offer light weight crampons with sharper points. Practical: user-friendly binding systems, ANTISNOW and interchangeable front sections.</p>

<p>The <strong>IRVIS, VASAK and SARKEN Crampons</strong> have front sections that are interchangeable and available as accessories, which means you can have one crampon for all your needs and don’t need two or more of crampons in the house. Now you can simply &amp; fast convert for example a technical mountaineering crampon into one for glacier travel. All of them come with the new ANTISNOW, which limits snow balling up under your crampon. The VASAK will weigh 810 g, the IRVIS 710 g and the SARKEN 810 g, all with the FLEXLOCK binding. The linking bar in all three can be shortened to fit small sizes (Size 36 is the smallest size all three will fit, with Size 50 being the max).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261527636/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl Vasak Crampon"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/266/20261527636_0a5b15084a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Vasak Crampon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>ELIA</strong> is a new Women’s helmet with the OMEGA headband system. The notch in the back is for the long hair and allows ladies to put the helmet on and off very easily with a lot of comfort. It is 285 g light and also has a new webbing adjustment mechanism which allows the helmet to be precisely adjusted for different head shapes. The ABS shell and expanded polystyrene liner will keep the wearer save.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099784168/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl Elia helmet"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/367/20099784168_48ce174be7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Elia helmet" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>TIBLOC</strong> has been around for a while and gets a update for 2016. The new ultralight emergency ascender gets a system that automatically presses the carabiner against the rope to initiate the clamping action on the rope. You can see this advantage in comparison to the current TIBLOC in the 2nd photo underneath. The new TIBLOC has a rope compatibility from 8 to 11 mm and weighs 35 g.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279450132/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl TIBLOC"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/255/20279450132_475d419f27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl TIBLOC" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099789690/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl TIBLOC New &amp; Old"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/270/20099789690_24cc760bea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl TIBLOC New &amp; Old" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Furthermore there’s two new <strong>Semi-static ropes</strong> coming, two new <strong>carabiners</strong>, the <strong>ALCANADRE</strong>, a large volume pack for transporting canyoning equipment and the <strong>BUG</strong>, a small backpack for single-day multi-pitch climbing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101171129/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/256/20101171129_1a96229815_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293742921/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Petzl"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/532/20293742921_ae05b89662_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="rjk">Röjk</h2>

<p>Doesn’t the <a href="http://rojksuperwear.com/en/">Röjk</a> booth look fantastic? Of course it does - Linus &amp; Jan shanghaied me in helping it putting it up! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287797785/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/315/20287797785_a0bb2fee35_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That’s the Guys PrimaLoft Zippen Hood in purple, which rocks. It’s a S.O.A. Winner, too. But new is the <strong>Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood</strong> that Linus models underneath. It’s a lighter weight hoody jacket. The PrimaLoft Polyester makes it lightweight and nicely soft on the skin, is wicking very fast while the Merino wool makes it stay fresh. The cool look makes it a fine choice for chilling at the campfire or going to town. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261528726/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3791/20261528726_0343b99044_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Guys PrimaLoft Drifter Hood" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Somehow I managed to not take a photo of Röjk’s new T-Shirt designs for the <strong>SuperTee</strong>, which is a shame because they were awesome. Röjk continues their Inka, Maya &amp; Aztec theme with very pretty designs on their 60% Merino wool &amp; 40% Modal shirts for Chicks and Guys, so please excuse the absence of the photos and believe me: They rock. What I did photograph, though, is the new <strong>Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody</strong>. These are made from Merino wool and Lyocell for a lightweight and comfortable backpacking hoody that stays fresh and cool for a long time. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19665161864/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/473/19665161864_18f7e5c3ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Chicks &amp; Guys Roamer Hoody" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Sadly not pictured are the great looking <strong>SuperTank</strong> tops, which are made from Merino wool and Modal and also come in sick Inca patterns. What I can show you is the <strong>PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock</strong> which should be super breathable thanks to the open mesh structure on top and help avoid sweaty feet. Made from PrimaLoft Yarn, Merino wool and Polyamide they should be durable, keeping your toes warm, dry and looking good!  </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666843133/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Röjk PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/552/19666843133_73ca83b1b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk PrimaLoft Hiker Lightweight Sock" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Most importantly, you can shop their gear online right now in the <a href="http://rojksuperwear.com/en/">Röjk online shop</a>!</p>

<h2 id="ortovox">Ortovox</h2>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://www.ortovox.de/">Ortovox</a> were the backpacks, especially the <strong>PEAK</strong> which has a unique SWISSWOOL back system that’s made from pressed Swiss wool. The ideas is that in exactly the same way as with clothing you would benefit from the wool’s great moisture and microclimate management and therefore the backpanel feels comfortable and dry on your back. Otherwise the PEAK is a good looking climbing backpack with a c circumferential front zipper for easy access. Will be interesting to see if the backpanel works as imagined or if it just sucks itself full with sweat and stays wet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261545696/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/323/20261545696_888b79ac59_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20287805525/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack Swisswool backpanel"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/284/20287805525_5ba8004bda_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack Swisswool backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293731291/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/298/20293731291_2701787a89_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX PEAK backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET</strong> is from Ortovox’s new softshell line (called, yes, MERINO SHIELD SHELL) and will weigh 353 g (Size ?). The line is made for high-alpine tours and has hence the features you’d want from a jacket for such outings: Freedom of movement, high abrasion-resistance, breathability and comfort. It has a protective shell made from Cordura®, the outer side of front pocket is made of felted wool and has an athletic fit. It was a comfortable jacket and felt very nice.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20101189529/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="ORTOVOX MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/395/20101189529_1064533f20_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX MERINO SHIELD SHELL (MI) PIZ BADILE JACKET" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kitka">Kitka</h2>

<p>It was pretty cool to meet the guys from <a href="http://kitkaclimbing.com">Kitka Climbing</a> at the fair, especially with their own booth! Kitka makes polyurethane climbing holds, handcrafted in Finland, with a lot of unique &amp; cool shapes. They felt great and I reckon I will need to get a few sets for my own boulder wall!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20293717451/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Kitka Climbing Holds"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/461/20293717451_35656e4206_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kitka Climbing Holds" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="rab">Rab</h2>

<p>As always I enjoyed my visit to <a href="http://rab.equipment/">Rab</a>, and their new kit really rocks. There was a lot of new lightweight gear for the ladies, like the fine <strong>Women’s Flashpoint Jacket</strong> which is made from 3L Pertex Shield+ Fabric and will weigh 160 g for a Women’s 12. It has a helmet compatible hood with a lightweight &amp; flexible polymer peak to keep your eyes dry in the rain. It’s designed as the jacket that you have along in case the rain hits you while you are on a Multi-Pitch route or an alpine ascent, and as it is so light you don’t need to ponder if you take it along. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261546376/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Rab Women’s Flashpoint Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/303/20261546376_843ff13911_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Rab Women’s Flashpoint Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>New is also the <strong>Women’s Continuum Jacket</strong> which will be the lightest option in the women’s insulation range at 240 g in Size 12. It’s filled with 100g of 850FP European Goose Down that’s hydrophobic. It will pack down also very small and thus also can always come along on your mountain adventures.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20266787270/in/dateposted/" title="Rab Women&#x27;s Continuum Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/397/20266787270_c43e929260_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab Women&#x27;s Continuum Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And I liked the new Rock Climbing garments immensely. Functional and stylish, the assortment of pants - from the <strong>Oblique &amp; Rockover Pants</strong> to the <strong>Rampage Jacket</strong> and the many great T-Shirts and hoodies, the Rock Climbing &amp; Lifestyle Collection is great for days at the crag - be it in Kalymnos, Olhava or the Peak District. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20461137201/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/490/20461137201_b89427b206_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20268246319/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/351/20268246319_3f8c184aab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20446195202/in/dateposted/" title="Rab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/402/20446195202_d09a4723c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sea-to-summit">Sea to Summit</h2>

<p>After not visiting <a href="http://www.seatosummit.com">Sea to Summit</a> in 2014 I was happy to check out what they had new this year. The <strong>XSet Pots</strong> are collapsible cooking pots, which should be ideal with simple gas or alcohol stoves. The bottoms are made from hard anodized aluminium with food-grade &amp; heat-resistant silicone walls that fold down for transport, making for small packages while in your pack. The 3 piece kit consists of a 1,3 l kettle, one 2,8 l pot and a 8” frying pan that weigh together 756 g. The kettle on its own is 186 g and the lightest of the whole series and could be all a lightweight backpacker needs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20099778470/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit XSet Pots"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/433/20099778470_24e75f5526_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Sea to Summit XSet Pots" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>New is also the <strong>Aeros Pillow Ultralight</strong> which will weigh 70 g and packs as big as a Kiwi. If you value a good nights sleep and want a lightweight pillow that is very comfortable, this looks like an interesting new offering to the market. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666823983/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Aeros Pillow Ultralight"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/544/19666823983_8fcaf2283a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Aeros Pillow Ultralight" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Ground Control Tent Pegs</strong> are made from high-quality aluminium, weigh 14 g each and have a luminescent pull loop which is easily seen at night, adding a bit more security to your nightly stumbles around your tent. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20261534766/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Ground Control Tent Pegs"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/508/20261534766_ee6a63a867_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Ground Control Tent Pegs" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Self-Adhesive Lash Points</strong> should be especially interesting for packrafters. These allow you to add extra tie-down points to your packraft, either to tie down gear, install thigh straps or or or. And at 18 g per lash point they’re ultralight, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19666827693/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Sea to Summit Self-Adhesive Lash Points"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/536/19666827693_a44f650efd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sea to Summit Self-Adhesive Lash Points" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="vertical-life">Vertical Life</h2>

<p>New at <a href="https://www.vertical-life.info">Vertical-Life</a> was the <strong>Zlag Up!</strong>, a variation on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/zlagboard-pro-review.html">Zlagboard</a> which I use. It’s a smart pull-up bar which works like the Zlagboard with an App on your smartphone to keep track of your training, and as a very special extra there’s the rolley bar which is pretty cool to train your balance.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20279448742/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Zlag Up"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3786/20279448742_904d6fd21e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Zlag Up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="http://guide.vertical-life.info/en/app/">Climbing App Guides</a> also get a lot of new topos all the time, and you can test the app for South Tyrol’s crags for free (I wish I’d known this before my trip to the Dolomites!). </p>

<h2 id="stay-tuned-for-the-next-part-coming-soon">Stay tuned for the next part, coming soon™!</h2>

<p>As usual you can see a lot more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157656356655229">OutDoor 2015 Flickr Album</a>. Sweet. And if you liked this follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for more gear &amp; outdoor updates.  And <a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a> as a payment for my work =)</p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 208]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/twir-208.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-09T23:27:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/twir-208</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“There are nights when the wolves are silent and only the moon howls.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1KYtKqy">George Carlin</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20121805748/in/dateposted/" title="Night at the Lake"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/293/20121805748_d946d1f0ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Night at the Lake" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://semi-rad.com/2015/08/what-is-it-we-love-about-someone-quitting-their-job/">What is it we love about someone quitting their job</a>?</p>

<p>Maybe this: <a href="http://uk.businessinsider.com/ultraromance-bike-camping-free-spirit-does-not-like-work-2015-7">35-year-old American who thinks modern life is too stressful works 6 months a year, then lives on $10 a day adventuring around the world on a bicycle</a>.</p>

<p>Chad is <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2015/08/04/taking-a-break/">taking a break</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://amzn.to/1KYtRm4">Adventure Cycle-Touring Handbook</a> just got a 3rd Edition.</p>

<p><a href="http://robgreenwoodclimbing.com/2015/08/07/a-walk-amongst-the-trees/">A Walk amongst the Trees</a>.</p>

<p>Support <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1065102948/colin-fletcher-the-walking-mans-biography">Colin Fletcher - The Walking Man’s biography</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/new-ultrashell-colours">PHD has new Ultrashell colours</a> - I love the purple!</p>

<p>Did you know that <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=49341&amp;pw=73183">ULA Equipment Backpacks Ship FREE</a> with the purchase of a Pack Cover? Happy Trails!</p>

<p>Have a look at the massive <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/info/listings/ssv-bis-zu-50/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Globetrotter Summer Sale</a> and save up to 50% on a lot of sweet gear.</p>

<p>At the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=464273&amp;pw=73183">Camping Sale at Eastern Mountain Sports</a> you can get up to 40% off on Camping &amp; Hiking Gear.</p>

<p>And the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schlafsaecke/rabatt-bf--true/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc&amp;">Bergfreunde Summer Sale</a> has a lot of great backpacking gear for very low prices.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Craig heads to the <a href="https://sweepingthegarden.wordpress.com/2015/08/05/upper-kern-basin-2015/">Upper Kern Basin</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.skimolife.com/journal/2015/8/6/las-leas-post-numero-uno.html">Las Leñas - Post Numero Uno</a>.</p>

<p>Peter went out on a nice looking <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/08/archipelago-sea-filming-and-paddling.html">Archipelago Sea filming and paddling trip</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/pile-it-on-packrafting-a-first-descent-in-lake-clark-national-park-alaska/">Pile It On – Packrafting a First Descent in Lake Clark National Park, Alaska</a>.</p>

<p>The Goat is <a href="http://thegoatthatwrote.net/2015/08/07/just-a-tiny-bit-lost-in-the-big-snowy-mountains/">just a tiny bit lost in the Big Snowy Mountains</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://kidproject.org/2015/08/07/the-one-thing-my-kids-really-want/">The one thing kids really want</a>.</p>

<p>Colin on his <a href="http://www.tramplite.com/2015/08/cdt-early-exit.html">early CDT Exit</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.walkingwithwired.com/2015/08/day-30-lost-sometimes-found.html">Lost &amp; Sometimes Found</a>.</p>

<p>KulturNatur hikes <a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2015/08/03/alter-hochstapler/">from the Prinz-Luitpold-Haus on the Hochvogel</a>. [German]</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/134183666?color=ffffff&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2015/8/8/black-magic">Black Magic</a>.</p>

<p>Keith’s photos of his <a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/cape-wrath-trail-the-west-highland-way-the-photos/">Cape Wrath Trail &amp; The West Highland Way</a> hike.</p>

<p><a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2015/08/the-burr-trail-and-other-backroads.html">The Burr Trail And Other Backroads</a>.</p>

<p>Ute takes the kids to the <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/wandern-mit-kind-zum-taubensee-chiemgau/">Taubensee</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2015/08/rode-trip-lolo-pass-lost-lake-hood-river/">Lolo Pass – Lost Lake – Hood River</a>.</p>

<p>Martin hikes on the <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/zentralalpenweg-02-totalphuette-schesaplana-brandnergletscher-pfaelzer-huette/">Zentralalpenweg 02</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/bikepacking-slovenia/">Bikepacking Slovenia: The West Loop</a>.</p>

<p>Erik &amp; Jakke went on <a href="http://www.packgofind.com/summer-chill-out">a relaxed pedaling trip to Repovesi</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpinestyle.ca/2015/08/05/the_east_face_of_snowpatch_the_gift_that_keeps_on_giving">The East face of Snowpatch, the gift that keeps on giving</a>.</p>

<p>Enjoying the <a href="http://urbanflyfisher.com/weekenders/">Weekends</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://lightfromthenorth.blogspot.fi/2015/08/the-stanage-vs-challenge-two-thirds.html">The Stanage VS Challenge - a two thirds-successful attempt</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin hikes to the <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/grizzlys-nebel-wanderung-lost-lake-alaska/">Lost Lake</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://haolite.blogspot.tw/2015/08/blog-post_9.html">嵐山回憶 , 回憶嵐山(五):地獄與天堂</a>. [Taiwanese]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19714074614/in/dateposted/" title="Said Belhaj on Great White 7b, Vaxlax, Vaasa"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3770/19714074614_fb95984901_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Said Belhaj on Great White 7b, Vaxlax, Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Sven reviews the <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2015/08/garmin-forerunner-225-mit-optischem-hf-sensor-im-test/">Garmin Forerunner 225 with optical HF Sensor</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A look at the <a href="http://bicycledesign.net/2015/08/livall-bling-smart-helmet/">LIVALL Bling Smart Helmet</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid Review</a>.</p>

<p>Derek shows you some <a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2015/08/pitching-options-for-a-square-tarp/">Pitching Options for a Square Tarp</a>.</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for On-The-Trail updates! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em> </p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 207]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/twir-207.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-02T23:29:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/twir-207</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The secret isn’t in your legs, but in your strength of mind. You need to go for a run when it is raining, windy, and snowing, when lightning sets trees on fire as you pass them, when snowflakes or hailstones strike your legs and body in the storm and make you weep, and in order to keep running, you have to wipe away the tears to see the stones, walls, or sky.</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1VUIPgn">Kilian Jornet, Run or Die</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692405060/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="A break between Thunderstorms"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/309/19692405060_906ac422e5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="A break between Thunderstorms" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://greenecasey.blogspot.fi/2015/07/the-boulder-white-cloud-bonanza.html">The Boulder &amp; White Cloud Bonanza</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://booktwo.org/notebook/citizen-ex/">Citizen Ex</a>.</p>

<p>Hyperlite Mountain Gear will offer their Summit Packs, Ice Packs and a brand new 140L Duffel Bag made of <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=462021&amp;pw=73183">100% woven Dyneema® /non-woven Cuben Fiber laminated fabric</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/07/26/opinion/sunday/the-rise-of-climbing.html">The Rise of Climbing</a> or <a href="http://www.palemorningmedia.com/waterproof-breathable/2015/7/28/the-rise-of-soft-outdoor">The Rise of Soft Outdoor</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.epictv.com/media/podcast/philippe-ribires-near-death-experience-and-middle-east-travels-%7C-epictv-climbing-daily-ep-545/603071">Philippe Ribière’s Near-Death Experience And Middle East Travels</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2015/07/29/3602/">Anger is an Energy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://woodtrekker.blogspot.fi/2015/07/the-neglect-of-backpacking.html">The Neglect of Backpacking</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/weitwander-rueckblick-juli-2015/">Long distance hiking tidbits</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/sporting-scene/selling-rock-climbing-in-the-social-media-era">Selling Rock Climbing in the Social Media Era</a>.</p>

<p>Use Coupon Code: AWESOMESHOE for <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=463573&amp;pw=73183">20% off regular priced Salewa, Adidas Outdoor, Vasque and Chaco footwear at CampSaver.com</a>.</p>

<p>Get a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/climbing-set-configurator/">Via Ferrata Set</a> at Bergzeit.co.uk and check out their <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/outlet-clothing/">Summaer Sale</a> while you’re there!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/sierra-sniveller/">Save an extra $25 on the Jacks ‘R’ Better Sierra Sniveller</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=259941&amp;pw=73183">Save 30% on Popular Patagonia Jackets, Shirts, Pants &amp; more + Free Shipping at Patagonia.com</a>!</p>

<p>And also at the Bergfreunde you can save an extra 10% on all shoes with the Coupon “_extra_shoe” on all <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-schuhe/">shoes</a> - a great time to save on <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/trailrunningschuhe/">a new pair of trailrunners</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/gear/salsa-bucksaw-review/">Salsa Bucksaw Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gearexposure.com/z-cam-e1-the-worlds-smallest-4k-action-camera/">Z-Cam E1, the world´s smallest 4k action camera</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://velo-orange.blogspot.fi/2015/07/if-i-could-only-have-one-bike.html">If You Could Only Have One Bike</a>.</p>

<p>Erika reviews the <a href="http://ulligunde.com/2015/07/alpinhose-makke-von-lundhags-test-kletterhose/">Lundhags Makke Trousers</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.appalachiaandbeyond.com/2015/07/gear-review-thule-capstone-32l-backpack.html">Thule Capstone 32L Backpack</a> Review.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/bergfilm-und-outdoor-buch/klettern-und-bouldern-fuer-kids/">Klettern und Bouldern für Kids</a> Book Review. [German]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20098768321/in/dateposted/" title="Stovemania"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/275/20098768321_6506d9da08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stovemania" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Christy enjoys <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2015/08/02/july-28-pct-its-a-ten/">splendid views on her PCT hike</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://joecruz.wordpress.com/2015/07/28/traverse-in-light-sweden/">Traverse in Light</a>.</p>

<p>Rich spends <a href="https://runrideandsleepoutside.wordpress.com/2015/08/02/a-night-in-the-hole/">a night in the hole</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorwomensalliance.com/2015/07/summer-skiing-in-the-cascades.html">Summer Skiing in the Cascades</a>.</p>

<p>Jill is <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2015/07/at-home-with-ghosts-in-national-park.html">at home with the ghosts in the national park</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ethanwalkerclimbing.blogspot.fi/2015/07/rodellar.html">Rodellar</a>.</p>

<p>Toby goes <a href="http://lightfromthenorth.blogspot.fi/2015/07/bikepacking-around-peak-district.html">bikepacking around the Peak District</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://revontulia.com/2015/08/02/kvaloya-and-the-art-of-bailing/">Kvaløya and the Art of Bailing</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/132244795?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="600" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2015/07/27/alles-nur-kopfsache/">Kopfsache</a>! [German]</p>

<p>David enjoys <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2015/7/28/the-beautiful-south">the beautiful South</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.skadinagrani.pl/2015/07/co-sychac-w-dolince-rumanowej.html">What’s going on in the valley Rumanowej?</a> [Polish]</p>

<p>Fräulein Draußen’s <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/alaska-reise-highlights/">Alaska Highlights</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2015/07/kesaloma-selected-climbs.html">Selected Kesäloma Climbs</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p>Sam got out for a <a href="http://samh.net/backpacking/blog/2015/08/sub-24-hour-overnight-bikepacking-in-the-gallatin-mountains.html">Sub-24 Hour Overnight Bikepacking in the Gallatin Mountains</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/bikepacking-the-colorado-trail/">The Colorado Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Getting out to <a href="http://www.antlersandgills.com/2015/07/getting-out-there-ptarmigan-lake.html">Ptarmigan Lake</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.fi/2015/08/utra-climb-mt-nebo-king-of-wasatch.html">Mt. Nebo, King of the Wasatch</a>.</p>

<p>Hiking in the <a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/into-the-wild-wandern-im-aurlandsdalen/">Aurlandsdalen</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://pantilat.wordpress.com/2015/07/27/seven-gables-gemini-via-bear-basin/">Seven Gables &amp; Gemini via Bear Basin</a>.</p>

<p>3 Girls cycle the <a href="http://ueber66grad.de/erfahrungsbericht-fahrradtour-archipelago-route/">Finnish Archipelago Route</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/backpacking-granite-lake-emigrant-wilderness/">Backpacking Granite Lake, Emigrant Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>Paul &amp; friends are <a href="http://alpinejustice.blogspot.fi/2015/07/rollin-to-rockies.html">Rollin’ to the Rockies</a>.</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for On-The-Trail updates! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em> </p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 206]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-week-in-review-206.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-26T23:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-week-in-review-206</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Nothing is worth more than this day.</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1GQqBBe">Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19872954152/in/dateposted/" title="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19872954152_05a10af0d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.transcontinental.cc/">Transcontinental</a> from Flandern to Istanbul started on Friday morning, follow the best European self-supprted bike race live! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/1997566/scott-jurek-completes-appalachian-trail-run?">Scott Jurek Breaks Appalachian Trail Record</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/?refID=hif">Outdoorline.sk</a> has a new look and lots of ultralight gear not available anywhere else in Europe.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.climbing.com/blog/climbing-media-is-not-sexist-you-are/">Climbing Media Is Not Sexist, You Are</a>.</p>

<p>Pedaling Nowhere is now <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/introducing-bikepacking-com/">Bikepacking.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://semi-rad.com/2015/07/why-are-you-not-using-all-your-vacation-days/">Why Are You Not Using All Your Vacation Days</a>?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.spoon-tamago.com/2015/07/23/japans-largest-treehouse-is-a-sprawling-structure-built-around-a-300-year-old-tree/">Japan’s largest Treehouse</a>.</p>

<p>Get a packraft, paddle and PFD with the <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Offers/Packrafting-touring-package-Nortik-Trekraft-Anfibio-Buoy-Boy-Moll-Playa::621.html?language=en">Packrafting touring package</a> for just 699€! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/15/your-money/what-mountain-climbing-can-teach-you-about-business.html?smid=fb-share&amp;_r=0">What Mountain Climbing Can Teach You About Business</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=2267&amp;pw=73183">Take an additional 25% off Outlet Items at Backcountry.com + Free 2-Day Shipping Over $50. Coupon Code: OUTLET25</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1TZFPxd">20% off on all climbing shoes this weekend at Bergfreunde</a>! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=264573&amp;pw=73183">REI Members can earn a $20 Bonus Card</a> when they spend $100 or more till August 2. Not yet a member? Then join today.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=45773&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10083/45773/55699/73183/image.gif" width="728" height="145" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://blog.scottjurek.com/post/124919853524/reflections-on-the-appalachian-trail">Scott Jurek reflects on the Appalachian Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Jessie hikes on the <a href="http://bunterwegs.com/isola-chiavenna-via-spluga/">Via Spluga</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://bicyclenomad.com/2015/07/21/tasmania-granville-harbour-to-arthur-river/">Granville Harbour to Arthur River</a> by bike.</p>

<p>Alex <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/06/i-hiked-cape-wrath-trail.html">hiked the Cape Wrath Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://dailey7779.blogspot.fi/2015/07/southwest-is-best-grand-canyon-bryce.html">Hiking Adventures in the Canyons of Arizona and Utah</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YvS6O9lVkkg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://campillustrated.com/post/124768723541/mobile-art-studio-week-2">Mobile Art Studio</a>, Week two.</p>

<p><a href="http://fisterrabicicleta.com/2015/07/23/la-ultima-frontera-alaska/">Alaska</a>, the last frontier. [Spanish]</p>

<p><a href="http://hikerdawn.blogspot.fi/2015/07/dawn-westrum-this-was-perfect-ending-to.html">Dawn’s perfect ending to the Red Bull X-Alps</a>.</p>

<p>Jacob made <a href="http://urbanpackrafter.com/Guide-to-the-River-Fjatan">a (packrafting) Guide to the River Fjätan</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://howlingmist.blogspot.fi/2015/07/mount-brandon-to-connor-pass.html">Mount Brandon to the Connor Pass</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/21485627/">MPB</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.williswall.com/willis-wall-blog/2015/7/25/mt-rainier-grand-tour-part-1-east.html">Mt. Rainier Grand Tour</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://amzn.to/1MrPMRV" title="Olympus OM-D E-M5"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/289/19138599368_5d09b38efb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Olympus OM-D E-M5" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip Review</a>.</p>

<p>Check out Benjamin’s <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2015/07/outdoor-show-2015-impressions-day-2/">Imressions from the 2015 OutDoor</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/jottnar-fjorm-review/">Jöttnar Fjörm review</a>.</p>

<p>A look at the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hsBmWGDakgw">new Scarpa Phanotom Line</a> with Ueli Steck.</p>

<p><a href="http://fuusora.blogspot.fi/2015/07/hiker-directions-showcase.html">Hiker directions showcase</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://pig-monkey.com/2015/07/apek/">APEK Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://injuringeternity.net/2015/07/25/ocun-crack-gloves-review/">Ocun Crack Gloves Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cbjimtrip.blogspot.fi/2015/07/andwander-trek-2way-pants.html">andwander Trek 2Way Pants Review</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for On-The-Trail updates! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em> </p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=197&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/197/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="468" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Wide Open]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Wide Open</em> has the byline <em>New Outdoor and Landscape Photography</em>. If it is really new and if you should get a copy, you read in my review.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968932345/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/319/19968932345_8fc222df65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gestalten-verlag/">Gestalten Verlag</a>. They make cool coffee table books with great photos and texts, so when <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">The Great Wide Open</a> appeared on my radar I was eager to check it out. An email and a few days later the heavy book slammed on my porch, ready to be browsed. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19780862558/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3665/19780862558_72b216d413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>However, opening the book the euphoria quickly ended. Sure, there are very fine images in there, but just as much of them look like they’re shot on an iPhone for Instagram and not for a large coffee table book. It feels like every other photo is a grainy mess that looked great on your Instagram feed when seen on a smartphone but shouldn’t have been printed in such a large format. Speaking of Instagram, if you’re on it and follow some landscape photographers then you’ll have seen the vast majority of these images in one form or another already. Another disappointment was that you could clearly see in many images that they have been taken not far away from a road or civilization - given that the Prologue of the book refers to <a href="http://amzn.to/1SFXAis">Ansel Adams</a> and how he would set off on long expeditions to capture expansive, wild landscapes that feels a bit wrong. Oh, and if you don’t like Chris Burkard - don’t get the book. Half the images are from him, and while they’re technically very good I personally find them a bit boring. On ther other hand, if you love him - get the book!</p>

<p>But for all that there’s also some very great &amp; inspiring photos in the book. The pictures from Anki Grøthe, Kilian Schönberger, Jimmy Chin, Logan Watts and a few others are crisp, sharp and with a fresh perspective on the outdoors. Add in the small stories and anecdotes from the photographers, athletes and outdoor folks and you get a book that will inspire you at least for one afternoon. Well, maybe a couple more. And if you like Instagram photos and would love to see them in a big book, you’ll probably read it every day! So if you feel like you want to give The Great Wide Open a chance and browse it yourself then order it directly at <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">Gestalten</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1RXDe9B">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJyEz">Amazon.co.uk</a> &amp; <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJFzT">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968931705/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/374/19968931705_29152e803e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The SOA Jury Meeting]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-soa-jury-meeting.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-23T23:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-soa-jury-meeting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorgroup.com/projects-activities/scandinavian-outdoor-award/">Scandinavian Outdoor Award</a> is the only Award for Outdoor Gear (<em>if compared to the ISPO Award, OutDoor Industry Award et al.</em>) which tests gear where it’s meant to be used - in the outdoors. I was honoured to be invited to this years Jury meeting in <a href="http://www.montafon.at/en">Montafon</a>, right after my Dolomites Tour and before the <a href="">2015 OutDoor</a>. Here’s an inside look at the Jury meeting and my thoughts on the kit I have tested.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19749486148/in/dateposted/" title="Back at camp"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/451/19749486148_57f3f5db4d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Back at camp" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-testing">The Testing</h2>

<p>The SOA exists since 2006 and I have been following it actively since around 2010/ 2011, always curious to see which new gear was being tested and awarded. As the name suggests, only companies who are located in Scandinavia - Denmark, Norway, Sweden, Iceland and Finland - can be a part of the group, and it’s also only their gear that gets tested. This year there were 19 Nominees from 13 brands, and the kit included amongst others four tents, three pair of shoes, two compasses and a pair of Undies =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19314886004/in/dateposted/" title="Group Photo half way up the mountain"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/349/19314886004_1752cc0f32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Group Photo half way up the mountain" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The SOA Summer Jury 2015 came from from six countries and included esteemed Outdoor Journalists, Retailers, a Photographer - and for the first time ever an Outdoor Blogger =) Well, I obviously also <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/summer-writing-slash-reading.html">write for a few magazines</a> but Hiking in Finland remains the most-read Outdoor blog in Scandinavia, so it was cool to be along and bring some Blogger views to the Jury. </p>

<p>The gear testing was well done, some of us spent two days out with the kit in the mountains, which is more than any other Award does, but does not compare to my own testing (which takes months, if not years). After checking the gear out on Sunday evening and everyone got a few pieces to test we got up early at dawn on Monday and hiked for two hours to a hut, where we had breakfast. The weather was a mixed bag of rain and clouds which was in my opinion pretty good testing weather - so we could see about the waterproofness, breathability, grip and comfort in bad weather. After a great breakfast we headed further up the mountain and pitched the tents, after which it started to clear a bit. A short Via Ferrata hike, lunch and a stroll back to the gondola rounded out the afternoon for most, but five of us headed back up after dinner to sleep in the tents. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19937539195/in/dateposted/" title="Time to go to sleep"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/410/19937539195_1a9f138559_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Time to go to sleep" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Gijs from <a href="http://www.oppad.nl/">Oppad</a>, Karen from <a href="http://www.norrmagazin.de/">NORR</a>, Frank from <a href="http://www.outdoor-magazin.com/">Outdoor</a>, Piotr from <a href="http://www.goryonline.com/">Gory</a> and me slept up on the mountain in the four tents and enjoyed chatting by the fire and drinking a glass of red wine before turning in. The next morning we headed down to the valley with the first gondola and had the final Jury meeting, where we quickly were able to agree on the winners in the different categories. After that it was time to pack up and head to the OutDoor in Friedrichshafen, where the Gear Fest would start the next day.</p>

<p><em>Here’s a quick look at the gear I have tested during the SOA Jury meeting, much of it will first hit the stores in 2016 so have patience!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19316551233/in/album-72157653909966154/" title="A bit of Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/543/19316551233_bdc4a09d8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="A bit of Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="lundhags-baalka">Lundhags Baalka</h2>

<p>This was the first <a href="http://lundhags.se/home-2/">Lundhags</a> trousers I have worn, and I liked the Baalka a lot. They were not too hot - especially as soon as we were above 2000 m where it was nice and cool, and stayed dry also in the small rain showers we had. It has stretchy Schoeller inserts and a Fluorcarbon-free DWR and is made from a Polyester &amp; Cotton material mix. On the sides are ventilation zippers and it was very stretchy so that the scrambles, running and Via Ferrata were no problem. It will be available in March 2016 and will cost 170€. I especially liked the colour, though the hand pockets could have been a bit deeper. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19937534375/in/dateposted/" title="Lundhags Baalka Pant"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3670/19937534375_0061b277ac_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Lundhags Baalka Pant" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="rjk-primaloft-superundies">Röjk Primaloft SuperUndies</h2>

<p>Testing underwear is fun. I own a handful of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/gear-outtakes-winter-2015.html">Icebreaker Anatomica Boxers</a> which I rate high, but given the lower price of around 30€ of the Primaloft SuperUndies, that they don’t move uop and feel drier I likely will buy the <a href="http://rojksuperwear.com/en/">Röjk</a> Primaloft SuperUndies when they come out in spring/ summer 2016. I wore these for 24+ hours during the Jury meeting and they didn’t smell either, so for me a strong contender for outdoor underwear.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19753546238/in/dateposted/" title="Röjk Primaloft SuperUndies"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/442/19753546238_f0462e28c9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Primaloft SuperUndies" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="klttermusen-fjorgyn-anorak">Klättermusen Fjorgyn Anorak</h2>

<p>I also was lucky enough to wear the <a href="http://www.klattermusen.com/">Klättermusen</a> Fjorgyn Anorak. There were two other jackets in for test but this was the only one that everyone was excited about - for a good reason, it’s the first time Klättermusen launches a Summer line, and the Fjorgyn Anorak is a good fitting and great looking shell layer. Made from a 48 g/ m² 2,5 layer fabric with a carbon print on the inside it feels very comfy on the skin, even if you’re just wearing a T-Shirt. I liked the drawstring which sat in the middle of the buttocks and so created a sort of flap where rain could run off and not straight to your pants. The Neoprene brim protected the face well and the hood had a good fit. A fine anorak, and at 202 g in Size M even lightweight!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19937538415/in/album-72157653909966154/" title="Selfie in the new Klättermusen Fjorgyn Jacket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/548/19937538415_2cf95d3d3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Selfie in the new Klättermusen Fjorgyn Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="viking-apex-ii-gtx">Viking Apex II GTX</h2>

<p>The Apex II GTX from <a href="http://www.vikingfootwear.com/">Viking</a> were a good fit for me, had great grip on any surface I threw at them and were pretty comfortable. However, the Boa Closure System blew open on each shoe once during the day, once while trail running, which isn’t very nice. The Coolmax/ Merino material didn’t seem to make any difference in the wet weather we had, and the Gore-Tex lining didn’t do it’s job well - a good thing that I’m used to hiking in wet shoes. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19942661841/in/dateposted/" title="Viking Apex II GTX"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/270/19942661841_f193876b71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Viking Apex II GTX" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hilleberg-niak">Hilleberg Niak</h2>

<p>I pitched the <a href="http://europe.hilleberg.com/EN/index.php">Hilleberg</a> Niak and saw that it was large enough to sleep two - and that’s what we then did in the night. The Niak is claimed to be a 1,5 Person tent, but rest assured that two adults + gear fit without problem in this ~ 1,6 kg tent. It was very easy to put up and pack, has the possibility to roll up both flysheet doors for fine views, is equipped with a large inner door and has all the attention to detail you’d expect from a Hilleberg tent - sadly this also includes the rather hefty price tag of 890 €.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19749485238/in/dateposted/" title="Closed"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3733/19749485238_e2d13efb07_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Closed" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>It was a great three days and I really enjoyed being able to test the kit and help decide on worthy winners. Most of all it was great to spend time with so many passionate gear nerds and hear their views on the kit, see and learn how they test and come together to conclusions. It showed me that the Scandinavian Outdoor Award is rightfully well regarded amongst consumers &amp; retailers - because all Jury members take their job serious. We for example didn’t award a Sustainability Award because we felt that while all entries had made a good effort, from an Award winner we expect even more! Finally, also Montafon looked like a fine region for hiking, climbing and snowboarding/ skiing, so I might need to plan a trip back there with some more time =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157653909966154">More photos on Flickr</a>. Check out <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorgroup.com/projects-activities/scandinavian-outdoor-award/soa-ss-16-finalists/">the other gear</a> which was entered, view the <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorgroup.com/winners-of-scandinavian-outdoor-award-ss16/">winners</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/ScandinavianOutdoorAward">follow the SOA on Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/scandoutdoors">Twitter</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19749488218/in/dateposted/" title="Onwards"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/356/19749488218_42e0b2a7c3_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Onwards" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summer Writing / Reading]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/summer-writing-slash-reading.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-21T23:18:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/summer-writing-slash-reading</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lots of firsts in my regular Magazine update, as this time there’s half a dozen Magazines included for whom I have penned down articles. Lots of work for me and lots to read for you! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19259973054/in/dateposted/" title="Summer writing"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/393/19259973054_7cfefd936a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Summer writing" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="mountain-pro">Mountain Pro</h2>

<p>For the digital Mountain Pro Magazine I interview the BMG Mountain Guide <a href="http://www.mountainpromag.com/imag/mountainprojuly2015/files/34.html">Tim Blakemore</a> whom I met last year at the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a>. It’s a nice story that looks at the work of a Mountain Guide and fits well in with the Alpine topic of the issue, where also Jon Griffith, <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/index.html">Alex Roddie</a> and many others have contributed fascinating stories. <a href="http://www.mountainpromag.com/imag/mountainprojuly2015/">Available for free online</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19694959858/in/dateposted/" title="Mountain Pro Interview"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/450/19694959858_f3870c75a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="640" alt="Mountain Pro Interview" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="adventure-travel">Adventure Travel</h2>

<p>In the <a href="http://adventuretravelmagazine.co.uk/">Adventure Travel Magazine</a> I wrote about my Polish Tatras trip last year, and the change from busy streets to lonely summits. It looks great and has all the details to plan your own trip to the Tatras, which I too hope to visit again very soon. <a href="http://adventuretravelmagazine.co.uk/index.php/magazine">Buy the magazine online</a> or at your local news agent.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19856410546/in/dateposted/" title="Adventure Travel 118"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/452/19856410546_2ced2a1fe4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Adventure Travel 118" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="klettern">klettern</h2>

<p>My first story for the German <a href="http://www.klettern.de/">klettern</a> is about our Åland trip last autumn and features the stunning photos of my mate <a href="http://vertical-axis.de/">Nico Altmaier</a>. It’s a great looking Mini Guide to an area which surely will see a lot more visitors soon! <a href="http://www.klettern.de/heft.243.5.htm">Order it online</a> or pick it up at your news agent. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19261700603/in/dateposted/" title="klettern 05/ 2015"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/503/19261700603_4d2a02c42c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="klettern 05/ 2015" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="trekking-magazin">trekking Magazin</h2>

<p>For the trekking Magazin I reviewed my favourite summer shirts and wrote a reportage about packrafting and how it opens up new possibilities for backpackers and trekkers. It’s a fine looking article with lots of infos on four different packrafts I have tested and a variety of packrafting gear. You can pick it up at your local news agent or <a href="http://shop.trekkingmagazin.com/de/trekking-magazin/einzelhefte">order it here</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19259974084/in/dateposted/" title="trekking Magazin 04/2015"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3690/19259974084_9c2e3efe4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="trekking Magazin 04/2015" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kiipeily">Kiipeily</h2>

<p>I joined the Finnish Climbing Association as a Gear Editor at the beginning of the year and will have a regular gear review column in the magazine. In this issue I reviewed the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-hirundos-klettergurt/">Petzl Hirundos</a> harness and the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-smart-sicherungsgeraet/">Mammut Smart</a>, both items which I rated very high. To get the magazine <a href="http://climbing.fi/skil/">join the Finnish Climbing Association</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19694627830/in/dateposted/" title="Kiipeily 2/ 2015"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/462/19694627830_30e89578c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kiipeily 2/ 2015" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bike--travel">Bike &amp; Travel</h2>

<p>And finally I wrote for the newest German cycling Magazine <a href="http://www.biketravel-magazin.com/">Bike &amp; Travel</a> about Bikepacking and exploring non-paved roads with your bike and about staying hydrated on your bike. You can grab a copy at the news agent or <a href="http://shop.trekkingmagazin.com/de/biketravel/biketravel-magazin-1-2015">order it online</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19875172132/in/dateposted/" title="Bike &amp; Travel 02/ 2015"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19875172132_64ee941e41_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Bike &amp; Travel 02/ 2015" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Via Dinarica - Day 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/via-dinarica-day-1.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-02T23:13:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/via-dinarica-day-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What makes the Via Dinarica <em>The best trail of 2014</em>? Is it the idea of connecting seven countries via humanities simplest activity, walking? Or something else? Reason enough for me to pack my backpack, book a flight to Sarajevo and investigate.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19297808236" title="Almost there by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/393/19297808236_97eaf58052_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost there" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>“What are your expectations of this trip?”</em> Tim asked me after he picked me up at the airport in Sarajevo. <em>“Well”</em>, I started, <em>“I don’t have any. I never expect anything when I go on a research trip, and let the region show me what it has to offer. It’s only fair and more adventurous, too.”</em>  But Bosnia and Herzegovina has impressed me, very positively. It’s a beautiful country with warm, welcoming people, delicious food, and the views are quite decent, too. In the following series of trip reports I’ll walk you through the Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina part of the Via Dinarica Trail, and will answer questions in the final post where I also will give more information on the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19136258770" title="Sarajevo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3666/19136258770_cc1244bbdd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sarajevo" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sarajevo">Sarajevo</h2>

<p><em>“Coffee?”</em> Sure. As an European Finn I seldom say no to coffee, and the coffee in Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina is superb, especially when brewed in the traditional way. Besides, I was up since 4 am and already had three different flights so something to keep me awake in the sweltering heat of this bustling city was always welcome. We had good coffee and then a stroll through the old part of Sarajevo, which was gorgeous with small, narrow streets lined with stalls, open air Cafés, Restaurants where delicious smells wafted from the open windows, and lots of people. Mosques stood next to Churches, and the peaceful co-existence of the religions in this country is certainly something the world could learn. </p>

<p>Later in the afternoon I meet the rest of the Terra Dinarica team, Olja, Stefan and Kenan, who would be my Guide over the next five days. We had a tasty dinner high above Sarajevo, before Kenan dropped me off at my Hostel for the night. <em>“Pick up is at 5 am”</em> he said with a smile, and so I turned in after a quick shower to get some sleep before the Alarm would wake me up yet again so early.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19327840381" title="Entry to a Mosque in Sarajevo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/488/19327840381_2a8db26d5d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Entry to a Mosque in Sarajevo" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19136294080" title="Catholic Church by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/457/19136294080_1da943acab_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Catholic Church" /></a></p>

<h2 id="risovac-to-diva-grabovica">Risovac to Diva Grabovica</h2>

<p>This 27,6 km section started at a ski slope a couple of hours drive south west of Sarajevo. Already on the way there we passed with the car scenery which would make any backpacker and climber very happy indeed, with a <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703305363/in/album-72157650519579023/">Mini El Cap</a> and lush, green valleys which would make for fine hiking. Here at the Risovac ski centre Kenan and me shoulder our backpacks, said bye to Tim who’d meet us at the other side, and set off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703269283" title="At the start by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/516/18703269283_e92f6c0d92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the start" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19327844291" title="Through the forest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/428/19327844291_1d0a97d467_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Through the forest" /></a></p>

<p>We quickly reach the top of the ski slope and turned into the forest, where patches of snow still lined the trail. It didn’t take us long to be so high that the trail was under the snow, and I was pondering if my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/arcteryx-acrux2-fl-gtx.html">Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX</a> shoes would be up to the task (They were, and great on the snow indeed). Where the trail skirts the mountain on the south/ west side, the snow was happily gone, but also walking on the snow was fine - it was still fairly compact with just a thin, mushy layer on top which gave good grip.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19327855101" title="Trailmarker by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3919/19327855101_aa9c6a7a5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trailmarker" /></a></p>

<p>The weather was great - so warm that I quickly shed layers and hiked in my T-Shirt. Kenan tells me about the mountain we traverse, the sights, where the Via Dinarica passes here and local lore. He’s also a good model and doesn’t protest when I let him walk several sections twice to get the right shot, but even with all the chatting and taking photos we make good speed and soon see the summit we’re aiming for today, the Great Vilinac Summit. The trail towards it sneaks through patches of low-growing shrubbery, and spring crocuses are piercing their white and violet heads already through the ground there where the snow has melted.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703292873" title="Snow &amp; Green by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/381/18703292873_43f737a76c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow &amp; Green" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18701483194" title="Under the snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/494/18701483194_990870e0c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Under the snow" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19136404998" title="Summit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3750/19136404998_9fbf454c9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit" /></a></p>

<p>The summit is snow-free and after signing the summit book we sit and have a drink. The view is fantastic and we’re lucky with the weather. But we arranged to have lunch at a mountain hut a bit further along the trail, and so we soon shoulder our light packs again and head onwards to the Tise Mountain Hut. It’s a bit off the trail and we descent for ten minutes, but already from a distance it looks like it is closed. As we stand in front of the locked doors we’re certain that we won’t be eating lunch here, a good thing we have some snacks with us and that the bench and table have a scenic view to enjoy. We go for a look to find the water spring nearby, but it is still buried under a meter of snow, and so we just continue.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703352493" title="Mountain Hut by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/456/18703352493_0e1322e538_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mountain Hut" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17482621798" title="Lunch with a view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5455/17482621798_55e05af41e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lunch with a view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703354393" title="Voda?! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/414/18703354393_4dc5ba09e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Voda?!" /></a></p>

<p>We follow the trailmarkers - a red circle with a white dot in the middle - for a while, until we’re back on the snow. While it allows us to make short-cuts it’s also a bit more strenuous to walk on it, and of course it also soaks your shoes and socks. But it’s warm &amp; sunny, so not a problem, merely a slight inconvenience. We’re high up and descent and ascend just a little for several kilometres, until it is time for the big 1.600 m descent to the Diva Grabovica valley. The views which open up before us are breath-taking, but you have to stop to enjoy then, as the descent is steep on a trail which is often just a mere foot wide, if it’s not entirely covered under the snow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19323948775" title="Trailmarker with a view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/314/19323948775_27ed95b999_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trailmarker with a view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703316503" title="Spring snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/334/18703316503_2ff0aeff59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Spring snow" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18701466584" title="At the gate of Moria by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/463/18701466584_299e1fa670_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the gate of Moria" /></a></p>

<p>Ahead of us we also can see Prenj, the mountain range we will be traversing in the next two days. Soon enough we reach the tree line and lush green beech trees with fresh, young leaves make the walking in the warm weather more pleasant. From afar we already saw a rustic cabin - the former Kings Hunting Cabin - and we made a little detour to visit it. It was pretty from the outside, with wooden shingles on the face of the building, but the inside was mouldy, dark and not welcoming. Also the garbage which was left wasn’t a nice sight, and so we continued further down. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19317902182" title="Taking in the view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3691/19317902182_a3020d88a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Taking in the view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19297857296" title="King&#x27;s Hunting Cabin by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/281/19297857296_0d593b596b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="King&#x27;s Hunting Cabin" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17644112776" title="Green by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5332/17644112776_fc113f88dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Green" /></a></p>

<p>We heard voices already further up the mountain, and as we happened on the 2nd hut - which was in much better shape - we meet Tim and friends of Kenan, who did a <a href="http://planinarenje.ba/planinarske-ture/cvrsnica/712-zli-potok-tise-zlijeb-9-5-2015#!">Via Ferrata Route</a> (scroll down to see their photos!) and were now also on the way back down. We decided to go check out the Look out point and have a cup of coffee all together, and it was a nice place to rest and drink some good Bosnian coffee. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703362883" title="Side view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/477/18703362883_0b88684653_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Side view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19327915261" title="Sunstar by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/523/19327915261_d88f5b2a36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunstar" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18701431824" title="Coffee break with friends by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/352/18701431824_ea046175d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Coffee break with friends" /></a></p>

<p>On the way to the valley the trail soon became a gorgeous green tunnel which smelled so wonderful, it was unbelievable. Colourful flowers, buzzing insects, colourful butterflies and bubbling wells we found the further we descended the trail, and as we finally broke out of the dense green forest a magnificent panorama opened up before us. A colourful little meadow stood in full flowers, while the sun was hiding behind big, dramatic grey clouds, throwing a few rays on the mountains we just left behind. It was such a perfect place that I’d loved to have put my tarp up right there, but we still had a few hundred meters to descent and move onwards, so we left the meadow behind and hiked on.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18701473974" title="Well by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/423/18701473974_a7f5e49cfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Well" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19136359170" title="Yellow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/275/19136359170_92902860bd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yellow" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19327886971" title="Almost at the car by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/320/19327886971_1846da891d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost at the car" /></a></p>

<p>At the car we threw our packs into the car and drove towards the next Restaurant, where we enjoyed a dinner of lamb and a local beer before Tim brought us to Prenj. It was night as we arrived the start of the trail, and after a quick repack for the next two days we set off. I was completely destroyed as we started to hike, but pushed on. While I was planning to sleep in my bivy outside instead of the Medjuprenje Mountain Hut where we were headed, after I saw a few Scorpions on the trail and Kenan told me about the Black Widows Spiders which can be encountered here I decided that the hut it would be. It was close to 23 o’clock as we stumbled into the Medjuprenje Mountain Hut, where other friends of Kenan right away offered us a Rakija, and after a zip of this tasty fruit brandy I headed up to roll out my quilt and call it a night. <strong>To be continued.</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/336849101">View the section on Strava</a>. <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157650519579023">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19317873912" title="Alpenglow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/391/19317873912_eb230056e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alpenglow" /></a></p>

<p><em>Liked this? Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for On-The-Trail updates! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em> </p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 205]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/the-week-in-review-205.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-28T23:47:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/the-week-in-review-205</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I am not afraid of storms for I am learning how to sail my ship.</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1FIyJ6n">Louisa May Alcott</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19112250691" title="PackSailRafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/331/19112250691_9e2b8db875_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PackSailRafting" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.change.org/p/european-parliament-save-the-freedom-of-photography">Save the Freedom of Photography</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.indiegogo.com/projects/27-crags-rock-climbing-app#/story">Support the 27Crags.com App</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Kirschvogel/status/612925632016683008">Blogger Relations Bullshit Bingo</a>.</p>

<p>There’s an <a href="http://packraftingitalia.jimdo.com/whitewater-packrafting-meeting/english-version/">European packrafting meeting</a> in France in August - are you joining, too? </p>

<p><a href="http://www.dpreview.com/articles/7945517371/opinion-did-sony-just-do-the-impossible">Did Sony just do the impossible</a>? It did, so <a href="http://amzn.to/1eSqEHc">pre-order the A7R II now</a>!</p>

<p>Martin wrote <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/zwei-neue-wanderbuecher-aus-eigener-feder-wien-wandert-beethoven-wanderweg-40/">two new hiking books</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/14/sports/dean-potter-final-yosemite-jump.html?nytmobile=0&amp;_r=0">Lost Brother in Yosemite</a>.</p>

<p>July 4th is soon, and that means you can now already <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">save up to 50% Off Gear &amp; Apparel for Summer at Backcountry.com</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.pelagobicycles.com/pelago-commuter-front-rack-m.html">Pelago Commuter Front Racks</a>.</p>

<p>Outdoorline.sk has <a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/26_westcomb">30% off on Westcomb garments</a>.</p>

<p>The trekking-lite-store.com now has the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/Zelte/MSR-Flylite::915.html?refID=HiF">MSR Flylit Tent</a> in stock.</p>

<p>And on Monday, the 29th of June you can <a href="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=cc&amp;cpid=1&amp;target=http://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-simple-guide-jacket-softshelljacke/">save 55% on the Patagonia Simple Guide Jacket</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.fi/2015/06/ultraleicht-auf-dem-urwaldsteig.html">Ultralight on the Urwaldsteig</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2015/06/rode-trip-a-long-ride-for-some-fish/">A Long Ride for Some Fish</a>.</p>

<p>Nick enjoys the <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/?p=1608">Transitions</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://woolbeard.blogspot.fi/2015/06/go-east-riding-into-roztocze.html">Riding into Roztocze</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://coastkid.blogspot.fi/2015/06/saturday-morning-cycle-at-tyninghame.html">Saturday morning cycle at Tyninghame</a>.</p>

<p>Dennis reports from the <a href="http://www.abenteuersuechtig.de/index.php/gore-tex-experience-tour-2015-hochtour-balmhorn/">GORE-TEX Experience Tour 2015</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/kurt-ross-the-french-route-mount-hunter/">The French Route on Mount Hunter</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/31576498?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://graniteandice.blogspot.fi/2015/06/cycling-outer-hebrides.html">Cycling the Outer Hebrides</a>.</p>

<p>Visit % climb in the <a href="http://philipperibiere.blogspot.fi/2015/06/valley-of-giants.html">Valley of Giants</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://alpinejustice.blogspot.fi/2015/06/cham-part-un.html">Cham: Part Un</a>.</p>

<p>Roger enjoys Sweden along the <a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/2015/06/22/e1-vastra-vatterleden-molltorp-to-mullsjo/">Västra Vätterleden</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2015/06/17/day-1-lct-sleep-shuttle-sand-seals-rocks-and-waves/">LCT Day 1</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://linaluftig.de/maedels-bootcamp-zur-sommersonnenwende/">Girls Summer Bootcamp</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pedalingnowhere.com/plog/planning-the-perfect-bikepacking-route-vol-01/">Planning the perfect bikepacking trip</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://wanderingthewild.com/2015/06/25/waterton-lakes-national-park/">Waterton Lakes National Park</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19116315626" title="LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack Plus in Alpine mode by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/455/19116315626_1e3c7e9895_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack Plus in Alpine mode" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-acrux-ar-alpine-boot.html">A Look at the Arc’teryx 2016 Footwear</a>.</p>

<p>Christian reviews the <a href="https://1001miles.wordpress.com/2015/06/17/therm-a-rest-trail-pro/">Therm-A-Rest Trail Pro</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gearexposure.com/kniper-the-ultimate-survival-tool/">Kniper, the ultimate survival tool</a>?</p>

<p><a href="http://offroute.ca/2015/06/25/tech-talk-touring-bicycles-2015/">Touring Bicycles 2015 and Luddite Resistance</a>, a recommended read!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.guthookhikes.com/2015/06/mountain-laurel-designs-bug-bivy-review.html">Mountain Laurel Designs Bug Bivy Review</a>.</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for On-The-Trail updates! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em> </p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kelly Cordes: The Tower]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/kelly-cordes-the-tower.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-26T23:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/kelly-cordes-the-tower</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1BQVH0i">Kelly Cordes - The Tower</a> is a gripping book about the history of climbing on Cerro Torre. If you’re in love with Patagonia, it’s mountaineering history, and the Chalten massiv, read on to hear my verdict on this book.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19165133102" title="Kelly Cordes - The Tower by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/302/19165133102_bd1146bf09_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kelly Cordes - The Tower" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Oh Patagonia, how I long to see thee!</em> As <a href="http://bit.ly/1BR9bcu">Patagonia Books</a> asked me if I’d like to read Kelly Cordes new book about Cerro Torre, my answer was of course <em>Yes!</em> How would one who likes to climb and loves the mountains not read the book about one of the most beautiful mountains on this planet? Also history enthusiasts will enjoy this fine book, which is written in such a way that also non-climbers will find it fascinating and read chapter after chapter.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Climbing is not a democracy. It never has been. That’s one of the things we love about it. Climbing is about freedom, and just as Maestri scarred Cerro Torre when he put in all those bolt ladders, Jason and I removed about 120 of his bolts on our descent.”</em> - Hayden Kennedy</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In a nutshell the book chronicles the history of climbing on Cerro Torre and the controversy surrounding the claimed first ascent in 1959 and the 1970 Compressor Route of Cesare Maestri, an Italian climber who became world-famous because of these two routes. The book has four distinct parts, divided into 35 chapters on 400 pages. Cordes tries on these pages to uncover the truth about the claimed First Ascent in 1959 &amp; the death of Toni Egger, who died under unknown circumstances on the claimed descent. Cordes interviews supporters and opponents of Maestri, talks with Reinhold Messner, and many of the Alpinists which have climbed new routes on Cerro Torre. In the end he draws logical conclusions, but lets you, the reader, come to your own results. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19170902365" title="Kelly Cordes - The Tower by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/318/19170902365_ed1f2005d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kelly Cordes - The Tower" /></a></p>

<p>On the side he also looks at how modern technology and tourism has changed the landscape in El Chalten, the removal of 120 of Maestri’s bolts and the ensuing discussion, and then gives you in three Appendixes a Timeline of Cerro Torre Ascents, the people mentioned and a climbing glossary, as well as maps and a selected bibliography. It’s a well rounded book with gorgeous photos and will inspire many to climb in Patagonia, or at least visit the area and hike underneath these stunning peaks. If you’re an Alpinist, climber, mountaineer or just barely interested in mountains and Cerro Torre then you should read this book. It’s an enthralling read and you’ll fly through the chapters, eager to learn more about the history and climbing on this beautiful mountain &amp; it’s difficult history. You can order the book directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1BQVH0i">Patagonia</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1GBoCAZ">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Jngv26">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1Cy6NlF">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Julbo Trek Sunglasses]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/julbo-trek-zebra.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-25T23:34:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/julbo-trek-zebra</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/04/julbo-dolgan-sunglasses.html">Julbo Dolgan Sunglasses</a> started to arrive at the end of their life-cycle, so I was looking around for a new pair that’s suitable for hiking, mountaineering and cycling alike. I settled on the <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/en/julbo-trek-503333.html?farbe=schwarz%2Fgrün">Julbo Trek</a> shades with Zebra lenses, and after using them for several months &amp; on five trips it’s time for a review.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18954779610" title="Julbo Trek underneath Otiš and Zelena Glava in Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/499/18954779610_18fc8a33e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Julbo Trek underneath Otiš and Zelena Glava in Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I like sunglasses and wear a pair almost all the time, be it for cycling, walking through town, mountaineering or ice climbing, if I’m outside I 8 out of 10 times am having a pair of shades on my nose. The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/04/julbo-dolgan-sunglasses.html">Julbo Dolgan Sunglasses</a> I own have seen over five years of use and countless trips, and it started to be time to pick up a new pair. The Golgan were great, but I wanted something with lighter lenses that’s more suitable for cycling in spring and autumn, when the main reason to wear glasses for me is to keep rain, dirt and bugs out of my eyes. After some research I settled on the <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/en/julbo-trek-503333.html?farbe=schwarz%2Fgrün">Julbo Trek Sunglasses with Zebra lenses</a>, and <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/en/">Unterwegs.biz</a> was friendly enough to send me a pair for review.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18954780390" title="Julbo Trek Zebra Front by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/526/18954780390_c17b747d74_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek Zebra Front" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19116318046" title="Julbo Trek Zebra Top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/292/19116318046_f37bc7d342_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek Zebra Top" /></a></p>

<p>The Trek with Zebra lenses are a multifunctional pair of shades and fulfill all my needs. I have worn them backpacking in Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina, packrafting in Austria, paragliding in Italy, cycling at home and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-alpine-academy-chamonix-2015.html">mountaineering in France</a>, and have worn them almost daily since they arrived here four months ago. The pair with all parts attached weighs 45 g with the weight being broken down like this:</p>

<ul>
  <li>32 g Julbo Trek sunglasses</li>
  <li>04 g Sweat Blocker</li>
  <li>03 g Side pieces (two)</li>
  <li>06 g Headband</li>
</ul>

<p>That makes the Trek shades slightly heavier as the Dolgan, but I like the added protection of the larger glasses, the Sweat Blocker and the headband, which keeps the Trek securely on my head and of course the better lenses in my opinion. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18954781430" title="Julbo Trek Zebra Headband by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/265/18954781430_c01d0d9168_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek Zebra Headband" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18956356919" title="Julbo Trek Zebra Frontside with pieces detached by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/285/18956356919_de384df2ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek Zebra Frontside with pieces detached" /></a></p>

<p>It’s not all great, though: The foam on the Sweat Blocker piece which you can attach to the top of the glasses started to come off after just a couple of weeks of use, which I find poor design. It also helps to trap more heat and lets the glasses fog up more easily. It also doesn’t stop all sweat, but then I can excuse that as hiking in 30°C temperatures for 30 km with over 2.000 m ascent is a sweaty business and sweat running down your brow an expected outcome. I hope Julbo will look into this, I find it not really acceptable for this to happen.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18956355149" title="Julbo Trek Zebra Back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/527/18956355149_af67415ef4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek Zebra Back" /></a></p>

<p>After the foam started to come lose I took the Sweat Blocker part off, and it has been good thus far. Either I have started to sweat less or just haven’t hiked in 30°C weather, but I had no sweat yet run into my eyes. Also the foggin up problems has been solved, which I blame on the improved ventilation. The side parts, which are also removable and are easily clipped on and off, are good to keep side glares away and headwind/ side wind out. The big thing about these sunglasses are obviously the lenses, and you pay 50€ extra for them over the standard Spectron 4 lenses (which I have on the Dolgan). Here’s what Julbo says about the Zebra lenses:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>The Zebra® photochromic lens darkens or lightens depending on the light’s intensity. It can change from a light transmission rate of 42% to just 7%! Its anti-fog coating, directly integrated via laser, guarantees maximum efficiency and long life. Zebra® is recommended for mountain biking, trail biking, running, climbing, skiing, riding and other outdoor sports.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18954782190" title="Julbo Trek Zebra Frontside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/257/18954782190_d43e043fce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek Zebra Frontside" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18956354569" title="Julbo Trek Zebra inside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/428/18956354569_21df201b4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek Zebra inside" /></a></p>

<p>The lenses are lighter in terms of opacity than the Dolgan, and that’s something I value in traffic &amp; cycling, especially in spring when dusk comes earlier than now and darker lenses like the Spectron 4 make driving safely more difficult, especially if it’s also raining. In bright weather, like high in the mountains and on summer days, the Zebra lenses darken enough to make bright conditions less stressful on the eyes. I found the lighter Zebra lenses also comfortable on snow &amp; ice and found they block glare just as well as darker lenses, and they made seeing details in snow &amp; ice no problem. Fogging up has been only a problem with the Sweat Blocker on the shades, without it the ventilation is superb and even when running up a hill in 20°C sunshine &amp; running hot I didn’t get the shades to fog up. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18954777480" title="Julbo Trek with Zebra Lenses after cycling up to Heuberg, Kaiserwinkl by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/303/18954777480_21f699d1ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Julbo Trek with Zebra Lenses after cycling up to Heuberg, Kaiserwinkl" /></a></p>

<p>The fit of the Trek is on the larger side for my head, and hence I find the headband necessary to keep the shades securely on my head. They fit well under my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Sirocco Helmet</a> with a thin beanie underneath it, and also on their own make for a good fit. At the beginning the nose piece was slightly uncomfortable after several hours of wearing them, but that was just a question of getting used to them and nowadays I can wear them for 8 hours straight without needing to take them off. They do look big if you hold them in your hands, but I find they fit my rather slim face well &amp; then don’t look big anymore and are much smaller than e.g. Oakley shades I own. The Trek come with a soft bag which doubles as a cleaning wipe and a hard protective case. I haven’t used the protective case yet as I find it too bulky for transport on the trail, but the soft bag is all the time along when I’m out with the Trek on my nose. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19136742902" title="Julbo Trek with sweat-guard &amp; side pieces by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/411/19136742902_c3df868ba1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek with sweat-guard &amp; side pieces" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19142484395" title="Julbo Trek Zebra Protective Cases by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/495/19142484395_fc6ca7cfe0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Julbo Trek Zebra Protective Cases" /></a></p>

<p><strong>In conclussion</strong> I can say that I can recommend the Julbo Trek Sunglasses with Zebra lenses. They fit me well, work great for all activities I do - from hiking over cycling to mountaineering - and are protecting my eyes well from the sun, glare, rain and dirt. I like that they’re adaptable and that I can take off the extra side pieces and Sweat Blocker, though I’d wish that the latter would be better constructed. The lenses adapt well to different light situations and the headband ensures a secure fit, be it under a helmet or over a beanie. At 135€ they’re not the cheapest pair, but I recognice that I’ll be using them for the next five years at least very actively so I think they’re worth it.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/en/sunglasses.html">eyewear for mountaineers, cyclists and hikers</a> at <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/en/">Unterwegs.biz</a>.</p>

<p><em>By the way, a thing I really like from Unterwegs.biz is that they pay attention to the size of shipping packages. I always wince if I get a large package just to find a carabiner and a boxershorts in it, it feels like a massive waste of space &amp; generates more emissions and costs. Unterwegs.biz always seems to send gear in the smallest package possible, which I value highly from an environmental point of view.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19112250891" title="PackSailRafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3912/19112250891_74dac9c6b5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PackSailRafting" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zlagboard Pro Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/zlagboard-pro-review.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-24T23:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/zlagboard-pro-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/outdoor-2014-wrap-up-and-conclusions.html">OutDoor</a> last year I stumbled on the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/">Zlagboard</a> for the first time and immediately thought it’s an awesome way to train at home. The Zlagboard comes with a Smartphone App and training plans for every level, which allows you to track your progress over months. I have been training with the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-pro">Zlagboard Pro</a> since February and this is my review of it. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18490892773" title="Start Screen II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/468/18490892773_d873e8b60c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Start Screen II" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>As a father &amp; entrepreneur it’s right now not as easy for me to go to the gym or outdoors for a round of climbing, but I feel bad if I can’t go. I’ve had a pair of <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/metolius-rock-rings-3d-trainingsgriffe/">Metolius Rock Rings</a> for several years but wanted something more - something that allows me to track my training, measure progress, set goals and let me get strong. Enter the Zlagboard and the great App. I’ll look at these two components and then the training with both.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19085360396" title="Workout Plans by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/388/19085360396_4af11ce9fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Workout Plans" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-zlagboard-app">The Zlagboard App</h2>

<p>The Zlagboard <a href="https://zlagboard.com/app">App</a> (available on iOS and Android) is the digital part of your training. Modern smartphones like the iPhone come with a lot of sensors, and the physical Zlagboard in combination with the App make use of these sensors to measure your training. On the Start Screen you probably first want to set up your Profile and then head to the Store to activate your Zlagboard - you’ll find the code on the back of the Zlagboard to do so, and it’s good for five users. In the Store you also can purchase additional training plans, for example from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html">GimmeKraft!</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19104282642" title="Training Plans for Purchase in the Zlagboard Store by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3886/19104282642_674d3f4bb5_c.jpg" width="451" height="800" alt="Training Plans for Purchase in the Zlagboard Store" /></a><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18922333978" title="Trainings Overview Screen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/368/18922333978_b38447bf2d_c.jpg" width="451" height="800" alt="Trainings Overview Screen" /></a></p>

<p>Once activated I did the Test which recommends you which Training Plan to follow, but I decided I start at the lowest Level and went with the Basic (free) Plan. The four Training Plans that are shown were developed by <a href="http://patxiusobiaga.com">Patxi Usobiaga</a> and all run 12 weeks. You’re not bound to stick to the scheduled days, but it of course would make sense to do so for the best training effect. And if you miss your Wednesday training you can just do it on Thursday.</p>

<p>I found the App well structured but missed some more instructions on some exercises, if not in the App at least on the website. This would have made it more beginner-friendly, as likely not every climber knows e.g. what’s the Full-Lock position. I think the prices for the Pro Plans are very fair and everything else in the App was very well designed. It worked without flaws on my old iPhone 5 (running iOS 8) and also should work well on any Android phone.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18923828330" title="Zlagboard! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3769/18923828330_68dca4328d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="454" alt="Zlagboard!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-zlagboard-pro-fingerboard">The Zlagboard Pro Fingerboard</h2>

<p>Fingerboard, hangboard, trainingboard - there’s many different names for this, but they essentially all mean the same. It’s a board made of wood or plastic with different sized finger holds for training at home. What’s different about the Zlagboard is that it’s a mounted on a separate frame - it is made of two (three if you count the steel) parts. The Nilo is attached to the wall and allows you to mount the Zlagboard Pro or <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-vario">Vario</a> to it, and you could even mount several Nilo boards in your house and then just move the fingerboards around to use them. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19105859642" title="Side view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/437/19105859642_12f9a67d68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Side view" /></a></p>

<p>The actual fingerboard is mounted on a steel frame, and so when you hang on the board the steel frame stays in place but the wooden part moves softly a centimetre down. It’s super stable (unless you mounted it sloppily!) and makes for a good feeling when training. The board self is made of Alder wood and weighs 7 kg, with a size of 70 x 16 x 6 cm. It has 24 different holds in 10 pairs with four holds in the centre. There’s two Jugs, one 10° Sloper and two 35° Slopers, and many Crimps &amp; Pockets with a depth from 10 to 45 mm. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19085367456" title="Holds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/437/19085367456_46d305b056_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Holds" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18923826010" title="Smartphone Mount by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/416/18923826010_7ecc16bee5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Smartphone Mount" /></a></p>

<p>Your smartphone is attached via the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/additional-equipment#smartphone-mount">Smartphone Mount</a>, which is an elastic gadget that attaches over the four corners of your phone and then you can slide it easily over the top metal part, so that you always easily can see what’s to be done next. These also can be bought separately and in different colours, in case you tend to missplace such things.</p>

<p>Besides the Zlagboard Pro which you see in my photos there’s also a <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-mini">Zlagboard Mini</a> and a <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-vario">Zlagboard Vario</a>. The former is, as the name suggests, smaller and optimized for GimmeKraft! workouts, while the latter allows you to attach a <a href="http://bit.ly/1LB72By">fingerboard</a> of your choice on it, be it a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beastmaker-2000-series-trainingsboard/">Beastmaker 2000</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1GHpW8s">Metolius Wood Grips Compact Training Board</a>, you can attach almost any board to it and then create custom workouts for it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18923837050" title="Hang-time by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/483/18923837050_0a8c1fd32b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hang-time" /></a></p>

<h2 id="training">Training</h2>

<p>Now that you know about the soft- and hardware, it is time to look at the training. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19111537695" title="Day 10 Trainings Plan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/473/19111537695_63664516c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Day 10 Trainings Plan" /></a></p>

<p>I choose the Basic Training Plan for starters and found it a good 50 minute workout three times a week. It’s organized in such a way that you first build up strength over the first month, in the 2nd month strength &amp; endurance and in the 3rd month you go for power. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19114895991" title="Break by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/312/19114895991_c041ac4566_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Break" /></a></p>

<p>In between exercises the App counts down your break time, tells you what’s next and also allows you to skip the break or pause the exercise if you gotta interrupt it. There’s a varied mix of exercises that makes use of increasingly difficult holds, for longer times, in more difficult positions. Pull-ups on the jugs are a good warm-up, and you can configure the App so that it either automatically counts them or that you need to touch the screen with your nose, as I so stylish demonstrate underneath. The breaks between exercises can go from 7 seconds to 5 minutes, which means you could read a book or answer some emails in between exercises - or just skip the breaks and continue in one go! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18490903563" title="Touch the screen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3678/18490903563_c7608b07c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="845" alt="Touch the screen" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If you can not get to the climbing gym or crag as often as you would like to or are tired of your non-interactive fingerboard, then you’ll love the Zlagboard. For me it is one of the best innovations in the climbing market in the last years and allows me to train efficiently at home, with professionally developed training plans, and it tracks my progress so that I can measure my results. The wooden fingerboard is very well made and the App easy &amp; intuitively to use. The training plans are fun and get increasingly difficult, helping to build up strength and techniques for real-world projects - like my trip to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html">Dolomites</a> next week. For me the Zlagboard is a great tool and I often just do a few pull-ups or hangs on it when standing in front of the computer gets too much. I really rate it very high and would recommend it to everyone who’d like to train at home with professional training plans &amp; measure the progress.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Lets get Strong!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can get your choice of Zlagboard directly from <a href="https://shop.vertical-life.info/products/zlagboard">Vertical-Life</a>, at the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/zlagboard-pro-trainingsboard/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/zlagboard-zlagboard-trainingsboard/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>. <em>And if you liked this post share it with your mates on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157655005832735">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19105861882" title="Pull-ups by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/517/19105861882_aecb349cd5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Pull-ups" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Look at the Arc'teryx 2016 Footwear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-acrux-ar-alpine-boot.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-23T23:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-acrux-ar-alpine-boot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the 2015 <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-alpine-academy-chamonix-2015.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> I got a sneak peek at the new Arc’teryx Acrux AR Alpine Boot, the first alpine climbing boot from Arc’teryx. I was lucky enough to try it on and play around with it in Chamonix, and also take a look at the two new Approach and Crag shoes, the Acrux SL and Arakys. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19052626366" title="The 2016 Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear News - Outsides by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/444/19052626366_d607d066f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="521" alt="The 2016 Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear News - Outsides" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="acrux-ar-alpine-boot">Acrux AR Alpine Boot</h2>

<p>The goal of Arc’teryx with the Acrux AR was to create a light, durable, weatherproof and well fitting double boot. The boot we saw and tried on at the Arc’teryx Academy arrived just that morning and so was an early pre-production model, but it should be relatively close to the boot that will be standing in the stores in 2016. I will share my impressions on the Arc’teryx boot and compare them to my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx.html">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html">Scarpa Phantom Ultra Boots</a>, both boots that I think are damn near perfect. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18458184033" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot in its natural Habitat by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3695/18458184033_16a7489781_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot in its natural Habitat" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18427468573" title="I &lt;3 my Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX Boots by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/290/18427468573_44079149bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="I &lt;3 my Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX Boots" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-lightness-of-being">The Lightness of Being</h2>

<p>My Rebel Ultra GTX are 773 g per boot in Size 42,5 or 1.546 g for the pair, and the Phantom Ultra Boots are 918 g per shoe in Size 42,5 or 1.845 g for the pair. Keep in mind that these both are single boots! The Acrux AR GTX is a double boot - it has a removable liner - and one boot will weigh 940 g or 1.880 g for the pair in UK Size 8.5. So it is better to compare it to something like the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/scarpa-phantom-6000-schuhe-orange-38/">Scarpa Phantom Ultra 6000</a> (2.000 g per pair in Size 42) and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/la-sportiva-spantik-schuhe-grey-yellow-grey-yellow-38/">La Sportiva Spantik</a> (2.400 g per pair in Size 42). These are quite a bit more heavy than the Acrux AR GTX, and I am not aware of a lighter alpine double boot (there are lighter skiing boots available).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18891197418" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/370/18891197418_1fe5583699_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot" /></a></p>

<h2 id="durable--weatherproof-construction">Durable &amp; Weatherproof Construction</h2>

<p>The boot is made to last - how long that is depends on how often you’re out in the mountains. If that’s just once a year for two weeks these probably will last you several years, while if you’re a Mountain Guide they only might last a season or two. The boot made a very sturdy impression on me, with the weakest link probably being the T-Zip Zipper which makes the gaiter waterproof. Maybe a quick look at the construction is in order:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Inside you find a <strong>Removable Gore-Tex Liner Booty</strong> which also packs some insulation and so keeps your feet warm</li>
  <li>The Boot has on the inside a <strong>PE Inner Shell</strong> construction which does not absorb moisture and has a lacing system for a secure and good fit</li>
  <li>On the outside we have a <strong>Laminated Waterproof Gaiter</strong> which closes with the T-Zip zipper for complete protection from snow, water and the cold</li>
  <li>Around the bottom of the boot there’s a <strong>Laminated Watertight Construction</strong> which has a 0,6 mm thick TPU film for high abrasion and puncture resistance</li>
  <li>The <strong>Midsole</strong> is very elaborate and made from six pieces which are custom made for this boot, in every size! It’s made up of a Carbon Fibre frame, an EVA Midsole and is protected by a wrapped TPU moulded heel and toe cap</li>
  <li>And underneath this all is a <strong>Vibram Mountaineering Outsole</strong></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18458178933" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot Sole Parts by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/420/18458178933_c6fb463767_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot Sole Parts" /></a></p>

<p>This all creates a durable boot which will be great for your alpine adventures and ice climbing alike. Oh, and a really cool is that the shoe can be re-soled, despite the elaborate sole construction.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19082087401" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/435/19082087401_7f2ebc7519_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot" /></a></p>

<p>The goal of the Acrux AR GTX Boot was to make a double liner boot that low in volume - more akin to the Scarpa Phantom Ultra - while bing warmer than the Rebel Ultra GTX. The boot we saw certainly achieved that goal, and was not much bigger than the Rebel Ultra GTX in volume, and lower in volume than the Phantom Ultras I have. I find low volume boots not just aesthetically better, but they also more practical in use in my opinion: I can climb better in a low volume boot, find easier foot holds in tight spots and it’s easier to get your pants over them, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18458165843" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/528/18458165843_aa936d77db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot" /></a></p>

<h2 id="impressions--conclusions">Impressions &amp; Conclusions</h2>

<p>I’m used to very light footwear - <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a> I love for hiking and every day use, and on the trail I often sport a pair of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/inov-8-trailroc-235.html">trailrunners</a> - so boots always will feel heavy to me. I tried the Acrux AR GTX Boot on and walked a bit around in them - not really a test thus - and they certainly felt heavy to me, especially since I also had my Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX boots along for my clinics. But they weren’t uncomfortably heavy and of course it is better to evaluate them when using them in cold weather in the mountains and not in front of a Restaurant, where they will probably not feel heavy anymore, but I’d likely appreciate their warmth at -5°C at 3.800 m altitude.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18458171633" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3832/18458171633_4aa257f560_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot" /></a></p>

<p>The boot was comfortable on my foot, the inside lacing enabled a secure fit with a Velcro Strap which held it in place. The Gaiter is adjusted via a Drawstring in the back and the gaiter is easy to open and close with the T-Zip zipper. The liner was warm and comfortable, and the adaptive fit will mould the liner over time to your foot for a personal fit. The seamless construction of the liner should minimize blisters and pressure points if that’s something you have problems with in other boots, and because it can be removed you can dry it faster or use it as a hut/ camp bootie.</p>

<p>The <strong>Conclusion</strong> is that the Arc’teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot certainly is a boot waiting for if you’re often out on Multi-Day adventures in the mountains. At 600€ it is competitively priced, the low volume and being a double boot sets it apart from the competition and it is very well made. I hope to be able to put them through their paces in the future and share a detailed review on them after a lot of use.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18891192148" title="Acrux SL Men&#x27;s &amp; Women&#x27;s + Arakys Men&#x27;s by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/377/18891192148_e57cbdc64a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Acrux SL Men&#x27;s &amp; Women&#x27;s + Arakys Men&#x27;s" /></a></p>

<h2 id="acrux-sl--arakys-shoes">Acrux SL &amp; Arakys Shoes</h2>

<p>Besides the Acrux AR Alpine Boot Arc’teryx will also launch a <strong>S</strong>uper<strong>L</strong>ight version of the Acrux, which will tip the scales at 300 g per shoe. It has no Gote-Tex lining (Yay!), a Vibram Megagrip sole and is made for demanding approaches and descents. The Acrux SL comes in a Men’s and Women’s Version in four colours each. I think this will be a great crag/ every day outdoor shoe that will be popular, I certaily would pick a pair up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19082127781" title="Acrux SL Women&#x27;s Above by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/308/19082127781_e5d1fcf646_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Acrux SL Women&#x27;s Above" /></a></p>

<p>And the other new shoe is the Arakys. Arc’teryx promotes it as a “<em>ultralight bouldering and single pitch approach shoe designed for indoor and outdoor climbers</em>”. The closure system can be operated with one hand and is easy to switch from climbing (closed) to belaying (open). The heel is collapsible and turns it into a slipper. It will weigh about 270 g per shoe in UK Size 8.5, has a Vibram MegaGrip sole and comes also in a Men’s and Women’s Version with four colours per sex. I probably wouldn’t use it for climbing &amp; bouldering, but for approaches, at the crag and scrambles it probably would be very nice. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19082093501" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Arakys Men&#x27;s Side by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/319/19082093501_3cc742e332_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Arakys Men&#x27;s Side" /></a></p>

<p>That’s the first look at the 2016 Arc’teryx Footwear line. There’s <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157654541709680">more photos on Flickr</a>, if you liked this post share it with your mates on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19082131411" title="Complete Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear Line-up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/303/19082131411_8c1b5d2c9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Complete Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear Line-up" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc'teryx Alpine Academy Chamonix 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-alpine-academy-chamonix-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-22T23:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-alpine-academy-chamonix-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A reflection on the fourth <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy in Chamonix</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18863780819" title="&quot;And over there...&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/518/18863780819_3527250da3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;And over there...&quot;" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>2015 was the 4th <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> overall and my second one to attend. I was lucky enough to be invited as a member of the Press this year so got a sneak peak at the cool new gear that will come next year from Arc’teryx, and like everyone got the chance to hang out with the athletes, try out cool gear from Arc’teryx, Petzl, Scarpa, MSR and LYO Food and have a great time in Chamonix with the other participants. Here’s a re-cap of the three clinics I visited, which should be interesting if you’re considering to visit the Arc’teryx Academy in 2016!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18860432990" title="At the Base Station by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/499/18860432990_234d5c5a7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="At the Base Station" /></a></p>

<h2 id="glacier-preparation-clinic">Glacier Preparation Clinic</h2>

<p>I haven’t been to Mer de Glace last year so decided that the <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/shop/a-beginners/clinic-03-glacier-preparation-clinic/">Glacier Preparation Clinic</a> would be a good start for the weekend in Chamonix. The Mer de Glace is also only at about 1.900 m height which makes for easier acclimatisation, which worked well for me - last year I went straight up to 3.800 m, and living at sea level that’s quite a bit of difference. </p>

<p>Our group of four were with BMG and IFMGA Mountain Guide <a href="http://stuartmacdonald.org/">Stuart MacDonald</a> which was a great guy which explained us everything we needed to know about walking on a Glacier. After taking the train up to the Grand Hotel Du Montevers we walked to the ladders and started the descent down to the Glacier. It’s an interesting thing, as less than 150 years ago you could walk onto the Glacier from where you embark the train - climate change is showing its ugly face here, and it will be interesting to see how much more the glacier will retreat.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19046370865" title="Grand Hotel Montevers Hotel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/474/19046370865_4085701c4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Grand Hotel Montevers Hotel" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18861943339" title="Down the ladders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/432/18861943339_3cebe64d02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Down the ladders" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19042575182" title="Boulder-hoping by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/396/19042575182_7cc12f1051_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Boulder-hoping" /></a></p>

<p>Once you’re down the ladders you walk over the moraine till you’re at the proper glacier. Here Stuart explained us how to put on our crampons and how to walk normally in them, which we did for a bit. Then we moved on to learn more crampon techniques, front pointing, and how to use our ice axe. If you haven’t used these ever before its a good clinic to get to know the basics, so that you can do for example glacier hikes in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18860391730" title="Rock &amp; Ice by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/296/18860391730_ff5a10a7f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rock &amp; Ice" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19042544702" title="Approach by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/255/19042544702_8efeb42fef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Approach" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19042558292" title="Jumping crevasses by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/284/19042558292_86aaae53c1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jumping crevasses" /></a></p>

<p>After that we went to a steep section where a glacial river has carved a deep gorge into the ice, set up anchors and started to first walk steep ice up, and then ice climb it. The latter exercise was great fun, as we went from two ice tools to one ice tool to no ice tool, which taught you about proper foot placement and keeping your balance. This was the most fun part for me and I could have done it all afternoon long. Alas, we wanted to catch the 15 o’clock train down so after everyone made a lap down and up we started the walk back to the train station. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18861939059" title="On belay by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/333/18861939059_bab394c014_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On belay" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18860454288" title="Stuart MacDonald, BMG &amp; IFMGA Mountain Guide by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/436/18860454288_fef1f40dd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stuart MacDonald, BMG &amp; IFMGA Mountain Guide" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19051268351" title="Ascending the ladders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/547/19051268351_a795791827_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ascending the ladders" /></a></p>

<h2 id="advanced-alpine-techniques">Advanced Alpine Techniques</h2>

<p>The Arête des Cosmiques has been on my Tick List for a long time, and I was a bit jealous when my mate did it last year in his Technical Mountaineering course while we did the Pointes Lachenal Traverse. Waking up on Saturday morning after maybe one Génépi too much I was sure that today I’d be going on the Cosmiques, and lo and behold: As I arrived punctually at the Aiguille du Midi base station <a href="http://www.chamonix-guides.eu/Trombinoscope/251/contact/jean_villard_guides/23-trombinoscope.htm">Jean Villard</a> told me with a smile that the weather is so good that he thinks we should do the Cosmiques today, because we can learn &amp; practice all the techniques on it that we should do in our <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/shop/c-advanced/clinic-06-sat-adv-tech-alpinism/">Advanced Alpine Techniques clinic</a>. We drove up in the first Gondola and met the two other clients who slept the night up on the glacier, roped up and started the approach to the Arête des Cosmiques. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053159461" title="The start of the Arête des Cosmiques by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/421/19053159461_dfe9b0da84_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The start of the Arête des Cosmiques" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19049953765" title="Jean Villard preparing the rope by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/559/19049953765_bf34d4de11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jean Villard preparing the rope" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19044428282" title="Blue-Bird weather by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/476/19044428282_6f2375c22a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Blue-Bird weather" /></a></p>

<p>At the Abri Simond hut we untied, roped up again and started up the route. It starts off with easy snow &amp; ice covered slabs which we protected with an occasional friend. At the Gendarme then came the first abseil, which had me a bit nervous - wrongly, though. Then it are a few more steps to the 2nd abseil, where you need to squeeze yourself backwards through a narrow chimney, which again was somehow feeling a bit dodgy to me, but again was no problem. After that followed some easy traversing to the 2nd tower, where we passed the <a href="http://www.chamonixtopo.com/digital-crack-aiguille-du-midi">Digital Crack</a>, the highest 8a in Europe. It looked like a beautiful line and should I ever reach that level, I’m sure to try it. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19023712866" title="Scrambling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/520/19023712866_9dcd627ea1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scrambling" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053150951" title="1st Rappel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/400/19053150951_91b1417a73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="1st Rappel" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18427455014" title="2nd Rappel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3931/18427455014_fb2865d367_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2nd Rappel" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862277738" title="Follow the leader by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/488/18862277738_4b1a17e008_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Follow the leader" /></a></p>

<p>But our climbing, at a much lower grade, was coming: The 4a Crux pitch. Jean free soloed it up without problems - he probably does that route a dozen times per year, and he’s already very long a Mountain Guide! - and then we followed. It was very easy even with crampons on, so even if you’re not a climber this shouldn’t have you worried in my opinion. As we were the first rope team on the route that day and we lost our pursuers after the first rappel we had a leisurely lunch on top of the Crux pitch, enjoyed the Alpine Choughs which were sailing above us and the beautiful sunshine. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18863787319" title="The 4c Crux and Jean on belay! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/264/18863787319_bcc114fd65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The 4c Crux and Jean on belay!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862253370" title="Almost there by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/469/18862253370_a063ddcef1_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Almost there" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862284358" title="Jean having Johannes on belay by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/384/18862284358_8b84068d78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jean having Johannes on belay" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053145441" title="Alpine Chough take-off by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3925/19053145441_3139abbae2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Alpine Chough take-off" /></a></p>

<p>After the nice break we continued onto the North Face of the route, and it got a wee bit colder in the shadow. But the scrambling over large boulders and through chimneys kept us warm enough until we reached the final plateau before the Aiguille du Midi cable car station. I had Georg, Johannes and Jean walk up to a pillar to take a few photos, and the people on the view platform went completely mad =) As we climbed the wee ladder up we were welcomed like celebrities and had our photos taken with strangers!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053168201" title="&quot;And then you swing your leg over it like this!&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/391/19053168201_dd50af4a14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;And then you swing your leg over it like this!&quot;" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862276668" title="Final scramble by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3743/18862276668_b5f74731bb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Final scramble" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053169731" title="The Aiguille du Midi Station by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3882/19053169731_e7d1eedeba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The Aiguille du Midi Station" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19044388832" title="A look back again by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/380/19044388832_4bd2b8c937_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="A look back again" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862246870" title="And up the ladder to the station by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/343/18862246870_4104f5ecff_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="And up the ladder to the station" /></a></p>

<p>It was a four hour round trip for us four (three clients, one Guide) with one long break for lunch, if you go alone or just two you probably can do it in a couple of hours or less - when there’s not a lot of people on the route, as it is very popular! It definitely is worth a visit, as it is a very scenic route that’s great to practice alpine climbing and mountaineering skills.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19049977945" title="Arrived! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/474/19049977945_ff89f288f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arrived!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bigwall-climbing">Bigwall Climbing</h2>

<p>Sunday and <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/shop/c-advanced/clinic-19-sun-big-wall-climbing/">Bigwall Climbing</a> was a great combination. The Bigwall Climbing clinic was new this year and very popular, and I think for a good reason: With a Client to Athlete to Guide Ratio of 3:1:1 it’s a fantastic clinic to learn new skills, ask a lot of questions and practice a lot. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18863698930" title="On the way to the Gongola by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/562/18863698930_34a87765fc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On the way to the Gongola" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19025173796" title="Bigwall Clinic group by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3746/19025173796_f7399d1035_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Bigwall Clinic group" /></a></p>

<p>The Bigwall Climbing consisted of four stations: The Portaledge Station, Jumaring, and two Aid Climbing stations - one with friends and nuts, the other with pitons and skyhooks. Because of time constraints I only got to try the first three, but on the plus side I was able to practice how to ascend the rope with some of my own gear (<a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/wild-country-ropeman-mk2f-steigklemme/">Ropeman 2</a> + <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-micro-traxion-seilrolle/?pid=81">Micro Traxion</a> in case you’re wondering). <a href="https://www.facebook.com/marcandreclimb">Marc-André Leclerc</a> showed us how to jumar the traditional way, with two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/petzl-ascension-ascender/">Jumars</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/black-diamond-alpine-aiders-ladder/">Aider Ladders</a>. It was interesting to try this, as it always looks so easy in movies, but until you have found out the rhythm it wasn’t as easy as it looks!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18428873064" title="Marc-André explaining how to jumar by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3777/18428873064_d2a06da4f9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Marc-André explaining how to jumar" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19025176476" title="Me jumaring by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/366/19025176476_7e9f1d6c4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Me jumaring" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19045837982" title="Brett showing another way to jumar by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3892/19045837982_3aea9c2756_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Brett showing another way to jumar" /></a></p>

<p>After that <a href="http://arcteryx.com/Athlete.aspx?EN/PaulMcSorley">Paul McSorley</a> showed us how to set up a Portaledge Camp, keep the camp in order and haul gear up. It was super interesting and as Paul has slept a few nights in Portaledges it was cool to hear his stories and tips on how to camp comfortably on a Bigwall. Sleeping on a Portaledge in Yosemite is high on my list, and this clinic certainly has me psyched to make that dream come true some day soon.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18865219979" title="&quot;And that&#x27;s how you keep things tidy&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/316/18865219979_96ac17bd8d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;And that&#x27;s how you keep things tidy&quot;" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19045823222" title="Jasmine trying out the Portaledge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/523/19045823222_abc5ef9ff0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jasmine trying out the Portaledge" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18428878174" title="Knot Protector™ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/495/18428878174_8b0b55d11e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Knot Protector™" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19054563981" title="HAUL! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/373/19054563981_c69512dd4b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HAUL!" /></a></p>

<p>And then we went Aid Climbing. <a href="http://www.bigwall.ch/">Pesche Wüthrich</a> explained Hayden and me the ins and outs, and then we both scaled the crack on aid. Slowly. Because Aid Climbing, we learned, needs a lot of time. You place gear, clip in the ladder and Daisy Chain, slowly weigh it to see if it holds, then clip in your Fiffi hook, and repeat. The route we climbed was a super easy crack which we probably could have climbed half a dozen times without Aid gear on lead, but this was a cool way to try it out and learn about it. The beauty/ attractiveness of it is certainly that you can climb safely on your own.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18863695980" title="Pesche Wüthrich explaining Aid Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/496/18863695980_157b4b6db6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pesche Wüthrich explaining Aid Climbing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19051392185" title="Hayden about to try Aid Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/432/19051392185_ea1f897688_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hayden about to try Aid Climbing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18617727928" title="Hayden Carpenter Aid Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/424/18617727928_9a4196d5b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hayden Carpenter Aid Climbing" /></a></p>

<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>

<p>I arrived Thursday morning and left Sunday afternoon, but happily would have stayed a bit longer in this fine Alpine Climbing &amp; Mountaineering Playground. My 2nd Arc’teryx Alpine Academy was again a lot of fun &amp; very inspirational, where I met great people, learned new skills, and got to climb in Europe’s best alpine climbing destination. What made me very happy was that there were a lot of people from all skill levels who decided to come to the <a href="https://instagram.com/explore/tags/arcteryxacademy/">#ArcteryxAcademy</a> to learn mountaineering and climbing skills. I shared the rope with hillwalkers from the UK &amp; Malaysia, aspiring mountaineers from Austria and Bigwall Climbers from the USA, Canada and France, and met old friends from across the globe. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19045840552" title="Hiking into the fog by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3818/19045840552_36c47c9f90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hiking into the fog" /></a></p>

<p>Again I can only recommend aspiring mountaineers and alpinists as well as backpackers &amp; hikers who’d like to up their skills to visit the <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a>. This year there were less people which in my opinion improved the learning and safety on the mountains, and made the groups more cozy &amp; personal, with more time for asking questions and trying techniques. The price-to-quality ratio still is superb, and if you consider all the free stuff available - the <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/movie-night/">Movie Night</a>, the interesting <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/seminar-night/">Seminars</a> and the <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/demo-gear/">Demo Gear</a> - it really is very affordable. I certainly will keep a weekend free for next year for the 5th Arc’teryx Alpine Academy - if you’re smart, you’ll too! </p>

<p>There’s a lot <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157654457553021">more photos on Flickr</a> and here are <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Tips on Accommodation &amp; Getting there</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19044416802" title="Rope team crossing Vallé Blanche by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/561/19044416802_c5d748fe08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rope team crossing Vallé Blanche" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 204]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/the-week-in-review-204.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-08T23:18:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/the-week-in-review-204</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“It is not to be expected that human nature will change in a day.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1FDbAn5">Frank B. Kellogg</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18572119925" title="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/266/18572119925_8e67987dba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>GoPro launched a new entry level camera, the <a href="http://bit.ly/1Qg8cZA">GoPro HERO+ LCD</a> which has a LCD back-screen.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.welt.de/vermischtes/article141813503/Der-mysterioese-Tod-der-Luchse-im-Bayerischen-Wald.html">The mysterious Lynx deaths in the Bavarian Forest</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://patagoniandreams.com/2015/06/06/nepal-why-your-visit-is-paramount-visitnepalautumn2015/">Nepal – why your visit is paramount</a>. #VisitNepalAutumn2015</p>

<p>The <a href="https://youtu.be/KzdCmUDnTpc">Eureka Wall with Hazel &amp; Alex Interview</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/1928211/top-secret-food-will-change-way-you-eat">Vegan Meat</a>.</p>

<p>The awesome <a href="http://bit.ly/1EDIFSR">Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle 50</a> is on offer!</p>

<p>Lots of great trailrunning &amp; hiking shoes on sale in the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/outlet/running-shoes/">Bergfreunde.co.uk Outlet</a>.</p>

<p>Buy a GoPro &amp; Receive $50 in Accessories + <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=49133&amp;pw=73183">Free 2-Day Shipping at Backcountry.com</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.davemacleod.com/shop.html">davemacleod.com shop summer sale</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=42809&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/42809/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Joery is bak from Patagonia and his rip report <a href="http://dzjow.com/2015/06/04/wild-patagonia-a-wilderness-expedition-through-wind-wet-and-cold/">A wilderness expedition through wind, wet and cold</a> is a recommended read &amp; see.</p>

<p><a href="https://fearlessandunique.wordpress.com/2015/06/03/highland-trail-550-pictures-and-what-to-take/">Highland Trail 550 - Pictures and what to take</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.pedalingnowhere.com/routes/grand-traversee-du-massif-central-gtmc/">GTMC mountain bike route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cbjimtrip.blogspot.fi/2015/06/blog-post.html">気田川　川下り＆キャンプ</a>, a very cool packrafting trip report. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Greg hikes on the <a href="http://www.hikingfiasco.com/2015/06/werribee-gorge-circuit-and-centenary.html">Werribee Gorge Circuit and the Centenary Walk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://fisterrabicicleta.com/2015/06/05/british-columbia-tierras-maravillosamente-salvajes/">Bikepacking in British Columbia</a>. [Spanish]</p>

<p>Roger hikes from <a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/2015/05/31/e1-mullsjo-to-boras/">Mullsjö to Borås on the E1</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/129958437?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="600" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://therepublicofdoom.blogspot.fi/2015/06/curecanti-needle.html">Curecanti Needle</a>.</p>

<p>Angelica hikes the <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/06/05/die-eifelleiter-extra-rundtour-vinxtbachtal/">Eifelleiter Extra-Rundtour Vinxtbachtal</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cedricbernardini.com/2015/06/03/norway-finland/">Norway, Finland</a>.</p>

<p>Bikepacking Scotland – <a href="https://northernwalker.wordpress.com/2015/06/05/cycling-scotland-the-west-highland-way/">The West Highland Way</a>.</p>

<p>Erika trains her thighs in the <a href="http://ulligunde.com/2015/06/wadentraining-im-alpstein-massiv/">Alpstein-Massive</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Keith’s <a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/continental-divide-trail-part-three-2/">Continental Divide Trail Part 3</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18493538621" title="Friday&#x27;s Outdoor Office by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/410/18493538621_e46dd8d195_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Friday&#x27;s Outdoor Office" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/phd-minix-sleeping-bag.html">PHD Minix Sleeping Bag Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/gear-reviews/bikes/review-ground-effect-body-bag">Ground Effect Body Bag Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2015/06/wilderness-logics-tadpole-tarp-and-door-mod-review/">Wilderness Logics Tadpole Tarp and Door Mod Review</a>.</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> for On-The-Trail updates! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em> </p>

<script id="fbz8es0">(function(i){var f,s=document.getElementById(i);f=document.createElement('iframe');f.src='//api.flattr.com/button/view/?uid=HendrikM&button=compact&url='+encodeURIComponent(document.URL);f.title='Flattr';f.height=20;f.width=110;f.style.borderWidth=0;s.parentNode.insertBefore(f,s);})('fbz8es0');</script>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=319733&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/319733/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHD Minix Sleeping Bag]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/phd-minix-sleeping-bag.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-02T23:19:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/phd-minix-sleeping-bag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/minix-down-primaloft-sleeping-bag">PHD Minix Sleeping Bag</a> is interesting: Down on top and Primaloft in the bottom with a water-resistant shell, which makes it a warm and very lightweight sleeping bag. If it’s a good choice for your 3-season backpacking trips you read in my review.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18387083991" title="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8879/18387083991_18fcbe74b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/minix-down-primaloft-sleeping-bag">PHD Minix Sleeping Bag</a> arrived last year May and has been used on several trips since, like my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/bouldering-on-aland.html">climbing roadtrip in Finland</a> and backpacking on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">Högakustenleden</a>.</p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The Minix is a sleeping bag, and so it’s function is to keep you warm while you sleep outdoors. </p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>PHD has this to say about the Minix:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Water-resistant Ultrashell outer (40 g/ m²)</li>
  <li>Primaloft Gold insulation on the base to handle damp &amp; maximise insulation under compression</li>
  <li>Box wall construction on top to maximise down loft</li>
  <li>900 fillpower European goose down</li>
  <li>Superlight MX inner (32 g/ m²)</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18199309079" title="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag bottom &amp; top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/289/18199309079_157412966a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag bottom &amp; top" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>PHD uses high-quality fabrics - a water-resistant outer, a box-wall construction for the 900 cuin down and Primaloft Gold - to create a ultralight sleeping bag. There’s also not many sleeping bags available that have a synthetic bottom and down on top - a smart way to use these two insulation materials.</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>I own a few garments and the Minix from PHD and they are really of a superb quality. All of them are hand made in the UK, from the best and most functional materials. That quality has its price, but you’ll get many years of use out of them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18197780400" title="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag Bottom by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7750/18197780400_0e075a9a30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag Bottom" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Minix I have - it’s the 2014 model which has a different colour than the 2015 one, otherwise they’re the same - weighs 575 g in Standard length, with the stuff sack tipping the scales at 25 g.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I really like using the Minix. While it needed some time to get used to the restricted movement that a sleeping bag offers, and that you only can get in via the top, once inside it was warm and comfy to sleep in. PHD gives the Minix a Comfort rating of 0°C and I can confirm that. With a T-shirt on the Minix kept me warm till 0°C, but once there was just some light minus degrees I immediately was cold in the sleeping bag. So for early spring and autumn trips you might want to take an extra baselayer along to sleep warm in the Minix, for all other times when the temperatures stay warm you can sleep just in your shirt and underwear in the Minix.</p>

<p>If it gets too warm - for me that’s +10°C and over - the Minix was very hot and I would start to perspire. This meant I would either pull the sleeping bag down to my waist to cool off or get completely out of the bag and just use it as a blanket over me, which allowed me to also leave a leg out to cool down. The Minix is very wide above so using it as a blanket worked well for me when laying on my back. I think the sleeping bag is ideal for temperatures between +1°C and +9°C, if it goes under 0°C you want to wear something in it, and if it goes over 10°C I do run to warm in it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18387090991" title="PHD Minix Hood Open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/540/18387090991_edecbec72d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Hood Open" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18381395682" title="PHD Minix Hood Closed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/438/18381395682_1677d102c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Hood Closed" /></a></p>

<p>The freedom of movement inside of the sleeping bag is good, too. Because the Minix does not have a collar and just one drawstring to close the hole there’s not anything in the way on top, which makes turning around inside of the bag easy. The foot box was big enough for my size 42 feet and I also could lay in comfort on my side inside of the bag. </p>

<p>The Minix comes with a mesh storage bag and a 2 l stuff sack, the latter is great and well-suited for the bag but for the mesh bag I would prefer something larger from organic cotton. I have used the Minix with and without a bivy and with a bivy you have the added benefit of a mosquito protection and a few degrees more warmth. The Minix packs nice and small and lofts very quickly at camp. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17764852993" title="PHD Minix Footbox by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/277/17764852993_dd73e687ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Footbox" /></a></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>A small pocket for the drawstring on top would be great, I hate straps flying around my head and a pocket where I can stuff the drawstring in would take it out of the way and add just a couple of gram of weight. I’m also wondering if a light zipper down one side would be of benefit, while this would add quite a bit of weight it would make it easier to get in to the sleeping bag and also venting would be improved. </p>

<p>Finally, I wonder if the concept of the Minix - synthetic bottom and down top - would not be a great idea for a quilt. It would lose the hood most likely, but freedom of movement and venting would be improved a lot, and it even should be able to be lighter.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>If I just think about sleeping bags then the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mountain-hardwear-hyperlamina-spark-kunstfaserschlafsack/">Mountain Hardwear Hyperlamina Spark</a>, the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/montane-featherlite-5-schlafsack-reg-links/">Montane Featherlite 5</a>, the <a href="http://bit.ly/1AInDmz">Rab Ascent 300</a> and the <a href="http://bit.ly/1cvmt1X">Western Mountaineering MegaLite</a> sleeping bags come to mind. The first is a synthetic sleeping bag while the other three are very good down sleeping bags, but none of these have two insulation materials in combination.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If the idea of quilts is alien to you, then the Minix sleeping bag will be great for you. An ultralight sleeping bag that has a water-resistant shell you can use it without a bivy from spring to autumn as long as the thermometer stays above 0°C. The Primaloft bottom allows you to use a lighter, less insulated <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/sleeping-pads/">sleeping pad</a> as it is warm, even when compressed, and also is less sensitive to dew and moisture than down. The warm layer of 900 cuin down in box-wall construction on top keeps you toasty on fresh nights, and if it gets too warm you can even improvise the Minix into a narrow blanket. The water-resistant Ultrashell withstands dew and a light drizzle, protects the down and lets it loft nicely. If you want one sleeping bag for your 3-season trips that’s water-resistant, light, has a small pack size and is toasty warm, consider the Minix from PHD!</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/minix-down-primaloft-sleeping-bag">Minix</a> is part of the PHD <a href="http://stories.phdesigns.co.uk/summer-lightning-2015">Summer Lightning Collection</a> that is only available in May &amp; June from PHD directly - so hurry if you want this sleeping bag!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18387085671" title="PHD Minix Packed Size by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/420/18387085671_180a8b2f5c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Packed Size" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
