<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-24T22:28:20+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bikepacking Framebag Manufacturer List]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-24T18:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fatbikes, Mountain Bikes, 29er, Road Bikes and Bikepacking go hand-in-hand. So that you are ready for your next bikepacking adventure and don’t need to rely on old panniers which make riding Singletrack simply not fun, here’s an up-to-date list of people and companies which produce framebags.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410128705" title="Dawn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/10410128705_2ce65c655f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Dawn" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Framebags allow you to explore trails and tracks with all your gear packed in a lightweight, streamlined and rack-less method, without any panniers which hang off the back and front wheels and which make navigating singletrail tracks not pleasueable - if not impossible. With your camping gear in framebags - which covers handelbar bags, seatbags, top tube bags and (half) frame bags - you have a possibility to carry all your gear on your bike and are able to explore trails far off the beaten track, with your bike behaving as responsive and ergonomic as usual. </p>

<p>But not just for off-road travel by bike framebags are a smart choice, also for cycle-touring and commuting a half frame bag and top tube bag are great choices to store essential gear on the go. You easily can carry a pump, patch kit and more in a half frame bag, and the top tube bag stores snacks, your camera and phone with easy access during your ride. Both my bikes sport frame bags and I wouldn’t want to miss them on bikepacking adventures and commutes to town.</p>

<p>For easier reference I sorted the makers into locations - Europe, North America and the rest of the world. Know someone who should be on this list? <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Email me</a>.</p>

<h1 id="north-american-makers">North American Makers</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16439818958" title="Porcelain Rocket Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8573/16439818958_87688c7c3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="620" alt="Porcelain Rocket Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="revelate-designs">Revelate Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.revelatedesigns.com">Revelate Designs</a> is probably the first framebag maker which many come across. Eric and his team have been making framebags in Alaska since 2007 and nowadays also make framebags for Salsa and other bike companies. They produce the whole setup and also offer custom work. You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/11/interview-eric-parsons-from-revelate-designs.html">read my interview with Eric here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="porcelain-rocket">Porcelain Rocket</h2>

<p>I own a complete set of <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com">Porcelain Rocket</a> Framebags for my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/driving-in-the-mud-rain.html">29er</a> and love them. Scott and his team make a lot of custom bags and also have many great standard bags which will fit your bike. You can get your whole setup from PR as well as Salsa Anything Cage Bags. <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/interview-scott-felter-of-porcelain-rocket.html">Read the interview with Scott here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bedrock-bags">Bedrock Bags</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.bedrockbags.com">Bedrock Bags</a> are from Colorado. All bags are custom order and you can get a whole set from them.</p>

<h2 id="becker-gear">Becker Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.beckergear.com">Becker Gear</a> is another Alaskan framebag maker that offers custom work.</p>

<h2 id="jpaks">J.Paks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jpaks.com">J.Paks</a> packs are made in Denver, Colorado. They have besides the standard flavours of framebags also many special versions available, like an insulated stash bag.</p>

<h2 id="nuclear-sunrise-stitchworks">Nuclear Sunrise Stitchworks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nukesunrise.com">Nuclear Sunrise Stitchworks</a> packs are made in El Paso, Texas. Get every framebag possiblity from them.</p>

<h2 id="oveja-negra">Oveja Negra</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.ovejanegrathreadworks.com/">Oveja Negra</a> offers the whole bikepacking setup, from stock half frame bags to full custom bags. Based in Salida, Colorado.</p>

<h2 id="wanderlust">Wanderlust</h2>

<p><a href="http://wanderlust-gear.com">Wanderlust</a> is the former <a href="http://hansbagworks.com">Hans Bagworks</a> and you can get Framebags and Handlebar bags as well as some accessories from them. They’re based in Harrisonburg, Virginia.</p>

<h2 id="rogue-panda-designs">Rogue Panda Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://roguepanda.com">Rogue Panda Designs</a> is from Flagstaff, Arizona and makes seatbags, handlebar rolls, framebags and also lightweight panniers.</p>

<h2 id="bolder-bikepacking-gear">Bolder Bikepacking Gear</h2>

<p><a href="https://bolderbikepacking.wordpress.com">Bolder Bikepacking Gear</a> has been making bikepacking gear in Boulder, Colorado since 2010. You can get the whole bikepacking setup from them.</p>

<h2 id="andrew-the-maker">Andrew The Maker</h2>

<p><a href="http://atmhandmadegoods.com">Andrew The Maker</a> is a new framebag maker tht currently only offers a handlebar bag.</p>

<h2 id="phantom-pack-systems">Phantom Pack Systems</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.phantompacksystems.com">Phantom Pack Systems</a> are a maker from Canada and also offer the full bikepacking framebag setup.</p>

<h2 id="crater-packs">Crater Packs</h2>

<p><a href="http://craterpacks.com">Crater Packs</a> are made in Telluride, Colorado. They make frame bags, seat packs and handlebar bags from cuben and vinyl.</p>

<h2 id="cleaveland-mountaineering">Cleaveland Mountaineering</h2>

<p><a href="http://cleavelandmountaineering.blogspot.fi">Cleaveland Mountaineering</a> is located in Grand Junction, Colorado and makes custom frame packs, handlebar bags, Everything bags and top tube bags.</p>

<h2 id="jandd">Jandd</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jandd.com/bikes.asp">Jandd</a> has been making bags since 1983 (!) and offers a wide variety of bikepacking bags.</p>

<h2 id="lone-mountain-innovations">Lone Mountain Innovations</h2>

<p><a href="http://lonemountaininnovations.com">Lone Mountain Innovations</a> has been making framebags. They’re currently re-designing their products and will be back in a few months, so keep an eye on them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855481330" title="Pimpin&#x27; at the beach by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8429/7855481330_49fdb544f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Pimpin&#x27; at the beach" /></a></p>

<h1 id="european-makers">European Makers</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16007444033" title="Apidura Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8662/16007444033_7343c4d374_b.jpg" width="1024" height="617" alt="Apidura Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="apidura">Apidura</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.apidura.com">Apidura</a> is a British company which makes frame bags, seat bags, handlebar bags and top tube bags - the whole shebang thus - in standard sizes. Measure your bike, pick the bags and your ready to go!</p>

<h2 id="inuvik-studio">Inuvik Studio</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.inuvik.es">Inuvik Studio</a> produces their framebags and Top Tube bags in beautiful Spain.</p>

<h2 id="spk-werks">SpōK Werks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.spokwerks.com/bikepacking-gear.html">SpōK Werks</a> is a German maker of framebags, with the whole setup available.</p>

<h2 id="bike-pack">Bike Pack</h2>

<p><a href="http://bikepack.pl/en/">Bike Pack</a> hails from Poland. They make all sort of frame bags and do so for a very good price.</p>

<h2 id="alpkit">Alpkit</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.alpkit.com/bikepacking">Alpkit</a> nowadays also make the whole setup. Framebags are custom-made while seatpacks, top tube bags and handlebar bags are standards.</p>

<h2 id="wildcat-gear">Wildcat Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.wildcatgear.co.uk">Wildcat Gear</a> are from Wales and offer the whole framebag setup, both basic and custom options.</p>

<h2 id="bikebag">BikeBAG</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.buggybags.co.uk/pages/BikeBagOptions.htm">BikeBAG</a> is another UK maker of framebags. Only custom framebags are available.</p>

<h1 id="rest-of-the-world">Rest of the World</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16440220550" title="Wanderlust Equipment Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/16440220550_f24609baa9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="609" alt="Wanderlust Equipment Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="wanderlust-equipment">Wanderlust Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/products/g219-blade-frame-bag/">Wanderlust Equipment</a> from Japan makes a half frame bag to order. They look pretty neat and the craftsmanship should be superb!</p>

<h2 id="bike-bag-dude">Bike Bag Dude</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bikebagdude.com">Bike Bag Dude</a> is from Australia and offers standard bags and custom work, the whole range of framebags as well as Anything Cage Bags and Chaff Bags. They’re also a dealer for <a href="http://www.bikebagdude.com/#!oveja-negra-accessories/c1jyy">Oveja Negra Threadworks</a> framebags in Australia.</p>

<h2 id="myog">MYOG!</h2>

<p>Don’t want to spend money on a framebag? That’s not needed if you can use a sewing machine. Here are a couple of Guides to get you started:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pedalingnowhere.com/gear/how-to-make-a-bikepacking-framebag-krampus/">Making a simple frame bag for the Krampus</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/oWDRiexLA0I">How to make your own frame bag for bikepacking Video</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tourintune.com/constructing-my-diy-frame-bag/">Constructing My DIY Frame Bag</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.shanecycles.com/make-your-own-gear-myog-bikepacking-frame-bag/">Make your own gear (MYOG) Bikepacking frame bag</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15923653420" title="Salsa Mukluk on the ice by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8605/15923653420_5b51d86efe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salsa Mukluk on the ice" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-23T20:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">ISPO 2015</a> gear bonanza continues with sweet new hardware and soft goods for backpackers, climbers, skiers and hikers!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557811671" title="Dynafit Khion Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7367/16557811671_d2d2a49edc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit Khion Carbon" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html">Read Part 1 here</a></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research">Outdoor Research</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371946330" title="Outdoor Research M&#x27;s Diode Hooded Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16371946330_4138aba056_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research M&#x27;s Diode Hooded Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>At <a href="http://outdoorresearch.com/">Outdoor Research</a> a whole lotta new gear was to be tried on and tested indoors, like the M’s Diode Hooded Jacket up there. A jacket made with Body Mapping technology it uses DWR-treated down and Primaloft Gold. The latter is on the shoulders, hood, top of the sleeves and hips - areas which usually get more wet - while the core is filled with warm down to keep your torso toasty. All that is under a Pertex® Endurance 2L shell where the Primaloft is and the down is protected by Pertex® Quantum. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533381316" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/16533381316_95ee1e8e2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a></p>

<p>The Uberlayer Hooded Jacket (the blue on on the left) on the other hand trusts Polartec Alpha insulation completely to keep you warm, but not too hot. It has a stretch mesh lining which wicks sweat quickly away form your baselayer, where it meets on the Polartec Alpha insulation which further transports it to the outside. There’s plenty of pockets on the Uberlayer, a helmet-compatible hood and the shell is also wind and water resistant. The Men’s Uberlayer is 563 g in Size L, the Women’s is 472 in Size M.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558277002" title="Outdoor Research Furio Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8582/16558277002_3d65a62968_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Furio Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Furio Jacket uses the new Gore-Tex® C-Knit fabric in the shoulders, hood and hip, Paclite in the rest of the jacket and is fully seam taped. It has a Standard Fit and is 535 g light and is made for your alpine adventures where it will keep you dry, warm and protected in case the weather turns nasty. I do like OR’s TorsoFlo™ technology which are hem-to-bicep side zips that offer ventilation when the going gets steep. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936813154" title="Outdoor Research Luminary Sensor Glove by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7299/15936813154_921a82e670_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Luminary Sensor Glove" /></a></p>

<p>The Luminary Sensor Glove is an alpine climbing and skiing glove that allows you to take <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> photos without taking the gloves off. The indoor test the glove mastered without difficulties as you can see above. Made from Windstopper the shell gloves are windproof and water-resistant while the warm, removable wool blend liners keep your fingers toasty. The dexterity was good in these and with removable liners you’re able to dry them in your quilt during the night. The pair in L will weigh 236 g. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371894050" title="Outdoor Research Extravert Glove by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16371894050_52555e3dc0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Extravert Glove" /></a></p>

<p>The Extravert Gloves have a stretch nylon shell outer, a durable goat leather palm with textured fingertips and a warm wool lining. These ski-touring gloves will keep you warm when you’re skinning up and shed the powder on your turns down. The pair in L will be 165 g light.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559340835" title="Outdoor Research Untold Balaclava by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7427/16559340835_8430a96a97_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Untold Balaclava" /></a></p>

<p>The Untold Balaclava is made from acrylic and weighs 51 g. It’s a convertible balaclava that can be transformed into a cap when you roll the lower part up. It’s probably a very nice piece for winter use when the conditions change from cold and shady to sunny.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533325976" title="Outdoor Research Toasty Beanie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/16533325976_46f3f6dbcb_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Toasty Beanie" /></a></p>

<p>And then there were literally about a dozen new hats and even more gloves - after all that’s what Outdoor Research does very well. I did like the stylish hats and beanies which would be functional on the trail and stylish at the Aprés Bar after your hike. Lots of nice stuff coming from them, so keep an eye out for them.</p>

<h2 id="vertical-life--zlagboard">Vertical-Life / Zlagboard</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16588486191" title="ZlagBoards! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7336/16588486191_5df67be72b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ZlagBoards!" /></a></p>

<p>I’m pretty psyched about the news from <a href="https://www.vertical-life.info">Vertical-Life</a> and especially <a href="https://zlagboard.com">Zlagboard</a>. The latter I tried already at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/outdoor-2014-wrap-up-and-conclusions.html">OutDoor</a> and liked it but was wondering if the price was too high. Well, it seems my ideas were heard and the Zlagboard Team not just dropped the price on the Zlagboard Pro to 250€ but also introduced the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-mini">Zlagboard Mini</a> which will retail for 150€ and also the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-vario">Zlagboard Vario</a> which sells for 190€ and which allows you to attach a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/trainingsboards/">training board</a> you already have (like a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beastmaker-2000-series-trainingsboard/">Beastmaker</a>) to it. That’s not all, though, as the Team also has updated the App and there’s now a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html">Gimme Kraft!</a> training plan available and the option to create your own. I really love this and you can stay tuned for a review of the Zlagboard on these digital pages soon.</p>

<p>Vertical Life is the publishing arm of the business and they do have some <a href="http://guide.vertical-life.info/en/publications/">superb Guidebooks</a> available. Add to that already good line-up are four more guides in 2015: Sportclimbing in Südtirol, Bouldering in Südtirol, Arco Plaisir and Zillertal Multi-Pitch. Besides the dead tree versions they also will be coming as a digital app which you can download to your phone. </p>

<h2 id="salewa">Salewa</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371948468" title="Salewa North X Ice Axe, Speed Ascent shoe &amp; Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16371948468_fbfd3529e8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salewa North X Ice Axe, Speed Ascent shoe &amp; Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.salewa.com">Salewa</a> had equally interesting hardware and soft good news. Lets start with the hard goods: The North X ice axe is a 52,5 cm long and 540 g light technical ice axe for technical mountaineering. It has a steel head and blade, a 7075 aluminium shaft and a steel spike which makes it both light and durable. The hand rest can be precision-adjusted to the correct height with one hand without tools. The pick is interchangeable and the lower shaft is insulated and it has a integrated belay loop which has a 5kN breaking strength. It’s an ISPO Award Winner, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939441043" title="Salewa Ice screws by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/15939441043_ccedddc1a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Ice screws" /></a></p>

<p>I tried the new Salewa ice screws and did like them. They are an all-in-one solution: The come equipped with a Quickdraw and cap to protect the sharp points and thread, have an integrated crank and they rack very efficiently on your harness. They will be available in three lengths if I remember correctly and will start at 80€. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558505442" title="Salewa Vert Helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8636/16558505442_2232827397_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Vert Helmet" /></a></p>

<p>The Vert helmet is certified as both a climbing and skiing helmet, which makes it an ideal choice for ski-mountaineers. It has an heat-dissipating insulation and removable ear pads, the total goggle integration ensures a clear view and works together with anti-fog systems in modern ski eyewear. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533605556" title="Salewa Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/16533605556_0027b98732_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket is part of the Sesvenna Ski Touring Collection which Gore-Tex, Polartec and Windproof fabrics with Schoeller fabrics and Tyrol and merino wool for garments that combine functionality and traditional looks. They’re made with ski mountaineers in mind and are wind- and water-resistant, warm and breathable. The jacket above also won an ISPO Award and looked pretty good, a fresh design. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939447073" title="Salewa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8647/15939447073_322dfecf19_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa" /></a></p>

<p>And then there were several other new things coming from the Italian company. The Speed Ascent shoe won an ISPO Award, the climbing &amp; bouldering line gets some fresh new designs, there’s a line of products which are 100% made in Italy.</p>

<h2 id="garmin">Garmin</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15967528014" title="Garmin fēnix 3 Sapphire by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7357/15967528014_ed75eaba99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Garmin fēnix 3 Sapphire" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.garmin.com/">Garmin</a> presented the <a href="http://fenix3.garmin.com/en-US/">fēnix 3</a> and fēnix 3 Sapphire which had some major updates on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">fēnix</a> I have. The major difference between the two models is that the latter comes with a scratch resistant sapphire lens and a steel wristband (in addition to a normal plastic one) which allows you to wear your outdoor watch to the office. The watch is made for a host of activities, from backpacking to trailrunning to Triathlon. I think it’s a great looking watch, but that ain’t all of course: Under the hood the watch got some major updates: A color display that can be read in the sun (although I had major difficulties getting a good photo under them lamps indoors =), a stainless steel EXO™ antenna with GPS + GLONASS support for fast fix and accuracy, a host of Fitness training features &amp; Outdoor navigation features and Connect IQ™ compatibility for customized apps, widgets, watch faces and data fields. The fēnix 3 should be available in about a month or two, and retails for 500€ to 600€.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16620722281" title="Garmin epix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8599/16620722281_eb4fc2167b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Garmin epix" /></a></p>

<p>The Garmin epix on the other hand is a GPS watch which comes with a European Freetime Map pre-installed. It also has a Chroma colour display, an EXO Antenna for GPS &amp; GLONASS reception, several sports profiles and connects with several accessories. The  idea is that here you really have a high-resolution, color, touchscreen GPS/GLONASS mapping watch with worldwide, shaded relief basemap and 8 gb memory for further maps. I do like the classic look and the epix will be 500€ and also available in about two months. </p>

<h2 id="mountain-equipment">Mountain Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557871341" title="Mountain Equipment Compressor ¾ Pant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8655/16557871341_a8f03e3708_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Compressor ¾ Pant" /></a></p>

<p>Filled with PrimaLoft® GOLD between a Helium 30 fabric that’s windproof is the Compressor Pant and the Compressor ¾ Pant which I model above. The ¾ Pant version tips the scales at 240 g and the length is chosen so it stays above your skiing boots. It’s easy to put on with a full-length zippers on each side, and it packs into its own seat pocket. The ¾ Compressor will be 160€ will the full length version will set you back a tenner more and you’re able to carry 95 g extra, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373263039" title="Mountain Equipment by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7416/16373263039_e615d2d75a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment" /></a></p>

<p>The Switch Vest is a hybrid garment that combines Polartec® Alpha® in the front and Polartec® Power Dry® 225 Fleece at the sides and back. The idea is that the breathable and warm Alpha® insulation keeps away the headwind while you can lose the sweat and heat via the back when you’re skinning, running or climbing up a mountain. At 240 g and 100€ it’s looks like an interesting piece for the fast &amp; light readership. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373271959" title="Mountain Equipment Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/16373271959_9154aec292_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant" /></a></p>

<p>The Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant is <a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.co.uk">Mountain Equipments</a> foray into the Ski-touring market. Both garments are made from burly GoreTex Pro 80D. The Super Alpine Hood has been developed further for ski helmets and has an integrated collar, and the Alpine Fit with articulated sleeves ensures you have the freedom of movement you need when you earn your turns. The jacket also has a removable snow-guard while the pants have removable gaiters &amp; suspenders. A pocket on the thigh stores your avalanche beacon. The combo weighs together 1.335 g and will set you back 1100€. </p>

<h2 id="la-sportiva">La Sportiva</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16592940652" title="La Sportiva Ultra Raptor GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7410/16592940652_6b78d41f9e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Ultra Raptor GTX" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.sportiva.com">La Sportiva</a>’s News I’d divided in these Categories: Trailrunning, Mountaineering, High-Altitude News. Lets take a look at them in that order. The Ultra Raptor GTX weighs 410 g per shoe, has a 12 mm drop and a FriXion XF sole with the Trail Bite heel stabilizer which enhances the downhill grip. The shoe isn’t new, but the colour is =) </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16406374858" title="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7365/16406374858_8b978a4691_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX" /></a></p>

<p>The Crossover 2.0 GTX isn’t new either, but at 370 g light per shoe it’s worth a mention. This is the third shoe from La Sportiva in this round-up with an integrated gaiter, and considering this shoe is made for winter trailrunning (and hence is ideal to be “misused” as a backpacking shoe) and Winter being the sorry excuse it currently is I’m sure a few will be interested in it. Beneath the water-repellant gaiter you find a trailrunning shoe with 10 mm drop, a Ortholite Mountain Running Ergonomic footbed and underneath is a FriXion AT sole with Impact Brake System and AT Grip zone. La Sportiva offers a Grip Spike kit which allows you to get even more grip on ice. Good stuff.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15971418784" title="Trango Ice Cube GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7370/15971418784_e2534e7f0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trango Ice Cube GTX" /></a></p>

<p>The Trango Ice Cube GTX is a new boot and carries on the trend of integrated gaiters. Made for up to 4.000 m in terms of its warmth rating the 1.380 g heavy pair of boots comes with a Schoeller fabric gaiter that’s stretchy and water-resistant, a Gore-Tex Insulated Comfort lining, an insulated carbon Honeycomb Tech 3 mm insole and a La Sportiva Cube sole, made by Vibram® with the Impact Brake System lugs on the heel and a climbing zone at the toe. It’s so lightweight because of the seamless construction method on the uppers which use the Thermo Tech Injection™ technology. The boot is obviously fully crampon compatible and can be resoled.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16407729549" title="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7327/16407729549_3a1b2b283c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro" /></a></p>

<p>The G2 SM, which stands for Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro, is a sexy boot. Oh, its functional too. What I liked about it the most was the sense of adventure it communicates - Gasherbrum 2, Karakoram, 8.035 m, and of course the first winter ascent of Cory Richards, Denis Urubko and Simone Moro in 2011. It’s a very technical boot: Integrated Cordura gaiter, internal shell with BOA® quick lacing System, HoneyComb Tech midsole in carbon fibre, Vibram® Matterhorn sole with Impact Brake System lugs and a removable liner boot. It’s a super warm boot made for expeditions to the high ranges, and the pair will weigh 1.940 g. </p>

<p>Otherwise garments got some colour updates, there were a few rather nice new carbon skis and ski boots. </p>

<h2 id="grivel">Grivel</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16593580955" title="Grivel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/16593580955_e6acb0d845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Grivel" /></a></p>

<p>I do like what <a href="http://www.grivel.com">Grivel</a> does. Take the A&amp;D above: It’s an Ascender that also allows you to descend. Just thread the rope through the slit in the A&amp;D, clip it into a carabiner, open the Ascender part and you can abseil down. This allows you to use one less piece of kit, and the ascender is also easy to unlock when the teeth have dug deep into your rope. It works with ropes from 8,3 mm to 13 mm in diameter when going up and 7,3 mm to 13 mm when going down and weighs 259 g. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16001900693" title="Grivel Tech Machine Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8642/16001900693_54f2653a73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grivel Tech Machine Carbon" /></a></p>

<p>Then there’s the new Tech Machine which will be available as an aluminium and carbon version. The former is 660 g for the tool, the carbon version saves you 100 g - they work both just as good, as Stevie Haston ensured me - though the carbon one will be warmer. The interesting new development on these is the G Bone Shaft, which should allow for an ergonomic grip along the whole shaft. This technology will also be used in the Air Tech Evo ice axe (which also gets a Hammer Version next winter) and the North Machine ice tool. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15973805963" title="Grivel Mountain Runner Comp backpack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/15973805963_176c1e7bbe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Grivel Mountain Runner Comp backpack" /></a></p>

<p>The Mountain Runner Comp backpack is a 450 g light trailrunning pack with 5 l volume. These packs were designed with experience from the Tor de Geants Race, are one-size-fits-all, have multiple pockets to carry your gear and even allow you to carry your ice axes or poles on it. </p>

<p>Oh, and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-lambda-twin-lock-hms-karabiner/">Twin Gate carabiners</a> are now in stores. Get one to try them, I do quite like them.</p>

<h2 id="dynafit">Dynafit</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533475316" title="Dynafit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7431/16533475316_657af5fcd2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit" /></a></p>

<p>If I am at the ISPO a visit to <a href="http://dynafit.com">Dynafit</a> is always in order - gotta know what this company is up to if you like lightweight kit. The Chugach is a free touring ski which will launch for the 2015/ 2016 season and is for free riders who want to conquer new terrain by mountaineering means. Named after Alaska’s Chugach Mountains which represent untouched wilderness and awesome descents, the ski offers an optimal ratio of surface area to weight, which is 1.950 g. It has a double ellipse rocker construction and enables maximum edging on steep, icy terrain without losing the playful lightness when initiating turns. This is going to be a ski to watch if you like to play in big, wild mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373204349" title="Dynafit Khion Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7339/16373204349_020299b5ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit Khion Carbon" /></a></p>

<p>The Khiôn is a free touring boot which combines the rigidity and support of an alpine downhill boot with the comfort and lightness of a modern ski touring boot on the ascent. The boot will be available as a Khiôn MS model, a stiffer Khiôn Carbon version which adds more performance on the descent and also a Women’s version. The boot will give you performance and precision with direct power transmission and maximal support thanks to the new Precision Lock System which enables the various parts of the boot to work together as a torsionally stiff unit. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557822481" title="Dynafit Radical 2 Binding by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7302/16557822481_ab6d563ebc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Dynafit Radical 2 Binding" /></a></p>

<p>The Radical 2 Binding takes a step forward in safety and comfort 30 years after the invention of the frameless system. The Radical 2 weighs 599 g and the biggest update is the a pivoting toe piece combined with the Step in Side Towers. This has several advantages: It functions as an additional release mechanism and works to prevent early release from side impacts. It has a a precise release mechanism at the toe and heel piece with a release value between 4 and 10 for the Radical 2 ST version or up to 12 for the Radical FT.</p>

<h2 id="mountain-hardwear">Mountain Hardwear</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937000064" title="Mountain Hardwear HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8650/15937000064_16b2b942f8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com">Mountain Hardwear</a> HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag and it’s sibling Spark are synthetic sleeping bags which employ a central zipper for you to get in and comfortably sit in your bag during your morning coffee. The Spark will be 737 g and the Flame 1106 g with temperature ratings to 0°C and -6°C respectively. The bags are made with MH’s Lamina™ construction which welds the Thermal.Q™ insulation to the shell and lining, eliminating the cold spots caused by traditional stitching. Bodymapping technology was employed throughout the top of the bag to concentrate warmth where you need it most – around your core and feet. The bags will set you back 220 or 240€.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXIII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxiii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-22T21:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxiii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“There are always two people in every picture: The photographer and the viewer.”</em>
- <a href="http://amzn.to/19RTIM4">Ansel Adams</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6961553731" title="Sunset II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7176/6961553731_903b678b97_b.jpg" width="1024" height="480" alt="Sunset II" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://semi-rad.com/2015/02/dear-winter/">Dear Winter</a>.</p>

<p>Always felt like your feedback should be heard when developing a new outdoor jacket? Now’s your chance: <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/aktuelles/prototyp-tester-hagloefs-isolationsjacke/">Test a Haglöfs Insulation Jacket Prototype</a> and let Toray &amp; Haglöfs know what should be improved!</p>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/1zWgNSX">Adobe Lightroom</a> 6 comes March 6th. Conincidence with the date? </p>

<p>Bunyan Velo Issue 5 is out. <a href="http://bunyanvelo.com/issues/">Read it for free</a> or <a href="http://bunyanvelo.myshopify.com/collections/all/products/bunyan-velo-issue-no-05">buy it</a>.</p>

<p>Win a warm &amp; waterproof <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/66-north-raffle/">66° North Snafell Down Parka</a> at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/walking-el-camino-year-camino-companion-smartphone-app/">The Camino Companion Smartphone App is Out</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nationalparks.org/ook/every-kid-in-a-park">Every Kid in a Park</a>, a great iniative in the USA.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpinist.com/doc/web15w/wfeature-searching-for-jensen">Searching for Jensen</a>.</p>

<p>Antti’s <a href="https://longdistancetrail.wordpress.com/2015/02/18/gr5-book-now-available/">GR5 Book is now available</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://gizmodo.com/a-beginners-guide-to-doing-drugs-in-the-outdoors-1686617842">A Beginner’s Guide To Doing Drugs In The Outdoors</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.groundtruthtrekking.org/blog/?p=3472">Sixth Year in the Woods (Musings of a Wilderness Parent)</a>.</p>

<p>Aender &amp; Sven visit <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2015/02/caspers-climbing-shop-ein-besuch/">Casper’s Climbing Shop</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/22/opinion/sunday/mountaineerings-greatest-climb-unravels.html">Mountaineering’s Greatest Climb Unravels</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/">Outdoorline.sk</a> has 20% off all <a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/26_westcomb">Westcomb Gear</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=313709&amp;pw=73183">Sign up for Campsaver.com’s newsletter</a> and receive 15% off your first order!</p>

<p>At the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=371565&amp;pw=73183">REI OUTLET Odds &amp; Ends</a> you can save 70% or more!</p>

<p>And the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/?refID=hif">trekking-lite-store.com</a> celebrates it’s fifth birthday this weekend with 10% off everything.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=45773&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10083/45773/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="145" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20910655/">天狗岳 2日目</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikeovernights.org/post/sources-of-inspiration-fat-bikes-canyon-country">Fat Bikes &amp; Canyon Country</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://chamconditions.blogspot.fi/2015/02/skiing-in-kosovo-and-macedonia.html">Skiing in Kosovo and Macedonia</a>.</p>

<p>Tips for a <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/roadtrip-baltikum-tipps/">Roadtrip through the Baltic States</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2015/02/los-volcanes-seccion-2.html">The Volcanoes</a>. </p>

<p>Part 13 of Gerald’s Trip Report takes him <a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/02/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-13.html">along ridges with great views</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Peter heads out for a <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/02/levaneva-ski-overnighter.html">Levaneva Ski Overnighter</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/119981667?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/blue-mountains-valley-of-the-waters-and-the-national-pass-tread-lightly/">A week in the Blue Mountains</a> – Part 2.</p>

<p>Stefanie hikes to the <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/winterwanderung-herzogstand/">Herzogstand</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.carbon-monkey.co.uk/wp/index.php/2015/02/south-downs-way/">UK Bikepacking Trip</a>.</p>

<p>Ski-touring to the <a href="http://biwak.blogspot.fi/2015/02/chli-bielenhorn-2940m.html">Chli Bielenhorn</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A Winter hike to the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/rotwand-1884m-in-spitzingsee-a-winter-hike/">Rotwand 1884m in Spitzingsee</a>.</p>

<p>Skiing on the <a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2015/02/18/uebers-wasser-laufen/">Königssee</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Linda visits <a href="http://photomomlinda.blogspot.fi/2015/02/smith-rock-in-winter.html">Smith Rock in Winter</a>.</p>

<p>Dave &amp; M go <a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2015/02/17/the-harsh-fiords/">sea kayaking in New Zealand</a>.</p>

<p>Dr. Tomás is back with <a href="http://www.scandinavian-hiking.com/2015/02/Ph.D.html">Piled Higher &amp; Deeper</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://becausetheyrethere.com/2015/02/17/arkengarthdale-moor-and-the-death-of-sods-law/">Arkengarthdale Moor and the Death of Sods Law</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/primus-winter-gas.html" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7452/16577006692_b45cdfda48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Corinna’s <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2015/02/weltgroesste-sportmesse-ispo-2015-bunt-wars.html">ISPO Impressions</a> were colourful. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://coastkid.blogspot.fi/2015/02/diy-fatbike-pvc-pipe-washstand.html">DIY Fatbike PVC pipe washstand</a>.</p>

<p>Will Gadd explains the <a href="http://willgadd.com/bd-spray-ice-hooks/">Pectre Ice Hooks</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://ivovanmontfort.blogspot.fi/2015/02/zelfbouw-gtx-regenjas.html">MYOG Gore-Tex Rain Jacket</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.alpin-blog.com/leichter-hochtouren-gurt-blue-ice-choucas/">Blue Ice Cou­cas Harness</a> reviewed. [German]</p>

<p>Roger prefers <a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/2015/02/15/why-i-prefer-klymit-mattresses/">Klymit Mattresses</a> and explains why.</p>

<p><a href="http://seattlebackpackersmagazine.com/clif-shot-bloks-energy-chews-review/">Clif Shot Bloks – Energy Chews Review</a>.</p>

<p>Derek reviews the <a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2015/02/antigravitygear-quicksilver-ultralight-hammock-review/">AntiGravityGear Quicksilver Ultralight Hammock</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" title="Zum Winterschlussverkauf 2015 bei Bergfreunde.de"><img src="http://www.bergfreunde-partner.de/banner/wsv/af_wsv_728x90.jpg" border="0" alt="Zum Winterschlussverkauf 2015 bei Bergfreunde.de" /></a><img src="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=402&amp;cpid=1&amp;prid=1&amp;view=1" height="1" width="1" border="0" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Primus Winter Gas]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/primus-winter-gas.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-19T13:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/primus-winter-gas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.primus.eu/winter-gas-230-g">Primus Winter Gas</a> Test. In real Winter™ conditions. Answering the age-long question: <em>Does it really work?</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16018424719" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8657/16018424719_cbbf145d70_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>A cartridge of <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Primus Winter Gas</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1DrYz2T">Primus Power Gas</a> arrived in December on my porch, courtesy of <a href="http://www.primus.eu">Primus</a>. With Climate Change being a reality in Finland and the winter 2015 turning out to be as shite as <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/the-four-week-winter.html">last year</a> I was eagerly waiting for the temperatures to drop to see if the gas really works as claimed. On a magical day which combined sunshine with -13°C (which felt like -18°C my Weather App ensured me) it was so far and I <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">dressed up in layers</a>, took my two MSR Reactor stoves and headed out to conduct my sort of <em>scientific outdoor test in Finnish Winter conditions</em>. Before we watch a video of me talking and playing with fire, here’s what Primus says about the Winter Gas: </p>

<p><em>“Everybody who has used a gas cartridge stove in cold conditions knows this: The lower the temperature, the poorer the performance of the stove. Even though the cartridge might be brand new! Why? Liquefied gas doesn’t evaporate properly the colder it gets. In addition, the evaporation process has a self-cooling effect on the cartridge, so
conventional LP gas canisters perform poorer and poorer during use.</em></p>

<p><em>Primus Winter Gas improves the performance of LP gas cartridge at temperatures down to –22°C. After 60 minutes of cooking, a Winter Gas cartridge is approximately 9 % more powerful than one without Vapor Mesh. After 120 minutes of use it delivers about 15 % more power. The reason for the even better performance over time is that the Vapor Mesh works better the emptier the cartridge gets, because more of its surface is exposed.”</em></p>

<p>Good, lets look a bit at that in detail. </p>

<ul>
  <li><em>The lower the temperature the poorer the performance</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Yeps, I can sign that for gas stoves. See my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/primus-omnilite-ti.html">OmniLite Ti Review</a> and scroll down to the video at the bottom. Took quite a bit to boil that water and that was with an inverted canister (Canister, cartridge, they’re the same in case you’re wondering).</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Primus Winter Gas improves the performance of LP gas cartridge at temperatures down to –22°C</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Lets call this the hypothesis, which I am trying to prove. </p>

<ul>
  <li><em>The reason for the even better performance over time is that the Vapor Mesh works better the emptier the cartridge gets, because more of its surface is exposed</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Are you wondering HOW that Vapor Mesh looks like? I surely was. Happily Primus made the effort to cut one of their canisters in half so we can look inside and have an idea:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557911141" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7411/16557911141_182ddf4be5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<p>Some more information on the Vapor Mesh is in order, me thinks. It’s a type of paper that absorbs the liquid gas. When I went to school and learned to write with a fountain pen I always had a sheet of <em>Löschpapier</em> - Blotting Paper - next to me in case of a mistake. So <em>Vapor Mesh</em> seems to be working like blotting paper, but what’s the idea of putting that paper in there? </p>

<p>As you saw, the Vapor Mesh paper is on the sides of the canister, from the bottom till almost the valve on top of the canister. The liquid gas in the canister is <em>liquid</em> and so the paper absorbs the liquid gas which then travels to the top, which widens the surface area of the gas. More surface area means more gas can evaporate from liquid to gas which also increases the pressure in the canister. How it works, according to Primus, is:</p>

<p>a) Faster phase transition from liquid to gas
<br />b) Burner receives more fuel
<br />c) Boiling times in low temperatures become shorter</p>

<p>This should get even better the less liquid gas is in the canister, as this makes the Vapor Mesh surface area larger. Gas goes down = more Vapor Mesh paper becomes exposed, sucking liquid gas up = more surface area for the liquid gas going from liquid to gas. OK, done, lets go outside.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16576488681" title="Primus Power Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8592/16576488681_80fd9c23be_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Power Gas" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-test">The Test</h2>

<p>So lets get down to testing. The conditions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Outside temperature was -13°C</li>
  <li>Two identical stoves, the <a href="http://bit.ly/1ilDgDz">MSR Reactor 1.0 l</a></li>
  <li>Valves were opened at the exactly same time</li>
  <li>Stoves were lightened up at the exactly same time <em>x¹</em></li>
  <li>Both pots were filled with exactly 500 ml of cold water</li>
  <li>Both pots were put on the stoves at exactly same time</li>
  <li>Power Gas Operating Temperature is -15°C to +25°C</li>
  <li>Winter Gas Operating Temperature is -22°C to +10°C</li>
</ul>

<p>This is how that looks in moving pictures: </p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mj-vaft7hF8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<p>Or watch it on <a href="http://youtu.be/Mj-vaft7hF8">Youtube</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-result">The Result</h2>

<p>Look, I made a nice table to present my initial findings! </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td> Power Gas</td>
      <td> Winter Gas</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> Weight 1</td>
      <td>369 g</td>
      <td>374 g</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> Weight 2</td>
      <td> 351 g</td>
      <td>356 g</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> Time</td>
      <td>2:50 min</td>
      <td>2:20 min</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br />Both canisters ignited equally well at -13°C and there wasn’t a winner - the temperature was well within the capabilities of the Power Gas, which might get problems if the temperature drops down to -20°C and more. Both the Power Gas and the Winter Gas used the same amount of fuel (18 g) to boil the 500 ml of water, but the Winter Gas was 30 seconds faster. This means at least the <em>a), b) and c)</em> points above hold true. I wouldn’t go as far as proving the hypothesis right as this was after all only <em>one</em> short test with two new canisters. The real test would be to repeat these tests until both canisters are empty, and then draw conclusions. <em>x²</em> As I usually don’t cook food on the trail and just melt snow and boil water in winter, I’d do this long-term test like the above one, just several times in a row till the canisters are empty. This represents the real-world conditions for backpackers much closer than letting the stove run for as long as possible in one session.</p>

<h2 id="what-it-means-in-the-real-winter-outdoor-world">What it means in the Real-Winter-Outdoor-World</h2>

<p>Obviously my test is just starting to show the possibilities of the Primus Winter Gas, and I didn’t even touch on their claims of better performance over longer time. I’m happy to do that (<em>x²</em>) if time and responsibilities permit, but right now it’s either way to warm outside to test it and it will need to wait till I go north and chase winter. However, it did show that the Winter Gas did perform better than its sibling Power Gas, which was the de-facto gas most of us used in Winter (usually with an inverted canister stove). Now most often people that are serious about winter backpacking use a gas stove that allows them to invert the canister where the pre-heat tube at the stove lets the liquid gas vaporize to gas before it arrives at the burner, so I don’t know if Winter Gas is a must-have for them (the gas compositions of both Power &amp; Winter Gas seem to be the same, only the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-summer-gas-gaskartusche/">Summer Gas</a> uses a different gas mix).</p>

<p>However, many of us don’t want to buy an inverted canister stove just for the few times we go out in winter. And that’s where I see the possibilities of the <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Primus Winter Gas</a>: For all those people who use an upright gas stove like the <a href="http://bit.ly/1LgbO86">Jetboil MiniMo</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1AJrnU6">MSR Windboiler</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1A8sdHY">MSR Reactor</a> or <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-eta-lite-sturmkocher/">Primus Lite+</a> and who want to try winter backpacking but <strong>not</strong> buy a new stove. The Primus Winter Gas is around 2,50 € more expensive than the Power Gas but allows you to use the gas stove you have in cold winter temperatures. Which is a pretty neat thing, because usually upright gas stoves start to perform badly when the temperature drops and the canister gets emptier - the Winter Gas with its Vapor Mesh liner promises that your stove now will function just as good as in warm weather. I for one liked what my initial tests showed, and am looking forward to chase Winter up North and see if it performs also in the long run.</p>

<p>You can get the Winter Gas at your local <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/tuotemerkit/primus">Partioaitta Store</a> in Finland or online at the usual suspects like <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Globetrotter</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/primus/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16576491401" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7383/16576491401_01f554e0c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<p><em>I usually don’t do <strong>Disclaimers</strong> but here’s one: The Power Gas and Winter Gas have been sent to me for free and I was under no obligation to produce any content about nor endorse it. The statements represents my findings after using these items, at the time of testing and writing.</em></p>

<p><em>x¹</em> This needed several tries as either the Reactor stove with the Power Gas or the Reactor Stove with the Winter Gas didn’t catch a flame, so then I closed the valves and did the whole process from the beginning again
<br /><em>x²</em> If you’d like me to do just that, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> so I have something warm to drink while I’m standing outside in the cold.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16552157116" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7454/16552157116_c3ce614152_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-17T21:59:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The ISPO is the annual trade fair where outdoor companies present their autumn &amp; winter collections for the coming seasons. I travelled down to München once again to check out what new kit we can expect next winter and here is the first batch of my finds.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371800168" title="VAUDE by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7308/16371800168_23b1e71f13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="VAUDE" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="arcteryx">Arc’teryx</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557800531" title="Arc&#x27;teryx by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8579/16557800531_dab20040d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373187969" title="Arc&#x27;teryx by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7358/16373187969_85d819e367_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx" /></a></p>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> is that their glove line has been completely re-designed and like their clothing the gloves now work as a layer system. I tried on the different gloves and really loved them and found them better than the already great <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-alpha-sv-glove-black-xs/?pid=81">Alpha SV Gloves</a> I’m using right now. Most of the new gloves don’t use leather anymore which makes them more flexible and allows for better dexterity, and the liner gloves and shells also can be used completely on their own. For durability the gloves are made from a 3 layer Gore-Tex fabric with TPU laminates on the palm and fingers so that they’re highly abrasion resistant (and waterproof!). The Beta Shell Glove (110 g in M) &amp; Atom Glove Liner (90 g in M) are for the climbers and mountaineers while the Lithic Glove (an ISPO Gold Award Winner) is an insulated glove for backcountry skiers &amp; snowboarders that uses three kinds of PrimaLoft® synthetic insulation in the construction. Also the Mittens I tried on where fantastic and I imagine if you’re a lot out in really cold winter then these gloves will be high on your list.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558836791" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7363/16558836791_9d2067f3a3_b.jpg" width="751" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Canadians also will be using the new Gore-Tex® C-Knit™ fabric in their new Zeta LT Jacket which will weigh in at 335 g for a Men’s Medium and the even lighter Norvan Jacket (215 g in M). C-Knit from Gore should be ideal for hikers &amp; backpackers as it combines the durable Gore-Tex Pro membrane with an extremely thin, dense &amp; lightweight circular knit backer on the inside. The result makes the jacket much softer next to the skin and also less noisy and stiff. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15940472133" title="Nuclei AR Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/15940472133_4b223c94fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="536" alt="Nuclei AR Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>And the new Nuclei AR Jacket (also an ISPO Gold Award Winner) is an all-round belay parka that combines 100 grams/m2 of Coreloft synthetic insulation with a seam taped Windstopper exterior, making it a warm, windproof and water-resistant insulation piece that you can put on when you’re hanging in the middle of a frozen waterfall and are belaying your mate. The Nuclei in Medium will tip the scales at 465 g and set you back 475 €.</p>

<h2 id="primus">Primus</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557911141" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7411/16557911141_182ddf4be5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<p>Lots of good stuff coming from <a href="http://www.primus.eu">Primus</a>. <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Winter Gas is now available in stores</a> (and expect a spot review from me this week on it, too) which is good news for winter adventurers. It was announced at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor 2014</a> and now helps you to cook, melt snow and boil water in cold temperatures. Seriously good stuff.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559583855" title="Primus Silencer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7421/16559583855_94195b900f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Silencer" /></a></p>

<p>Have you seen my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/primus-omnilite-ti.html">Omnilite Ti with Gas in Winter Video</a>? Do you remember how LOUD the stove was? That’s a thing of the past with the Primus Silencer. The Silencer is mounted in a few seconds by unscrewing the upper part of the OmniLite Ti burner and replacing it with the Silencer and only adds 17 g to the stove weight but doesn’t reduce fuel efficiency or power output. It is not suitable for diesel, kerosene or jet fuel and will set you back 60 €, but the silence it gives you is well worth that in my opinion.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16374728849" title="Primus Stove Paw Ti by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7281/16374728849_9d0556f5f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="941" alt="Primus Stove Paw Ti" /></a></p>

<p>Serious winter backpackers usually take a plate of sort along for their stoves when they’re cooking and melting snow, as stove feet tend to sink into the snow or melt it and two litres of melted snow tipping over in your tent is inconvenient. Enter the Stove Paw Ti, a baseplate that supports stoves when cooking in snow or on other soft, slippery surfaces. The Stove Paw Ti folds super-compact and weighs in at 55 g and is made from Titanium as the name suggests. It fits with the Primus’ OmniFuel, MultiFuel, OmniLite Ti, EasyFuel and Express Spider stoves and the different stove’s feet attach quickly and securely to the slots in the plate, making cooking safer and easier. Again a rather simple yet smart accessory that makes your winter adventure a tiny bit more convenient.</p>

<h2 id="therm-a-rest">Therm-A-Rest</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373717847" title="Therm-A-Rest Voyager Mattress by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7440/16373717847_b3bc02c271_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Therm-A-Rest Voyager Mattress" /></a></p>

<p>There was only one new item at <a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/therm-a-rest/">Therm-A-Rest</a> at the ISPO, and that was their Voyager Mattress. It’s a mattress for the camper as the Regular length model weighs in at 650 g (R-Value 2,2) with a length of 183 cm and a width of 51 cm. The selling argument for the mat is its thickness of 6,3 cm and the WaveCore construction, which will make it a nice, warm camping mat for 3 Season use. </p>

<h2 id="jetboil">Jetboil</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559537985" title="Jetboil by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8563/16559537985_bf898d2a54_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Jetboil" /></a></p>

<p>You’ve likely seen some of the pre-ISPO Press Releases about the new <a href="http://www.jetboil.com">Jetboil</a> Flash Lite and I too got the Press Release well before the fair and so knew what was waiting for me. Like usual at Jetboil I asked for 500 ml of cold water and then made the indoor fair test, in which the Flash Lite boiled that half litre in 2:15 minutes to a rolling boil. The whole stove system weighs 312 g and measures 104 mm x 165 mm, with a suggested Retail Price of 100€. It’s a well-constructed little stove that replaces the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti.html">Sol Ti</a> and like its predecessor you can fit the stove, legs and a 100 g cartridge inside of the pot. Unlike the Sol Ti it shouldn’t have any problems with the flux ring and bottom of the pot dissolving as everything is made from aluminium. </p>

<h2 id="rjk">Röjk</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939424333" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7399/15939424333_ac073dca09_b.jpg" width="1024" height="654" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://rojksuperwear.com">Röjk</a> goes Inca Patterns in 2015. The designs are growing on me, from an initial <em>Hmmm, interesting</em> my opinion has matured into a <em>I think they’re onto something there</em> and give it a few more weeks and I’m sure I’ll totally love it. Except those T-Shirts. Those I love already:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558486002" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/16558486002_83f89b2252_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533585186" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8598/16533585186_31807106c9_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p>The Röjk crew partners with different artists each season who develop the designs and I yet have to see a SuperTee I didn’t like. They’re great. As I’m on a hyperbole train already, let me continue with the sweet packaging Jan has designed for the SuperBase baselayers: </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533597336" title="Röjk Packaging by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/16533597336_8c74017d91_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Röjk Packaging" /></a></p>

<p>As a former sustainability consultant this totally hit home with me. Flat packaging allows you to ship more SuperBase baselayers in one box which minimizes unused space and so brings the efficiency up and the fuel used down. The packaging can be recycled by the end user very easily and it’s pretty, too. Awesome! But back to them garments:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937025654" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7452/15937025654_b507853293_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p>Another new garment the Swedish company brought back is their ChillOut Pant. I saw it on the mannequins and Linus and wanted one immediately. It felt very comfortable with laces at the cuffs and waist that keep the pants in place. It looks stylish and I would have no problem heading to a Café in it, but most likely I’d be wearing them when heading to the climbing gym or chilling at home. Because style and comfiness are häftigt =)</p>

<h2 id="inov-8">inov-8</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559448265" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7409/16559448265_2d0b13a067_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.inov-8.com/">inov-8</a> had several ISPO Winners in their line-up but the best news for the backpacking inov-8 community is that their much-loved X-Talon 212 will come in 2015 besides the good old Regular version also in a Version with a Wide Toebox called Standard Fit. Both have the great close-fitting heel which locks the shoe into position but the wide toebox allows your toes to splay, which probably will make this already popular shoe even more, yeps, popular.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936887794" title="Inov-8 TerraClaw Line-Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/15936887794_ec1e7fdff4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8 TerraClaw Line-Up" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373527077" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7358/16373527077_56bc3bfcef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>New in the inov-8 Line-Up is the TerraClaw family. It comes in 220 and 250 g versions (per shoe) for Men and Women (left &amp; right on the above photo). The TerraClaw 220 is the stripped-down version for super-fast racing, while the TerraClaw 250 adds more protection and comfort and I reckon this could be a good ultralight backpacking shoe. inov-8 sees these shoes as their most versatile yet which should perform well on loose, rocky trails as well as hard-packed paths. It’s an ISPO Award winner and the judges valued the Multi-Directional Lugs which provide traction when climbing, descending and contouring alike. The Dual-C™ Outsole uses two types of sticky rubber - the darker one is more durable and is in areas of high wear while the lighter rubber maximizes grip. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558347592" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8648/16558347592_f873320966_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Inov-8" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936858314" title="Inov-8 RaceUltra Shell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7325/15936858314_45095e2823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8 RaceUltra Shell" /></a></p>

<p>Then there’s the garments. High on the list for Ultralight backpackers and Ultra Racers alike will be the Race Ultra Shell, a 125 g shell anorak that has a 10.000 mm hydrostatic head (the minimum requirement for many Ultra races nowadays), taped seams, a long venting zipper and the material is also breathable. The fabric is transparent so that race numbers can be seen underneath it and the fabric is stretchy, and best of all: When not needed it packs to the size of an orange. There’s a Race Ultra Pants, too, which tips the scales at 95 g and probably packs down o the size of an apple.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371756968" title="inov-8 Race Elite Merino LSZ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7361/16371756968_f81da06d79_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="inov-8 Race Elite Merino LSZ" /></a></p>

<p>The Race Elite Merino LSZ (yeps, also an ISPO Award Winner =) is a 263 g Merino wool hoody that uses a lighter fabric in the back and under the arms while at the fron there’s a heavier Merino wool. It has a close fitting hood and built in hand mitts (yes, REAL mitts) that fold into the cuffs when not needed. Add in a long zipper for venting and you got a new Merino hoody on the block which should delight not just trailrunners!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936852414" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/15936852414_486098ef3b_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>And finally there was the RaceUltra 10 backpack, an ISPO Gold Award Winner, which also has a little 5 l sibling. I tried this pack on, jumped around like a rubber ball and concluded my indoor test that the zero bounce claim holds true. The pack has several hydration options and ten pockets, which makes it a good choice for 100 miles and longer Ultras where you need to carry more mandatory kit and food. Both packs come with two 500 ml soft flasks with tubes and there’s a compartment for your hydration bladder, too.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> The <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>

<p><em>Check back on Thursday for Batch II!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-15T21:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Snow falls/ water freezes/ air floats.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15909703263" title="Winter Bliss by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8641/15909703263_1634276c02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Winter Bliss" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.gourmetguerilla.de/2015/02/ein-blog-im-monat-kostet-und-warum-die-leser-das-wissen-sollten/">What a blog costs per month</a>. [German]</p>

<p>David &amp; David announce their <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2015/1/29/c2c4k">C2C4K</a> in aid of the John Muir Award.</p>

<p>Ulrich’s <a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/outdoor-ausrustung/auf-der-ispo-2015/">ISPO Impressions</a> and Ute’s <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/ispo-2015-outdoorbekleidung-kinder/">ISPO Kids Trends</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A interview with <a href="http://www.outdoorwomensalliance.com/2015/02/charlotte-austin-mountain-guide-adventure-writer.html">Charlotte Austin, Adventure Writer and Mountain Guide</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2015/02/11/pepper-and-trauma/">Video Interview with Pepper and Trauma on their Winter PCT Thru-Hike</a>.</p>

<p>And the third interview is with Luc Mehl: <a href="http://www.thebicyclestory.com/2015/02/luc-mehl/">Life, Death, and Philosophy in the Alaskan Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>Alex <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/02/i-forgot-i-was-backpacker.html">forgot he was a backpacker</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.massdrop.com/buy/5394/?vendor_key=d02488acd6a84620c688c207d702d645">BlackRock Gear had a Flash Sale on MassDrop</a> - request a 2nd sale via the website for your chance to get a Down Hat for a great price!</p>

<p>What happens when <a href="http://www.powderguide.com/magazin/report/artikel/was-passiert-wenn-freeriden-volkssport-wird.html">Freeriding gets more popular</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A tidy &amp; cool <a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-gear/The-Ultimate-Gear-Storage-Facility.html">gear shed</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-25-bis-die-sohle-qualmt/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #25</a> is out! [German]</p>

<p>And the <a href="http://bit.ly/1Ew04tP">Bergfreunde Wintersale</a> is coming to an end. Order some warm garments or gear for your summer hikes today while you still get up to 60% off!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/cheese-grouse-pricey-socks/">Cheese, grouse and pricey socks</a>, a recommended read.</p>

<p><a href="http://hematula.vsco.co/journal/antarctica-2">Antarctica</a>, inspiring photos from a beautiful summer down south.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://hillplodder.com/2015/02/04/dartmoor-a-north-eastern-backpack/">North-Eastern Dartmoor Backpack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2015/02/guarapo-y-mortinos-con-cafe-trans.html">Trans Ecuador, Seccion 1</a>.</p>

<p>Mike &amp; friends are <a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2015/02/finding-flow.html">finding flow down the Grand Canyon</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.rockandice.com/lates-news/tnb-my-first-epic">My First Epic</a>.</p>

<p>Joe on <a href="http://alpine-works.com/2015/02/the-coastal-challenge/">the Coastal Challenge</a>.</p>

<p>Watching the moon set at the <a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/02/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-12.html">Saipal Chuli</a>. [German]</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/118996487?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="634" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.pureoutdoor.de/reisen/usa-westen-reise-camping">Travelling two months in the USA with a baby &amp; Toddler</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://tomripleyclimbing.blogspot.fi/2015/02/no-tfa-on-mount-kenya.html">No T.F.A on Mount Kenya</a>.</p>

<p>Peter goes <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/02/vigu-ice-skiing.html">ice skiing</a> around Vaasa.</p>

<p><a href="http://fuusora.blogspot.fi/2015/02/snowshoe-hiking-in-kitayatugatake.html">Snowshoe Hiking in Kitayatugatake</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Angelica is in love with <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/02/10/schneeschuhwandern-eine-liebeserklarung/">Snowshoe hiking</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A <a href="http://ulligunde.com/2015/02/unbeschreiblich-bloggertreffen-amberger-hutte/">ski-touring blogger meet at the Amberger Hütte</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://surfnslide.wordpress.com/2015/02/13/winter-in-snowdonia-with-the-junior-sherpa/">Winter in Snowdonia with The Junior Sherpa</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16508620976" title="After a good wash this hardshell&#x27;s DWR again functions as it should by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7397/16508620976_fa486c326c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="After a good wash this hardshell&#x27;s DWR again functions as it should" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/XjRxUfQAfHw">Tips for hiking with a child carrier (backpack) in winter</a> - a great, informative video! [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://briangreen.net/2015/02/review-paleo-meals-go.html">Paleo Meals To Go</a>, reviewed.</p>

<p>Very cool <a href="http://woodtrekker.blogspot.fi/2015/02/msr-xgk-exreactor-hybrid-cold-weather.html">MSR XGK EX/Reactor Hybrid Cold Weather Stove System</a> from Ross.</p>

<p><a href="https://joecruz.wordpress.com/2015/02/09/folding-bike-touring/">Folding Bike Touring</a>.</p>

<p>John updated his <a href="http://hikelighter.com/2015/02/12/lightest-fully-enclosed-shelters/">Lightest Fully Enclosed Shelters</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=42809&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/42809/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Said Belhaj, Climber]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/mountain-people-said-belhaj.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-11T22:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/mountain-people-said-belhaj</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Travelling, climbing, family and training - how do you fit that all into a year well spent without going to a nine-to-five job? If you’re Said Belhaj, a professional climber from Sweden, it’s easy. You train three months at home and then travel the world and climb each day! <em>A <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mountain-people/">Mountain People Interview</a>.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16504232795" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7299/16504232795_1aab6675e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Said, I know you a bit - but my reader’s don’t. Could you please briefly introduce yourself and tell us what you do?</strong></p>

<p>I was born and raised in Göteborg, Sweden to a father from Morocco and mother from Finland. I have 2 brothers and I live with my girlfriend. I’m 33 years old and have been climbing for over 20 years, 14 years as pro. We have an appartment in Stockholm with my girlfriend but are renting it out as we are travelling so much for the moment. Right now I’m staying in Santiago, Chile. Tomorrow - who knows?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15881673364" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7396/15881673364_1af82e9851_b.jpg" width="1024" height="658" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the Abisko Ice Climbing Festival in Sweden in February 2014 - was that the first time for you to climb ice, or have you been secretly planning your alpine climbing career and soon will stand on an 8.000 m peak in the Himalayas?</strong></p>

<p>I’ve ice climbed a little bit in my life, when I’ve gotten the chance. I like to try a bit of everything but unfortunately there is not always time. I don’t see myself on top of a 8000 meter peaks in the near future but at the same time who knows? I started climbing because I was seeking the adventure and the unknown, a 8000 meter climb would probably be both!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16316772330" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7375/16316772330_bac20af718_b.jpg" width="1024" height="698" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>In your “20 years as a climber” presentation you highlighted how you started climbing - from “free-soloing” as a kid to trad climbing to sports climbing - all outdoors. Nowadays most people start climbing indoors at gyms, and just a small percentage of them head outside to climb on rock. How do you feel about that?</strong></p>

<p>For me it’s strange to do an outdoor activity indoors - it’s impossible. My life and climbing has always been about beeing outdoors. Indoor climbing is good for training, comps and meeting people sometimes. I can totally see why people who start indoors stay indoors and it’s the easy access to indoor walls that have made climbing grow. At the same time it’s starnge to be out climbing in areas that used to be packed with people 20 years ago and find them almost empy now. But I wonder what would happen if all those indoor climbers went out on real rock?!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16318319937" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7320/16318319937_067a5137ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="752" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You are nowadays - thanks to the great <a href="http://www.rockandice.com/lates-news/the-seeker-said-belhaj">Rock &amp; Ice portrait</a> - probably best known for hard sport climbing, but you also do some bouldering. Is bouldering for you something to keep fit for rock climbing, or do you see bouldering as an art of climbing in itself that you enjoy?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t categorize myself as a certain type of climber; all my climbing life I’ve been doing trad, sport, boulder, big-wall, comps and even some ice. I just love to climb and like all types. I think this is what makes climbing so unique: all types, their all fun, I never get bored, always something new to learn and discover. I do more of some dicipline during certain periods of the year but would never say no to any of them - they are all climbing and thats what we do every day.</p>

<p><strong>You’ve climbed across the globe - is there a route or crag that you did that really stands out for you, and that you would recommend to any climber to visit?</strong></p>

<p>It’s almost an impossible question as I’ve climbed in hundreds of different places in about 40 countries. I think you can’t compare them, they are just different. I’ve had amazing experiences in one way or another in all of them exept some boring days of training in the gym maybe.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16478236376" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7457/16478236376_a8611e0c60_b.jpg" width="685" height="1024" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Is there a rock climbing route somewhere that you look forward to on leaving behind for others to enjoy?</strong></p>

<p>Well, I’ve put up quite a few routes on the Swedish Westcoast that people are climbing, some of them yet looking for a 2nd ascent. But because of the stupid political bolting situation in the area I’ve stopped for the moment. I’ve also put up trad routes and boulders but they never get mentioned. Anyway, I thinks it always destroys creativity when there are people who only criticize when we are trying to do something for everybody. We still have many things to learn as  humans and this can especially be said about climbers!</p>

<p><strong>How do you go about planning a climbing trip, how much time does it take to plan nine months of travelling and climbing?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t need so much time to plan these days. Usually I have some fixed plans for the year and leave some parts open. I usually do trips between 2 weeks - 3 months.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16503220012" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7302/16503220012_b10df947ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Who are your sponsors and how do they support you?</strong></p>

<p>My main partners are <a href="http://www.haglofs.com/">Haglöfs</a>, <a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a>, <a href="http://www.sportiva.com">La Sportiva</a> and <a href="http://www.c2safety.com">C2</a> who support me with gear and money. Then I also have some other brands that support me with gear and food such as Clif Bar, <a href="http://hilleberg.se">Hilleberg</a>, <a href="http://www.primus.eu">Primus</a> and Nokia. With these partners I can do that I want and I have never really had a “normal” job in my life. I will never get really rich but I’ve always done what I wanted in life - the biggest wealth if you ask me.</p>

<p><strong>Where does your next trip take you?</strong></p>

<p>For the moment I’m climbing in Perú, Bolivia and Chile in South America. In the spring I’m planning to go back to Spain &amp; France which I do every year. I also have plans for next summer and autumn but let’s first see what happens in the near future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16502501731" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8561/16502501731_ddcbbf1351_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Your family is living across the globe - your father is from Morocco, your mother from Finland and you grew up in Sweden. You travel a lot and speak six languages fluently. How do they see your career, and is it hard to see them not that often?</strong></p>

<p>I think my family didn’t like my choise in life at first, mainly because they were afraid. But they have accepted and realized I’m taking care of myself. Not seeing my family &amp; friends as often as I’d like it’s the prize I’ve had to pay to do what I do. All great things in life come to a high prize.</p>

<p><strong>You wrote on your blog that your usual yearly schedule is to train January to March at home and then travel the rest of the year. What does your training at home look like?</strong></p>

<p>I follow a 12 week training program that we’ve put together with Carlos Cabrera. I do about 10 sessions per week indoor and if possible I try to get outside on rock once a week -to stay sane. This might sound crazy but it’s totally worth it, then I can climb on rock for the rest of the year. Also, it gives me time to be in Sweden and see my family and friends. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15881673704" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/15881673704_cd8efa54fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="734" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Andy Kirkpatrick, a mountaineer from the UK, made in his essay “How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche” his first point to not have kids. You’re not yet a father, which makes climbing hard and travelling a lot easier. But do you think that at some point in time you will settle down and start a family?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, of course I’d love to have a family and get married soon. I don’t want to end up being this dirtbag dude who lives out of his van alone when I’m 50! But this doens’t mean I will stop climbing, climbing is for life.</p>

<p><strong>Said, gracias for taking the time to answer my questions.</strong></p>

<p><em>You can follow Said via his <a href="http://www.said-belhaj.com">blog</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/darsaidbelhaj">Facebook</a>.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16503220122" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7456/16503220122_9084374669_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony RX100III Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T18:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You want to go lighter than a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Full Frame Camera</a> but still want to have superb images for online and print? Then the Sony RX100III is what you want - an Ultralight Backpackers &amp; Climber’s Dream.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033934580" title="Sony RX100III Size Comparison with a Field Notes notebook by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7571/16033934580_a455c13d76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III Size Comparison with a Field Notes notebook" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’m still looking for the <em>Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> in terms of photographic equipment. It’s the camera which has only advantages, satisfies all my needs and is good enough for all my requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Print-quality photographs</li>
  <li>Nightshots possible</li>
  <li>Video capable</li>
  <li>Tiltscreen</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
</ul>

<p>That are <strong>MINE</strong>. Yours might be different. Mine are from a perspective of someone who needs high-quality photos for articles in magazines and online, likes to shot videos once in a while and does not like to carry heavy. I have plenty of colleagues who think like me, while others prefer something more substantial in terms of cameras. There’s no wrong or right and it always depends on your needs, and add in that I like to experiment and you can see why I was happy to give the <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/cyber-shot-kompaktikamerat/dsc-rx100m3">Sony RX100III</a> a spin when Sony asked me to. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033806418" title="Sony RX100III with EVF open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/16033806418_f4324c7d8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III with EVF open" /></a></p>

<p>Like usual this is no pixel-peeping review. <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-cybershot-dsc-rx100-m3">DP Review</a> does a good job looking at all the tech inside, I prefer to take the camera along outdoors and see how it performs in the field. So, 80% of the photos in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">Höga Kusten Trip Report</a> where shot with the RX100III, which means I got a full four days of photos out of the RX100III, or a total of 632 photos on one fully charged battery. That’s significantly above what is claimed (that would be 320 on one battery charge), and given that the weather on the Högakustenleden was cold and wet I find it a superb performance. It ticked one need of my list, so lets see how the others fared.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601476623" title="Sony RX100III in Selfie Mode by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8646/15601476623_65c5770695_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III in Selfie Mode" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033910680" title="Sony RX100III side with screen open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7476/16033910680_49c341d4d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III side with screen open" /></a></p>

<p>Tilt-able screen? ✓</p>

<p>The screen can be tilted fully up, great for Selfies, or at an angle, which is great if you want to shoot very low or from above your head. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033949750" title="Sony RX100III handling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7462/16033949750_519d7a2c36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III handling" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219705131" title="Viewing the view stop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7514/16219705131_dd6c0e5321_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the view stop" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601446823" title="Sony RX100III with Flash open and EVF on by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7573/15601446823_fea0a0e911_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III with Flash open and EVF on" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601438203" title="Sony RX100III taking a photo with the EVF by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7479/15601438203_b4d5205bc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III taking a photo with the EVF" /></a></p>

<p>Easy to use? ✓</p>

<p>Yeps, it is. Give it a mate in the hand who is not a camera geek and he will be able to make a great photo of you &amp; be delighted about the lightweight and easy to use camera. Sun is shining? No problem: Pop up the EVF and use it to take a photo. Although it does look a bit funny if you put that tiny camera up to your face to take a photo. </p>

<p>Print-quality photographs? ✓</p>

<p>Yes, it does produce stunning photos which have and will be printed in magazines from me. It can shoot in Sony’s Raw format which is fully supported by <a href="http://amzn.to/1LLfGPC">Lightroom</a> which makes it a great choice for professional photographers, too - I even have colleagues which only use this camera for all their photos. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15598868014" title="Sony RX100III front with open battery compartment and battery &amp; SDHD Card out by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/15598868014_e442886a44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III front with open battery compartment and battery &amp; SDHD Card out" /></a></p>

<p>Lightweight ✓</p>

<p>The RX100III is 290 g with the battery inside, with an extra 9 g for the <a href="http://amzn.to/1LLgc01">SanDisk Extreme 16GB Memory Card</a> I use. Which tips the scales at less than 300 g. Which is superb. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034258558" title="Night Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8603/16034258558_8d5ccdb6a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night Selfie" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15306067413" title="Helsinki Adventure Night by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15306067413_6fb9848e71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Helsinki Adventure Night" /></a></p>

<p>Nightshots possible ✓</p>

<p>You might think that a small and lightweight camera like the RX100III might need to have some things it does not excel at. Low light and night time photography is difficult already, usually requiring high ISO capabilities and large sensors. I wasn’t sure what I could expect from this little camera, but was positively surprised at the photos it produced in low light and at night. That Night Selfie was just after dusk, and while it’s not 100% sharp it’s a fine image, capturing the rain well, giving it a nice atmosphere. Also the indoor shot at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/helsinki-adventure-night.html">Helsinki adventure Night</a> came out superb, which ticks this point for me. Sadly I wasn’t able to try star photography with it, though I am positive that it should be possible.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220528902" title="Sony RX100III back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8624/16220528902_74fa472068_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III back" /></a></p>

<p>Video capable ✓</p>

<p>Yes, the RX100III also shoots some crisp, fine videos. It’s a bit counter-intuitive to shoot video after you took a photo, as you need to turn the dial on top into the Video mode to be able to record something. I also found the Record button at a strange location, and operating it with anything else than super-thing liner gloves is something where you can learn patience. Once it is rolling you can make adjustments to settings, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220497942" title="Sony RX100III handling with index finger on trigger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7524/16220497942_678635c6ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III handling with index finger on trigger" /></a></p>

<p><strong>And then for some further usability thoughts on it.</strong> I used the RX100III with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> and the <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/leash?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Leash</a> which I found a superb combo. I bought the <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/microplate?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Micro Plate</a> for it which is ideal with it and allows me to have the small &amp; lightweight camera securely attached to me. Speaking of small &amp; light: If you’re used to large &amp; heavy cameras this will be quite a change. I use usually cameras which are slightly bigger in size so having such a tiny camera, which easily fits in even the smallest chest pockets, is something I first needed to get used to. But then it was great.</p>

<p>Because the camera is so small people with large hands also might it difficult to operate. I have probably Medium-sized hands and found it OK to use with one hand, but usually used two. One with the finger on the trigger, the other to slightly stabilize it. Taking Selfies with the camera is easy as pie, and the Flash and EVF which can be stored away are good, too. The Focal length is 24–70 mm and the Aperture is a magnificent F1.8 - F2.8 which I liked a lot. The lens is from ZEISS which means it’s high-quality, take a look at the photos in some of the mentioned articles above or Albums underneath and you’ll see. </p>

<p>I found the battery life superb, sadly you can charge the battery online inside the camera via an USB cable, which is crap if you want to take photos with it while it loads. There’s an external Sony car charger available so at least if you’re on the go you can charge it, as well as several third-party chargers. For longer trips I’d always take an extra battery or two along, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033758968" title="Sony RX100III top and On by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16033758968_295fa5532c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III top and On" /></a></p>

<p>But are there problems with it? Well, I’m again hard-pressed to say something negative about the camera. Sure, looked at some things in isolation you could find some errors. But if I keep in mind that this is a 290 g, super-compact camera which produces superb images and has a long battery life then complaining about things like little buttons seem senseless. At 900€ the RX100III isn’t cheap, either, but there’s only a handful of cameras which play in the same league than it, and those all are a tad heavier and more expensive. </p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong>. If weight is at a premium in your pack or on your harness, but I still want to take great photos, then the RX100III would be my choice. I have <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/the-sony-rx100/">discussed with Jacob</a> about the different iterations of the RX100 before and agree that the high price might be what might keep most people getting it. But once you have it and take it on a trip, see how it performs on the trail and on the rock, in sunshine and rain, and the fine photos it takes you’re very unlikely to leave it at home. If only the lightest and best image quality does the job for you, consider the RX100III. For me it is the closest to an <em>Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> yet. </p>

<p>View <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157649751997029/">more photos of the Sony RX100III on Flickr</a> and more photos shot with it in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157648982512379/">Höga Kusten Album</a>.</p>

<p>You can support Hiking in Finland and buy the RX100III at your flavour of <a href="http://amzn.to/1BUbRPZ">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1DESZa3">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1DET2Ta">Amazon.de</a> or get it from your local <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/sony-dsc-rx100m3-kompaktikamera.html">photography shop</a> or directly from <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/cyber-shot-kompaktikamerat/dsc-rx100m3">Sony</a>. And if you think that you won’t need the latest Sony RX100 camera then you’re in luck: The <a href="http://amzn.to/1BUdbCp">RX100II</a> can be found in a tasty bundle for as low as $600 and the still great <a href="http://amzn.to/1yGsLAC">RX100</a> I found in a sweet bundle for as low as $400. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035685067" title="Views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8682/16035685067_1c22604b18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Gear from the Cottages 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T22:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What new gear can you expect to see from the ultralight cottages in 2015? We have talked with our sources and deliver you the lightest and finest new gear for 2015!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16240736587" title="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7455/16240736587_ee1a0957b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="685" alt="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Remember your roots,</strong> they say. Our roots are in ultralight backpacking. We have spread the gospel about ultralight backpacking since a long time, have <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/interviews/">interviewed cottage manufacturers</a> and used a lot of ultralight kit on our hikes and treks. And even when I nowadays am attending the big outdoor trade fairs like <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/ispo-news-2014.html">ISPO</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor</a>, it’s the new gear from the cottages that I am most excited about. And so <a href="http://hrxxlight.com">Benjamin</a> and me again set out to ask Cottage Manufacturers about the new gear they have been developing, prototyping and testing in the last months and are now ready to release to you. So here we are, and we wish you a lot of fun checking out the <strong>New Gear from the Cottages 2015</strong>!</p>

<p><em>You have a cottage and should be on this list with your new gear? <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Email me</a> and I’ll add you!</em> </p>

<h2 id="locus-gear">Locus Gear</h2>

<p>Jotaro and the team at <a href="http://locusgear.com">Locus Gear</a> have been dreaming big. Big in two ways: A ultralight, breathable dome tent for the winter mountains and a massive 8 Person shelter. The Djedi eVent Dome Shelter sleeps 2 persons, is 2,3 m long and 1,3 m wide with a height of 1 m and will tip the scales at 1,2 kg with the poles included. It looks like a spacious mountain shelter and being made from eVent you know it will be breathable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425702462" title="Locus Gear Djedi eVent Dome by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7321/16425702462_abcb9f94df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Locus Gear Djedi eVent Dome" /></a></p>

<p>I dubbed it the “Party Tent” as I saw the Prototype Photos on the Locus Gear Instagram stream and I still think that the Soris Sil Shelter could be that. Or a great group tent for scouts, a family with kids, or a a handful of hiking buddies. It can sleep six to eight persons and is pitched with two poles - and it is huge: 6 m long, 3 m wide and 1,8 m high. But it only weighs in at 1,7 kg (without poles, stakes and extra guylines) which, if broken down on the number of people it can sleep, is very light (283 g per person if there’s six in it!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239236370" title="Locus Gear Soris Sil Shelter 149 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7458/16239236370_73bae29845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Soris Sil Shelter 149" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hanchor">Hanchor</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.hanchor.com/">Hanchor</a> releases two new backpacks in 2015 which are currently in the prototyping stage. The Marble is a 65 l roll-top closure pack that will weigh around 918 g (or 1032 g with aluminum stays). Made from XPac vx07 it has a backpanel that allows for some ventilation. Horizontal seams of the Marble are folded to the upper side to make it more waterproof though they are not seam taped, while the seam between bottom panel and the body are seam taped with wide webbing from the outside to prevent water coming in. It can carry a lot of gear, too: It has one large Kangaroo pocket, 2 side pockets, 2 hip pockets and 2 daisy chains for attaching shock cord, accessories and gear. The two aluminum stays are removable, as is the padded hip belt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15804131964" title="Hanchor Marble by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8651/15804131964_ca206f9d87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hanchor Marble" /></a></p>

<p>The Chert on the other hand is a 51 l pack that will be made from XPac wx20 and has a removable frame pad and stays which will weigh in at 847 g or 961 g with the aluminum stays. It also comes with a lot of features: A roll top closure, 2 daisy chains for shock cord, accessories and gear, 2 removable aluminum stays, a removable, padded hip belt, 4 gear loops and straps and buckles for attaching ice axes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238994458" title="Hanchor Chert by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/16238994458_9a3d5dfa5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hanchor Chert" /></a></p>

<p>The guys at Hanchor are also working on a new version of their patents-pending, built-in chock sock chalk bag. The opening of the built in chalk sock is constructed with a circular plastic ring that makes it super easy to fill in the chalk and the amount of chalk coming out is enhanced. If you can’t wait for it to come out, have a look at their <a href="http://www.hanchor.com/products/SUL%20Series/Steam_drawstring_backpack?locale=en">STEAM Cuben drawstring pack</a> which came out last December.</p>

<h2 id="porcelain-rocket">Porcelain Rocket</h2>

<p>The big news from <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com">Porcelain Rocket</a> is that they just opened a Workshop in the USA which will be manufacturing their most popular items in the most popular colours, decreasing lead times and making shipping within the States easier. There’s still the option for the custom gear you can dream up, with the usual lead times =)</p>

<p>New this years is the MCA Handlebar System which replaces the PR Mission Control as their sole handlebar offering. It is easier to use, accepts any commercial drybag in the 5 - 15 l range, is lighter and works with drop bars. It consists of a simple series of nylon webbing straps mounted to a rubberized fabric plate which will keep everything organized and tidy. The drybag loads hassle-free from the front and comes with the accessory pouch which is easy to attach &amp; detach. The whole set sans drybag weighs in at 284 g and is made from 500D Cordura and now available.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/53243955@N05/16327109566" title="Porcelain Rocket &quot;MCA&quot; by Sim Works, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7287/16327109566_29bd105424_b.jpg" width="900" height="900" alt="Porcelain Rocket &quot;MCA&quot;" /></a>
© Sim Works, used with Permission</p>

<p>You might have seen the custom-made PR Panniers in the past, which where probably what has led to the development of the Micro Panniers. They’re intended as an auxiliary to the other gear systems for more volume on longer tours and allow you to get rid of your Ortlieb panniers and invest into a pair of these. They attach to most popular racks on the market including fatbike-specific racks, and are made from 500D &amp; 1000D Cordura with a weight of 340 g per pannier. You don’t need to wait to get these, either, as they’re available now and cost $250 CAD for a set of two.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/53243955@N05/16350764831" title="Porcelain Rocket &quot;Micro Panniers&quot; by Sim Works, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7349/16350764831_46d48677a9_b.jpg" width="900" height="900" alt="Porcelain Rocket &quot;Micro Panniers&quot;" /></a>
© Sim Works, used with Permission</p>

<h2 id="mountain-laurel-designs">Mountain Laurel Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> has updated the Burn, Prophet, Exodus and Ark. They now come with hybrid solid/ mesh outside pockets which was done after research on the areas where mesh pockets wear or snag in brush - those parts are now solid Dyneema X. Also the side pocket’s front edges are solid and the bottom of the large rear pocket is solid, while the large mesh holes allows faster drying times. The 2015 packs also come with improved hardware and webbing: The 10 mm and 15 mm buckles MLD now uses are twice as strong as the 25/ 30 mm buckles of the past and the narrower webbing is a lot lighter without being thin and fragile. </p>

<p>MLD continues to uses their tried &amp; tested Dyneema X fabric, which has the highest strength and is much better than the weaker Robic fabric and regular ripstop nylons that some other manufacturers use. The reason for cheaper fabrics like Robic is obvious: It’s just $3 a yard - versus $25 a yard for DXG! I imagine you’re a gear freak if your following this blog, so you’ll appreciate this little nugget Ron shared: </p>

<p><em>Interestingly, the white Dyneema ripstop threads that makes the Dyneema X so recognizable and known for the highest quality has lead to some pack makers now using regular nylon woven with a plain white nylon thread ripstop pattern (no Dyneema in the weave at all) to look like it is Dyneema X ripstop!</em></p>

<p>So the next time you’re shopping for a pack, make sure to read the material descriptions well! Right, onwards to the new gear.  MLD has replaced the Newt with a small and ultra clean and simple pack code named Core, and all backpacks will be available in the new Wasabi Green and the signature MLD Stealth Gray colours, with a shipping date of Mid-February.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426661665" title="MLD Corepack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7400/16426661665_d61f16733b_b.jpg" width="720" height="918" alt="MLD Corepack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806623933" title="MLD Wasabi Exodus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/15806623933_065e5e7684_b.jpg" width="720" height="907" alt="MLD Wasabi Exodus" /></a></p>

<p>Also coming from MLD in 2015 is an Apex Balaclavas in three sizes, <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?products_id=222">Cuben Packing Cubes</a> for the lightweight traveller and Size Small eVENT Rain Mitts, while all 2015 Mids now use the stronger 10 mm buckles &amp; the SuperLight bivys use the new Mountain 10d fabric and nicer nickel zip pulls. The Superlight Bivy Duo is already available and additional sizes of the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=47&amp;products_id=127">PyraMid InnerNets</a> are on the website.</p>

<h2 id="nature-base">Nature-Base</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.naturebase.de/">Nature-Base</a> from Germany has several products on offer which are interesting for the ultralight winter backpacker. Their <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/pulka">Folding Pulka</a> has been improved and now can be ordered with a few options like skids, a stiffening rail and a pack sack. It’s a great option for lightweight ski and snow-shoe hikes where you might want to pull your kit instead of carrying it most of the time.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16424876091" title="Nature-Base UL Pulka by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8627/16424876091_61b77fc790_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nature-Base UL Pulka" /></a></p>

<p>Great looking is the EtaProof 110g/m² <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/ul_weste">Vest</a> which tips the scales at 130 g in Size L! The material is windproof and water-resistant which makes it ideal for your skiing adventures on the fjells, while it has a hood that also protects your head. EtaProof is a material with great environmental credentials, and all Nature-Base garments can be fully customized.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238993008" title="Nature-Base UL Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16238993008_43813e7247_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Nature-Base UL Vest" /></a></p>

<h2 id="waldschneider">Waldschneider</h2>

<p><a href="">Waldschneider</a> is a new cottage in stealth mode that will launch in the summer 2015. Based in Germany they have been working since a couple of years on different shelter designs, from Tarps to Pyramids and Inners, as well as bivy bags and bathtub floors. You can check out some of their work here: <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/1643-solo-pyramide/page-2#entry28601">Trollhaus 1</a>, <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/2296-und-noch-ein-lavvu/">Laavu</a> and <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/983-nur-ein-tarp/page-2#entry30186">Sägewerk 2</a>. When they have launched their webshop you’ll hear it here first =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/16078382599" title="014 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8643/16078382599_0970a80c30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="014" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/16263679582" title="010 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7538/16263679582_169cfda566_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="010" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/14463223102" title="001 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2902/14463223102_c7eb32716c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="001" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hyperlite-mountain-gear">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> has a lot of news coming in 2015 - though keeps its card close to their chest. Coming soon is their 100% Woven Dyneema Canyoneering Pack which you might already have spotted on their Social Media outlets. There are also inserts for the Ultamid 2 and Ultamid 4 coming, Chalk Bags for climbing, Throw Bags for packrafting and several other items. Right now <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-of-hyperlite-mountain-gear-two-years-on.html">Mike</a> and his team are working on getting inventory to be built up, so expect some of these items to be available soon!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16400660386" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Canyoneering Pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8619/16400660386_9b7eaf759e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Canyoneering Pack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="packrafting-store">Packrafting Store</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de">Packrafting Store</a> helps in 2015 even more people to enjoy packrafting. They will start to offer some alternative Packrafts in the familiar shape, from a reasonable material (TPU), a good construction, slightly heavier, less varied (= less colors etc.) and <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Packrafts/Nortik-Trekraft-no-deck::598.html">more affordable</a>. There will be also superlight and high performance packrafts available later this spring, but the Classic Alpacka Rafts will remain their prime product. </p>

<p>You’ll also be able to shop for a new paddle from them this year or build your own. There’s four options:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Anfibio Ultimate, a full Carbon Packraft Paddle, 730 g, 5 pieces, fully adjustable (length/angle), stiff and tough at 335€</li>
  <li>Anfibio Smash is the Whitewater Packraft Paddle, 1025 g, 4 pieces, rigid carbon shaft, full size blades, a real “smasher” 209€</li>
  <li>Anfibio Vertex is their well-loved combi paddle (Vertex multi) in a classic version (double blade), fine shaft and very reasonable specs (920 g/ 129€)</li>
  <li>Or make your own webbed paddle with the Shearwater DIY kits. Webbs, rods &amp; clamp shell are provide. Find your shaft (in the garage or in the forest) and follow the instructions (300 g/ 69€)</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425701182" title="Packrafting Store Paddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16425701182_e436981b4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packrafting Store Paddle" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806595653" title="Anfibio Shearwater Paddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8612/15806595653_19b14b066b_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Shearwater Paddle" /></a></p>

<p>The Anfibio Multibag come snow in 60 l and in black, selling for 39€. Also the Anfibio Buoy Boy grows up in Size and now will be available in XL (in black), gets pockets and secured inflation tubes for 89€. The Anfibio Packsuit gets enhanced materials and will be lighter (~100 g per suit), more breathable (25.000 g/m2/24h), softer (better packing) but retains its robustness and price! The fabric also now is Bluesign certificated (environmentally friendly). And as usually each suit can be tailored - That’s cottage style! Also new neoprene gloves, a lightweight whitewater PFD and other accessories as well as courses on the river Soca in Slovenia are coming, and most of this sweet gear will be launched on their 3rd anniversary on February 15th. Check their website then or subscribe to the <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/newsletter.php?language=en">Newsletter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426633735" title="Anfibio Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/16426633735_23a6f0bd9c_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Vest" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16240402769" title="Anfibio Multibag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8668/16240402769_bbd00aea0b_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Multibag" /></a></p>

<h2 id="as-tucas">As Tucas</h2>

<p><a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a> introduces the new schoeller®-ftc fabric with ecorepel® finish this year to their offerings. It’s not just a lighter fabric at 28 g/m2, it is also stronger, more breathable and softer to the skin than any other fabric they have seen so far. Their quilts, insulated &amp; windproof garments are being upgraded to this new fabric, which I find rather exciting. </p>

<p>Their collection of quilts just was expanded with a wearable quilt: the Sestrals 2 Poncho. It features an insulated collar, which they think is more efficient and elegant than the simpler slit designs. Marco expects it will become the cornerstone of those who are looking for a truly versatile sleeping system that also doubles as a insulation garment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806594903" title="As Tucas Sestrals 2 Poncho by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7377/15806594903_e65805e35a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Sestrals 2 Poncho" /></a></p>

<p>As Tucas enters in 2015 the waterproofs market with two new ultralight pants: the Otal Pants made with a 2,5 layer WPB fabric and the Acher Pants made with WPB Cuben fiber. Starting at 120 &amp; 85 grams respectively they are really light but don’t skimp on essential features like an elasticated waist and adjustable cuffs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238993098" title="As Tucas Otal Acher Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/16238993098_f1c454c4e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Otal Acher Pants" /></a></p>

<p>Marco is very busy designing and testing new products, too: The Zilindro 2 collection of base layers made from a new grid fabric by Eschler is almost ready, a Sestrals 2 insulated bivy is under development, and their down quilts are coming soon, too! </p>

<h2 id="tarptent">Tarptent</h2>

<p>Henry has been busy at <a href="http://www.tarptent.com/">Tarptent</a>, redesigning the popular Contrail which is available from February onwards as the ProTrail. It includes all the feedback Tarptent has received over the years since they introduced the Contrail in 2006.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426661605" title="Tarprent Proshelter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8674/16426661605_09c54b282d_o.jpg" width="640" height="360" alt="Tarprent Proshelter" /></a></p>

<p>Here’s a short statement from Henry on Cuben Fibre: <em>We receive our share of requests for cuben fiber products from the die-hards but have opted not to go that route due to the extreme cost. I have always prided myself on producing lightweight shelters that are also affordable and unfortunately cuben just isn’t. I understand that there are people who are willing to pay but if we’re going to do a product it has to pass the “would Henry buy it?” test and at the price of cuben (and the labor involved in hand seam-taping all the seams) the answer is no. I would very much love to move to lighter fabrics but is has to make cost/ benefit sense.</em> So for a Cuben Tarptent to become a reality CubicTech would need to drop their prices, which they as a Monopolist probably aren’t likely to do just yet. </p>

<h2 id="yama-mountain-gear">YAMA Mountain Gear</h2>

<p>Do you like the opener pic at the far top of this article? Because I do. It says freedom and ultralight to me. I think <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/interview-gen-shimizu-from-alpinlite-gear.html">Gen</a> from <a href="http://www.yamamountaingear.com">YAMA Mountain Gear</a> hopefully thinks the same, and maybe it even where some of the ideas he had in mind when he designed the <a href="http://www.yamamountaingear.com/swiftline-2P/">Swiftline Tent</a>, a sub 1 kilo, 2-person, side-entry tent. The versatile new design lets users roll up the walls in nice weather to enjoy bug-free views, while two unobstructed entrances make entry &amp; exit a breeze with a large vestibule that keeps your gear protected and out of the way.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806594923" title="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/15806594923_3267baebdd_o.jpg" width="1200" height="803" alt="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P" /></a></p>

<p>What I also like about YAMA is that they help thru-hikers. In 2015 they welcome five aspiring Pacific Crest Trail thru-hikers to the second year of their <a href="http://mYAMAdventure.com">mYAMAdventure program</a>. The program’s team of mentors is currently helping the 2015 hikers prepare for their upcoming hikes, which will also benefit the Pacific Crest Trail Association. It’s definitely something worth checking out if you plan to hike the PCT!</p>

<h2 id="katabatic-gear">Katabatic Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://katabaticgear.com">Katabatic Gear</a> has released three <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/category/backpacks/">backpacks</a> in 2014 will appeal to both the lightweight and traditional crowds, because they do not sacrifice function, comfort or design while shedding weight from your shoulders. All packs are Made in Colorado, and here’s a quick look at the three packs: </p>

<p>The Artemis is a lightweight, durable pack with 55 l Volume. It’s made from durable 420D nylon fabrics throughout with a Dual Density, Ventilated Framesheet with a removable Aluminum Stay. The ribbed and perforated backpanel provides airflow while the stretch side pockets expand to accommodate loads while keeping pockets low profile when empty. The large zippered front pocket allows for easy access and the stretch woven hipbelt pockets with have an inner key clip. Finally, dual hydration ports ensure you can keep hydrated on the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16400660046" title="Katabatic Gear Artemis 55 Quarter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7336/16400660046_eb5f583b1e_o.jpg" width="475" height="606" alt="Katabatic Gear Artemis 55 Quarter" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/helios-40-backpack/">Helios</a> is similar in design to the Artemis, but focuses more on saving weight. It is made from a lightweight Cuben Fiber laminate which delivers exceptional strength for it’s weight. The woven polyester face fabric gives it additional abrasion resistance and seam strength. The Helios features all of the same design elements as the Artemis, above except that the front pocket is zipper free and uses durable stretch panels. It is currently available in 40 and 55 liter volumes, with the 40 l version tipping the scales at around 850 g in Size Medium.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16424876241" title="Katabatic Gear Helios 55 Quarter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8635/16424876241_4b8ef522a3_o.jpg" width="470" height="594" alt="Katabatic Gear Helios 55 Quarter" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, the Eos is their 30 l lightweight, durable alpine climbing pack. Made from the same durable and water resistant fabric as the Artemis it is designed with climbing and ski-mountaineering in mind. The compression straps allow for carrying skis while the front daisy chain and bungee securely carry ice tools and crampons. The webbing waist belt, compression straps, ice tool bungee, and aluminum stay can be removed when not needed - saving weight when you wanna go really fast &amp; light, but the padded bottom adds durability while carrying a climbing rack. The extension collar expands capacity to 39 l and the zippered inner security pocket with key hook stores your wallet and keys while you’re climbing your Dawn Wall. Finally, major seams are sewn with Dyneema thread for maximum seam strength. Expect this pack to last!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425700432" title="Katabatic Gear Eos 30 Tool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7403/16425700432_3234424f01_o.jpg" width="466" height="554" alt="Katabatic Gear Eos 30 Tool" /></a></p>

<h2 id="yamatomichi">YAMATOMICHI</h2>

<p><a href="http://yamatomichi.com">YAMATOMICHI</a> is also one of the fine Japanese cottages which add style to the ultralight + functionality equation. Right now in the prototyping stage are their YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap, the U.L.Backpack No.3 and their 5-Pockets Long pants. Here’s a couple of photos to get you curious, with the gear coming out in March.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239235120" title="YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7365/16239235120_a5f60764ca_o.jpg" width="640" height="640" alt="YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239235200" title="YAMATOMICHI U.L.Backpack No.3 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7300/16239235200_e90cae49b8_o.jpg" width="640" height="640" alt="YAMATOMICHI U.L.Backpack No.3" /></a></p>

<h2 id="terra-rosa-gear">Terra Rosa Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.terrarosagear.com">Terra Rosa Gear</a> is teaming up with Australian DIY supplier and hammock maker <a href="http://www.tiergear.com.au">Tier Gear</a> for a hammock tarp. It will be available as a package with the Tier Gear hammock shortly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15812036024" title="TRG Tarp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7404/15812036024_7300e9bf2e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="TRG Tarp" /></a></p>

<h2 id="underground-quilts">Underground Quilts</h2>

<p><a href="http://undergroundquilts.com/">Underground Quilts</a> has several new items coming in 2015. Just a month ago they released their <a href="http://undergroundquilts.com/renegade/default.html">RENEGADE TQ</a>. The cold weather quilt uses a combination of vertical and horizontal chambers and can be made with your choice of HyperDRY 800/ 850 fillpower down. The quilt is fully customizable so you can get the quilt of your dreams. Underground Quilts also now offers a 10d fabric option for the inner shell on their top and bottom quilts and 20d fabrics for their our tarps - going lighter!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16429141215" title="RENEGADE TQ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8659/16429141215_4733bfa2f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="RENEGADE TQ" /></a></p>

<h2 id="flat-cat-gear">Flat Cat Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flatcatgear.com">Flat Cat Gear</a> has a new website! Besides that they offer a trio of DIY titanium Stove kits which should be interesting for the MYOG girls and guys out there: </p>

<ul>
  <li>The Epicurean Titanium UL 15 is designed for use with Esbit and will burn up to 50-60 minutes</li>
  <li>The Focus Fire 14 in Titanium is designed to burn Esbit efficiently, one 14 gram tablet can bring 4 cups of 70F water up to 200F</li>
  <li>The new TiLight stove is a tea light replacement stove and weighs 2,84 g</li>
</ul>

<p>They are pre-assembled and you do the final sanding and folding, and cost $10 in the USA and $15 Internationally.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16243283067" title="Flat Cat Gear Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/16243283067_4a53feef8e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="617" alt="Flat Cat Gear Website" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15804132074" title="Flat Cat Gear  Flight by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8584/15804132074_ab3b89bcfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="Flat Cat Gear  Flight" /></a></p>

<h2 id="zpacks">ZPacks</h2>

<p><a href="http://zpacks.com">ZPacks</a> has a few things coming soon, like a synthetic insulated jacket. It will be similar to their <a href="http://zpacks.com/accessories/wind_shell.shtml">wind shell</a> but with Climashield insulation. ZPacks has the insulation in stock and have a prototype which right now is out on the trail, but it needs some work on the patterns. Joe and his team also just got Dyneema X Gridstop fabric in stock and a prototyp Arc Blast and Arc Zip backpacks are being tested right now - expect some photos later this week. Finally Joe is working in a Dyneema pack that can handle 35-40 lbs. There will be some changes to their frame system and more padding on the belt and straps . again, a prototyp is being tested as I write this, so expect some news on it later on. What’s available already since last November is their <a href="http://zpacks.com/shelter/altaplex.shtml">Altaplex shelter</a>. The whole system weighs in at 479 g and is very versatile in use.</p>

<h2 id="warbonnet-outdoors">Warbonnet Outdoors</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.warbonnetoutdoors.com">Warbonnet Outdoors</a> is working on a new Camo pattern specifically designed for larger items like tarps and hopes to have it available later this spring. This should be pretty interesting for the hunters and Bushcrafters out there, so keep your eyes on the Warbonnet website this spring.</p>

<h2 id="more">More</h2>

<p>Cottage Manufacturers are busy people - some are just now out hiking, other’s are finishing up your gear. That’s why not every cottage is on this list. It’s a living document, though, and likely will be updated a couple of times during the next few days while more companies are added. Either check back at the end of the week or follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> where I will announce updates.</p>

<p>And if you liked this article, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> =)</p>

<p><strong>Want more gear news?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> &amp; <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a> for gear reviews and previews!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXI]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxi.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-01T13:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“What you get by achieving your goals is not as important as what you become by achieving your goals.”</em>
- <a href="http://amzn.to/16eP3T3">Henry David Thoreau, Walden</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6925228481" title="Dusk on skis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7054/6925228481_58b4796f9c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Dusk on skis" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://swedishmoments.se">What sort of visitor to Sweden are you</a>?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3025957/work-smart/what-happens-to-our-brains-when-we-exercise-and-how-it-makes-us-happier">This is your brain on exercise</a> (and how hiking makes you happier).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/">Bergfreunde</a> enter <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc&amp;">Round 2 of their Wintersale</a>, with 50% off on garments and equipment.</p>

<p><a href="http://folkstreams.net/film/288">How to Build an Igloo</a>, a mini documentary from 1949. Recommended see.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/hiking-competitions-feb-2015/">February 2015 Online Competitions for Hikers</a>.</p>

<p>Need a customs quilt or hoody? Contact <a href="http://astucas.com/en/custom-works/">As Tucas</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/dynafit/?_artperpage=100&amp;sort=4&amp;utm_source=facebook&amp;utm_medium=cpc&amp;utm_campaign=nl_dynafit?pid=81">60% off on Dynafit equipment and garments</a> at Bergzeit!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/photo-galleries/outdoor-adventure/Take-the-Best-Nighttime-Photo-of-Your-Life.html">Take the Best Nighttime Photo of Your Life</a>.</p>

<p>An <a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2015/01/articulo-entrevista-con-moe-witschard.html">interview with Moe Witschard</a>. [Spanish]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Mikko enjoys his <a href="https://xpeditionlife.wordpress.com/2015/01/25/alpine-apprenticeship-in-chamonix/">Alpine apprenticeship in Chamonix</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/01/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-11.html">Into the Magical Forest</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2015/1/31/cruach-ardrain">Cruach Ardrain</a>.</p>

<p>John reflects <a href="http://overthehillsblog.com/2015/01/28/reflections-on-the-tgoc-2014-in-preparation-for-2015/">on the TGOC 2014, in preparation for 2015</a>.</p>

<p>Roger is <a href="http://www.rogerodoherty.com/2015/01/walking-colorado-trail-julyaug-2014.html">Walking the Colorado Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://seakayakingetc.blogspot.fi/2015/01/exploring-death-valley-national-park.html">Exploring Death Valley National Park</a>.</p>

<p>Guthook went for a wee <a href="http://www.guthookhikes.com/2015/01/cabot-mtn-winter-backpacking-trip-124-2515.html">Cabot Mtn Winter Backpacking Trip</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/116691902?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://talusfield.net/blog/2015/1/10/traversing-the-talkeetna-range">Traversing the Talkeetna Range, Central Alaska</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://therepublicofdoom.blogspot.fi/2015/01/grand-time.html">Grand Time</a> in the Grand Canyon.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/ecuador/quilatoa-loop-ecuador-a-family-ride">Quilatoa Loop, Ecuador; a family bicycle ride</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://atkypne.blogspot.fi/2015/01/bowfell-via-climbers-traverse.html">Bowfell via the climbers traverse</a>, a nice winter advenure in the Lakes.</p>

<p>Angelica goes out for a snowshoe hike at the <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/01/31/schneeschuhtour-am-weissen-stein-eifel/">Weißen Stein</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://niksbikingblog.blogspot.fi/2015/01/ardnamurchan-northern-route-here-are.html">Ardnamurchan Northern Route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15641750204" title="Entre Nord by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8582/15641750204_e7780aeeee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Entre Nord" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">Winter Layering Guide</a>.</p>

<p>Great post from Chris Townsend: <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2015/01/pacific-crest-trail-gear-in-1982-and.html">Pacific Crest Trail Gear in 1982 - and what I’d take now</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://onehundredmountains.blogspot.fi/2015/01/was-walter-weston-gear-freak.html">Was Walter Weston a gear freak</a>?</p>

<p>Stefanie reviews a <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/test-daunenjacke-x-light-decathlon/">cheap down jacket from Decathlon</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2015/ultimate-direction-pb-hydration-vest/">Ultimate Direction Peter Bakwin Adventure Vest (2.0)</a> Review.</p>

<p><a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/osprey-kestrel-38-test-review/">Osprey Kestrel 38</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Top of the World - Herausforderung 8000er]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/on-top-of-the-world-herausforderung-8000er.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-30T14:56:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/on-top-of-the-world-herausforderung-8000er</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you like to know more about the history of the highest peaks on this planet, then <em>On Top of the World. The New Millennium</em> as <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/list?back=9db5a3e1b607eeefc414b4266862f7c2&amp;xid=11345923">Herausforderung 8000er</a> is called in English, should be on your bookshelf. Packed with detailed information and chronics from the first ascents to the newest route attempts, Herausforderung 8000er is required reading if you want to climb one of the highest mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16213778198" title="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7355/16213778198_ccd2dbe9e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="765" alt="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>After reading <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters.html">8000 Metres</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html">Alpine Exposures</a> Herausforderung 8000er from the <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/">Tyrolia Verlag</a> is the third book in the mountaineering corner on my bookshelf which is about the highest of peaks. Besides detailed topographic photos and lists of the first ascents on the different routes it are the captivating stories from the ascents and expeditions which are worth getting this book. </p>

<p>The book has 17 chapter - after an introduction each 8.000 m peak has its own chapter where stories about the first ascents, the different expeditions, tragic accidents and solo ascents are given, with lists on the first ascents on the many routes on the peaks. It gets interesting in the “The New Millennium” sections, where stories about more current ascents are told. So the book goes from Annapurna to Shisha Pangma and then finishes with an outlook on the next decade and all relevant statistics.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16399669221" title="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/16399669221_1d67e65f4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="796" alt="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World" /></a></p>

<p>Not just the stories are captivating, also the superb photos from the mountains &amp; expeditions will let you forget the time when you’re reading this book. It highlights how some 8.000 m mountains nowadays can be attempted by normal people while at the same time alpinists on the cutting edge still find new routes up these same peaks. If you dream about standing on the top of the world on one of these mountains, then you should get Herausforderung 8000er - <em>On Top of the World. The New Millennium</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/leseproben/9783702232948/leseprobe.pdf">View the sample</a> and then get the book in German directly from <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/list?back=9db5a3e1b607eeefc414b4266862f7c2&amp;xid=11345923">Tyrolia</a>, your local bookshop or <a href="http://amzn.to/1uIeFNA">Amazon.de</a> or buy the English Edition at <a href="http://amzn.to/1uIf6ay">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1CiQkpf">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reader Survey]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/reader-survey.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-26T11:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/reader-survey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first HiF Reader Survey lets you decide how to improve Hiking in Finland in the future!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9370758910" title="Thoughts, high as mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5530/9370758910_76bc9d7fb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Thoughts, high as mountains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-goal">The Goal</h2>

<p>Hiking in Finland will be six years old this year and it has been going from strength to strength. It is the most-read outdoor blog in Scandinavia and loved for its <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/destinations/">trip reports</a>, detailed <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">gear reviews</a>, interesting <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/interviews/">interviews</a> and the classic <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">TWIR</a> which brings you the best finds from the digital outdoors.</p>

<p>But standing still and resting on my laurels is something I have never been good at. I switched to a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/07/welcome-to-the-new-hikinginfinland-dot-com.html">new platform</a> almost three years ago, have created new <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mountain-people/">content</a> <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gear-outtakes/">ideas</a>, have been working on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/writing/">writing</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/photography/">photography</a>, looking over the borders for inspiration so that I can continue to entertain you with interesting and varied outdoor content from the north and elsewhere. Best of all, Hiking in Finland is probably the only outdoor blog that’s also a proud <a href="https://onepercentfortheplanet.org/">One Percent for the Planet</a> member since 2012 and helps protect the outdoors we enjoy so much.</p>

<p>To further enhance the experience of Hiking in Finland for you, I’d love to know what topics, categories and posts you are most interested in. Tell me via the underneath questionnaire if I’m still on the right trail, where my navigation is off, and what else you’d like to see. Your time and effort shall not go unrewarded, either. </p>

<h2 id="the-prizes">The Prizes</h2>

<p>Of course I am very thankful that you complete my questionnaire, and that’s why you have the chance to win a few nice prizes for your time and effort. If you’d like to be entered into the raffle you just need to enter a valid email address at the end of the questionnaire before you push <em>Submit</em> and you’ll be entered into the raffle to win one of these prizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A <a href="http://www.haglofs.com">Haglöfs</a> Type 16 backpack &amp; Twice Beanie</li>
  <li>A one year subscription to <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com">trekking Magazin</a></li>
  <li>2 x 50€ Gift Card from <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk</a></li>
  <li>4 x 25€ Gift Cards from <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/?refID=hif">trekking-lite-store.com</a></li>
  <li>2 x 25€ Gift Card from <a href="http://bit.ly/1yc4iWV">Bergfreunde.de</a></li>
  <li>A <a href="http://nikwax.co.uk/en-us/productselector/cleaning.php">Nikwax Hardshell DuoPack</a></li>
</ul>

<p><em>Your answers have Zero influence on winning so be honest!</em></p>

<h2 id="the-questionnaire">The Questionnaire</h2>

<p>You can access the Questionnaire here if you read Hiking in Finland via a RSS Reader or just answer the questions via the underneath embedded form. It is built with Typeform which lets you use your Keyboard and/ or Trackpad to answer and also works great on tablets and phones. The survey is open till midnight 1st of February so you got almost a week to answer.</p>

<p><strong>Thanks for answering the survey. It closed now and winners will be contacted via Email shortly.</strong></p>

<p><br /><strong>If you like to read more news and trip reports</strong> please follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, and <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> where I often post current photos and stuff which don’t make it to the blog. And to not miss any future articles you should subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/the-week-in-review-clxxxx.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-25T19:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/the-week-in-review-clxxxx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Winter is coming.”</em> 
― George R.R. Martin, <a href="http://amzn.to/15G4nI6">A Game of Thrones</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/bmp_creep/8187022731" title="Khufu Sil Aspen Gold - Locus Gear by Hikesinatra aka creep, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8350/8187022731_6056a68b12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="537" alt="Khufu Sil Aspen Gold - Locus Gear" /></a>
© <a href="https://twitter.com/bmp">HikeSinatra</a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.andy-kirkpatrick.com/blog/view/the_extraordinary_nobody">The extraordinary nobody</a>.</p>

<p>Win a spot on the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/outdoor-research-freetouring/?pid=81">Outdoor Research Alpine Camp</a> with Bergzeit!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/">Outdoorline.sk</a> has free world-wide shipping on all Westcomb hardshell jackets! </p>

<p>Pre-order Dave MacLeod’s latest climbing injury book, <a href="http://davemacleod.com/shop/makeorbreak.html">Make or Break</a>.</p>

<p>Steven celebrates a <a href="http://stevenhorner.com/blog/2015/01/19/kittys-wood-prow-success/">Kitty’s Wood PRoW Success</a>.</p>

<p>Alex shares some <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/01/illustrations-from-after-alpine-golden.html">Illustrations from after the Alpine golden age</a>.</p>

<p>Vheck out the <a href="http://docs.hilleberg.net/Hilleberg2015Handbook-EN.pdf">2015 Hilleberg Tent Handbook</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/travel/2015/jan/20/best-climbing-areas-europe-improving-skills-el-capitan">The best climbing areas in Europe – for improving your skills</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A look at the <a href="http://cbjimtrip.blogspot.fi/2015/01/and-wander-20l-daypack.html">and wander 20L daypack</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/gear-outtakes-autumn-2014.html">Gear Outtakes Fall 2014</a>.</p>

<p>Running Hawaii’s Na Pali Coast: <a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.fi/2015/01/running-hawaiis-na-pali-coast-kalalau.html">The Kalalau Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Dennis tests the <a href="http://www.outdoor-blog.com/berghaus-mens-ulvetanna-hybrid-hydrodown-jacket/">Berghaus Ulvetanna Hybrid Hydrodown Jacket</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://ulning.dk/la-sportiva-crossover-punk-gtx/">La Sportiva Crossover GTX</a> reviewed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077617107" title="Looking back towards Slåttdalsskrevan, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/16077617107_32af27ea6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Looking back towards Slåttdalsskrevan, Skuleberget National Park" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://riversanddeserts.com/en/back-to-the-beach-and-fast/">Back to the beach and fast</a>!</p>

<p>Jon &amp; Ally head up the <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/blogs/chamonix-conditions/16608085-desmaison-gousseault-grandes-jorasses">Desmaison Gousseault Grandes Jorasses</a>.</p>

<p>Al &amp; friends visit <a href="http://alsoutdoorworld.blogspot.fi/2015/01/pike-oblisco.html">Pike O’Blisco</a> in the snow.</p>

<p><a href="http://cedricbernardini.com/2015/01/19/dicks-pussies-and-blasphemy/">Dicks, pussies and blasphemy</a>.</p>

<p>Running Hawaii’s Na Pali Coast: <a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.fi/2015/01/running-hawaiis-na-pali-coast-kalalau.html">The Kalalau Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Gerlad climbs <a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/ueber-das-brunntal-und-die-suedliche-turmscharte-iii-auf-den-turm-ca-1620m/">the tower</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Emily celebrates a <a href="http://emilyroolearnstorun.blogspot.fi/2015/01/solstice-party-with-spot-of-cosmiques.html">Solstice Party with a spot of Cosmiques Icefall Climbing</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://pantilat.wordpress.com/2015/01/20/marble-peak-50k/">Marble Peak 50k+</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/113889338?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>To the <a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/01/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-10.html">Rara Lake</a> in the land of the unnamed mountains, re commended read. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://fuusora.blogspot.fi/2015/01/fasthike-3days.html">伊豆FastHikeの旅 3DAYS</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Guillermo, Ross &amp; jon backpack <a href="https://guillermobarron.wordpress.com/2014/08/21/the-great-divide-trail-150-km-from-shark-mtn-to-highway-1/">The Great Divide Trail: 150 km from Shark Mtn. to Highway 1</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://outdoorsmh.blogspot.fi/2015/01/bowfell-climbers-traverse.html">Bowfell Climbers Traverse</a>.</p>

<p>Roger has some unexpected occurrences along the way from <a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/2015/01/24/e6-svendborg-to-sonderborg-and-the-unexpected-occurrences-along-the-way/">Svendborg to Sønderborg</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.haukkari.net/2015/01/weekend-warrior-in-austria.html">Weekend warrior in Austria</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/?p=1550">Winter camping in the Greater Yellowstone</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2015/01/rode-trip-stub-stewart-gravel-getaway/">Stub Stewart Gravel Getaway</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear Outtakes - Autumn 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/gear-outtakes-autumn-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-23T22:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/gear-outtakes-autumn-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bite-sized gear reviews, autumn/ fall edition.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15727425573" title="Gear Outtakes Autumn 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7480/15727425573_37e0828110_b.jpg" width="1024" height="714" alt="Gear Outtakes Autumn 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/09/gear-outtakes-summer-2014.html">Gear Outtakes</a> is a seasonal collection of kit and what I think about it.</p>

<p>★☆☆☆
Mediocre, I wouldn’t spend money on it.</p>

<p>★★☆☆
Good, but there are better options.</p>

<p>★★★☆
Great, worth your money.</p>

<p>★★★★
Outstanding, the benchmark of its category.</p>

<p>DISCLAIMER
<br />Some of these products have been sent to me for free by the manufacturer.</p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research-enchainment-jacket">Outdoor Research Enchainment Jacket</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16160009740" title="Outdoor Research Enchainment Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7571/16160009740_145511886d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="752" alt="Outdoor Research Enchainment Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />215€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1r4PNzZ">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-research-enchainment-jacket-softshelljacke/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1upmZkY">REI.com</a> and <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/mens/jackets/mens-enchainment-jacket.html">Outdoor Research</a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/mens/jackets/mens-enchainment-jacket.html">Enchainment Jacket</a> has been my jacket of choice on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/koli-national-park.html">UL Summit 2013</a> and many hikes before and after. It’s a very water-resistant softshell that can withstand the abuse of carrying a backpack, scrambling up hills and bushwhacking through dense undergrowth. Schoeller NanoSphere panels on the sides add breathability &amp; freedom of movement while the softshell fabric that’s used in the sleeves and torso keep the wind &amp; rain outside and me toasty on the inside - but not too hot &amp; neither too cold. The pockets are a tad small to take in a standard map but carry gloves &amp; beanie without problems while the triple adjustable hood ensure clear views also in a downpour. / 469 g in Size S. </p>

<h2 id="jung-emil-pants">JUNG emil pants</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16321423546" title="JUNG emil pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7466/16321423546_af7526b321_b.jpg" width="885" height="1024" alt="JUNG emil pants" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />105€, available at <a href="http://www.jung-ware.de/produkte/herren/hosen/306/emil-gruen?c=5">JUNG</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/jung-emil-bio-boulderhose/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/jung-emil-kletterhose-gruen-m/">Bergzeit</a></p>

<p>And the prize of the comfiest climbing pants of 2014 goes to: <a href="http://www.jung-ware.de/">JUNG</a>! The emil from JUNG is not just super comfortable and stylish, nope, it is Designed in Cologne, sewn in Poland from <em>Global Organic Textile Standard</em> certified organic cotton and comes in very limited runs. I love the stretchy waistband which is so comfortable you might think you’re naked, it’s a revelation. The deep pockets securely hold everyday items in them while the adjustable trouser legs are ideal for climbing and bouldering. This was the only pants I wore on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/petzl-roctrip-2014-turkey.html">Petzl RocTrip</a> and despite six intense days of climbing &amp; travelling it still looked the deal for the last Party on Saturday night. JUNG designs some super nice <a href="http://www.jung-ware.de/produkte/damen/hosen/">climbing trousers for women</a> and <a href="http://www.jung-ware.de/produkte/herren/hosen/">men</a>, so if you’re in the market for one - check them out! / 413 g in Size XS.</p>

<h2 id="adidas-terrex-solo">adidas Terrex Solo</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16321427016" title="adidas Terrex Solo Stealth approach 395 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7546/16321427016_ae0bc5cf5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="adidas Terrex Solo Stealth approach 395" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />130€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1wsd91v">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/adidas-black-uk6-5/">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/adidas-terrex-solo-approachschuhe/">Bergfreunde.de</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1zDfoq6">CampSaver.com</a></p>

<p>At 802 g for the adidas Terrex Solo pair in Size 41 1/3 the shoes are reasonably light. What makes this shoe special for me is the Stealth Rubber sole, which is the same rubber Five Ten uses in their climbing shoes. And as this is an approach shoe it makes sense that this shoe has such a grippy sole, because it means you can leave your climbing shoes longer in your pack. And if you’re out for Via Ferratas you’ll love these shoes, too - they give you grip on metal ladders and dry &amp; wet rocks alike. I wore these shoes on the Petzl RocTrip and my three week climbing road trip in Finland and look forward to using them again when the snow is gone. My only concern is the durabilty - because of the super-sticky sole the rubber is already starting to leave in the toe area, and I am curious to see how long they will last.</p>

<h2 id="primus-lite">Primus Lite+</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16347372575" title="Primus Lite+ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8585/16347372575_cee03e283f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Lite+" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />130€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1EBsC5M">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/primus-eta-lite-gas-stove/">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-eta-lite-sturmkocher/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1zDdkON">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1CJVdEs">REI.com</a></p>

<p>The Primus Lite+ was our stove of choice on the High Coast Trail in Sweden. It boiled up to 600 ml of water in less than five minutes and was efficient in gas use. A 100 g cartridge fits inside which makes this a very compact and light system indeed: It is 399 g for pot with sleeve &amp; lid and the stove. The stove has a piezo ignition which means you don’t need to bring a firesteel or lighter along, and the new connection between pot and stove is easy and efficient. The sleeve ensure you can hold the pot with boiling water without problems, and you can put the handle over the top and then hang the whole set. And if you’re wondering, because of ™ issues Primus has renamed the EtaLite to Lite+ in 2015. <strong>Expect a more detailed review &amp; video about the Lite+ later this year.</strong></p>

<h2 id="foldacup">Foldacup</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16161501017" title="Foldacup by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/16161501017_a7b16dd596_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Foldacup" /></a></p>

<p>★★☆☆
<br />3€, available at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/wildo-fold-a-cup-falttasse/">Bergfreunde.de</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/15l2nE5">CampSaver.com</a>.</p>

<p>A 25 g cup that packs small - that’s the Foldacup. I found mine on the trail two years ago and have been increasingly taking this one along instead of my Kuksa. The big plus for me is that it packs smaller and is lighter but just as easy to use for scooping water and drinking. It’s orange two - which makes it easier to find in my pack =)</p>

<h2 id="swiss-advance-crono-pocket-knife-tool">Swiss Advance Crono Pocket Knife Tool</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16321439846" title="Swiss Advance Crono Pocket Knife Tool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7529/16321439846_762fb10e11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swiss Advance Crono Pocket Knife Tool" /></a></p>

<p>★★☆☆
<br />45€, available at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/swiss-advance-taschenmesser/">Bergfreunde.de</a> and <a href="http://www.swiss-advance.com/produkt/pocket-knife?lang=en">Swiss Advance</a></p>

<p>The Swiss Advance Crono Pocket Knife Tool is so light and small that I forgot to take it out of my backpack when flying from Zürich home to Helsinki. The big surprise was that the Swiss security people had no problem with me taking this little Multittol inside of the plane - their only concern was that the bottle opener might not be durable enough, something that I can dismiss after opening plenty of beers with it. This little tool packs thirteen other tools, from a handy knife to a screw driver and awl. It’s a nifty little gadget but if you just need a knife then there are lighter options available. / 38 g</p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research-womens-helium-ii-jacket">Outdoor Research Women’s Helium II Jacket</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16161207239" title="Outdoor Research Women&#x27;s Helium II Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/16161207239_024b200afa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="786" alt="Outdoor Research Women&#x27;s Helium II Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />160€ , available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1zCmcV1">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-research-helium-ii-jacket-hardshelljacke/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1yXVmHc">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1CrpuK6">REI.com</a> and <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/womens/jackets/womens-helium-ii-jacket.html">Outdoor Research</a></p>

<p>This very lightweight jacket packs small in its own chest pocket when not needed and weighs a scant 159 g in Size M. It is waterproof though after an hour in heavy rain it leaked a bit, but for a spring or summer shower that shouldn’t be a problem at all. And it works as a great windjacket, too. My wife really liked the stylish look with the coloured zippers making it stand out, and it was simple in use but doesn’t lack anything - the sleeves that are tight from the wrists with no adjustments needed. It’s a womanly fit that’s not too loose but you can fit two layers comfortably under it (probably even three if the third one is a top). </p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research-womens-flyway-zip-hoody">Outdoor Research Women’s Flyway Zip Hoody</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15724959794" title="Outdoor Research Women&#x27;s Flyway Zip Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/15724959794_6e6d641421_b.jpg" width="1024" height="849" alt="Outdoor Research Women&#x27;s Flyway Zip Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />80€ , available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1AXPmJm">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/outdoor-research-flyway-w-039-s-tank-orchid/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-research-womens-flyway-tank-top/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, and <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/catalog/product/view/id/41026/category/4472/">Outdoor Research</a></p>

<p>The Women’s Flyway Zip Hoody is a versatile shirt that you can use for many different sports and also wear it in the city because of the neutral &amp; stylish look with the feminine fit. The fabric is neither too thick or too thin and feels smooth and light on the skin which makes it comfortable to wear. With 202 g in Size M it is light enough to use as a protector from the sun or as a layer, has a good breathability and it dries quickly. The hood and the long chest zipper help with venting while the thumbloops add a bit of warmth when its coller than expected. The small pocket stores keys, wallet and phone or a couple ot snacks when out running.</p>

<h2 id="patagonia-polarized-tee">Patagonia Polarized Tee</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16161485307" title="Patagonia Polarized Tee by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7521/16161485307_92e8164650_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Polarized Tee" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />50€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1ClOhz6">Patagonia</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/patagonia-polarized-graphic-boys-t-shirt-green-green-brg-1/">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-boys-polarized-graphic-tee-t-shirt/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1GHzTpj">Backcountry.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1upntHX">CampSaver.com</a></p>

<p>I bought the Patagonia Polarized Tee at the start of spring 2014 because I wanted a shirt that can be worn in the water (for packrafting and DWS) and on land, with a good UPF protection. The Polarized Tee fitted the bill, came in one of my current favoutite <em>colours</em> and also had a nice print on it (my son loves the print, too)! I can wear it for several days before it starts to develop a bit of a smell, then it just goes to the washing machine and is ready for another adventure. It ain’t as light as other <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts.html">hiking shirts</a> at 159 g in Size S, but it’s still light enough to not bother me. </p>

<h2 id="bern-brentwood-helmet">Bern Brentwood Helmet</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15727418333" title="Bern Brentwood Helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7473/15727418333_82d6b9f673_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bern Brentwood Helmet" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />80€, available at <a href="http://pelagobicycles.com/accessories/helmets/bern-brentwood.html">Pelago Bicycles</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1EAujQS">Backcountry.com</a></p>

<p>Wear a helmet, they say. But only a <a href="http://bernunlimited.com/shop/bike/men/brentwood-451.html">Bern Brentwood</a>, I say. Because if you already are bullied by the car industry in wearing this accessory, let it at least look cool. And with the visor it not just looks cool, it also keeps the sun and rain out of your eyes. The eleven ventilation openings ensure that I don’t overheat with the Brentwood on my skull, and in winter you even can add some warmer linings. And of course you can look down on the non-helmet wearing cyclists when you stop next to them at the stop light and get plus points when the police stops you for speeding. / 428 g in Size L </p>

<h2 id="knog-boomer-usb-front--back">Knog Boomer USB Front &amp; Back</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15727436273" title="Knog Boomer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/15727436273_ae3478c1a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Knog Boomer" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />37€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/1ClFnBQ">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1xJdD52">Amazon.com</a></p>

<p>I have the impression that this autumn there was an increase of cyclists who have figured out that having front &amp; rear lights on your bike is a smart thing in traffic. Of course there are still the un-illuminated Ninjas who cycle in black garments and without lights through the eternal darkness of November, but it’s survival of the illuminated ones, you see. Since four years the Knog Boomer USB is on my handlebar and seatpost, but it’s equally easy to attach to a pram. The lights are bright - the white front Boomer subjectively is seen from a couple of hundred meters away, and in Blink mode in winter it is good to go for five days until it needs to go back to a USB port to be powered up again. The red one keeps the traffic from behind aware of you, which makes these my favourite bike lights for urban cycling and cycle-touring on roads. / 85 g for front &amp; rear light </p>

<h2 id="knog-ringmaster-12--lock-combo">Knog Ringmaster 1.2 &amp; Lock Combo</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16159798268" title="Knog Ringmaster 1.2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/16159798268_21d1cec74d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Knog Ringmaster 1.2" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />$31, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/1AYtH3O">Amazon.com</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1y7SXCA">Amazon.co.uk</a></p>

<p>Lock your bike, they say. Done, I say. With the <a href="http://euro.knog.com.au/bike/locks/cable-locks/ringmaster-1-2.html">Knog Ringmaster 1.2</a> &amp; Lock Combo my bikes have been safely connected to lamp posts, bicycle stands and other immovable objects since four years, and yet one has to been stolen. Sure, the safest way to secure your bike would be with a U-lock <em>AND</em> a Cable lock, which I’d do if I’d need to park my bike in Amsterdam and other cities were bicycle thieves are on the loose, but right now, here in Finland, the Ringmaster and Lock Combo has been plenty of security. The Ringmaster allows me to secure both wheels and frame to a immovable object, which is enough to scare off the opportunistic bicycle thief in this country. / 601 g for cable &amp; lock</p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research-lumen-liner-gloves">Outdoor Research Lumen Liner Gloves</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16347387085" title="Outdoor Research Lumen Liner Gloves by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8669/16347387085_2d4ec3d038_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Lumen Liner Gloves" /></a></p>

<p>★★☆☆
<br />30€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1yWVabd">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-research-biosensor-liners-handschuhe/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1yRNDXP">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/mens/gloves/mens-biosensor-liners.html">Outdoor Research</a></p>

<p>The Lumen Liner Gloves are super-thin Merino wool gloves and you really shouldn’t do any hard work with them. Because they’re sensitive. And will break. I found them even too sensitive to cycle or walk with a pram, which means mine went broken at the finger tips. I still used them on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">Högakustenleden</a> last November where they were fine on the warmer days and when I needed dexterity and a bit of warmth, but they slowly are start to fall apart. It’s a shame as they’re warm and light. They’re no longer available, so you might want to look for the <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/mens/gloves/mens-biosensor-liners.html">Biosensor Liners</a> if you need liner gloves. / 24 g for the pair in Size M.</p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research-lodestar-gloves">Outdoor Research Lodestar Gloves</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16160113870" title="Outdoor Research Lodestar Gloves by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8635/16160113870_7f371258fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Lodestar Gloves" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />80€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1AXORz8">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-research-lodestar-gloves-handschuhe/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1nDE32A">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/mens/gloves/lodestar-gloves.html">Outdoor Research</a></p>

<p>I picked up a pair of Lodestar Gloves at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/ispo-news-2014.html">ISPO 2014</a> and have had them along ice climbing in Korouoma, Höstvesi and Abisko, mountaineering in Chamonix and was skiing with them just last week. They’ve seen also a fair bit of hiking and cycling here, and every time again I was happy to have such warm gloves along. They have a Polartec Power Shield High Loft filling which keeps my fingers toasty warm, while the leather palm ensure good grip on ice tools, ropes &amp; belay device and the handlebar of my bike. When out ice climbing these are my dedicated belay gloves as they’re warm, have a lot of grip and allow for dexterity - an important thing when you are belaying your mate or rappelling. / 120 g for the pair in Size M.</p>

<h2 id="woolpower-tube-lite--beanie-lite">Woolpower Tube LITE &amp; Beanie LITE</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16159783088" title="Woolpower Tube LITE &amp; Beanie LITE by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7485/16159783088_07cb32b57c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Woolpower Tube LITE &amp; Beanie LITE" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />Beanie 40€/ Tube 25€, available at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/woolpower-beanie-lite-muetze/">Bergfreunde.de</a> and <a href="http://shop.woolpower.se/c/lite-tunna-underst%E4ll">Woolpower</a></p>

<p>Also two pieces of kit I was given at the ISPO last year and who have seen regular use since. Beanie and Tube are both made from 80% Merino wool and 20% Polyamide which makes them soft and durable. The Beanie fits well under my Bern Helmet and various jacket hoods and is functional &amp; cool at the same time, definitely a garment you can wear in winter to the office - same goes for the tube. The Flatlock seam  in green on the Tube is a nice detail and does not bother. I have worn both garments in all seasons last year, from spring till winter, and loved them - one of these <em>Pack them &amp; Forget them</em> items. / Tube 44 g, Beanie 42 g </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Ulrika Rogeman, Product Designer at Hilleberg the Tentmaker]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/mountain-people-ulrika-rogeman.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-21T18:30:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/mountain-people-ulrika-rogeman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Where would you want to work if you love the outdoors and have studied design? If you live in Sweden and also like shelters then <a href="http://hilleberg.se">Hilleberg the Tentmaker</a> would be a good call. That’s also what Ulrika Rogeman thought - and now works as a Product Designer at Hilleberg. She is also the designer of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html">Hilleberg Enan</a>, the lightest Hilleberg tent yet! <em>Read this <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mountain-people/">Mountain People Interview</a> to find out about what goes into designing an ultralight tent that can carries the Hilleberg name!</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16323243841" title="Hilleberg Enan Magnus Brogren Jämtland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7506/16323243841_0e412a686a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hilleberg Enan Magnus Brogren Jämtland" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hej Ulrika, thanks for taking the time to answer my questions. Could you please introduce yourself briefly, so we have an idea what’s your 
background?</strong></p>

<p>My name is Ulrika Rogeman and I am 30 years old. I have been working at Hilleberg with Product Design for three years. Since September my responsibilities has extended to include Material Development as well. I came straight from University when I started at Hilleberg. I have a degree in Mechanical Engineering, but my education did focus on product development as well - and especially development of outdoor products. So the job at Hilleberg is exactly what I studied to work with! </p>

<p>I have always been an outdoor person and I enjoy any activity that takes me to the mountains. The last years there has been a lot of trailrunning, biking and ski mountaineering in my life. It is extra fun to develop a lightweight tent like Enan when I really can see myself use it when for example I go running in the mountains. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16332748675" title="Ulrika Rogeman by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8587/16332748675_acce85f67d_o.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Ulrika Rogeman" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor</a> and you showed me the new <a href="http://hilleberg.se/news/enan-new-2015">Hilleberg Enan</a> - your design! How was the idea born to create the Enan, as Hilleberg has two tents - the Anjan and Akto - which potentially could suit the space the Enan now takes?</strong></p>

<p>The plan to make a one person 3-season tent (at Hilleberg we call the 3-season tents <em>Yellow Label</em>) started when we made Anjan and Rogen, the other Hilleberg Yellow Label models. We definitely believe that there is room for a 1,1 kg Hilleberg tent between Anjan and Akto, for those who really need to prioritize weight but still want the security and quality that a Hilleberg tent offers. </p>

<p><strong>You told me the Enan is based on the footprint of the Akto and also uses some design features of this tent. Would it be correct to think that the Enan has been designed for Akto enthusiasts which want a 3-Season tent?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, definitely! Although Enan is not just an Akto with lighter materials. Once you start to use Enan you will see that there are several design details that are different in order to make the tent lighter. All these details have been thought through carefully so that we have a light tent but still a tent that is true to the other Hilleberg principles: Reliability, Adaptability, Ease of Use, Durability and Comfort.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16137655470" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7548/16137655470_69b8386b54_b.jpg" width="1024" height="592" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a></p>

<p><strong>How long have you been working on the Enan - from the idea was born till the final production model?</strong></p>

<p>About two years. First I made initial sketches of interesting designs, then sketches were transformed into 1-to-1 scale cord-skeletons just to get a feeling of the design and its behaviour. Then I made patterns and sew prototypes for the most interesting designs. These were tested out in the nature, but I also tested them in our wind machine, which actually is a snow cannon. At the same time as I was testing the design there were several different materials tested in the tent in order to find the best combination between low weight and strength. For example we tested using poles with a smaller diameter, but realized that in strong wind these poles did not have the strength that we looked for so instead we use the same strong 9 mm pole that we have in Akto. </p>

<p>When I finally found a design that matched both low weight and strength it was time to work with the details. One example is that I have tried to use the tent in rainstorm by adding water to the wind machine. It is the result of that test that the shutters that can cover the short ends were developed. In most weather they are absolutely unnecessary and it is much better to go with full ventilation. But when the rain is close to horizontal they will give you the extra security to prevent your outdoor adventure from turning into a nasty, unsafe experience. </p>

<p>When the tent was almost as perfect as we want it to be, it was time to send it out with people that are not working at Hilleberg to get their opinion of the tent. In total Enan has been outdoors more than 140 nights before we introduced the tent.</p>

<p><strong>Have you looked at other tent designs while designing the Enan? As it has some similarities with the <a href="http://www.tarptent.com/moment.html">Tarptent Moment</a> - would you say that’s coincidence and just shows that a good design can be conceived on opposite places of the world (like the Pyramids, which have been built by the Mayans and Egyptians)?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, I have looked at other tents, as a product developer you have to be aware of other products, maybe not because of the design, more in order to know the weight and price of the products that are in the same product range. But honestly, there are quite a few lightweight tents that resemble each other. I believe that Enan has more in common with Hilleberg’s own Akto rather than any model from another brand. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16332748705" title="Enan on Mallorca by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8595/16332748705_4f450e1fa2_o.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Enan on Mallorca" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Hilleberg also has for the first time created a tent that’s very close to the 1 kg packed weight limit, while keeping the Hilleberg principles of strength and durability. You’re using the new Kerlon 600 fabric as a shell for this tent, how did you set the specifics for this material?</strong></p>

<p>Ones again we have to go back to the Hilleberg principles. A low weight will always mean that we have to compromise with the other principles, but we are only willing to take the compromise to a certain limit. The initial specifications were set from the long experience of tent making that we have at Hilleberg. From these initial specifications different material designs were tested at the Mid Sweden University Textile Laboratory that we have access to. As I mentioned before, different fabrics were also tested in the different tent designs. Eventually we felt that Kerlon 600 was the fabric that matched our demands the best. It is also Kerlon 600 that has been used during the more than 140 nights that Enan has been out. Throughout all these tests we have been able to verify that the initial specification match what we need the fabric to perform.  </p>

<p><strong>What are other design details of the Enan you are really proud of?</strong></p>

<p>I am mostly proud of how simple the tent is, the tent design talks for itself and you do not have to be an engineer to use it correctly. Simplicity in combination with high quality gives a thought through product. It takes a lot of work and thinking to find out how a product can be simplified but still be a high quality product. It is the things that are removed that I am most proud of. </p>

<p><strong>You said the Enan fits two persons in a pinch - you have used it with your partner in Lapland, if I recall correctly - so do you think we’ll  see Adventure Racers use your tents in the future, or is Hilleberg maybe even sponsoring some Adventure Racing teams with the Enan?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, or well I have used it when me and my partner have been out running in the mountains of Jämtland, the region where the Hilleberg office is located. One time when we were out the weather was really bad and we were soaking wet when we stopped running and pitched the tent. But to hang out, two persons, in the tent the rest of the evening was really not a problem. Although I suggest that you know each other quite well! </p>

<p>I absolutely believe that Enan will be used in adventure races. Actually we have already lent out the tent during some competitions. For example our Hilleberg friend <a href="http://hilleberg.se/christine-hägglund">Christine Hägglund</a> used it with her teammate during the mountain orienteering race <a href="http://www.bamm.nu">BAMM</a> that takes place in the far north of Sweden. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16306801456" title="Pesonaltur 2014, Photographer: Magnus Brogren by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7492/16306801456_f9def5f54a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pesonaltur 2014, Photographer: Magnus Brogren" /></a></p>

<p><strong>The Enan will be available in 2015 to consumers - do you think it will be popular?</strong></p>

<p>I hope so! Or to be more specific, I hope that people that really need a low weight tent likes Enan. I think that if you want comfort and a long lasting tent you should look for one of our <a href="http://hilleberg.se/product/saivo">Black Label</a> models.  </p>

<p><strong>Ulrika, I thank you for taking the time for answering my questions! Any closing words?</strong></p>

<p>Go out and enjoy the mountains, fjells and wilderness!</p>

<p><em>Don’t miss future Mountain People Interviews and other posts and follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing: Mountain People Interviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/introducing-mountain-people-interviews.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-20T10:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/introducing-mountain-people-interviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new year and a new interview series on the most-read Scandinavian Outdoor Blog: Introducing the Mountain People Interviews Series.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14710726426" title="Rope Team Tacul by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2913/14710726426_e6150f2ff3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rope Team Tacul" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The idea for the <em>Mountain People Interviews</em> Series has been ripening in my head since spring 2014 and a lot of preperation and work has gone into it since, lining up the interview partners, coming up with the questions and editing the interviews. However, visiting the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a>, the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor Fair</a> and the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/petzl-roctrip-2014-turkey.html">Petzl RocTrip</a> really has allowed me to meet the interesting people I wanted to ask more questions.</p>

<p>I have a dozen interviews in the pipeline with designers, alpinists, photographers and climbers which should make for an interesting series with different views and perspectives on why people love the mountains. I’m really excited about this series as it allowed me to ask the people who design the gear we use, photograph the athletes we admire, and those that are <em>Living the Dream</em> to ask them about their passion for the fjells, hills and mountains of this world. Stay tuned for the first interview later this week!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mandj98/8658442801" title="Mountain View by James Marvin Phelps, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8658442801_a80bda06fd_b.jpg" width="1000" height="667" alt="Mountain View" /></a></p>

<p><em>Don’t miss any Mountain People Interviews and other posts and follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXIX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/the-week-in-review-clxxxix.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-18T16:30:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/the-week-in-review-clxxxix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Logic will get you from A to B. 
Imagination will take you everywhere.</em> 
- Albert Einstein</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16270063701" title="Mukluk &amp; Fox Tracks by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7534/16270063701_502d6935af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mukluk &amp; Fox Tracks" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/01/15/sports/el-capitans-dawn-wall-climbers-reach-top.html">Pursuing the Impossible, and Coming Out on Top</a>.</p>

<p>In less than three weeks I will be again on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/ispo-news-2014.html">ISPO</a>, scooping out the newest &amp; lightest gear for you. </p>

<p>Nice <a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/ralf-gantzhorn-fotograf-geologe/">interview with Ralf Gantzhorn</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://liisakorpela.fi/waiting-is-the-keyword/">Waiting is the keyword</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2015/01/financial-responsibilities.html">Financial Responsibilities</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-24-das-ging-ins-auge/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #24</a> is out.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/1Cc6v66">Begfreunde Winter Sale</a> is in full swing and Arc’teryx, Black Diamond, Marmot, Icebreaker and more brands are up to 50% reduced.</p>

<p>Bump any Outlet item to 50% Off at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Backcountry.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=42809&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/42809/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2015/01/vohvelityyppi.html">Vohvelityyppi</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">Högakustenleden Trip Report</a>.</p>

<p>The Latvian Alaskan Family has arrived in <a href="http://www.latvianalaskan.com/ensenada-guerro-negro-december-22nd-january-15th/">Guerro Negro</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2015/01/bikerafting-in-sibirien.html">Bikerafting in Sibiria</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2015/01/trans-ecuador-parte-1.html">Trans-Ecuador</a>.</p>

<p>Nico and Lael ride <a href="https://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2015/01/18/grassveld-battlefields-timberlands-swaziland/">Grassveld, Battlefields, Timberlands, Swaziland</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ulning.dk/white-out-x-mass/">White-out X-mas</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://kevshieldsclimbing.blogspot.fi/2015/01/anti-social-climbing.html">Anti Social Climbing</a> on the Ben.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/xlXk49Mh7go" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Lael reflects on <a href="https://laelsglobe.wordpress.com/2015/01/13/three-months-in-south-africa/">Three months in South Africa</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://lyhikeperroon.wordpress.com/2015/01/14/easy-just-isnt-worth-it/">Ski-touring in Urho Kekkonen National Park</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.hikebiketravel.com/32282/a-hike-to-grizzly-lake-in-the-tombstone-mountains/">A Hike to Grizzly Lake in the Tombstone Mountains</a>.</p>

<p>Toby heads to <a href="http://lightfromthenorth.blogspot.fi/2015/01/pinnacle-ridge-st-sunday-crag.html">Pinnacle Ridge &amp; St Sunday Crag</a> in the Lake District.</p>

<p><a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/mojas-y-tinto-barraquito-basalt-climbing-tenerife/">Climbing in Tenerife</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15685848634" title="Gas Stoves by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7513/15685848634_ba21da3284_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gas Stoves" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.aufundab.eu/test/fritzi-boulderhose-fuer-maedels-praxistest-testsieger">JUNG Fritzi Boulderpants reviewed</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://fearlessandunique.wordpress.com/2015/01/13/cycling-across-europe-in-winter-a-list-of-what-to-take-to-make-it-a-great-trip/">Cycling across Europe in Winter – A list of what to take to make it a great trip</a>.</p>

<p>Jens tests the <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/bekleidung/praxistest-patagonia-down-sweater-hoody/">Patagonia Down Sweater Hoody</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://dedpxl.com/fuji-x-buyers-guide-part-3-accessories/">Fuji X Buyer’s Guide - Accessories</a>.</p>

<p>Peter has spent <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/01/five-years-with-salsa-fargo.html">Five Years with the Salsa Fargo</a>.</p>

<p>Watch Chad’s <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2015/01/17/post-hike-gear-talk-january-2015-hot-springs-to-max-patch/">Post Hike Gear Talk</a>.</p>

<p>Alice does a <a href="http://alicehikes.com/2015/01/pct-clothing-review/">PCT clothing review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.minimallyminimal.com/blog/leica-t-m-adapter-t-summilux-m-35mm-f14-asph">Leica T + M-Adapter T + Summilux-M 35mm f/1.4 ASPH</a> Review.</p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/?utm_source=PTID13002584"><img src="http://ad.globetrotter-partnerprogramm.de/1-globetrotter-728x90.gif" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Högakustenleden - The High Coast Trail]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-13T18:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Högakustenleden - or High Coast Trail in English - is a new trail that passes through the UNESCO World Heritage site of the same name. The scenic trail passes through villages &amp; towns, along the coast, through the forest and a beautiful National Park and if you have a free week makes for a great walk along the Swedish coastal hills.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034082038" title="Jon Nils Berget is the highest point on the trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7571/16034082038_6e226a048a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jon Nils Berget is the highest point on the trail" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>November marks usually the last month of the year where I go out on a Press Trip to do research for <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/magazines/">magazine</a> articles. It’s far from the perfect backpacking month in the North and I had planned to hike the High Coast Trail in August, but changes in schedules meant it’d be the final backpacking trip of the year. Happily my good friend Martin agreed to accompany me, and so we met up late on a Sunday night in a <a href="http://umea.kfum.se">Hostel in Umeå</a>, him after flying in, me after taking the <a href="http://www.wasaline.com">ferry from Vaasa</a>. The next morning we enjoyed the breakfast at the Hostel and walked to the bus station from where we had a comfortable and fast bus ride to the bus stop at Hornöberget just before the High Coast Bridge, the start point of the trail. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221689035" title="Start at the High Coast Bridge in Hornöberget by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7551/16221689035_e5fb4a7ab7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start at the High Coast Bridge in Hornöberget" /></a></p>

<p>We followed the street for a bit, took to a forest road and soon saw our first Högakustenleden trail marker and were on a proper trail. It was a short one, though, because the next several kilometres took us along on village roads, along the street, across bridges until we finally walked along the Baltic Sea and came upon a proper trail into the forest. It wasn’t all pleasurable forest trails, though, we also passed a few deforested areas until we finally reached Sör-Lövvik, the end of section 1. The <a href="http://lovvikbedandbreakfast.se">Lövvik B&amp;B</a> looked inviting just along the trail, and while it was still early in the day we somehow wouldn’t have minded to stop there or at the free cottage in the village, but as it was closed for the winter we just continued until Fjärdbotten.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601850203" title="Fishing Nets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7503/15601850203_bcabd0086a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fishing Nets" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035884247" title="On streets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7487/16035884247_65a120cd5d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On streets" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195855506" title="And trail markers to keep us on course by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7542/16195855506_1793df18c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And trail markers to keep us on course" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219888711" title="A B&amp;B in Lövvik by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16219888711_bd1004d1a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A B&amp;B in Lövvik" /></a></p>

<p>We hiked for a while along the road and then took a turn onto a forest path. We found a stream to refill our water bottles and continued until the Laavu at Halsviken Bay. The place looked nice, and with dusk upon us we yet again were tempted to put the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">HMG UltaMid</a> up for the night. We resisted the early finish and continued on the trail, which then went through a boulder field along the shore. Sleet from the sky, strong winds and spray from the sea make walking on boulders a pleasurable past time, which only can be improved by onsetting darkness. We somehow managed to no break any feet or legs and were rather happy as we reached the forest road and road to Fjärdbotten. It was dark and raining as we arrived there, not knowing what to expect. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035659269" title="Boulder-hoping in the dark and rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7546/16035659269_bb0576bfb7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boulder-hoping in the dark and rain" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034258558" title="Night Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8603/16034258558_8d5ccdb6a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night Selfie" /></a></p>

<p>Fjärdbotten was a great camping place. Around six wooden cottages with tables, benches, beds and some with a stove in them were too good a chance to pass up. Martin quickly put a clothes line up, we hang our wet gear up to dry, got a fire started and then the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/primus-eta-lite-gaskocher/">Primus Lite+</a> came out and boiled us hot water for dinners and Minttu Kakaos! Well fed we soon dived into our sleeping bags and had a good night’s sleep. </p>

<p>The next morning was drizzly but looked like it might clear up. After we explored the Fjärdbotten summer farm and checked out the other cottages and got water from the well we had a warm breakfast &amp; coffee, boiled water for our <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos</a> and then soon were out on the trail again. The decision to stay at Fjärdbotten was a good one, and it was a very nice place.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035560289" title="Breakfast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16035560289_94649b7d5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Breakfast" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601808053" title="Inside our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/15601808053_901c543d1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inside our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034318520" title="Our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/16034318520_918a454e5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601795673" title="Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15601795673_efdbc0fec3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a></p>

<p>The next section took us on the highest point along the trail, Jon Nils Berget. We were lucky as the drizzle from the morning stopped after a few kilometres of hiking and we were treated by one of those fine, sunny days which you get after a night of rain. The trail was a mix of nice forest roads (they’re great to walk and talk on with a party of two!) where abandoned caravans were every few kilometres. As we reached Jon Nils Berget the sun came out and we really enjoyed this beautiful moment. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195729126" title="Supertramp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16195729126_3621a39362_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Supertramp" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237534596" title="Martin taking in the view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16237534596_140c3a9356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Martin taking in the view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219705131" title="Viewing the view stop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7514/16219705131_dd6c0e5321_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the view stop" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035459759" title="And looking outta the window by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7523/16035459759_b39d89a0c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And looking outta the window" /></a></p>

<p>We had a quick tea and cookies break at the Nipstugan on Lidenipan, and the sun just continued to treat us with warmth and light on the way to Gavik, the end of the 3rd Section. Behind Gavik we hiked on a forest road along summer cottages which had been closed up for winter, and had a very late lunch as the sun was just setting somewhere in the West. Soon the headlamps came on as we hiked on dark and wet forest trails and snowy forest roads.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034049618" title="Well, lets get moving by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16034049618_5c2d180b64_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Well, lets get moving" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601684713" title="Back on asphalt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7521/15601684713_a62f3aef77_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back on asphalt" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033999978" title="Where the road stops by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7495/16033999978_94444f9be6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Where the road stops" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601652373" title="Views without trees by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8576/15601652373_c0ddf9bf12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views without trees" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220694082" title="Headlamp illuminated views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7490/16220694082_cb669dd0de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Headlamp illuminated views" /></a></p>

<p>The goal of Section 4 was Lappuden, which was hailed as <em>the</em> camping spot along the Högakustenleden. Well, it was not. As it was closed. Closed up for winter. After the luxury of the Fjärdbotten hut we were going to sleep outside, and as the lake and grass fields already were covered with thin ice we knew we’d be in for a cold night. Alas, not even a fire we were able to lighten up, for a lack of wood and a fire place. We still had a good night, even if my <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk">PHD Minix Sleeping Bag</a> was a tad too less insulation for these temperatures. The next morning the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">fēnix</a> said -3°C and we packed up while the Lite+ boiled water for breakfast &amp; coffee. We were early on the trail again, and we were happy to leave the disappointment of Lappuden behind.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601643623" title="Lappuden by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/15601643623_59636ae21f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lappuden" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035648837" title="Reindeer moss by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/16035648837_9c8c2cea2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reindeer moss" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15599059654" title="Quartz veins by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7525/15599059654_c6e420dee6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Quartz veins" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035354489" title="Erikskojan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7547/16035354489_03b5cf6996_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Erikskojan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221453515" title="Inside Erikskojan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7582/16221453515_d0cda2ee6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inside Erikskojan" /></a></p>

<p>The trail was again a mix of enjoyable forest trails, OK forest roads and less enjoyable asphalt streets, but happily the trails made up the majority os Section 5 to Ullånger. The highlight for Martin and me was the beautiful Erikskojan hut high up in the middle of the forest. It stood lonely there, and if I hadn’t pulled like someone who really wants to sit inside with his tea we probably would have drunk our hot tea on its steps as the door was very tightly closed =) Of all the huts we passed this was the one we both really would have loved to stay in for the night, as it was cozy and comfortable. Alas, we needed to continue onwards.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195558186" title="Lovely deforestation views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7568/16195558186_41f1ab48d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lovely deforestation views" /></a></p>

<p>As we hiked into Ullånger it was still lunch time, and we didn’t need long to decide on the Värdshuset Restaurang Snäckan to get our business. A Lunch Buffet is a Hiker’s dream, and tasty Swedish food was consumed in large amounts, topped off with coffee and cookies. It was fortunate that we didn’t need to hike a long distance to our next camping place, the Gårdberget Stugan just above Ullånger. We didn’t really know what to expect, but were delighted by the hut, which was decorated in a 70s style and had a big stove inside. A fire was roaring quickly while night fell, and we enjoyed the evening by talking and drinking a good Whisky.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263362435" title="Gårdberget Stugan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7529/16263362435_bf07675705_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gårdberget Stugan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262537602" title="Mäjasjön Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16262537602_c7326acd44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mäjasjön Summer Farm" /></a></p>

<p>The night over a powdery coat of snow covered the land and we enjoyed the walk in the morning through the silent forest. That silence was interrupted the closer we got to Sjöland and Skoved as the trail went along the highway. It was an interesting experience to hike with trucks and cars passing by at high speeds, and I do hope that the trail finds a different route in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262738312" title="Church door by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7555/16262738312_90e05236cb_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Church door" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16075793398" title="Truck by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7559/16075793398_dc2885d33f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Truck" /></a></p>

<p>We flew through Section 7 from Skoved to Skuleberget and the <a href="http://www.naturumhogakusten.se/">Naturum Höga Kusten</a> Centre. Sadly the Museum also was closed, and as we still had well over 15 km before us we also didn’t take the detour over the top of the Skuleberget. The hill was impressive, though, and it’s nice to see that local entrepreneurs have installed Via Ferratas on it. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15643755233" title="Naturum Höga Kusten by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7561/15643755233_c0fd06d8dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Naturum Höga Kusten" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076092610" title="Skuleberget National Park South Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7537/16076092610_7e0d2a9016_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park South Entry" /></a></p>

<p>Section 8 from Skuleberget to the Skuleberget National Park South Entry must have been one of the most frustrating ones on the trail. After the Naturum Höga Kusten Centre we had another quick lunch break outside and then followed the nice Kids Adventure/ Robber Trail, passed an Open Air Theatre and then crossed the highway once more to hike on trails and forest roads to the South Entry of the National Park. Some sections of the trail were flooded and it was impossible to keep your feet dry, which usually doesn’t bother me at all, but somehow that day it really annoyed me a lot. The trail wasn’t fun in the wet dirt &amp; mud, but happily I recovered as soon as the trail became dry again. As we came closer and closer to the Skuleberget National Park the better our moods got, and the view from the South Entry was indeed well worth coming there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263434465" title="View at Skuleberget National Park South Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8609/16263434465_9a283ba21d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View at Skuleberget National Park South Entry" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263398085" title="Skuleberget National Park Signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16263398085_8e31435fc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park Signs" /></a></p>

<p>As frustrating as that wet part of the trail previously was, so wonderful was the <a href="http://www.sverigesnationalparker.se/skuleskogen#.VLUOe8bJhJc">Skuleskogen National Park</a>. The National Park probably was the highlight of our trip, and we were a bit sad that we spend only such a short time in day light in it. We hiked on duck boards for kilometres, passed waterfalls and then hiked up to the impressive Slåttdalsskrevan, a 200 m long, 40 m deep and 7 m wide crevice. We explored it in the shine of our headlamps and then made us on the way down to the Tärnättvattnen Stuga in the middle of the National Park. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237633986" title="Checking out the small waterfall, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7481/16237633986_fdcba0d04b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Checking out the small waterfall, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238289906" title="Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7464/16238289906_fa3b941b49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237741036" title="Frozen, slippery, smooth granite at night by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7478/16237741036_d5b335e1dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Frozen, slippery, smooth granite at night" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16261636721" title="Frozen lake at Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7578/16261636721_4058a06423_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Frozen lake at Skuleberget National Park" /></a></p>

<p>The hut was gorgeous from the inside and outside, though as it often happens with such huts, they seem to accumulate rubbish and trinkets which previous visitors <em>left for others to enjoy</em> or simply <em>forgot</em>. We cleaned up, got a fire started and enjoyed the evening with the a <em>Feierabendbier</em> which we carried all the way from the Supermarket in Docksta till here to enjoy in this rustic hut. The next morning grey clouds still hung thickly in the sky and the sun wasn’t to be seen. We brought some more wood for the next visitors to the hut, cleaned up and packed and where on our way again.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076128100" title="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16076128100_74c11ae583_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076804860" title="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/16076804860_db7f85d833_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15641095154" title="Signs in Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7528/15641095154_3e564daab1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signs in Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076115510" title="Looking back towards Slåttdalsskrevan, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7572/16076115510_c722693948_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Looking back towards Slåttdalsskrevan, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077690687" title="Dot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8619/16077690687_48928e6a0a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dot" /></a></p>

<p>The way out of the National Park was again very beautiful, along frozen lakes, via Duckboards over swamps, over small streams and soft forest trails until the North Entry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15643662733" title="Stream crossing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8643/15643662733_6e3a184cbc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Stream crossing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077649527" title="The sea, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8636/16077649527_664f582c49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The sea, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262745482" title="Skuleberget National Park North Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7469/16262745482_6731323942_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park North Entry" /></a></p>

<p>It was noon as we arrived in Köpmanholmen, and as every good tourist hiker does we immediately located the local Pizzeria and ordered their lunch Pizza. 60 SEK for a Pizza, salad, drink and coffee is a real bargain, especially considering that the Pizzas were about 40 cm (!) in diameter. We were stuffed as we walked out of the village and walked on a sandy road until the where we would enter the Balesudden Nature Reserve. It was a very beautiful reserve and not even a kilometre from the start of the forest trail we passed the prettiest Laavu on the whole Högakustenleden, up on the hill overlooking the Baltic Sea. Again we regretted that we needed to push on and couldn’t stay here, as the view and atmosphere was gorgeous.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15640967264" title="Party time by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15640967264_7ba6d83d27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Party time" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076221740" title="Sweden! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8676/16076221740_3f181081cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sweden!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077751717" title="Högakustenleden Signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16077751717_bc80426d93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Högakustenleden Signs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262764232" title="Laavu with a view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7521/16262764232_d025afbe1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Laavu with a view" /></a></p>

<p>Instead we pushed on through on and up through the Balesudden Nature Reserve, though with dusk coming upon us and a light drizzle we had our eyes mostly on the slippery trail in front of us. We passed a nice fireplace and camping spot near a bay until we happened upon the Bodviken Stugan, our hut for the night. The drizzle had become rain and I was happy as Martin offered to go chop the wood. I started the fire and rolled out my sleeping bag and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html">mattress</a> and again fired up the Primus Lite+. Soon we were well fed and had a whisky in our cups, which ensured we had another good, relaxed and warm night.</p>

<p>In winter you can sleep long and still catch the sunrise. So after we had breakfast I took a little stroll around the hut to photograph the sunrise. It was just a brief moment where one could spot the sun, as it passed up from the sea to hide again behind the clouds. It was our last day on the trail, and we only had 21 km till Örnsköldsvik, with the last part in civilization, so that we took it easy. We passed a few more Laavus in the morning, hiked on forest roads and streets, up hills and had a quick break in the Småtjärnstugan, and then were very quickly in Svedje, the end of Section 12. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238233526" title="Sunrise by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7565/16238233526_786eec69cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15672818967" title="Natur Reservat by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/15672818967_bc83905b3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Natur Reservat" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16261709811" title="Bodviken Stugan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/16261709811_108f7dfe02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodviken Stugan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076028498" title="Along the frozen lake by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7503/16076028498_a1176918ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Along the frozen lake" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16078073489" title="That way! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7494/16078073489_fed4a67d95_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="That way!" /></a></p>

<p>From here we passed through the town and climbed the local recreation area. As it was windy, 0°C and grey we just marched on towards Örnsköldsvik, the end of Section 13 of the Högakustenleden. Early in the afternoon we reached town. Done.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076823010" title="Örnskoldvik by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7566/16076823010_6ce886089b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Örnskoldvik" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076101788" title="Örnköldsvik! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8616/16076101788_c758bc15da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Örnköldsvik!" /></a></p>

<p>While standing on the square in the centre a young Swede came talking to us, who recognized me as <em>the writer of Hiking in Finland</em>. It was a fun coincidence as he said he saw that we’d be hiking the trail that week and he met us just as we finished! Very cool! After inquiring about a good place to eat in the evening we walked to our hostel, <a href="http://www.vindarnashus.se">Vindarnas Hus</a>. It was a nice &amp; quiet hostel with Wifi, hot showers and good beds, and we chilled there in the evening until we headed out to eat at <a href="http://www.bishopsarms.com/Ornskoldsvik">The Bishops Arms</a> which not only had superb food but also impeccable service and great beers. It was a worthy finish to a great Högakustenleden thru-hike!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221464365" title="Still plenty of signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7539/16221464365_a08cce908d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Still plenty of signs" /></a></p>

<h2 id="planning-your-high-coast-trail-hike">Planning your High Coast Trail hike</h2>

<p>To see about 150 more photos check out the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157648982512379/">Höga Kusten Trail Album</a> on Flickr.</p>

<p>The funniest thing about the Högakustenleden was for Martin and me how the distances were way off from what the signs and the guide booklet said. It makes me wonder if the trail is actually hiked by the people who planned it and if they made the effort to check the distance, or if these were just made via some mapping tool. Because the Högakustenleden is supposed to be 128,6 km from Hornöberget to Örnsköldsvik, but I tracked with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">Garmin fēnix</a> 141,8 km in the six days we hiked it. This isn’t uncommon and I regularly hike trails and sections which are longer/ shorter than they’re claimed to be, but still is something to keep in mind when you plan to hike the trail. </p>

<p>Also important to know is that the trail goes quite a bit along forest roads and streets. It does feel like at least 50% of the trail makes use of such infrastructure, and while it can make for fast hiking (5 km an hour and easy to chat while walking next to each other) it isn’t really very inspiring. Happily there are enough of nice forest trails, too, and the section through the Skuleskogen National Park was gorgeous. If you have time I’d recommend planning a day to just explore the National Park and then hike on.</p>

<p>Plan the travel there and back via <a href="http://reseplanerare.resrobot.se/bin/help.exe/sn?L=vs_resrobot&amp;tpl=webapp">Resrobot</a>, one of the best travel apps I have used. It helps you to find the best Bus/ Train/ Flight connections from e.g. Stockholm to Hornöberget and Örnsköldsvik and also lets you book the tickets right away. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.visitsweden.com/sweden/">Visit Sweden</a> and the <a href="http://www.hogakustenleden.com">Högakustenleden</a> + <a href="http://hogakusten.com/en/hk/high-coast-trail.html">High Coast Trail</a> websites offer a host of information about Sweden and the trail, especially the last page has a great overview map and a description of each section. You can order from there also the useful <a href="http://hogakusten.com/information/en/brochures.html">Trail Guide</a>, though don’t bother with the (free) map as it’s too large a scale to be useful for hiking. Speaking of maps, you really can hike it just with the maps in the Trail Guide. The trail is exceptionally well marked and so very beginner-friendly, sometimes every third tree has an orange dot or stripe. </p>

<p>We slept every night in one of the free huts or Laavus and were completely alone on the trail, we once encountered day hikers. But then we were hiking in November, so in the spring, summer and autumn that could look very differently. I recommend you take a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">shelter</a> along when hiking in those months, or make use of the various accommodation options along the trail. Basic ultralight gear choices would suit the trail well, you can practice pitching tarps and sleeping with a quilt here very well as you could always head to one of the Laavus or Huts. From Ullånger on you almost daily would pass a village with a supermarket, Café and Restaurant, so you could easily resupply along the trail (or buy a Swedish Beer for the evening each day =).</p>

<p>Along the trail you also could easily go packrafting, sea kayaking, climbing and Via Ferrata. While you could do some of these activities just besides the trail you’d need to plan an extra day for some others. Because of the good infrastructure (huts &amp; Laavus, Restaurants and Shops along the way) the trail could be a good choice for families who want to try backpacking with their kids. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 01/2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/trekking-magazin-01-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-12T15:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/trekking-magazin-01-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first trekking Magazin of 2015 is at the Newsstand - and these great articles are in it!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077458409" title="trekking Magazin 01/2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7568/16077458409_28ba44035a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 01/2015" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>My <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/from-russia-with-love.html">From Russia With Love</a> trip report is still super popular and in the first trekking Magazin issue of 2015 I wrote a trip report auf Deutsch. It’s a great looking article and gives tips to plan your own hike in Karelia, so well worth to pick it up just for that. In my gear column I talk about down jackets and review the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hagloefs-essens-ii-down-weste-noble-blue-s/?pid=81">Häglöfs Essens II Down Vest</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/14pEniz">Arc’teryx Cerium SL Jacket</a>, <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/yukon-down-jacket">PHD Yukon Down Jacket</a> and the <a href="http://bit.ly/1hh35k8">Mountain Equipment Vega Jacket</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262752882" title="trekking Magazin 01/2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7545/16262752882_95e18731f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 01/2015" /></a></p>

<p>There’s still plenty more in there, from fine hikes in Luxembourg and Sweden to a Winter Gear Guide. Pick up the first issue of 2015 at a Newsstand near you or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> to not miss any future issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXVIII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/the-week-in-review-clxxxviii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-11T17:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/the-week-in-review-clxxxviii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>When you get older, like I am, you will find that your emotions are very close to the surface and you will not contain them very well. I started crying - I just couldn’t help it. I was so happy for him, because I knew what this meant and how hard he had battled to be standing at that belay.</em> - <a href="http://www.elcapreport.com/content/elcap-report-192015-special-dawn-wall-edition-day-14">Captain Tom</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16066228560" title="MInna swinging and winning by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8640/16066228560_98d19b8ecd_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="MInna swinging and winning" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>El Cap Report - <a href="http://www.elcapreport.com/content/elcap-report-192015-special-dawn-wall-edition-day-14">Special Dawn Wall Edition Day 14</a>.</p>

<p>And look at this NY Times special, too: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2015/01/09/sports/the-dawn-wall-el-capitan.html?hp&amp;action=click&amp;pgtype=Homepage&amp;module=second-column-region&amp;region=top-news&amp;WT.nav=top-news&amp;_r=1">El Capitan’s Most Unwelcoming Route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alanarnette.com/blog/2015/01/06/inside-look-everest-2015-may-bring/">An Inside Look at What Everest 2015 May Bring</a>.</p>

<p>Stevie the Supremacist Haston’s <a href="http://steviehaston.blogspot.fi/2015/01/my-bigoted-beliefs-stevie-supremacist.html">Bigoted Beliefs</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.powder.com/human-factor/#">The Human Factor</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.americangrouch.com/2015/01/hare-snaring-basics.html">Hare Snaring Basics</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2015/01/05/road-kill/">Road Kill</a>.</p>

<p>Christina explains <a href="http://christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi/2015/01/how-long-distance-hiking-will-change.html">How long-distance hiking will change your personality</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de">Bergfreunde Wintersale</a> has started - act quick while all sizes and colours are still available!</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=38125&amp;pw=73183">Official REI Coupons &amp; Rebates page</a> for great deals or make use of <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=61341&amp;pw=73183">The After Christmas Sale</a> and save up to 50% at Backcountry.com and get Free Shipping on orders over $50.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=126685&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/11545/126685/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Chris hikes <a href="http://dailey7779.blogspot.fi/2015/01/the-freak-of-franconia-notch-cannon.html">Cannon Mountain</a>.</p>

<p>I reported from the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/petzl-roctrip-2014-turkey.html">Petzl RocTrip 2014</a> in Turkey. </p>

<p>Bernadette goes for a ski-tour in the ski region of her youth, <a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/skitour-im-ehemaligen-skigebiet-viehtaleralm/">Viehtaleralm</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3s6qrxypgS4">Hike the Pacific Crest Trail in 3 minutes</a>. [Video]</p>

<p>Adam hikes to <a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2015/01/skookum-volcano.html">Skookum Volcano</a>.</p>

<p>Chris’ 1st <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2015/01/first-hill-walk-of-year.html">Hill Walk of the Year</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/ZOScetWwEwc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2012/10/in-dag-we-trust-a-rock-climbing-trip-to-turkeys-ala-dag-mountains.html">A Rock Climbing Trip to Turkey’s Ala Dag Mountains</a>.</p>

<p>Nick and Lael ride <a href="https://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2015/01/08/dragons-spine-semonkong-lesotho-to-monantsa-pass-south-africa/">Dragon’s Spine: Semonkong, Lesotho to Monantsa Pass, South Africa</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ASs95G49OjI">The Hard Way - Annapurna South Face (1970)</a>. [Video]</p>

<p>Marika goes for her <a href="http://ainaylamaki.blogspot.fi/2015/01/vetoharjoitus-numero-yksi.html">first winter skiing/ pulling-run with her dog</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.albertodegiuli.com/2015/01/dolomiti-sci-alpinismo-tra-la-fine-e-il-nuovo-anno-cima-loschiesuoi-culea-integrale-val-setus-e-tofane/">Alpine skiing in the Dolomites</a>. [Italian]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.haukkari.net/2015/01/x-mas-in-osp.html">X-mas in Osp</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/sightseeing/10-lesser-known-places-visit-near-tokyo/">10 Lesser Known Places to Visit near Tokyo</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://climbjapan.blogspot.fi/2014/12/jogosawa-ice.html">Jogosawa (ジョーゴ沢) ice</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://therepublicofdoom.blogspot.fi/2015/01/desert-crunch.html">Desert Crunch</a> or <a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2015/01/plan-d.html">Plan D</a>?</p>

<p><a href="http://adventureswithpackraft.blogspot.fi/2015/01/a-new-year-ski-tour.html">A New Year Ski Tour</a>.</p>

<p>Roger hikes from <a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/2015/01/02/ystad-to-simrishamn-a-walk-with-new-found-friends/">Ystad to Simrishamn with new found friends</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/L4O-RJ-UfCc?list=PL4D038F3F367C906B">2014/2015 Banff Mountain Film Festival World Tour</a>. [Video]</p>

<p>Nick’s <a href="http://tms.nickbramhall.com/blog/2014/12/2014-in-the-scottish-hills/">2014 in the Scottish Hills</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://talusfield.net/southern-sierra-high-route">Southern Sierra High Route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16252765212" title="Time for cake and tea after a day ice climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7480/16252765212_43239b18b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Time for cake and tea after a day ice climbing" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A nice <a href="http://kaspergeuns.com/2015/01/11/osprey-aether-60/">Osprey Aether 60 Review</a>. [Dutch]</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx.html">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX Review</a> - one of the lightest fully-featuered mountaineering and climbing boots.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.willmayo.us/sharpening-petzl-picks/">Sharpening Petzl Picks</a>.</p>

<p>Joni <a href="http://leftbound.com/gear/Nordic-Skates-Revamped/">revamped his Nordic skates</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ulning.dk/motivation-008-breaking-borders/">Breaking Borders</a>.</p>

<p>Rene helps you to pimp your <a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/kleiner-hack-verbessert-die-silva-trailrunner-kopflampe/">Silva Trailrunner headlamp</a>.</p>

<p>Ross reviews the <a href="http://woodtrekker.blogspot.fi/2015/01/mountain-hardwear-direkt-2-tent-long.html">Mountain Hardwear Direkt 2 Tent</a>.</p>

<p>Toby reviews the <a href="http://lightfromthenorth.blogspot.fi/2015/01/the-jottnar-alfar-review.html">Jöttnar Alfar</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://outdoorhighlights.de/adventure-food-test/">Adventure Food Espresso &amp; Seeds Energy Bar review</a>.</p>

<p>Keith gives you the <a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/pros-cons-using-umbrella-hiking/">Pros &amp; Cons of using an Umbrella for Hiking</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
