<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-06T19:17:28+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor 2016: Backpacks]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/OutDoor-2016-Backpacks.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-07T23:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/OutDoor-2016-Backpacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/outdoor-2016-news-tents.html">tents</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-news-stoves.html">stoves</a> it is time to take a look at backpacks that are coming for hikers &amp; climbers in 2017!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874615013/in/dateposted/" title="HIKE with the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8378/28874615013_fc2f3945a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HIKE with the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Lets start with the <strong>Arc’teryx</strong> Bora AR Pack, which will debut in 2017 again - the Bora has been a very popular pack in the past but has been unavailable while it was being re-designed. Berrett Willet is the designer of the pack and showed me and <a href="https://twitter.com/WillWalksWales">Will from TGO</a> the pack and explained the ins-and-outs of it to us. The basic Bora design dates back to 1994 and the moveable hipbelt idea has been just as old, but it was back then not as easily to realize. Fast forward 20 years and manufacturing technologies and the possibility to design a reliable, moveable hipbelt are completely possible. The RotoGlide™ hipbelt and Tegris® back panel accommodate the movement of your back when you move up and down in the mountains: It glides up and down along its track to fluidly follow the lengthening &amp; straightening of your back and rotates freely along with the natural movement of your hips. The GridLock™ shoulder strap adjustment system allows the straps to be custom fit for both your height and width. It will come in a Women’s and Men’s version next year in Regular and Tall sizes, and in two volumes: 50 l and 63 l for men and 49 l and 61 l for women. The packs will retail for 470€ and 520€ respectively.</p>

<p>They’re made to haul heavy loads - think about moving to a far away wall you want to climb, carry gear in for a Backcountry skiing weekend, or just very long treks. For that they’re made from durable materials, to be precise from the N420r-AC2 waterproof fabric which is also used in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/one-duffle-to-rule-them-all-the-arcteryx-carrier-duffle.html">Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle</a>. It has a large zippered pocket on the front, a zippered lid pocket and a side zipper which allows on-the-go access to the main compartment. Trekking poles and ice axes also can be attached. The packs are made in the Philippines and have been designed &amp; tested in Vancouver, B.C.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874600603/in/dateposted/" title="The moving hipbelt of the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8145/28874600603_c2fd88b2b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The moving hipbelt of the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29416920571/in/dateposted/" title="Backside of the Hipbelt of the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8556/29416920571_629e3fde6d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Backside of the Hipbelt of the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874616363/in/dateposted/" title="Adjustable shoulder straps of the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8463/28874616363_94bfae38ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Adjustable shoulder straps of the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29416922231/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack in motion"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8130/29416922231_bff3dc5f20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack in motion" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874602103/in/dateposted/" title="Side &amp; Back-view of the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8481/28874602103_15435d0344_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Side &amp; Back-view of the Arc&#x27;teryx Bora AR Pack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Made for fast &amp; light alpinists <strong>Black Diamond</strong> comes out with the Blitz pack, which will be available in a 20 and 28 l volume. The packs are made from Dyneema which makes them durable enough to be pulled up rough granite walls and dropped down crevasses, as well as daily contact with ice tools and crampons. It has a one-hand top closure which did remind me of the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">Patagonia Ascensionist</a> lid design. There’s a waterproof zip pocket on that lid for small items, a rope strap carries the rope up and a removable bivy pad lets you shiver out the night up on the mountain. The Blitz 28 will weigh 444 g and the smaller 20 l version is 398 g.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874603823/in/dateposted/" title="Black Diamond Blitz pack"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8349/28874603823_79612f8377_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Blitz pack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Ortovox</strong> Trad 18 climbing pack weighs 198 g and come sin six visible colours. It’s much lighter than its big brother, the Trad 25 (which weighs 750 g!) but does pack quite some features. For starters there’s also a Patagonia Ascensionist-ish lid closure, while the pack rides low on your back so it does not interfere with your helmet. At the front there’s gear loops where you can clip in gear, while on the inside there’s a zippered valuables pocket and also a possibility to carry your hydration system. You can strap a rope to the top, too! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874612563/in/dateposted/" title="Ortovox Trad 18 climbing backpack"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8238/28874612563_fc4dbebaae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ortovox Trad 18 climbing backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I don’t think the <strong>Gregory</strong> packs are as light as the Trad pack above (or other UL packs), but I have an spot for the brand in my heart as it was the first backpacking pack I ever bought. They still make super-large and heavy packs, but also some lighter packs are nowadays to be found from their line-up. The Paragon is one of these packs, available in four volumes from 38 l to 68 l it weighs between 1,36 kg and 1,64 kg. The Paragon (and the Maven Women’s model) comes in two adjustable back lengths and also the hipbelt is easily adjustable on the go. The new Aerolon suspension system is made from an ultra-lightweight 7001 aluminium tubular frame and is specially designed so that stability is not compromised when the back length is adjusted. The back panel is made from a light and airy matrix foam and covered in a mesh
fabric for good ventilation and increased wear comfort. The lid can be removed to save some more weight, and on the inside you find a the small Sidekick pack, which is a combination of hydration reservoir sleeve and ultra-light removable daypack. It lets you run to the peak and back with leaving the main pack at camp. The backpack has all the pockets you’d want, from a front mesh pocket over mesh side pockets and hipbelt pockets to a zippered lid pocket. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29207977150/in/dateposted/" title="Gregory Paragon &amp; its Summit pack"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8216/29207977150_186e400c07_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Gregory Paragon &amp; its Summit pack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29207978020/in/dateposted/" title="Summit pack in the Gregory Paragon"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8031/29207978020_1748aa9de8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit pack in the Gregory Paragon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29388467062/in/dateposted/" title="Gregory Paragon adjustable hipbelt"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8224/29388467062_0a893fab84_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gregory Paragon adjustable hipbelt" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29416926941/in/dateposted/" title="Gregory Paragon back-panel and shoulder straps"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8643/29416926941_d5642be0d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gregory Paragon back-panel and shoulder straps" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And finally a look at a pack from <strong>Helsport</strong> (<em>Disclaimer</em>: I’m a Helsport Ambassador). At 65 l volume it is slightly larger as most packs I am used to carry, but it does weigh <em>“only”</em> 2,1 kg for the S/M Size pack, so it’s not the heaviest pack here (that’s the Arc’teryx pack above). It has a rain cover included, the top lid can be carried as a small summit pack or in front of the chest as I demonstrate underneath, and there’s some other nice-to-have features on the pack which I will write more about after I have used it this autumn =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874621763/in/dateposted/" title="Helsport Alta backpack"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8580/28874621763_d569bd90ca_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Helsport Alta backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874620663/in/dateposted/" title="Helsport Alta backpack back view"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8452/28874620663_012b357a7a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Helsport Alta backpack back view" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28874619403/in/dateposted/" title="Helsport Alta Lady backpack"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8158/28874619403_9ca2db2d37_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Helsport Alta Lady backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: I’m a Helsport Ambassador and have cooperated with some of the companies in this article in the past. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/swix-pro-trail-carbon-120-trekking-pole.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-06T23:37:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/swix-pro-trail-carbon-120-trekking-pole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking for a light carbon trekking pole which accompanies you through the day and stands tall when you pitch your shelter in the evening? Then take a peek at the new Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole from Swix!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29203718760/in/dateposted/" title="Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8470/29203718760_f0e4fde0cf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>The trekking poles were sent for free to me for a Swix campaign via the <a href="http://en.outdoor-blogger-network.com/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Network</a> &amp; I got paid to write this article. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site.</em></p>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I got the <a href="http://www.swixsport.com/Products/Poles/Trekking-Poles/Swix-Sonic-Pro-Trail-Carbon">Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120</a> in July 2016 and have been using them on day hikes, a trail run and as poles for pitching my shelters on Microadventures. They haven’t seen as much use as I usually would put a piece of kit through before I write about them, but this being a sponsored post I sadly didn’t have the freedom to test them for 12 months &amp; longer =) However, I intend to take them along to a trip to the Alps this autumn where I’ll be backpacking for a week and after that I will feel more confident about a final statement.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29203718920/in/dateposted/" title="Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Poles"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8656/29203718920_d3e8be7790_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Poles" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>As I highlighted in my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles.html">Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles</a> Review, trekking poles have many advantages outdoors:</p>

<ul>
  <li>They help you to keep your balance on difficult terrain</li>
  <li>Useful in fording rivers</li>
  <li>Can be transformed into a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html">tripod</a> or used with a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/03/interview-rod-java-from-thestickpic-com.html">StickPic</a> for photography</li>
  <li>They can pitch your tarp or shelter</li>
  <li>They train your upper body muscles when hiking and running</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29492680305/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking!"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8162/29492680305_96b186eab1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon is available in fixed lengths from 100 to 135 cm in 5 cm intervals. All of the poles have the following features in common:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Compact folding system</li>
  <li>Comfort Connection system</li>
  <li>Multi grip from cork with EVA extension</li>
  <li>Flexi basket system</li>
  <li>Swix carbon technology Swix CT1 grade</li>
  <li>Folded pack size is 39 cm</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29492688575/in/dateposted/" title="Folded together"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8287/29492688575_8115ec76fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Folded together" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>I’ve used a fair share of trekking poles, some lighter, some heavier. I can’t really say that these poles have any mind-blowing innovations in them, although there’s a few things I do like about them - read on to find out what.</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The quality is very good. The trekking poles make a solid impression, the construction of the segments is clean and smooth and they fit well together, and also the grip is well made (from European cork!). As Swix has many years of experience in the making of carbon poles (for cross country skiing) they were able to use this expertise and apply it to the production of their trekking poles.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28867841714/in/dateposted/" title="The Tip protector"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7493/28867841714_414d044771_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Tip protector" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My poles in 120 cm length weigh 153 g per pole including the little baskets, so the pair of them weighs 306 g. This makes them more heavy than my BD Poles, but I imagine this weight will reflect positively on the durability of the poles. On the plus side, that’s 29 g lighter as Swix claims they would be!</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Swix has a page about their interaction with the <a href="http://www.swixsport.com/Environment">environment</a>. On their page about <a href="http://www.swixsport.com/Environment/Swix-Products-and-the-Environment">Swix Products and the environment</a> they tell us rather broadly that <em>“Swix maintains a strong social responsibility program and has a focus on environmental awareness in product production. This is repeated in all aspects, both in the choice of raw materials, the use of recyclable packaging and more.”</em> This is not really going into details and doesn’t tell us much besides that they use recycable packaging. Happily there’s some more info on the <a href="http://www.swixsport.com/Environment/Swix-Environmental-Ethics">Swix Environmental Ethics</a> page, where they tell us that they do Climate accounting (with quite old data from 2009) and in which organizations they’re members. I would have wished for more infos on how &amp; where I could get a pole fixed and how I should get rid of them in case they break one day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28867841314/in/dateposted/" title="The folding mechanism"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8679/28867841314_2f380b0500_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The folding mechanism" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Poles are for me a 3-season pole because of their cork grip - I imagine they would be OK when hiking in the winter as long as you don’t let the cork get wet. They come with indicated Left &amp; Right hand straps that sadly are not easy to remove. They are OK to use and don’t have any hard plastic parts which could push uncomfortably into the skin, but I really feel I don’t need them and want the option to easily remove them.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28872979203/in/dateposted/" title="L &amp; R straps"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8334/28872979203_778998eb0d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="L &amp; R straps" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In use the cork handles are very comfortable, the cork grip lays good in the hand when hiking in flat terrain and up, while the rounded top is good to hold when descending. When navigating through steep terrain the longer EVA part makes gripping the pole lower nice, though as I said - I’d prefer a full cork grip. Even with sweaty hands in hot weather the cork feels more comfortable and doesn’t slip as easily as EVA. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28867837064/in/dateposted/" title="Handle of the Sonic Pro"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8020/28867837064_02007c24fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Handle of the Sonic Pro" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Because I don’t use poles all the time and often fly in a plane to go backpacking the weight and pack size are important to me. The Sonic Pro carbon are pretty good in that respect, as they fold small and fit into the side pocket of my LAUFBURSCHE pack or can be wrapped into a insulation jacket when travelling by plane. Because they fit inside of my pack I even was able to take them along as a carry-on, which is great when you’re flying without checked in luggage!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28873223823/in/dateposted/" title="Folded up for travel, fitting into a carry-on compliant pack!"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8512/28873223823_883a00e6a7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Folded up for travel, fitting into a carry-on compliant pack!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Flexi basket system is really great, I long have wished for an easy way to switch baskets on poles and this has been so easy to use, it’s a pleasure. Where other poles let you change baskets only with the use of lots of force or tools here I simply could unscrew the basket and screw on another one. The small baskets are fine for normal forest trails and established mountain trails, but for swamps and the crossing of summer snow fields a larger one would have been useful. Anyhow, the thread system is great.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28867842054/in/dateposted/" title="Basket of &amp; thread exposed"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8333/28867842054_1b6d9e805c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Basket of &amp; thread exposed" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29203720670/in/dateposted/" title="Flexi basket system, partly unscrewed"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8802/29203720670_d574455666_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Flexi basket system, partly unscrewed" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then to the most important job of my trekking poles: Pitching a shelter! For pitching tarps and pyramides I found the Sonic Pro Trail Carbon splendid because they are very stiff - much more stiff than my BD poles. This is especially good when a single pole is used for putting up a pyramide shelter as it flexes less when gusts hit the shelter, which I find feels safer.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28867841064/in/dateposted/" title="As a tent pole, looking up"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8045/28867841064_833e651a8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As a tent pole, looking up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And finally deploying them and folding them up. Both are a breeze, fast &amp; easy. For getting them ready for hiking you simply hold the hand grip and pull the part out which automatically straightens the pole, until you hear a click and the button jumps out and locks the segments in place. Folding the poles together is just as simple: Push the button back in and the upper part moves slightly back into the handle. Then just push the segment completely in and fold the pole together! Swix wrote that you can use the strap to keep the pole folded together, but I haven’t found out how to do that with a single pole. With both poles I just put them together with the straps on the opposite ends and then thread the segments through them, that way they stay together well. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29492681885/in/dateposted/" title="Step 1: Push the button to collapse them"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8030/29492681885_5b2bdcaea8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Step 1: Push the button to collapse them" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29492680845/in/dateposted/" title="Step 2: The pole moves together for a wee bit"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8530/29492680845_8a7d638487_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Step 2: The pole moves together for a wee bit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29384387342/in/dateposted/" title="Step 3: Lower part pushed fully up the handle"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8389/29384387342_7c64689aa9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Step 3: Lower part pushed fully up the handle" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I really like the cork grip and would wish the Sonic Pro Trail Carbon pole would have a complete cork handle, thus that the lower EVA part is also cork. It just feels more comfortable on the hand to me, and it’s a shame the lower part is made from EVA. I also would have wished that the strap would be easy to remove. I rarely use straps with poles in the summer and am sure I’d liked it better to save a few more grams than being forced to have it along. I also think that if one buys these poles that it’d be nice to get a choice of baskets with them, because the small trekking baskets aren’t really great in summer snow, swamps and boulder fields where a larger basket would make it easier for the pole not to penetrate too deep. Finally, a notch in the basket so they stay locked together when folded would have been useful, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29203721160/in/dateposted/" title="Size comparison with the Locus Gear Hapi"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7502/29203721160_e3cae1920b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Size comparison with the Locus Gear Hapi" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>The at the beginning mentioned <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles.html">Black Diamond Poles</a> are a worthy competitor which I know are very long-lasting &amp; robust, and if you can life with poles that have a larger pack size also the <a href="http://www.rutalocura.com/trekking_poles.html">Ruta Locura Yana poles</a> are great poles that I have used since many years very happily. If you need adjustable poles I’d check out the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/swix-sonic-x-trail-carbon-trekkingstoecke/?pid=10239">Swix Sonic X-Trail Carbon</a> which some of my friends will surely write about in a while!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28867837604/in/dateposted/" title="Pro Trail Carbon"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8212/28867837604_f5a95658c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pro Trail Carbon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Despite not having used them as much as I’d like to the Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Poles have made a good first impression on me. They are light and comfortable when out hiking and backpacking, allow me to pitch my Pyramide shelters and tarps and let me train my upper body when out for a hike. Keep in mind that I still am not a big trekking pole user when hiking (I use them usually in difficult terrain and for river crossings) although I almost always carry a pair because I need them for my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shelters/">shelters</a>. As I will be backpacking several more weeks this autumn and will take the Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 poles with me for hiking and pitching my shelter I will try to update this article then and reflect on them again after more use.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p><em>Only BUY stuff if you really need it!</em></p>

<p>You can get the pole in every length from <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/swix-sonic-pro-trail-carbon-trekkingstoecke/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> (On offer for 135€!) and <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/swix-sonic-pro-trail-carbon-trailrunningstock/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29492681415/in/dateposted/" title="Locus Gear Hapi &amp; Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8345/29492681415_74d621d9f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Hapi &amp; Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The trekking poles were sent for free to me by <a href="http://en.outdoor-blogger-network.com/?noredirect=en_US">OBN</a> and Swix &amp; I got paid to write about them. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 248]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/twir-248.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-05T23:26:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/twir-248</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Nothing compares to the simple pleasure of riding a bike.”</em> – <a href="http://amzn.to/2bRk0lH">John F. Kennedy</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28847950353/in/dateposted/" title="Cycling with the Thule Chariot CX2"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8603/28847950353_54304c98d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cycling with the Thule Chariot CX2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.rockandice.com/climbing-news/search-called-off-for-missing-pair-in-pakistan">search for Kyle Dempster and Scott Adamson</a> has been called off :( </p>

<p>Martin enlightens us with his <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/weitwander-rueckblick-august-2016/">long-distance hike review of August</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Thoughts on <a href="https://freieberge.wordpress.com/2016/08/31/zelten-in-den-allgaeuer-alpen-teil-2/">camping in the Allgäu Alps</a>, Part 2. [German]</p>

<p>A look how to make <a href="http://bit.ly/2csCbQ0">Bushcrafting ultralight</a>.</p>

<p>Autumn is coming, get a <a href="HTTPS://WWW.PEAKDESIGN.COM/PRODUCT/COVERS/SHELL/?ACC=97">Peak Design Shell Cover</a> for your camera to protect it from the rain. And save 10% on it by clicking that link, too! </p>

<p>Dave explains how they <a href="https://bedrockandparadox.com/2016/09/01/how-to-backpack-with-an-infant/">backpack with an infant</a>.</p>

<p>Winter is coming - but you still can <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=2267&amp;pw=73183">get 50% off on Winter Apparel and Gear at Backcountry</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/brands/arcteryx/?bfc-brand[]=icebreaker&amp;bfc-brand[]=patagonia&amp;bfc-brand[]=mammut&amp;bfc-brand[]=maloja&amp;bfc-brand[]=fjaellraeven&amp;bfc-brand[]=hagloefs&amp;listorderby=oxinsert&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">new 2016/ 2017 gear from Fjällräven, Patagonia, Arc’teryx, Mammut and Icebreaker is now available at Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=558259&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12733/558259/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.fi/2016/08/colorado-river-to-mt-peale-traverse.html">Colorado River to Mt. Peale Traverse</a>.</p>

<p>Pita has a <a href="http://racewithwind.blogspot.fi/2016/09/norjassa-toistamiseen.html">good time in Norway</a>.</p>

<p>Paulina climbs <a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/soloing-north-peak-mt-conness/">North Peak and Mt. Conness</a>.</p>

<p>In less than ten hours <a href="http://www.schwarzfuchs.com/zugspitze360-rund-um-die-zugspitze/">around the Zugspitze</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Also <a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2016/08/footsteps-of-giants-lost-coast-north_31.html">Day 5 on the Lost Coast</a> was more Type 2 Fun.</p>

<p>Cool <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/sleep-climb-high-cool-briancon-climbs-in-summer/">Briançon Climbs in summer</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/158890346?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/158890346">Alpine Defined - Emma Twyford in Chamonix</a> from <a href="https://vimeo.com/rab">Rab</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p>

<p>Awesome &amp; beautiful <a href="http://seatosummitultralight.blogspot.fi/2016/09/xst-2016-cross-country-traverse-of-high.html">Cross Country Sierra Traverse</a>.</p>

<p>Equally inspiring is Joe’s <a href="https://joecruz.wordpress.com/2016/09/03/kyrgyzstan-journal-pt-1/">ride through Kyrgyzstan</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mitsackundpackraft.wordpress.com/2016/09/04/wandern-und-paddeln-in-finnisch-lappland-erste-impressionen/">Hiking &amp; packrafting in Finnish Lapland</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Backpacking to the <a href="http://kidproject.org/2016/08/31/backpacking-into-the-conrad-kain-hut-bugaboos-family-edition/">Conrad Kain Hut</a>.</p>

<p>A walk at <a href="http://hikinginmainewithkelley.blogspot.fi/2016/09/9116-stillwater-river.html">Stillwater River</a>.</p>

<p>Braving the Stormy Seas for a <a href="http://www.fangirlquest.com/travel/movie-roadtrip-2016/whale-watching-tour-iceland/">Whale Watching Tour in Iceland</a>.</p>

<p>Check out <a href="http://www.travelingjackie.com/rtw-trip-video/">Jackie’s 9-Month Solo RTW Trip Video</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28673333293/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset behind the dunes"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8734/28673333293_0372eb960c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sunset behind the dunes" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Ben reviews the <a href="http://www.gearexposure.com/osprey-talon-33-review-versatile-enough-everything/">Osprey Talon 33</a> and finds it versatile enough for everything.</p>

<p>Peter shares his first impressions of his new <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2016/08/seabird-scott-mv-hdpe-first-impressions.html">Seabird Scott MV HDPE</a>. </p>

<p>Nice <a href="http://outdoorsmh.blogspot.fi/2016/09/myog-dyneema-x-backpack.html">MYOG Dyneema X Backpack</a>.</p>

<p>Sven tests the <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2016/09/activeon-cx-gold-action-cam-im-test/">ACTIVEON CX Gold Action Cam</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Casey reviews the <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/gear/sea-to-summit-insulated-air-mat/">Sea To Summit’s Ember Eb1 quilt and UltraLight Insulated Mattress</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/musings/hiking-in-japan-sourcing-water-from-trail/">Sourcing Water from the Trail</a> in Japan.</p>

<p>Quasi explains <a href="http://quasiout.blogspot.fi/2016/09/hygiene-beim-bikepacking-die-dusche-fur.html">how to shower when bikepacking</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpsinsight.com/stories/ultralight-bike-touring-alps-europe/">Ultralight Bike Touring in the Alps</a>.</p>

<p>And Dave got a <a href="http://wildernessdave.com/our-teardrop-trailer-introducing-wilma/">Teardrop Trailer</a> called Wilma. </p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=557443&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12821/557443/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear and apparel via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 247]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/twir-247.html"/>
    <updated>2016-08-29T23:53:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/twir-247</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Autumn seemed to arrive suddenly that year. The morning of the first September was crisp and golden as an apple.”</em> ― <a href="http://amzn.to/2bv2qFD">J.K. Rowling</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28673333643/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8217/28673333643_1eaf573c68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Yvon Chouinard: <a href="http://www.flyfisherman.com/fly-tying/yvon-chouinard-lessons-from-a-simple-fly/">Lessons from a Simple Fly</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://mclovinmountains.com/2016/08/24/the-pendulum/">The Pendulum</a>.</p>

<p>How to ditch your office and <a href="https://www.fastcoexist.com/3061296/how-to-ditch-your-office-and-work-from-a-national-park/">work from a National Park</a>.</p>

<p>I want this bike so badly: <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com/bicycles/carhartt-x-pelago.html?___store=default">Pelago x Carhartt x Mission Workshop</a>. I accept donations towards it - or just send me a Size M ;) </p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1343021557/ncamp-stove">nCamp Stove</a> - a 420 g light wood-burning camping stove that costs a mere $25. </p>

<p>Want the best socks for hiking? <a href="https://www.outdoorline.sk/en/38_darn-tough">Darn Tough socks are now available from Outdoorline.sk</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://petapixel.com/2015/07/16/why-i-stopped-using-the-dng-file-format/">Should you still use the DNG File format</a> upon importing or ditch it?</p>

<p>The book “<a href="http://amzn.to/2bsdiSX">On the Nose: A Lifelong Obsession with Yosemite’s Most Iconic Climb</a>” is now out.</p>

<p>Awesome: <a href="https://gearjunkie.com/katahdin-woods-waters-national-monument">President Obama declared the creation of the Katahdin Woods and Waters National Monument to protect nearly 90,000 acres of wilderness from development in Maine</a>. And as that alone isn’t enough, also the <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2016/08/26/presidential-proclamation-papahanaumokuakea-marine-national-monument">Papahanaumokuakea Marine National Monument</a> around Hawaii was expanded massively!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/christownsendoutdoors/">Chris Townsend has joined Instagram</a> - go give him a follow!</p>

<p>Need a challenge? Less than 20 people finish the <a href="https://besthike.com/2016/08/26/canadas-great-divide-trail/">Canada’s Great Divide Trail</a> a year ;) </p>

<p>Rider’s Lens: <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/riders-lens-jamie-vickers/">Jamie Vickers</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rdejrApmxX0">Claim Freedom Teaser</a>.</p>

<p>Banff Mountain Film and Book Festival <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wfT_hYEwhcs">2016 Trailer</a>.</p>

<p>How to <a href="https://lesserplaces.wordpress.com/2016/08/24/so-you-want-to-take-your-toddler-camping/">take your toddle camping</a>.</p>

<p>Coming in October: The <a href="http://bit.ly/2bJOGr5">Sierra Designs Flex Capacitor Backpack</a>, the design being influenced by <a href="http://andrewskurka.com/2016/sierra-designs-flex-capacitor-40-60-backpack-teaser/">Andrew Skurka</a>.</p>

<p>Silently arrived has the <a href="http://bit.ly/2bPwFoO">Salomon Speedcross 4</a> - and doesn’t it look stealthy?!</p>

<p>Backpacks without shoulder straps? If that sounds intriguing, check out <a href="http://www.me-2packs.com">ME2 Packs</a>.</p>

<p>Go Beta-Test the new <a href="https://www.triboom.com/brooks/project/brooks-helmets">Brooks Helmets</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://bit.ly/2bsgaz0">ULA Fastpack</a>.</p>

<p>If you need it: The <a href="http://amzn.to/2bshZfl">Vargo Ultimate Fire Starter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://chasingmailboxes.com/2016/08/25/ride-your-bike-people/">Ride Your Bikes</a>, People.</p>

<p>View the <a href="https://youtu.be/FeybIrrgmQo">E.O.F.T. 16/17 Teaser</a>.</p>

<p>Campsaver has <a href="http://bit.ly/2ck2f0R">20% off Regular Price &amp; Outlet gear with the coupon code LABORDAY</a>.</p>

<p>Save up to 50% on Clothing &amp; Gear at the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Backcountry End of Summer Sale</a>!</p>

<p>Also Bergfreunde.co.uk have great deals, like <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/outlet/brands/arcteryx/?pid=10239">Arc’teryx Kit up to 50% off</a>, for example the great <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/arcteryx-atom-lt-hoody-synthetic-jacket/?pid=10239">Atom LT Hoody</a>!</p>

<p>And finally, take a peek into the <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/bargain-box">PHD Bargain Box</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=314573&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12493/314573/55699/73183/image.gif" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reviews">Trip Reviews</h2>

<p>Love this: Adam’s <a href="http://bikepacker.com/tour-aotearoa-diary/">Tour Aotearoa Diary</a>.</p>

<p>Escape to the gorgeous Tatras and hike up to <a href="http://www.skadinagrani.pl/2016/08/szpiglasowy-wierch-2172-m-npm.html">Szpiglasowy Wierch</a>. [Polish]</p>

<p><a href="https://walkingwomad.com/2016/08/24/grand-canyon-to-zion-day-14/">Grand Canyon to Zion</a>.</p>

<p>Out of Office also love <a href="http://www.oooyeah.de/dolomiten-alta-badia/?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=dolomiten-alta-badia">the Dolomites</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2016/08/hell-hole-canyon.html">Hell Hole Canyon</a>.</p>

<p>Pretty: <a href="https://freieberge.wordpress.com/2016/08/23/walser-steilgrasrunde/">Walser Steilgrasrunde</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://rambleonwild.com/2016/08/28/parenting-creates-better-athletes-believe-it/">Parenting creates better athletes</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mi08QSyNlmU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Antti’s <a href="https://longdistancetrail.wordpress.com/2016/08/22/gr11-homecoming/">GR11 Homecoming</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://thespanishtravelgirl.com/2016/08/24/que-debes-y-que-no-debes-hacer-en-tu-visita-a-santorini/">How to see the best of Santorini in Greece</a>. [Spanish]</p>

<p>Beat’s <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2016/08/beats-jaunt-around-mont-blanc.html">jaunt around Mont Blanc</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.ultimatedirection.com/unsupported-longs-peak-triathlon-fkt/">Unsupported Longs Peak Triathlon FKT</a>.</p>

<p>Day four on the <a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2016/08/footsteps-of-giants-lost-coast-north_26.html">Lost Coast</a> wasn’t too enjoyable.</p>

<p><a href="https://hillplodder.com/2016/08/26/the-eskdale-escapade/">The Eskdale Escapade</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.trailcooking.com/2016/08/23/artist-ridge-foraging-berries/">Artist Ridge &amp; Foraging Berries</a>.</p>

<p>Toni visits <a href="http://www.tonilund.fi/2016/08/paradise-shore-fatbiking-adventure.html">the finest Laavu of South-Finland</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpinestyle.ca/2016/08/24/two_new_routes_in_a_weekend">Two new routes in a weekend</a>!</p>

<p>Out on the trails in the <a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/pollux-und-castor/">Aosta Valley</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28673334323/in/dateposted/" title="Still wearing my adidas Solo shoes :D"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8536/28673334323_91815a4dbe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Still wearing my adidas Solo shoes :D" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Cool: The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TmZ0D_BGHQU">FREELIGHT Blast Burner</a>.</p>

<p>The five <a href="http://bit.ly/2bCsgEz">best ultralight backpacking hammocks</a> from indie brands.</p>

<p>Roger explains (again!) why he prefers <a href="https://nielsenbrown.com/2016/08/26/why-i-prefer-klymit-mattresses-updated/">Klymit mattresses</a>.</p>

<p>Hiking in the <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2016/08/24/gear-review-hiking-in-the-ergobaby-carrier-original/">ErgoBaby Carrier Original</a>.</p>

<p>Abenteuersüchtig tests <a href="http://www.abenteuersuechtig.de/index.php/produkttest-kaipara-merino-sportswear/">Kaipara Merino Sportswear</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A look at <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2016/08/summer-2016-hardware/">climbing hardware for 2017</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bikepacker.com/gore-alp-x-pro-2in1-shorts-review/">Gore ALP-X PRO 2in1 Shorts Review</a>.</p>

<p>Logan takes <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/gear/bikepacking-helmets-mips/">three ‘MIPS’ helmets</a> out bikepacking.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear and apparel via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HMQkV5cTuoY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 246]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/twir-246.html"/>
    <updated>2016-08-21T23:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/twir-246</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Coming back to where you started is not the same as never leaving.”</em> ― <a href="http://amzn.to/2bdEu6v">Terry Pratchett</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29014393751/in/photostream/" title="Scarecrow"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7545/29014393751_5daa600211_b.jpg" width="1024" height="571" alt="Scarecrow" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Fun: <a href="http://www.spoon-tamago.com/2016/08/15/park-pens-twigs-packaged-to-look-like-stationery/">Park Pens - twigs packaged to look like stationery</a>.</p>

<p>Necessary: <a href="http://www.bikemag.com/fully-loaded-bikepacking/in-it-for-the-long-haul/#F4IHjWgtHZky7oug.97">How to prepare for a bikepacking race</a>.</p>

<p>Vertical: <a href="http://www.dailycamera.com/recreation/ci_30224970/chris-weidner-why-climbings-olympic-debut-should-be">Why climbing’s Olympic debut should be making a bigger splash</a>.</p>

<p>Patagonia’s Balancing Act: <a href="http://www.wsj.com/articles/patagonias-balancing-act-chasing-mass-market-appeal-while-doing-no-harm-1471426200">Chasing Mass-Market Appeal While Doing No Harm</a>.</p>

<p>Insects to eat: <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/sensfoods/sens-all-natural-bars-packed-with-cricket-protein?ref=hikinginfinland">SENS Bars</a>.</p>

<p>Trailrunning: <a href="http://sportbleibtmord.de/alleine-laufen-oder-der-gruppe/">Alone or in a group</a>? [German]</p>

<p>Amusing: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xyo8OIp7aHM">One Selfie per Mile on the PCT</a>.</p>

<p>Smart: <a href="http://universalklister.blogspot.fi/2016/08/think-for-yourself.html">Think for yourself</a>.</p>

<p>Good design: <a href="http://www.goout.hk/2016/08/18/hike-to-run/">Hike to Run</a>.</p>

<p>134 g: <a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/dynafit-enduro-dstjacket-dawn-s/?pid=81">Dynafit Enduro DST Jacket</a>.</p>

<p>10.179: <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/outlet/2/?pid=10239">Items in the Bergfreunde Outlet</a>.</p>

<p>50%: <a href="http://bit.ly/2b7PM0i">Highest discount on Granite Gear packs</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28933&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28933/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="468" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Up the <a href="https://freieberge.wordpress.com/2016/08/16/chachany-einer-der-leichtesten-6000er/">Chachany</a>, one of the easiest 6000 m mountains. [German]</p>

<p>Jana’s <a href="http://upthatthing.blogspot.fi/2016/08/frankenjura-summer-2016.html">Frankenjura summer 2016</a>.</p>

<p>Jonathan likes the <a href="http://www.jstarinorbit.com/2016/08/rocky-mountains.html">Rocky Mountains</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.guthookhikes.com/2016/08/sangre-de-cristo-backpacking-715-1916.html">Sangre de Cristo Backpacking</a>.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oA0v5OrdhUk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/Tt-7TdkYWy4">Europe’s Last Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>Are We Losing the <a href="http://www.nationalgeographic.com/magazine/2016/09/grand-canyon-development-hiking-national-parks/">Grand Canyon</a>?</p>

<p>Stefanie hikes in the <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/hoellental/">Valley of Hell</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Day 9 on the <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2016/08/13/day-9-wind-river-high-route-divide/">Wind River High Route</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/boulder-bikepacking-loop/">Boulder bikepacking Weekend loop</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28505561654/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil MiniMo and LYO Food"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8490/28505561654_12400c25f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jetboil MiniMo and LYO Food" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A <a href="http://trekking-lite-store.blogspot.fi/2016/08/sul-packliste_19.html">SUL Packlist</a>.</p>

<p>Chris reviews the book <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2016/08/book-review-walking-man-secret-life-of.html">Walking Man The Secret Life of Colin Fletcher</a> and shares his <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2016/08/thoughts-on-bivouacking.html">Thoughts on Bivouacking</a>.</p>

<p>Nice <a href="http://matthewkirk.blogspot.fi/2016/08/fundamental-footwear.html">MYOG Sandals</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://quasiout.blogspot.fi/2016/08/aquapac-aquaman-rucksack-im-bikepackig.html">Aquapac Aquaman Backpack Review</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Alex reviews the book <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/08/icefall-by-alex-staniforth-book-review.html">Icefall</a>.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=357957&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12821/357957/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear and apparel via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 245]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/twir-245.html"/>
    <updated>2016-08-15T23:50:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/twir-245</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Life is like riding a bicycle. To keep your balance, you must keep moving.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/2buXYWO">Albert Einstein</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18572119925/in/album-72157654125779966/" title="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/1/266/18572119925_6b252d11ec_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Sweet lens for backpacking: <a href="http://petapixel.com/2016/08/01/samyang-unveils-ultra-fast-35mm-f1-2-mirrorless-aps-c-cameras/">Samyang Unveils Ultra-Fast 35mm f/1.2 for Mirrorless APS-C Cameras</a>.</p>

<p>Interesting: <a href="http://www.paddlinglight.com/articles/illusory-truth-effect-sea-kayaking-sort-off-topic/">Illusory Truth Effect and Sea Kayaking</a>.</p>

<p>Needed: <a href="http://arctic-home.greenpeace.org">Save the Arctic</a>.</p>

<p>Honourable: <a href="http://www.jeepermtj.com/2016/08/aktion-schutzwald-2016-freiwillig-ins-forst-arbeitslager.html">Voluntarily cleaning up the forest</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Fun: <a href="http://www.randalolson.com/2016/07/30/the-optimal-u-s-national-parks-centennial-road-trip/">The Optimal U.S. National Parks Centennial Road Trip</a>.</p>

<p>For couples: The <a href="http://bit.ly/2bktdk1">Klymit Double V mattress</a>.</p>

<p>Insane: <a href="http://freeskier.com/stories/vail-builds-1135-mile-long-gondola-whistler-blackcomb">1,135-mile-long gondola now connects Vail and Whistler Blackcomb</a>.</p>

<p>Finds his way: <a href="http://enormocast.com/episode-110-cheyne-lempe-finding-his-way/">Cheyne Lempe</a>.</p>

<p>Different: <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plan/guide-bike-fishing/">A Guide to Bikefishing</a>.</p>

<p>Packrafts: <a href="http://bit.ly/2buXShM">3 Reasons To Use Them in Zion’s Narrows</a>.</p>

<p>Cheap: <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Backcountry Semi-Annual Sale</a>.</p>

<p>Cheaper: <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/rabatt--35-60/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> 60% off sale.</p>

<p>Cheapest: <a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/summer-sale/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk Summer Sale</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=481725&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/481725/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="486" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Leor’s <a href="https://pantilat.wordpress.com/2016/08/14/sierra-high-route/">Sierra High Route</a>. </p>

<p>How Kathrin’s <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/wanderung-grossbritannien-fazit-ausblick/">LEJOG Hike will continue</a>. [German]</p>

<p>David explores the <a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/sightseeing/exploring-backroads-of-minakami/">Backroads of Minakami</a>.</p>

<p>Day 7 on the <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2016/08/12/day-7-wind-river-high-route-thats-came/">Wind River High Route</a>.</p>

<p>Peter heads out on the <a href="http://wanderingsupnorths.blogspot.fi/2016/08/langdale-circuit-for-two-nights.html">Langdale circuit for two nights</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.shinimichi.com/2016/08/instagram-takeover-govisitdenmark.html">Instagram Takeover @GoVisitDenmark</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://sweepingthegarden.wordpress.com/2016/08/08/high-sierra-glimpses/">High Sierra Glimpses</a> from Craig.</p>

<p>A failed trip that was fun: The <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2016/not-so-soshr/">Southern Sierra High Route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://tozantales.wordpress.com/2016/08/08/myojin2/">Myojin Daira</a>, Chapter 2.</p>

<p><a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/on-a-mission-2/">On a misson</a>.</p>

<p>A visit to <a href="https://freieberge.wordpress.com/2016/08/10/ausangate-ein-zaeher-6000er/">Ausangate in the Andes</a>.</p>

<p>Roman Dials Trip Report from the Lost Coast is worth reading: <a href="http://www.revelatedesigns.com/site/index.php/misery-loves-company-guest-post-by-roman-dial-part-1/">Part 1</a>, <a href="http://www.revelatedesigns.com/site/index.php/misery-loves-company-guest-post-by-roman-dial-part-2/">Part 2</a> and <a href="http://www.revelatedesigns.com/site/index.php/misery-loves-company-guest-post-by-roman-dial-part-3/">Part 3</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/85148657?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Awesome: The <a href="https://injuringeternity.net/2016/08/15/bosnia-and-herzegovina-hobo-trip/">Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina Hobo Packrafting Trip</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kristerjonsson.se/2016/08/sale-athee-aiguille-du-moine.html">Sale Athée - Aiguille du Moine</a>.</p>

<p>Roger is waiting for the sunrise in <a href="https://nielsenbrown.com/2016/08/11/fureso-waiting-for-sunrise/">Furesø</a>.</p>

<p>Urs is with his <a href="http://idnu.ch/wordpress/family-on-tour-in-saas-fee/">Family on Tour in Saas Fee</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Packrafts: <a href="http://bit.ly/2buXShM">3 Reasons To Use Them in Zion’s Narrows</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YOqeg4CaWkA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>An awesome, <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/4196-ein-kuppelzelt/">740 g light MYOG Tent</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Useful: <a href="https://hikingaroundtheworld.wordpress.com/2016/08/13/packraft-upgrade/">Packraft seat upgrade</a>.</p>

<p>Outcozo’s <a href="http://outcozo.com/ausruestung/highlights-outdoor-friedrichshafen/">OutDoor 2016 News</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Thomas’ <a href="https://www.istdochallesnursport.de/eindruecke-von-der-outdoor-friedrichshafen.html">One Day OutDoor Impressions</a>. [German]</p>

<p>And also Charlotte ran once across the <a href="http://matschbar.com/produktneuheiten-outdoor-2016/">OutDoor 2016</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Dave reviews the <a href="https://bedrockandparadox.com/2016/08/13/osprey-poco-ag-review/">Osprey Poco AG</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://ultralightandcomfortable.com/2016/08/12/video-review-haglofs-lim-essens-down-jacket/">Haglöfs LIM Essens down jacket</a> review.</p>

<p>Jake’s <a href="http://www.barefootjake.com/2016/08/minimalist-footwear.html">Truth About Minimalist Footwear</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://quasiout.blogspot.fi/2016/08/alpkit-airlok-dual-13l-robuster.html">Alpkit Airlok Dual 13L Dry Bag</a> reviewed.</p>

<p>A tent for families: <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/test/praxistest-decathlon-zelt-freshblack-air-seconds-familiy/">Decathlon Fresh&amp;Black Air Seconds Familiy Tent</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Bikepacking With Coffee – <a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/bikepacking-coffee-aeropress-experience/">An AeroPress Experience</a>.</p>

<p>Alex’s <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/08/haute-route-pyrenees-ultralight-gear-review.html">Haute Route Pyrenees gear report</a> is worth checking out.</p>

<p>Scott’s <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/gear/scott-elite-boa-shoes/">Elite Boa</a> review. </p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=357957&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12821/357957/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear and apparel via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Outdoor 2016 News - Tents]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/outdoor-2016-news-tents.html"/>
    <updated>2016-08-12T22:47:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/outdoor-2016-news-tents</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Need a new tent? There where halls full of new tents and here’s a bunch which caught my eye.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28929325915/in/dateposted/" title="Helsport Spitsbergen X-Trem Camp"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8740/28929325915_47d23de81e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Helsport Spitsbergen X-Trem Camp" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>As an <a href="http://www.helsport.no/hendrik-morkel">Helsport Ambassador</a> I obviously wanted to swing by at my partner and see what they have in store for 2017. What I saw was very much to my ultralight heart: The Lofoten Series. Helsport has most of their designs available in three to four different versions: The Trek version, which is heavier and the most affordable option. The colour of the fly of Trek tents is always a dark green, so they’re easy to distinguish. Next up are the Pro tents, which are made from slightly better &amp; lighter materials, and they have a green-yellow-ish fly. Next up are my favourite two series: The Pro Superlight tents with the blue flysheets, which are the lightest version of each design. And finally there’s the Extreme Series with their red-yellow flysheets. These are made for expeditions in any season, are super-durable and yet relatively light. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273021860/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Helsport Lofoten Series"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8511/28273021860_9677e89067_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Helsport Lofoten Series" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28353207676/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Helsport Lofoten Superlight Camp3"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8654/28353207676_0034cf25da_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="Helsport Lofoten Superlight Camp3" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That above is the <strong>Lofoten Superlight Camp 3</strong> tent, a 3-person tunnel tent which weighs 1.850 g. It has two doors in the spacious vestibule which has enough space for cooking and gear. As you can see at the Pro Camp underneath, the front also can be stored completely away, allowing for lots of ventilation and great views from the sleeping area. The large vestibule is also great for those of us who travel with a large dog, a packraft or bike as there’s plenty of space for storage.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273022640/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Helsport Lofoten Series"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8568/28273022640_5e3d0ff397_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Helsport Lofoten Series" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Lofoten Trek Camp</strong> tent above is available as a 3 and 5 person version. The 3-Person tent weighs 4.050 g and the 5-Person tent 4.800 g, so they’re better for short hiking or when you’re out with a canoe or bike. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273023210/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Helsport Lofoten Series"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8743/28273023210_bd0a50fc72_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Helsport Lofoten Series" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And the <strong>Lofoten X-Trem Camp 3</strong> tent here is the expedition version from the bunch. At 3.700 g it is best transported on a Pulka, but the DAC Featherlight NSL poles in combination with the design should withstand even the hardest wind gusts out in the fjell in winter. The sleeping compartment is 105 cm high, 220 cm long and 165 cm wide, so it is cozy but not too tight. Add in a 160 cm long vestibule and you have enough space for lots of kit and cooking. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28626218950/in/dateposted/" title="Helsport Bitihorn X-Trem Tarp"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8575/28626218950_4b58c508e4_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Helsport Bitihorn X-Trem Tarp" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s the <strong>Bitihorn X-Trem Tarp</strong> above, which also will be again as a Trek, Pro and Superlight Version. The X-Trem above is 435 cm x 435 cm large and is 1.340 g light, which is pretty good for such a massive tarp. The slightly smaller Superlight Tarp (350 cm long and 290 cm wide) is 400 g, which is pretty amazing if it is true. There will be poles available which are between 132 cm and 176 cm long and weigh 70 g and 220 g respectively. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273009790/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8897/28273009790_362c568d6d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28626219560/in/dateposted/" title="Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7772/28626219560_855c658bbe_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28626220770/in/dateposted/" title="Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8105/28626220770_f5e3f06e06_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273015090/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Nordisk Lofoten"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8318/28273015090_e94812efe9_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Nordisk Lofoten" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW</strong> above aims for the throne of the lightest tent in the world, and with a packed weight of 575 g incl. pegs and poles and guylines it is pretty close to that throne. But how about the usability? Well, the seating height is 70 cm, which is pretty low, even for a small guy like me. People with big feet also might find the end of the tent constricting, For smaller backpackers who can cook with fair weather in front of the tent it might be good, but we longer people might find it a bit too small. I will sit back and wait what real-world reviews will say about the tent, and while the weight is exciting there’s a reason why Pyramide shelters are so popular: They’re even lighter and have plenty of room.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28626218200/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Therm-A-Rest Tranquility 6 Tent"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8491/28626218200_8c2db08e39_h.jpg" width="1067" height="1600" alt="Therm-A-Rest Tranquility 6 Tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Talking of plenty of space, here’s a tent for Camping Enthusiasts: The <strong>Therm-A-Rest Tranquility 6 Tent</strong>. This two entry, two compartment, standing height tent is a great addition to the quiver if family Camping is in the books. Therm-A-Rest, which belongs to the Cascade family, picked the brains of the MSR tent designers while designing this tent, so expect this V 1.0 being actually quite good. It looked easy to pitch, with smart details like the protected corners in the entry for gear storage out of the muck and plenty of mesh inside pockets for storage. Certainly nothing for the UL backpacker, but if said UL backpacker takes the family along to a camping ground a good way to make all feel comfortable.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28557078565/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="MSR Advance Pro 2"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8835/28557078565_feefc19d82_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1329" alt="MSR Advance Pro 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450555352/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="MSR Advance Pro 2"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8180/28450555352_7c96c2b56d_h.jpg" width="1067" height="1600" alt="MSR Advance Pro 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28557077825/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="MSR Advance Pro 2"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8862/28557077825_f9424464c8_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="MSR Advance Pro 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28557077365/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="MSR Advance Pro 2"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8884/28557077365_c07e9eccb3_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="MSR Advance Pro 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A tent used by <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">Ueli Steck</a> is the <strong>MSR Advance Pro 2</strong>. Ueli was let go by MH earlier this year and was happy to find a new home with MSR, and the Advance Pro 2 certainly looks like a great home away form the basecamp. It’s made for expedition use in demanding environments, but also should stand up to the elements in the hills and fjells of lesser ranges. It uses Easton Syclone poles which are made from aerospace-grade composite materials, which can flex further &amp; take more abuse than any other pole material - which makes them probably the most resilient tent pole ever made. It is pretty spacious for one and cozy for two, easy to set up and the small footprint also fits on narrow snow ledges high up. At 585€ it is not cheap, but hey - few tents are!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273023950/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="4,99 € Tent"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8310/28273023950_093ad10ae2_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="4,99 € Tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But if you prefer cheap, I found this gem of a tent. At 4,99€ the price is unbeatable, however, I reckon that’s what the lady charges you only if you order a significant quantity of these. You could gift all your friends and family for years to come with such a fine tent, though, if you decide to walk down that road.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450559352/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Marmot Bolt 2P tent"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8615/28450559352_06a898c045_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Marmot Bolt 2P tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450559922/in/album-72157667997710903/" title="Marmot Bolt 2P tent"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8635/28450559922_75b7b5d1b0_h.jpg" width="1067" height="1600" alt="Marmot Bolt 2P tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Slightly more expensive, but undoubtedly better constructed &amp; designed is the <strong>Marmot Bolt 2P tent</strong>. Steep side walls ensure plenty of head room and a feeling of space in the 1.040 g light tent, and at 500€ it is also not overly expensive. The flysheet is highly waterproof and also UV resistent, which is good news for the longevity of the tent. There’s space for kit and cooking in the vestibule as I demonstrate so professionally above, and on the inside you also find Lamp-Shade-Pockets which diffuse the light of your headlamp for nice atmospheric light inside. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28313293173/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Hogan SUL 1-2P"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8399/28313293173_97ea914ff8_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Vaude Hogan SUL 1-2P" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And lastly a quick look at the new tents from Vaude. I already shed some light on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-first-gear-teasers.html">Hogan SUL 1-2P</a> and also in real life it looked good. A good seating height for me, a large vestibule and an overall streamlined and smooth design will make this already popular tent probably even more popular in the future. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28313294233/in/photostream/" title="Vaude Invenio SUL 2P Tent"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8589/28313294233_b55f848b08_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Vaude Invenio SUL 2P Tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28313295043/in/photostream/" title="Vaude Invenio SUL 2P Tent"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8815/28313295043_3c7efb1e02_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Vaude Invenio SUL 2P Tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Vaude Invenio SUL 2P Tent</strong> got an overhaul for 2017, and the tent poles went now under the fly. Design-wise it reminded me of the Hubba/ Soloplex/ Notch shelters, with two doors opposite of each other. The flysheet can be rolled up on both sides for wide views outside and also otherwise this tent has all the bells and whistles along which you want from a tent.</p>

<p>Benjamin from hrXXLight also highlights <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-news/#more-2405">some new tents</a>, and if you were this year at the OutDoor and have a post with tents online, please comment with a link and I’ll add it here!</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: I’m a Helsport Ambassador and have cooperated with some of the companies in this article in the past. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28313295923/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude tents"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7596/28313295923_889b42ddec_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Vaude tents" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycling & Bouldering on Åland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/cycling-and-bouldering-on-aland.html"/>
    <updated>2016-08-10T23:39:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/cycling-and-bouldering-on-aland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Three times a charm, they say. My love affair with Åland went into the third round last week as I was photographing a story for the <a href="http://www.norrmagazin.de">NORR</a> and <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/365klubi/365-lehti">365 Magazine</a> about cycling, bouldering and sea kayaking on the beautiful Åland Archipelago between Finland and Sweden. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810987961/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Cloudporn over the Baltic."><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8358/28810987961_443a331b7c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Cloudporn over the Baltic." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/aland-in-winter.html">The last time I was on Åland</a> was just in January, and how different it was back then: The roads under snow and ice, the Baltic partially frozen, a cold wind blowing. But it was also similar to the previous <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/bouldering-on-aland.html">bouldering trip to Åland</a> and this visit: The people were fantastic and made the trip even more memorable. Which made me realize once more: It’s more beautiful to share an outdoor adventure with friends. Sure it is nice to watch the sun set over the sea, but it is more fun to share that moment with a good friend. It’s cool if you topped out on your route, but it’s cooler if you have a friend to high-five with to celebrate that success. And while Sauna is always great, also on your own, it’s much better with friends who share your passion for a good <em>löyly</em>. So when you head out on your next outdoor adventure, take someone along: Your partner, kids, mate or someone who shares the same love for the outdoors than you do. I’m certain the trip will be more fun &amp; memorable for both of you =) </p>

<p>So much for advice, here’s a couple of B-Roll photos and one-liners to wet your appetite to head over to Åland with a bike and Crashpad on your back.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810986921/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="On the way onto the ferry"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8701/28810986921_d281162f39_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="On the way onto the ferry" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Kathrin from <a href="http://luminoucity.net">Luminoucity</a>, Kristof and me rolling onto the ferry by bike. My first time to roll on a bike onto a ferry, and a good one. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810987461/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Good Bye Helsinki"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8424/28810987461_9fe00bcb5c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Good Bye Helsinki" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We said Good-By to Helsinki on the sun deck, sans sun.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28269451094/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Morning cycling through along the fields"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7783/28269451094_8364170fbc_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Morning cycling through along the fields" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At dawn we arrived on Åland and started to cycle up north to <a href="http://www.havsvidden.com">HavsVidden</a> past golden fields and a rising sun. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810986491/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Kristof at Kasviken"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7730/28810986491_0b29a9ae18_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="Kristof at Kasviken" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We slipped in a session at Kasviken as it was so conveniently on the way. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810986241/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Relaxing at HavsVidden"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8846/28810986241_95f636f677_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="Relaxing at HavsVidden" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After that it was pretty chill at the beach house. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://amzn.to/2beNxGI" title="The Best We Can Do Is Nothing"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8160/28798090366_542e2ab604_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="The Best We Can Do Is Nothing" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I read an <a href="http://amzn.to/2beNxGI">inspiring book</a> the next morning, which motivated me to do… nothing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28798090286/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Relaxing at Fågelberget"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8269/28798090286_a9f93a9c13_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Relaxing at Fågelberget" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In between bouts of work I succeeded in following the books advice.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28855542636/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Stallhagen Beers are tasty!"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8646/28855542636_ea16422b1f_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Stallhagen Beers are tasty!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then I failed pretty badly by cycling close to 46 km to go eat at <a href="http://www.stallhagen.com/en/?ageok=yes">Stallhagen</a>, and yes, drink some of their fantastic beers. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28855541356/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Pelago Bicycles Capri"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8895/28855541356_f75340ee58_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Pelago Bicycles Capri" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>My friends were very happy with their <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com">Pelago Bicycles</a>, here the pretty <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com/bicycles/capri.html">Capri</a> which Vera rode.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810989711/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Portrait Sessions"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8776/28810989711_fe8e83bd40_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Portrait Sessions" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I myself had my much loved <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Stavanger</a> along, which performed flawlessly once again. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810989151/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="On the way back to Mariehamn from Kobba Klintar"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8695/28810989151_1951188c9e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="On the way back to Mariehamn from Kobba Klintar" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Jonas from <a href="http://www.paddelboden.com">The Paddle Shack</a> took us out to Kobba Klintar, the old pilot station which is really a great destination for a day of paddling. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28798090336/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Seakayaking with Paddelboden"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8895/28798090336_ebc0d4057a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="Seakayaking with Paddelboden" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the way back we had back wind and choppy seas, so it was nice when we weaved back into the Archipelago and let ourselves just drift in the wind back towards the shack. Then it was just about cycling back to the ferry harbour and waiting for our big boat back to Helsinki. It was once again a fantastic visit and I can highly recommend you to spend a week or more on Åland if you’re into any of the above activities. And I’ll let you know where to read the good story and see the proper photos when it’s out!</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> I was invited to Åland to photograph a story for <a href="http://www.norrmagazin.de">NORR magazine</a> which you can read next summer. Thanks to <a href="http://www.visitaland.com">Visit Åland</a> and its partners who supported us with this trip. A huge thanks also to <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com">Pelago Bicycles</a> and <a href="http://www.gamlastanscykel.se">Gamla Stan Cykel</a> for the awesome bicycles and <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en_FI/homepage">Black Diamond</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.oacsport.fi">OAC</a> for loaning us the crashpads. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 244]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/twir-244.html"/>
    <updated>2016-08-07T23:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/twir-244</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Ocean is more ancient than the mountains, and freighted with the memories and the dreams of Time.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/2aSxlsW">H. P. Lovecraft</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28798090336/in/dateposted/" title="Seakayaking with Paddelboden"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8895/28798090336_ebc0d4057a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="Seakayaking with Paddelboden" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>I’m humbled to have made Place 1 of the <a href="http://noplacelikeout.com/top-25-outdoor-bloggers/">Top 25 Awesome Outdoor Bloggers You Need To Follow Right Now</a> List! Check out the other fine blogs and find new outdoor inspiration from across the globe!</p>

<p>Garage Grown Gear has a <a href="http://bit.ly/2as7LwJ">sweet ultralight giveaway</a> going on with prices from Enlightened Equipment, Roscoe Outdoor, Hummingbird Hammocks, Cloudline Apparel and Outpost Titanium.</p>

<p>Abenteuersuechtig’s <a href="http://www.abenteuersuechtig.de/index.php/outdoor-2016-die-highlights-der-outdoorbranche/">OutDoor 2016 Highlights</a> are worth checking out! [German]</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/717365321/tenkara-the-book">tenkara book</a>.</p>

<p>Win an <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">Ortovox Outfit</a>! [German]</p>

<p>The <a href="http://gossamergear.com/the-one-shelter.html">Gossamer Gear “The One”</a> is available again after many year of absence. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4BFQIyhGiW8">The Zeroth Law of Packrafting</a>, Luc Mehl’s Keyote from the Annual Packrafting Meet-up.</p>

<p>Cool: <a href="http://www.collective-evolution.com/2016/03/10/the-shazam-for-plants-will-identify-any-plant-from-a-picture/">Shazam for plants</a>.</p>

<p>Martin’s <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/weitwander-rueckblick-juli-2016/">Long Distance Hiking Review</a> for July is out. [German]</p>

<p>And also <a href="http://www.trailgroove.com/issue29.html">Trail Groove Issue 29</a> is now available for your online reading pleasure. </p>

<p>It’s that time of the year again: The <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Backcountry Semi-Annual Sale</a> tempts you with up to 50% off clothing, gear &amp; accessories and Free 2-Day Shipping.</p>

<p>Also <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/rabatt--35-60/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> have heaps of kit reduced up to 60%. </p>

<p>And the <a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/summer-sale/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk Summer Sale</a> is massive with close to 6000 items being reduced up to 70%.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=314573&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12493/314573/55699/73183/image.gif" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reviews">Trip Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2016/08/tesoros-escondidos-hidden-treasures.html">Hidden Treasures</a>, great photos and story from bikepacking in the Ecuadorian Andes.</p>

<p><a href="https://freieberge.wordpress.com/2016/08/02/krottenspitzen-der-laengste-allgaeuer-grat/">The longest ridge of the Allgäu</a> looks pretty fantastic. [German]</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/bikepacking-annapurna/">Bikepacking the Annapurna Circuit</a> trip report is splendid and well worth a read. </p>

<p>Timo shares some beautiful impressions from <a href="http://www.timoanttalainen.com/2016/08/inarijarvi.html">Inarijärvi</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://quasiout.blogspot.fi/2016/08/auf-der-suche-nach-gravel-bikepacking.html">Gravelbike needs Gravel</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Alex shares some <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/08/photos-from-the-pyrenees.html">photos from the Pyrenees</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2016/08/rollins-pass.html">Rollins Pass</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/173908956?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Simon’s first <a href="http://simon-willis.blogspot.fi/2016/08/my-first-ironman-maastricht-2016.html">Ironman in Maastricht</a> was inspiring to read. </p>

<p>Lael’s <a href="https://laelwilcox.com/2016/08/03/trans-am-bike-race-2016-idaho/">Trans Am 2016: Idaho</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2016/08/greatwesternramble-bikefishing-the-bitterroot-300/">Bikefishing the Bitterroot 300</a>.</p>

<p>The river <a href="https://mitsackundpackraft.wordpress.com/2016/08/01/die-alz-mit-fahrrad-und-packraft/">Alz with bike &amp; packraft</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://mountaincoastriver.blogspot.fi/2016/08/beginning-book-shetland-in-july.html">The Kayak Down Atlantic Shetland</a>.</p>

<p>Photos from <a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.fi/2016/08/black-crook-peak-sheeprock-range-utah.html">Black Crook Peak, Sheeprock Range, Utah</a>.</p>

<p>Nice little hike to the <a href="http://biwak.blogspot.fi/2016/08/pazolastock-2740m.html">Pazolastock</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/2aDJ6Ar">Alaska Mountain Wilderness Classic</a>, 2016 Edition.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28798090366/in/dateposted/" title="The Best We Can Do Is Nothing"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8160/28798090366_542e2ab604_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="The Best We Can Do Is Nothing" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Wired reviews the <a href="http://www.wired.com/2016/07/review-yi-4k-action-camera/">Yi 4K Action Camera</a>.</p>

<p>Sven takes a look at my <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2016/08/outdoor-wanderfuehrer-finnland-pirkan-taival/">Pirkan Taival Guide Book</a> - Thanks! You can <a href="http://amzn.to/2aS5Srw">order it here</a>, by the way.</p>

<p>Jake reviews the <a href="http://www.barefootjake.com/2016/08/bedrock-cairn-sandals.html">Bedrock Cairn Sandals</a>, while Derek tests the <a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2016/08/crosskix-2-0/">Crosskix 2.0 Supreme Multi-sport Shoes</a>.</p>

<p>Matt shares tips for an <a href="http://matthewkirk.blogspot.fi/2016/08/do-it-yourself-trail-tracker.html">Do-it-yourself trail tracker</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/tipps/outdoor-zitat-des-monats-august-2016-optimal-vor-sonnenbrand-schuetzen/">First Aid for Sun Burns</a>. [German]</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=357957&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12821/357957/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear and apparel via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 243]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/twir-243.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-31T23:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/twir-243</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Those who travel to mountain-tops are half in love with themselves, and half in love with oblivion.”</em> ― <a href="http://amzn.to/2aCWQAd">Robert Macfarlane</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28200770821/in/dateposted/" title="Snowy Ljuboten Summit ridge"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8758/28200770821_32314b8225_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Snowy Ljuboten Summit ridge" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.astucas.com/en/products/">Free shipping on all As Tucas orders</a> in the European Union! </p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/sales-and-special-offers">PHD Minimus tops</a> are now lighter and more fully featured. </p>

<p>Have a tear in your favourite jacket? That new backpack has a small cut? Then get the awesome <a href="http://bit.ly/2arA5Lv">Noso Patch</a> which fixes your kit in seconds, all without ironing or sewing!</p>

<p>Nom nom, that’s tasty: The new <a href="http://bit.ly/2amzQqw">Wild Lummi Island Pink Salmon</a> from Patagonia Provisions is wild pink salmon, sourced only from abundant, thriving runs. Sustainable backpacking food at its best! </p>

<p>I was interviewed for the <a href="http://www.outdoordeals.de/magazin/unser-blog-des-monats-hikinginfinland-com/">Blog of the Month on Outdoordeals.de</a>! [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://www.thebmc.co.uk/bmc-to-change-its-name-to-climb-britain">BMC to change its name to Climb Britain</a>. As a climber I like it, as a hillwalker, backpacker and hiker I find that questionable. </p>

<p>Not as off-topic as it may seem: <a href="https://medium.com/@theonlytoby/history-tells-us-what-will-happen-next-with-brexit-trump-a3fefd154714#.al1k5for1">History tells us what may happen next with Brexit &amp; Trump</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LfgyoEBgKxU&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;a">Erin has no idea what she’s doing with her Vlog</a>. Episode 0 is cool nevertheless!</p>

<p>Making the Experience Yours: <a href="https://chasingmailboxes.com/2016/07/24/making-the-experience-yours-randonneuring/">Randonneuring</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://wickedoutdoorsy.blogspot.fi/2016/07/this-land-is-your-land-until-its-not.html">This land is your land. Until it’s not</a>.</p>

<p>Neil ponders is <a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/salsa-cycles-teams-rei/">Adventure Goes Mainstream</a> since Salsa Cycles will be available in REI.</p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/2anRGq6">Save 30% and more on your favourite gear from Patagonia</a>!</p>

<p>There’s <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=78977&amp;pw=73183">new gear in the REI Outlet</a> - save big on new closeouts from Osprey, SmartWool, Black Diamond, Big Agnes &amp; More!</p>

<p>And there’s a bunch of <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/marken/icebreaker/outdoor-ausruestung/?bfc-marke[]=salomon&amp;bfc-marke[]=mountain-hardwear&amp;bfc-marke[]=osprey&amp;bfc-marke[]=schoeffel&amp;bfc-marke[]=berghaus/?pid=10239">outdoor gear in the Bergfreunde Sale</a> that’s worth checking out, like the 1.226 g light <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/mountain-hardwear-ghost-ul-3-kuppelzelt/?pid=10239">Mountain Hardwear Ghost UL 3 tent</a>, the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/osprey-exos-48-tourenrucksack/?pid=10239">Osprey Exos backpacks</a> and the even lighter <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/salomon-x-alp-30-tourenrucksack/?pid=10239">Salomon X Alp 30</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=481725&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/481725/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="486" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Antoine Girard has <a href="http://www.xcmag.com/2016/07/antoine-girard-breaks-8100m-in-karakoram/">broken the 8,000m mark in high-altitude cross-country paragliding</a>, soaring Broad Peak.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.packgofind.com/a-beach-and-a-big-tree">beach and a big tree</a>.</p>

<p>Interesting: <a href="http://www.twistingspokes.com/returning-europe-turkey/">Returning through Europe - Turkey</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://willgadd.com/looking-fear-in-the-eye/">Looking Fear In The Eye</a>.</p>

<p>Lael’s <a href="https://laelwilcox.com/2016/07/26/2016-so-far/">2016</a> looks pretty epic so far.</p>

<p><a href="http://alpine-works.com/2016/07/the-tour-de-14ers/">The Tour de 14ers</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin’s <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/nervige-dinge-wanderung-grossbritannien/">Top 5 of most annoying things on her LEJOG</a> thus far. [German]</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/176729362?portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://universalklister.blogspot.fi/2016/07/the-sharpest-end.html">The sharpest end</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2016/07/packrafting-in-neuseelands.html">Packrafting in New Zealand</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Great <a href="https://pantilat.wordpress.com/2016/07/29/sierra-adventures-update/">Sierra Adventures Update</a> from Leor. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/bikepacking-reunion-island/">Bikepacking Reunion Island</a>.</p>

<p>Joe spent <a href="https://joecruz.wordpress.com/2016/07/30/three-days-on-the-colorado-trail/">three days on the Colorado Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/a-backyard-tour/">A backyard tour</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28557078565/" title="MSR Advance Pro 2"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8835/28557078565_e6d3e3bb18_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1701" alt="MSR Advance Pro 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Stuff that works - <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2016/7/28/stuff-that-works-dirty-girl-gaiters">Dirty Girl Gaiters</a>.</p>

<p>A First Look at the <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/gear/salsa-exp-series-bikepacking-bags/">Salsa EXP Series Bikepacking Bags</a>.</p>

<p>Dirtbag Climbers: <a href="https://fortheloveofclimbing.com/2016/07/26/dbc-handmade-climbing-goods-with-a-touch-of-beard/">Handmade climbing goods with a touch of beard</a>.</p>

<p>Review of the <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2016/07/review-la-sportiva-tx2-approach-shoe/">La Sportiva TX2 Approach Shoe</a>.</p>

<p>Ultralight Backpacking: <a href="http://bit.ly/2aUnYaS">Stay safe, warm, well-fed and happy</a>.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=467762&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/13582/467762/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="320" height="50" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear and apparel via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Outdoor 2016 News - Stoves, Waterfilters & Accessories]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-news-stoves.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-26T23:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-news-stoves</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new approach to OutDoor News posts this year, with a look at different categories instead of brands. Starting of with everyone’s favourite: Stoves!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273014340/in/dateposted/" title="Fjällräven"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8566/28273014340_deff01d426_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fjällräven" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I didn’t find too many new stoves this year, which I blame on my severely limited time at the show to walk around and visit the different booths. But at least I managed to see and play with two stoves on the fair, of which I found the <strong>Jetboil MightyMo</strong> the more interesting one. At 95 g it certainly isn’t the lightest stove around, especially if you factor in an additional windscreen and pot, but if we look at the stove only we see it is actually a pretty powerful little thing. It packs 10.000 BTU which is around 3.000 Watt in case these matters to you, in practice it means you can boil water &amp; melt snow at high altitude - although the reliable regulator is more responsible for that. It has a Piezo ignition which is comfortable and nice in use, and the output can be finely adjusted allowing you to simmer, cook or just boil. It is compatible with the <a href="http://bit.ly/2at9tLU">Jetboil FluxRing pans</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/2aqgAXf">pots</a> which have heat exchangers and works well with them. The MightyMo should retail in Europe for 59€ next year, while US Americans already will be able to buy it in the autumn.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27770563373/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil MightyMo"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8644/27770563373_5ebae1a1f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="790" alt="Jetboil MightyMo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28557073615/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil MightyMo"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8104/28557073615_809bda104c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jetboil MightyMo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28557073845/in/dateposted/" title="Jetboil MightyMo"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8302/28557073845_d7ca7e0f0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jetboil MightyMo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>MSR PocketRocket 2</strong> combines the MicroRocket’s light weight with the durability and quick boil time of the PocketRocket and also is more compact and stable as its predecessor. It is now 73 g light, 20% smaller as the original and boils one litre of water in 3,5 minutes. The new pot supports accommodate a wider range of pot sizes. No info on output, price and how reliable it would work at high altitude.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450555872/in/dateposted/" title="MSR Pocket Rocket 2"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8753/28450555872_484d88fdaf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="MSR Pocket Rocket 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450555672/in/dateposted/" title="MSR Pocket Rocket 2"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8169/28450555672_544682e074_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="MSR Pocket Rocket 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So much on stoves, lets stay with MSR and look at the new <strong>TrailShot Microfilter</strong>. Made for trailrunners &amp; hikers who do not want to carry much water on their runs &amp; hikes, this filter is a combination of a hose and filter. It’s pretty easy to use: Drop the hose into the water source - a stream in the mountains, a lake in the woods or even a puddle - and then squeeze the filter. The squeezing sucks water into the filter, and at the front, mouth piece clean &amp; filtered water comes out. The filter takes out Protozoa and bacteria, and weighs 142 g for the Filter &amp; Hose. The flow rate of 1 litre per minute is reasonably fast and you can treat up to 2.000 l of water with it. It should cost 50€ in Germany when it comes out next year.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450556132/in/dateposted/" title="MSR TrailShot Microfilter"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8596/28450556132_1793a116b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="MSR TrailShot Microfilter" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-first-gear-teasers.html">teaser post</a> I already looked at the <strong>Katadyn BeFree</strong> and it was cool to see one in action at the fair. It’s a nifty setup that weighs only 55 g including the 0,5 l Hydrapak Softflask. The filter is easy to clean and has a high output rate. The filter itself is good for 1.000 l of dirty water, then you can replace the filter unit for 35€ - given that the whole package is 45€ it’s a bit expensive for just the filter me thinks, but if your Softflask is still OK why replace it? Rumours on the show floor have it that there will be bigger flasks coming in 2017 as well as a possible system, but as the filter does already fit on bigger Hydrapak softflasks you could just use on of these already.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28557076125/in/photostream/" title="Katadyn BeFree"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8839/28557076125_e24b4950fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Katadyn BeFree" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Do you like to make pretty night time photos of your illuminated tent under the Milky Way? Read a book before you turn it? Need some light to search something in your tent at night? Then the <strong>Petzl Noctilight</strong> might be something for you. Put your Petzl Headlamp in there during transport or at camp, put it on and it will diffuse the light beautifully for reading, searching and taking photos. It’s 85 g heavy, so if you’re an ultralight backpacker you need to ponder hard if it comes along, but for glamping it will be a great little accessory.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273018650/in/dateposted/" title="Petzl Noctilight"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8572/28273018650_2f7a65181b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Noctilight" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273018930/in/dateposted/" title="Petzl Noctilight"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8802/28273018930_e0b42e7711_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Noctilight" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273019360/in/dateposted/" title="Petzl Noctilight"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8619/28273019360_9d267ba632_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Noctilight" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <em>HYBRID design allows Petzl’s new compact headlamps to run off both the CORE rechargeable battery or three AAA/LR03 batteries, without an adapter. A practical and flexible solution that allows the user to take advantage of each of these energy sources, depending on use. Compatible with all TIKKINA, TIKKA, ZIPKA, ACTIK, ACTIK CORE, TACTIKKA, TACTIKKA+ and TACTIKKA +RGB headlamps.</em> The CORE rechargeable battery weighs 23 g and can be recharged via the USB port of your headlamp or directly, as the CORE also has a mini USB port.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273017340/in/dateposted/" title="Petzl Hybrid battery"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7649/28273017340_89d1161484_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Hybrid battery" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Petzl eLite</strong> comes back, this time around with 50 Lumen at 27 g of weight. It keeps the red light, strobes, the whistle in the back and is still powered by two Lithium CR032 batteries. It now also has the red carrying case included again, and has a recommended retail price of 25€. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28453267462/in/dateposted/" title="Petzl eLite"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8726/28453267462_4d19cd7388_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl eLite" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Other Petzl headlamps have got minor updates - you know the drill: More lumen, new colours. But the <strong>Actik and Actik Core Headlamps</strong> are actually new and aimed at active people, or to be more precise as everyone that walks around outside in the dark is active: Active people who need lots of light and go fast. The Actik packs 300 Lumen and is designed for mountaineering, running, hiking and backpacking at night. It has red light for keeping your night vision, and reflective details on the headband make you visible to others outside in the dark. It works with the CORE rechargeable battery, weighs 90 g and should cost only 40€! The big brother Actik Core packs 350 Lumen, weighs only 80 g and costs only 55€. The CORE battery is included, hence the Core in the name. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273018200/in/dateposted/" title="Petzl Actik and Actik Core Headlamps"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8785/28273018200_a8d455583c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Actik and Actik Core Headlamps" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another light and rechargeable headlamp is the <strong>Black Diamond Iota</strong>. The 56 g light (and that’s including batteries) headlamp packs 150 Lumen and is powered by an lithium ion rechargeable battery which is loaded in three hours via USB. The Iota also has the PowerTap Technology which allows you to fast and simply transition between full and dimmed power, and a 3-level power meter shows the remaining battery life for three seconds after you switch on the headlamp. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273011820/in/dateposted/" title="Black Diamond Iota"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8589/28273011820_0eaa8b11da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Black Diamond Iota" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I’m a collapsible and Kuksa kind of man, but as I was strolling past the <strong>SIGG</strong> booth I was shang-haied in by a PR Person and informed about the new bottles from the Swiss company. So let me briefly tell you about them as well, alrighty? The <strong>Miracle Bottle</strong> on the far right (the blue one in case you don’t remember where right is) has a <em>revolutionary drinking cap that allows the desired amount of water to be released simply by pressing an ergonomic button</em>. Made of Tritan it holds 0,6 l of your favourite liquid. As stats such as weight and prize are often not of importance to PR people and I was in a hurry onwards and couldn’t be bothered to ask via Email we’ll need to find out next year when one of us buys it and weighs it. Lets ignore the green bottle next in line and move on to the grey-ish one, the <strong>Hero Bottle</strong>. It has a Tritan bottle neck and a polypropylene body that can be squeezed. It has also a 0,6 l volume, is Made in Germany and is easy to use with one hand, SIGG writes. Which brings us to the last bottle in the line-up on the left, the <strong>Total Clear Bottle</strong>. It is heat resistant and dishwasher safe, made in China from Tritan and has a SIGG Wide Mouth Bottle One Top lid which <em>allows you to fill up the bottle simply without having to remove the lid</em>. The volume is 0,75 l and it’s also possible to fill carbonated drinks in it. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28273011380/in/dateposted/" title="SIGG Bottles"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8559/28273011380_b0600c69a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SIGG Bottles" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Roll Doc from Ortovox</strong> is an emergency kit which you can roll up. It packs compact when not needed and in case of an emergency you roll it open where it reveals five compartments with different First Aid supplies, from an emergency blanket to scissors and bandages. The Roll Doc weighs 190 g fully filled, is waterproof and has illustrations on the inside which help you figure out how to help your injured friend.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450557642/in/dateposted/" title="Ortovox Roll Doc"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7565/28450557642_85bae9a895_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ortovox Roll Doc" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450557932/in/dateposted/" title="Ortovox Roll Doc"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8204/28450557932_96a58d2415_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ortovox Roll Doc" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And finally a look at a new knife. The <strong>Morakniv Eldris</strong> is 76 g light for knife &amp; sheath (the knife itself is 60 g light) and lays beautifully in the hand. It’s gonna be available later in the autumn of this year, in five colours which show the general trend of colours for the next few years: More toned down &amp; earthy. This fixed blade does actually fit into your pocket and super versatile in use: Take it along hiking &amp; camping, use it as a safety knife when climbing or even take it hunting. The thermoplastic rubber on the handle ensures a safe grip of the little knife, which is 143 mm long in total. The blade is 56 mm long, which theoretically would even make it carry-on compliant, but I wouldn’t try that personally. You can use the back of the blade to strike a firesteel, and indeed the Eldris is available in a set with a lanyard and firesteel. I might do a more detailed review on this little friend in the future, as I already have one!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28450556772/in/dateposted/" title="Morakniv Eldirs"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7660/28450556772_cc449348a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Morakniv Eldirs" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear and apparel via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 242]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/twir-242.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-24T23:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/twir-242</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Every mountain top is within reach if you just keep climbing.”</em> ― <a href="http://amzn.to/2aapGaO">Barry Finlay</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28244650176/in/dateposted/" title="Ljuboten Summit in the far distance"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8655/28244650176_d525edab57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ljuboten Summit in the far distance" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>I joined <a href="http://www.helsport.no/hendrik-morkel">Helsport</a> as an Ambassador and will be testing their tents and backpacks in the next years, and I am looking forward to try their packs which can carry a lot of kit and sleep with the family in their tents!</p>

<p>Trailrunning has its first Doping Scandal, as <a href="http://trailblog.de/doping-gonzalo-calisto-auf-epo-beim-utmb/">Gonzalo Calisto was on EOP at the UTMB</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Sadly the Freeriding community is mourning another of their own as <a href="http://wepowder.com/forum/topic/228591">Matilda Rapaport died in Chile</a>.</p>

<p>Marmot vs. Pikachu: <a href="http://www.bergwelten.com/blog/pokemon-go-am-berg">Pokémon Go on the mountains</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://adventure-journal.com/2016/07/the-disturbing-bro-ification-of-outdoor-recreation">The Disturbing Bro-ification of Outdoor Recreation</a>.</p>

<p>First time planning to go outdoors? Then check out the <a href="http://www.ut.no/fjellvettreglene/#fjellvettreglene">Fjellvettreglene</a>. [Norwegian]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2016/07/the-future-of-chris-townsend-outdoors.html">The Future of Chris Townsend Outdoors</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://semi-rad.com/2016/07/us-vs-us/">Us vs. Us</a>, a great piece by Brendan on the Hardrock 100 and the current political and human atmosphere.</p>

<p>Walking Man: <a href="http://amzn.to/29Xjhwp">The Secret Life of Colin Fletcher</a> is now out on Kindle.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/vari-fill-down-sleeping-bag">PHD Vari-Fill Down Sleeping Bag</a> is pretty cool - if they now would make it as a quilt, that’d be swell! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/area47-2016/">Win a canyoning trip</a>!</p>

<p>Lots of #OutDoorFN Posts are already up: </p>

<p>Chris looks back on the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/the-outdoor-2016-friedrichshafen%EF%BB%BF/">2016 OutDoor</a>.</p>

<p>Carsten was <a href="http://vitaminberge.de/s001-carsten-jost-zum-outdoor-blogger-network/">interviewed about the Outdoor Blogger Network</a> by Robert from Vitamin Berge. [German]</p>

<p>Robert also shows his <a href="http://vitaminberge.de/outdoor-friedrichshafen-top-10-messestaende/">ten favourite booths</a> at the show. [German]</p>

<p>Tina &amp; Daniel found a lot of <a href="http://lifeforfive.com/outdoor-2016/">sustainable &amp; fair-trade manufactured gear</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Simon looks <a href="http://www.simonpatur.de/wo-bitte-gehts-zu-gutem-content-die-outdoor-messe-2016/">where it goes to good content</a> at the OutDoor. [German]</p>

<p>Chris Townsend tells about <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2016/07/the-future-of-chris-townsend-outdoors.html">the future of his blog</a>.</p>

<p>Find out about the Idea Behind the <a href="http://www.travelingjackie.com/patagonia-2016-idea-behind-adventure/">Patagonia 2016 Adventure</a>.</p>

<p>Keep an eye on the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=36365&amp;pw=73183">Sale &amp; Clearance Items at REI.com</a> as the summer sale starts.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/p/100-articles-on-sale/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde.co.uk have lots of gear up to 50% off</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28933&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28933/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="468" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://unclippedadventure.com/wp/and-so-it-begins/">And so it begins</a>.</p>

<p>Lots of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/multi-adventures-in-macedonia.html">Adventures in Macedonia</a>.</p>

<p>Beardoh and SweetPea arrived at the <a href="http://longdistancehiker.com/pct-73-lassen-volcanic-national-park/">Lassen Volcanic National Park</a> on their PCT hike.</p>

<p><a href="https://heatherclimbs.com/2016/07/23/china-doll-dreams-come-true/">China Doll dreams come through</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://lesserplaces.wordpress.com/2016/07/21/on-knowing-when-to-turn-the-f-around/">On Knowing when to Turn the F*** Around</a>.</p>

<p>Beautiful hike to <a href="http://cbjimtrip.blogspot.fi/2016/07/blog-post_23.html">Mount Tengu</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uTtMtEbTdMM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Rick goes <a href="https://besthike.com/2016/07/24/cycle-hiking-san-juan-island/">cycle hiking San Juan island</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2016/07/la-finca-de-palugo-palugo-farm.html">La Finca de Palugo</a>.</p>

<p>David shares <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2016/7/22/twenty-from-tranter">Twenty from Tranter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.fi/2016/07/sea-2-summit-so-cals-san-gorgonio.html">Sea 2 Summit: So-Cal’s San Gorgonio</a>.</p>

<p>Sven goes backpackin in Chile’s <a href="http://www.aufundab.eu/tour/huerqueue-waelder-lagunen-vulkan">Parque Nacional Huerqueue</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.shanecycles.com/bikepacking-the-gr-5-trans-ardennes-pt-2/">Bikepacking the GR 5</a>.</p>

<p>A fine walk through the hills &amp; moors of <a href="https://beatingthebounds.wordpress.com/2016/07/20/hollow-moor-cocklaw-fell-and-skeggles-water/">Kentmere</a>.</p>

<p>Escape to the beautiful Tatras and scramble to the <a href="http://www.skadinagrani.pl/2016/07/lodowy-szczyt-2627-m-npm.html">Lodowy Szczyt</a> summit. Love the fox photo at the end! [Polish]</p>

<p><a href="http://yukonfrolics.blogspot.fi/2016/07/muncho-lake-to-rabbit-river.html">Muncho Lake to Rabbit River</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/musings/how-to-plan-an-overnight-hike-in-japan/">How to Plan an Overnight Hike in Japan</a>.</p>

<p>And Matthias’ <a href="http://photo.matthiaskodym.com/wordpress3/blog/2016/07/18/projekt-oe-3000-suedalpenweg-03-nassfeld-bad-radkersburg/">Projekt OE-3000</a> is in full swing and he has hiked already 650 km. [German]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/" title="Mora Kniv Eldris"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8598/28227431230_c4f1c61a35_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Mora Kniv Eldris" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://trailaddicted.com/news/recensione-occhiali-julbo-aero-zebra-light-leggerezza-comfort/">Julbo Aero Zebra Light Review</a>. [Italian]</p>

<p>A look at the <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2016/07/23/gear-preview-salomon-s-lab-wings-8/">Salomon S-Lab Wings 8</a>.</p>

<p>Peter helps you <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2016/07/choosing-kayak.html">choosing a kayak</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/2anbAkc">Tips to stay dry &amp; warm when you’re going packrafting</a>.</p>

<p>A first look at the <a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/first-look-jpaks-gravelpak/">JPaks GravelPak</a></p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=531991&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12493/531991/55699/73183/image.gif" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multi-Adventures in Macedonia]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/multi-adventures-in-macedonia.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-14T23:50:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/multi-adventures-in-macedonia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Macedonia?</em> As I was invited to the AdventureNEXT Balkans conference and the possibility of exploring this small Balkan country I didn’t hesitate long and said yes. Several days of hiking, climbing, mountaineering, caving and paddling adventures were to be had, and big smiles and wide views to be experienced. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634875673/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Poppies!"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7102/26634875673_b6f0315fee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Poppies!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="skopje-the-capital">Skopje, the capital</h2>

<p>I arrived late in the evening in Skopje, the capital of Macedonia, and was lucky enough to share a ride with three fellow AdventureNEXT attendants to the hotel. While I was travelling since 4 am of that day I didn’t feel like hitting the hay just yet, and so I went with James and Bernard to explore the centre a wee bit. Unknown to the outside world there were daily peaceful demonstrations in Skopje, called the colourful revolution. The signs of these could be seen on the dozens of monuments in the centre, as the demonstrators threw colourful bombs on them. We walked past the river to the central square and then on a more busy street back to the hotel, where I finally felt tired enough to hit the hay. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634874703/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Colourful Revolution, Skopje"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7347/26634874703_412ee3054a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Colourful Revolution, Skopje" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634875263/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Night at the Kiosk"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7765/26634875263_8879cb35ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night at the Kiosk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning I went off on my own to explore the city more. There’s an old castle on a hill overlooking the city, which made for a easy first destination. The entry to it is free and you get some nice views towards the centre and the hills behind it, as well as the distant mountains which we would be exploring a bit later on. After that I took a look at the Mosque Mustapha Pasha, which was a beautiful building. While I am anti-religious I really like Mosques with their Minaretts and their calls to prayer. They are beautiful structures and the people one meets there are in my experience always friendly and kind, much unlike what mainstream media would like you to believe about Moslems. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27143388722/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Skopje Fortress"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7417/27143388722_cab6e0aa1a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="655" alt="Skopje Fortress" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I wandered downwards towards the Old Bazaar of Skopje, where plenty of shops offered their goods for trade. Impressive was the street of gold, where one jewellery store was to the next and I was just left but wondering: Who has the money to buy these things, or are they cheap? As I’m also not really into gold, silver and diamonds I didn’t find out and just strolled on through the narrow streets of the Old Bazaar. Delicious smells from small restaurants wafted through the air and I was reminded by my stomach that it might just be time to eat. After I changed some Euros into the local currency I found a nice restaurant which served a delicious plate of kebap and salad. The old gentlemen was friendly and warm, and even when we didn’t share a common language we were able to communicate with hand &amp; feet and I got what I wanted. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27663638873/in/dateposted/" title="Mosque Mustapha Pasha"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8684/27663638873_5c24926d6f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mosque Mustapha Pasha" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27663636413/in/dateposted/" title="Gold Street"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8755/27663636413_835262fe57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gold Street" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27663635713/in/dateposted/" title="Restaurant"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7297/27663635713_8cf1521a77_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Restaurant" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With a belly full of good food and after a coffee I went on to explore the city more - the large square where pompous classical music was blarring out of hidden speakers, and then I wandered over the old Stone Bridge and was pondering for a moment if it would be possible to still take a hike up the hill next to the city. But the clock was late and I was about to meet my fellow adventurers, so I headed back to the hotel. After a dozen introductions we went for another exploration of Skopje, and much to my amusement it was almost identical to the round I made on my own in the morning. This time, however, we had our guides along who were able to tell us a bit more about the buildings, structures and monuments. It was very interesting, and if you like to explore old cities then Skopje is definitely worth a visit. </p>

<h2 id="hiking-climbing-and-paddling-at-matka-canyon">Hiking, climbing and paddling at Matka Canyon</h2>

<p>Matka Canyon is a mere 40 minute bus ride away from downtown Skopje so I already was fearing it’d be overrun with visitors who wanted to escape the city for the weekend. However, it was happily not the case! Our bus dropped us off at a bridge which crossed the river and then we hiked on a fine singletrack trail up into the mountains. It was simply lovely hiking with great views and lush green flowers &amp; plants along the track. We glimpsed views into the canyon and also towards our destination up on the hill, where we would be climbing in the morning. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27240432415/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Trail markers"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7739/27240432415_ea7a1873aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trail markers" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As we arrived up on the hill a beautiful old &amp; small monastary welcomed us and there was already quite a bit of activity from local climbing club members - there was going to be a climbing festival there this weekend from the <a href="">Macedonian Alpine Club</a>, and after us a steady stream of climbers arrived throughout the morning. Our guides set up a top rope and everyone was encouraged to go and try the fairly easy route, and almost everyone made it to the top 30 m higher up - even those who were climbing the first time in their life! I was eager to get some more climbing in and did one more route on a nice arete, but then it was sadly already time to move on as we were scheduled to go paddling. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27240433365/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="At the crag!"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/8/7138/27240433365_d77c7f9359_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the crag!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27240431875/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Matka Canyon"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7427/27240431875_b5a71e2748_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Matka Canyon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27240431875/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Matka Canyon"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7427/27240431875_b5a71e2748_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Matka Canyon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27171366551/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Climbing at Matka Canyon"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7440/27171366551_bf061c7717_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Climbing at Matka Canyon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27143421202/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Ferry at Matka Canyon"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7314/27143421202_18e2683a21_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Ferry at Matka Canyon" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The packs came back on and then it was happily just downhill until the shore down in the canyon. We rang a bell which resulted in a boat coming over to pick us up and ferry us over to the other side, where we quickly changed into clothes which could get wet - as we were going to be paddling for an hour in sit-on-top kayaks. I paired up with Avery, a fellow Journalist, and soon we were finding our rhytm and navigated our kayak over the turquoise waters of the Matka Canyon. After an hour of paddling through the steep canyon we arrived at a cave which some of us went in, but as I didn’t bring any shoes &amp; didn’t fancy walking through bat poop I waited outside. Just as we set out to paddle back we could hear the distant thunder in the mountains, and so it meant faster paddling in order to not get soaked and electrocuted by lightning. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27143424312/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Paddling at Matka Canyon 02"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7585/27143424312_f74dbf3524_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Paddling at Matka Canyon 02" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26965430150/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Paddling at Matka Canyon 01"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7138/26965430150_1868afd7c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Paddling at Matka Canyon 01" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Obviously we made it out alive, and as we were back on the shore it was time for lunch - at 17 o’clock! We had a short transfer to a local restaurant which served delicious vegetables which were grown in the garden behind the house and while we munched our starters a Gipsy Brass Band entered the local and set off to play for us. It was a great atmosphere as these passionate musicians played their instruments, and many of us felt the beat and one saw wipping feet. Well fed and feeling tired after a day of hiking, climbing and paddling we drove back to Skopje. As the next morning we would transfer to another area of the country it meant packing up - happily I travelled light!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27143422562/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Gipsy Brass Band"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7389/27143422562_74e0259203_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gipsy Brass Band" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="standing-on-a-summit-and-watching-into-kosovo">Standing on a summit and watching into Kosovo</h2>

<p>In case you didn’t know: I really do not like the transportation part of travelling. Bus and train rides as well as flying are pretty boring and a utter waste of time for me, and riding in a bus on small mountain roads which wind up the hill in serpentines is about the last ting I really want to do. Alas, this was what was in store for us this morning. We rode for several hours to Staro Selo where we transferred into 4 x 4s which shuttled us up the mountain to the Vila Ljuboten. This, happily, marked the end of the first transportation part of the day, and from here on we’d be using our own feet to move. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27997697920/in/dateposted/" title="Signs"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7639/27997697920_b36043e256_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signs" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28244664756/in/dateposted/" title="Ljuboten Summit Sign"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7034/28244664756_5aa3bfb076_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ljuboten Summit Sign" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After sitting for over three hours in a bus and car moving my feet in the mountains was exactly what I wanted, and happily also Tim, Matthias, Avery and Bernard felt that way. We set at a good pace off from the hut, with the goal being the summit of Ljuboten. Alas, in a big group the speed goes down pretty quickly, and so the five of us made a break-out and went ahead. Soon we reached a sign post &amp; decided it’d be just the right thing to do to wait for our guides and the rest of the group, and ask for permission to go ahead to the summit. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27663642853/in/dateposted/" title="Looking back"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8584/27663642853_1fb5e764a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Looking back" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28244650176/in/dateposted/" title="Ljuboten Summit in the far distance"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8655/28244650176_d525edab57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ljuboten Summit in the far distance" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Upon reaching us the guides gave us permission to make a summit attempt, and with the weather being a mixed back and a thick layer of snow on the ridge to the summit we weren’t sure how far we would come, so if our attempt would be crowned by success was unsure. For starters it was easy hiking until the upper snow field, and as a group of Macedonian mountaineers were just coming down from the summit we decided that we could also try it. The ridge towards the summit of Ljuboten falls pretty steep off towards the left, and just slightly less to the right, so it was careful hiking upwards.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28200770821/in/dateposted/" title="Snowy Ljuboten Summit ridge"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8758/28200770821_7ac74e6c7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy Ljuboten Summit ridge" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We were surprised how easy &amp; short it was in the end to reach the summit. We smiled and enjoyed the views as we stood on the broad summit shoulder: Down into the clouds towards the north we looked into Kosovo, and down towards the south we could see far into Macedonia. The clouds were racing around us, it was windy and there was thunder in the distance, so after a summit selfie we carefully proceeded to descent. The snowy ridge demanded concentration when going down, but as soon as we left the snow behind it was fast &amp; easy hiking again. We soon met up with the rest of our group which were waiting further down for us, and then we decended together towards the Vila Ljuboten and again a rather late lunch. After such a fine hike the food tasted amazing, and while the Macedonian kitchen often felt like it was the same the natural ingredients and fresh mountain air made this probably one of the best meals I ate in Macedonia. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27997693560/in/dateposted/" title="Summit Selfie"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8624/27997693560_bb5fd63a01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit Selfie" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27997694960/in/dateposted/" title="Nur wo Du zu Fuß warst, warst Du wirklich"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8663/27997694960_d9cd46b5d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nur wo Du zu Fuß warst, warst Du wirklich" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27997700380/in/dateposted/" title="Nom nom"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8622/27997700380_9c5e391c5c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nom nom" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="caving-with-bats-at-makedonski-brod">Caving with bats at Makedonski Brod</h2>

<p>After that tasty lunch we had another bus travel section, and we arrived at dawn at our next hotel close to the Mavrovo National Park. I slept in a beautiful apartment overlooking the village, but the real treat was definitely waking up and seeing the mountains from my window the next morning. Sadly instead of going to explore the surrounding mountains and villages on foot we had another transfer that morning, but happily it wasn’t too long. We arrived at the basecamp of the <a href="http://www.ursusspeleos.com.mk/index_en.htm">Macedonian Caving Society</a>, and after dressing up in our red overalls and helmets we were off to the Gorna Slatinska cave with our guides.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26633789634/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Valley view"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7070/26633789634_f2c37ae3a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Valley view" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26633789054/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Signage"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7319/26633789054_7296213f7d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signage" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now I’d lie if I didn’t say that I was thinking <em>Meh</em> about the caving before we entered the cave. I was not really excited about the whole caving thing, but what followed really was my favourite part of this Multi-activity trip. The Gorna Slatinska cave is around 400 m long and we needed with our group of six around 45 to 60 minutes from one end to the other. Those 400 m under the earth were just fantastic, with stalagmites and stalactites which grew over hundreds of years, small chambers and tight spots which one needed to squeeze through and then small climbs to get up or down. And of course the bats. I’d go as far as saying that Batman is my favourite comic character (Rorschach from Watchmen being a close second), so being in a cave with bats was just a very cool experience. There were hundreds of bats of all sizes flying around us, or hanging sleeping from the ceiling. As we exited the cave and the sunshine was again shining on us I had a huge smile on my face. I would do this again in an instant as it was just such a outlandish yet inspiring experience, so if you’re not too afraid of tight spaces I would urge you to go and explore the Makedonski Brod caves!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27143391232/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Cave Gorna Slatinska 19"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7643/27143391232_34727e6c0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cave Gorna Slatinska 19" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27143392702/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Cave Gorna Slatinska 17"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7094/27143392702_1269cefb7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cave Gorna Slatinska 17" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634869063/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Cave Gorna Slatinska 13"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7265/26634869063_296b974bce_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Cave Gorna Slatinska 13" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27171347871/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Bat"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7696/27171347871_434e6154a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bat" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27171409511/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Sleeping bat"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7087/27171409511_0eb2c5fcd6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sleeping bat" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, after I looked a last time into the mouth of the cave which I just had exited we walked the short distance back to the basecamp, where one of the guides was already busy at the BBQ grill. While the other group went to explore the cave we were having a beer and chating excitedly about the experience, and as our friends were back we shared a delicious feast of vegetables, beans, chicken and meats before we headed onwards to Ohrid and the AdventureNEXT conference - that, however, is another story for another day!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634868293/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Exit through the Gift Shop"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/8/7419/26634868293_442d643a1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Exit through the Gift Shop" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="getting-there--accommodation">Getting there &amp; accommodation</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.turkishairlines.com/">Turkish Airlines</a> flew me from Helsinki via Istanbul to Skopje and I need to say as far as airlines go they do a very good job. Punctual, friendly and with full service (yes, that means a 3-course meal in economic class as well as an <em>“open bar”</em>) I really liked my flights with them. They have their own Chef on board which apparently cooks for the business class passengers, but who then also would happily help out in the back of the plane. </p>

<p>The trip I was on was organized by <a href="http://www.macedoniaexperience.com">Macedonia Experience</a> which I found a friendly &amp; professional outfit. The guides knew what they were doing (always good when setting up anchors for climbing, paddlling, moving in the mountains and caving) and looked after evryone in the group. We had a condensed version of their normal <a href="http://www.macedoniaexperience.com/active/2013-04-05-15-20-38/multi-active-tour-of-macedonia">Multi-Activity Trip</a> and the normal tour you can book is longer and more relaxed. If you don’t want to go off exploring by yourself but rather have someone who has taken care of everything, give them your business.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27143419452/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="That way to climb Multi-pitch"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7791/27143419452_3a8de46cbf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="That way to climb Multi-pitch" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In Skopje we stayed at the <a href="http://www.duvet.mk">Hotel Duvet</a> which was central, clean and friendly. I liked the breakfast terrace overlooking the city towards the hills, and the rooms were pretty big (in case that’s important to you). </p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.vilaljuboten.com/">Vila Ljuboten</a> at the foot of the mountain of the same name also offers very basic rooms, so if you want to stay up in the mountains that would be a good place. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.bistra.com">Hotel Bistra</a> in the Mavrovo national park has great rooms and apartments overlooking the valley, and their breakfast &amp; dinner is also fantastic. If you’re into slowfood, herbs and spices this place is well worth checking in to, as the owner has a wealth of knowledge in this area and is happy to share it.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I was invited to Macedonia as part of the <a href="http://www.adventuretravel.biz/events/adventurenext/balkans-2016/">AdventureNEXT Balkans</a> conference where. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor 2016 - Gear Teasers]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-first-gear-teasers.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-11T23:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-first-gear-teasers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Can’t wait for ultralight gear news from the OutDoor 2016 anymore? I have you covered and show you a selection of new ultralight tents and backpacks, new shoes and apparel to make your hiking, climbing, backpacking and camping lighter! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28115365671/in/dateposted/" title="#OutDoorFN 2016 is coming!"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7304/28115365671_6eee8bb41d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="#OutDoorFN 2016 is coming!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>While the <a href="">OutDoor 2016</a> kicks off first in two days I already got a lot of information on new gear coming in 2017. Please keep in mind that I haven’t actually seen, touched or tested these items so all information are to be taken with a grain of salt and they still might change until they stand in stores in 2017. I will try to try on, lie in and walk in many of the items seen here while on the fair, but that also is just to get a taste of them and not a final judgement.</p>

<p>Instead of going by company in this teaser update, I will just go by categories. And as everyone loves tents and shelters, those make the start!</p>

<h2 id="tents--shelters">Tents &amp; Shelters</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28202203836/in/dateposted/" title="Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8899/28202203836_45182594ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nordisk Lofoten 1 ULW" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Nordisk</strong> takes the Ultralight crown this year with the Lofoten 1 ULW, as it has a claimed weight of just 490 g with a pack size of 11 x 22 cm. It’s a two layer tent with mesh doors, aluminum poles, Dyneema cords and Titanium stakes, and a repair set is also included. No info on Price or if you can sit in it, which I hope to find out on the fair =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28158403041/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Hogan SUL 1-2P"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7292/28158403041_8a334f8656_b.jpg" width="1024" height="788" alt="Vaude Hogan SUL 1-2P" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Vaude</strong> is revamping their Hogan tents which are especially popular with cyclists. The Vaude Hogan SUL 1-2P will weigh around 1.100 g and has a size of 235 x 110 cm. The larger tents which sleep two and three are a bit more heavy and wider, and a new model called Invenio has two doors opposite of each other. All these tents will have 5 years of warranty on them, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27955414880/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Bolt 2P tent"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7580/27955414880_d37d27d22e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Bolt 2P tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also <strong>Marmot</strong> comes out with a new lightweight tent. The Bolt 2P tent weighs 1.040 g and sleeps two. It will cost 500 € and will be in the shops from February 2017 onwards. The Specs: 20 D Polyester Fly, large entry, full mesh inner which can be pitched on its own on fine, mosquito-infested days, and there should be good sitting height.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27622202004/in/dateposted/" title="MSR Advance Pro 2"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7465/27622202004_960a5ac09e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="MSR Advance Pro 2" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>MSR</strong> launches a great looking Alpine/ Ultralight backpacking tent, the Advance Pro 2. It weighs 1.300 g packed and will retail for 585 € and should be available from Spring 2017. It has very durable Easton Syclone poles which are made from a carbon and aluminium composite. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28133567382/in/dateposted/" title="Therm-A-Rest Tranquility 6 Tent"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7308/28133567382_f5b719952b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="599" alt="Therm-A-Rest Tranquility 6 Tent" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And lastly <strong>Therm-A-Rest</strong> enters the Camping (Glamping!) Market with their Tranquility™ 4 and 6 tents. These weigh 5,19 kg and 7,87 kg respectively, sleep four or six people, have standing height and cost 530€ or 650€.</p>

<h2 id="backpacks--packs">Backpacks &amp; Packs</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27955415580/in/photostream/" title="GREGORY Paragon 48"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7320/27955415580_a36fa460e3_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="GREGORY Paragon 48" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>GREGORY</strong> Paragon 48 weighs 1.450 g and is one of several light-ish packs. The Paragon is the Male model while the Maven is the Women’s model. Available in four volumes from 38 l to 68 l these packs will cost between 160€ and 240€. It comes with an Aerolon carrying system which can be adjusted in length to your body and if you want to lighten it further up you can remove the top lid and use the inside compartment divider as one. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28158403401/in/photostream/" title="Vaude Zerum 48+ LW Backpack"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8623/28158403401_31584c1521_b.jpg" width="788" height="1024" alt="Vaude Zerum 48+ LW Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Zerum 48+ LW Backpack from <strong>Vaude</strong> concludes the German company’s step to offer lightweight versions for the big 3 (The <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/vaude-alpstein-450-down-decke/?pid=10239">Alpstein 450</a>, which I helped design &amp; test, launched last year). The pack comes in three sizes - 38 l, 48 l and 58 l. The medium 48 l pack weighs 1.180 g, has a PFC-free EcoFinish to let rain and dirt pearl off and is made from a light 70 D Rip-Stop. It has a light version of the Vaude Tergolight Carrying system.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27959237640/in/dateposted/" title="Ortlieb Bikepacking Packs"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7317/27959237640_24dbd89364_b.jpg" width="1024" height="631" alt="Ortlieb Bikepacking Packs" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And <strong>Ortlieb</strong> enters the Bikepacking Framebag market (see my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html">Bikepacking Framebag Manufacturer List</a> to see smaller companies making custom and Multi-size bags). The German company launches a Framebag (which comes out next year) and a Handlebar bag and Seatbag, both which are already available. The Seatpack is 430 g light and costs 130€, while the Handlebar Bag is 417 g and costs 100€. The former has a volume of 5 to 16,5 l while the latter packs 15 l of gear, with an Accessory-Pack for the Handlebar pack (206 g and 55€) which adds 3,5 l more. </p>

<h2 id="climbing-gear">Climbing Gear</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27955807950/in/dateposted/" title="Petzl GriGri 2017"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8880/27955807950_30cd44dc42_b.jpg" width="1024" height="841" alt="Petzl GriGri 2017" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Petzl</strong> seems to be launching a new GriGri - at least that’s my guess going by the above photo which was in my invite to their booth =) </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28236552315/in/dateposted/" title="Black Diamond Ropes"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7782/28236552315_c09b4b94c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="695" alt="Black Diamond Ropes" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Black Diamond</strong> enters the rope market. Available will be four different ropes: The 7,8 Half- and Twin-Rope, a 9,2 Triple Certified Rope and two Single Ropes in 9,6 and 9,9 diameter. They have a Full-Dry finish and will be available in lengths of 35 m, 40 m, 60 m and 70 m. </p>

<h2 id="footwear">Footwear</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28132885632/in/dateposted/" title="Merrell Agility Peak Flex"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7330/28132885632_1916b41a48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="737" alt="Merrell Agility Peak Flex" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The new <strong>Merrell</strong> Agility Peak Flex above is a new trailrunning shoe which has the new FlexConnect midsole. A Hyperlock Heel construction should lock in your heel while the breathable mesh upper makes it a solid choice on hot days. The shoe has a drop of 6 mm, 5 mm deep lugs on the sole and is available from spring/ summer 2017 onwards.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28203030476/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Epic Lite OD"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8702/28203030476_116bcc28d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="717" alt="Scarpa Epic Lite OD" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>From <strong>Scarpa</strong> comes the Epic Lite OD, with OD standing for OutDry, the waterproof-breathable membrane. It’s an approach shoe which should do well on Via Ferratas and hiking in the mountains. Again we have a Sock-Fit upper construction, and the laminated OutDry® membrane should keep your feet dry - from the inside and out. Underneath a Vibram Megagrip sole ensures you don’t slip away if its wet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28237378245/in/dateposted/" title="Dachstein Spürsinn EVO"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/8/7426/28237378245_0d8bb01408_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dachstein Spürsinn EVO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Dachstein</strong> is a new brand to me and their Spürsinn EVO shoe sounds really great. It has a sock-like, knitted shaft and has been developed with the blind mountaineer Andy Holzer. It is supposed to have a great feeling of what’s under your foot with the Vibram EVO 2.0 sole, and a shoe weighs 340 g in Size 42. The upper is made from mesh for breathability, and it has a climbing zone in the front which make sit good for Via Ferratas and approaches. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27623441363/in/dateposted/" title="KEEN Versago"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8700/27623441363_e244f52796_b.jpg" width="990" height="1024" alt="KEEN Versago" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>KEEN</strong> is another new company for me and their Versago is a shoe that combines great looks for urban use and functional details which should make him great on your hikes and runs. The upper and tongue wrap around your foot like a sock and are made from mesh, while the midsole has the S3™-Technology which gives stability and cushioning on demanding terrain. It comes in four colours and will retail for 110€. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28206488956/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan VT"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8724/28206488956_62d94be9cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="165" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan VT" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Arc’teryx</strong> Norvan VT is the latest shoe of the Canadians. This trailrunning shoe weighs 300 g in Men’s Size 8,5 UK or 320 g as a GTX shoe. The last 2/3 of the shoe have a Vibram Megagrip sole which ensures grip on wet &amp; dry terrain alike, while the front one-third has a Vibram Idrogrip sole which ensures you can scramble well on your Via Ferratas and approaches. Arc’teryx built the shoe for <em>alpinists and climbers who use trail running to increase their fitness, and dedicated trail runners looking for new territory to explore</em>. And the 360⁰ Support System should help you with that, as you can decrease the volume and ensure a climbing-like fit when you tighten it, and release it again for the running sections of the trail. They will cost 165€ for the non-lined version and 190€ for the GTX shoe, available from spring 2017 onwards.</p>

<h2 id="apparel">Apparel</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27955412350/in/photostream/" title="Marmot Airlite Jacket"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8668/27955412350_a66b834307_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Marmot Airlite Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Marmot</strong> launches the Airlite Jacket which will make UL backpackers and trailrunners happy, as it only weighs 102 g - and will “only” cost 120€. Made from Nylon Ripstop Stretch it is stretchy so great for running in the rain. It is supposed to be very breathable and of course keeps wind and rain at bay, with a hood and a zippered pocket, too. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28158404561/in/photostream/" title="Vaude Zebru UL 3L Jacket"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7471/28158404561_db0eb2d21c_b.jpg" width="788" height="1024" alt="Vaude Zebru UL 3L Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <strong>Vaude</strong> Zebru UL 3L Jacket weighs 198 g in Size L and is a hardshell with a PFC-free finish. It is made of a 3-layer Ceplex Pro-Membrane which should keep you dry and out of the wind and is also breathable. If that’s too heavy for you then the Zebru Windshell Jacket and the Zebru Windshell Vest which weigh 90 g and 70 g respectively might be more interesting!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28158406361/in/photostream/" title="Vaude - 95% PFC Free from 2017 onwards"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8620/28158406361_5d168437f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vaude - 95% PFC Free from 2017 onwards" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another great news from <strong>Vaude</strong> is that 95% of their range will be PFC-free from 2017 onwards. They will use almost exclusively PFC-free DWRs on their jackets and already faced the harmful substances out in other areas of the manufacturing chain. Great news for users and the environment!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28203717286/in/dateposted/" title="OMM AVA Jacket Womens"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8841/28203717286_a2e3050061_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="OMM AVA Jacket Womens" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And <strong>OMM</strong> launches the AVA Jacket, a sub-200 g fully featured mountain running jacket made from a new eVent DVSTORM 3 layer fabric. The OMM Team was focused on creating innovative closures around the wrist, waist and face and I am very much looking forward checking it out in person. It has an Dynamic Droptail to keep you bottoms a wee bit more dry in the rain, YKK Aquaguard zips and a newly designed Multi-Cuff. </p>

<h2 id="materials">Materials</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27959054270/in/dateposted/" title="THERMORE® ECODOWN®"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8824/27959054270_c78701c88d_b.jpg" width="961" height="453" alt="THERMORE® ECODOWN®" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Thermore</strong> Ecodown is a synthetic down which is made completely from recycled PET bottles. It is available in 8 variations (60, 80, 100, 115, 130, 150, 170, 200 g/m2) and in 20 different thicknesses, allowing manufacturers to create your favourite puffy jacket with a environmentally friendly material. Available immediately I hope many companies will start to use this material soon. </p>

<h2 id="accessories">Accessories</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27956036160/in/dateposted/" title="Exped Care Line"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7454/27956036160_c186d35f27_b.jpg" width="850" height="710" alt="Exped Care Line" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Exped</strong> launches their own Care Line products. Prices range from 3,95€ for the Down Cleaner to 8,95€ for the Tent Cleaner. Additionally there will be products for Gear Waterproofing, a Mat and Backpack Spray Cleaner and a Sleeping Bag Spray Cleaner. Expect them from March 2017 onwards.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28159489101/in/dateposted/" title="Katadyn BeFree"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/8/7330/28159489101_bacdf0c0e4_b.jpg" width="964" height="830" alt="Katadyn BeFree" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Katadyn</strong> launches this September their BeFree Waterbottle &amp; Filter. The soft bottle has an integrated 0,1 Micron hollow fibre filter in it, which can be replaced. The soft flask is 0,5 l and from Hydrapak. Usage is super-simple: Fill the bottle, screw on the filter and drink! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28239138305/in/dateposted/" title="Outdoor Tech Kodiak Plus 6"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8858/28239138305_93497e20f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1022" alt="Outdoor Tech Kodiak Plus 6" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Kodiak Plus 10 from <strong>Outdoor Tech</strong> is a 10k mAh Powerbank which weighs 308 g and will cost 80€. The Lithium battery is obviously rechargeable, and with two USB Ports it’s easy to keep several gadgets charged when out on the trail. It’s a compact size and best of all, it should be available already this October.</p>

<h2 id="and-more">And more</h2>

<p>Stay tuned on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more updates from the OutDoor in Friedrichshafen and expect the full low-down when I’m back at Hiking in Finland HQ next week!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 241]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/twir-241.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-10T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/twir-241</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Are you ready for summer nights in the mountains?</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19937539195/in/album-72157653909966154/" title="Time to go to sleep"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/1/410/19937539195_1a9f138559_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Time to go to sleep" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>I’m all for free internet access, and I totally think that <a href="https://act.openmedia.org/TollBooth">the Internet shouldn’t have a toll booth</a>- Act before it is too late.</p>

<p>Climate change is going to drive a lot of <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/energy-environment/wp/2016/05/18/national-park-service-director-climate-change-among-the-biggest-challenges-ahead/">change in the national parks</a>.</p>

<p>Couple of days and the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/outdoorfn-2016-is-a-go.html">OutDoor 2016</a> starts. I already have been sharing some <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">ultralight gear news over on Twitter</a> so if you want know about UL tents, packs, shoes and garments, head over there!</p>

<p>Awesome! <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1616617044/the-lift-cargo-bike">The LIFT transforms your bike into a Cargo Bike</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-31-fruehlingsloch/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #31</a> is out! [German]</p>

<p>A new issue of <a href="http://www.oe-mag.co.uk/imag/oejulyaugust2016/">Outdoor Enthusiast</a> is available for free online!</p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/29Eghrp">Need more Titanium in your outdoor life</a>?</p>

<p>Just today: <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/marken/black-diamond/outdoor-bekleidung/?pid=10239">50% off on Black Diamond apparel and gear</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=319733&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/319733/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip reports</h2>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/2016-six-months-in.html">2016 has been pretty great so far</a>.</p>

<p>Beardoh and SweetPea are now <a href="http://longdistancehiker.com/pct-57-carson-pass/">57 Days on the PCT</a>.</p>

<p>Carsten had <a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/uebungsleiter-hochtour/">a good course week in the mountains</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A cool <a href="http://bit.ly/29qwpJU">DIY Multisport Adventure in Alaska</a>.</p>

<p>Antsa finished his 10 year project of <a href="http://slowlifeofantsa.blogspot.fi/2016/07/10-year-paddling-project-completed.html">paddling to all 74 Finnish Lighthouses</a> - Congratulations!</p>

<p>A visit to <a href="http://wanderweib.de/schlucht-rairaikyo/">Rairaikyo Canyon</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Peter paddles in the <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2016/07/bothnian-sea-national-park.html">Bothnian Sea National Park</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/v8A0ad_2mPc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://blonde-gypsy.com/2016/07/05/48-hours-zagreb-croatia-capital-cool/">48 Hours in Croatia’s Capital of Cool</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.travelingjackie.com/via-ferrata-fear-of-heights/">Via Ferrata with Fear of Heights</a>.</p>

<p>Looks fantastic: The 550 Miles of the Scottish <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/highland-trail-550/">Highland Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Steve goes <a href="http://sdbwanderings.blogspot.fi/2016/07/wild-camping-with-9-year-old-blencathra.html">wild Camping with his 9 year old on Blencathra</a>.</p>

<p>Adam’s <a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2016/07/my-new-home.html">new home</a> looks sweet!</p>

<p>And James goes backpacking during Monsoon in the <a href="https://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2016/07/04/the-dales-south-to-north-a-monsoon-backpack-pt1/">Dales, south to north</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel" title="#OutDoorFN 2016 is coming!"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7304/28115365671_6eee8bb41d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="#OutDoorFN 2016 is coming!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Food: <a href="http://blog.trailcooking.com/2016/07/04/new-recipe-dehydrated-cinnamon-carrot-shreds/">Dehydrated Cinnamon Carrot Shreds Recipe</a> - Tasty! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2016/07/zegul-arrow-play-six-months-review.html">Zegul Arrow Play Six Months Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/gear/swift-hinterland-jr-ranger-panniers/">Swift Hinterland Jr. Ranger Panniers</a>.</p>

<p>Fits almost: <a href="http://velo-orange.blogspot.fi/2016/07/front-loading-basics.html">Front Loading Basics</a>.</p>

<p>Chris reviews the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/rendesvous-salomon-x-ultra-2-gtx/">Salomon X-Ultra 2 GTX</a>.</p>

<p>Review of the <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/bikes/salsa-pony-rustler-review/">Salsa Pony Rustler</a>.</p>

<p>Alex tests the double-layer <a href="http://www.bergreif.de/2016/07/04/wandersocken-test-wrightsocks-coolmesh-ii-merino-socke/">Wrightsocks</a>. [German]</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=357957&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/12821/357957/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/172053488?color=c9ff23&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;badge=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016: Six months in]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/2016-six-months-in.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-04T23:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/2016-six-months-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2016 is six months old, time to reflect on the past outdoor months and reveal what lays ahead!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27976948552/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking towards the sunset"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7417/27976948552_cefcfdeaf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking towards the sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="january">January</h2>

<p>In January I was again on <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/aland-in-winter.html">Åland</a>, this time as a Hostblogger with NBE Finland. It was a superb trip and I loved showing our beautiful country to my fellow blogger friends.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24766179696/in/album-72157663594014166/" title="Bloggers at work"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/2/1514/24766179696_3ccdf7c9fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bloggers at work" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24699056571/in/album-72157663594014166/" title="Kick!"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/2/1461/24699056571_3f05252121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kick!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="february">February</h2>

<p>In February I went <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/ski-touring-south-tyrol-and-salzburger-lungau.html">ski-touring in South Tyrol</a> with my brother, and then we continued to Austria and the Salzburger Lungau. It was a great trip with some good, and some not so good snow.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24460363514/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="I love me a nice cabin!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1466/24460363514_7edaab5590_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I love me a nice cabin!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I love cabins! And my DPS Skis like them too =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25736343534/in/album-72157664672954972/" title="Albert ripping it!"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1584/25736343534_f07a20c1bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert ripping it!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our ski guide Albert traded his ski school to backcountry touring. With views like this, who wouldn’t?</p>

<h2 id="march">March</h2>

<p>March started off in Switzerland, where my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/teaser-graubunden-haute-route.html">Graubünden Haute-Route Tour</a> didn’t go according to plan. But we had a great time nevertheless, and that’s what counts.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25455047716/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Going down."><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/2/1445/25455047716_5a5b16aa20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Going down." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>March was also the month of skiing and winter activities with the family. First we were in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">Hetta</a> and had a lot of fun with Huskies, XC skiing and winter hiking, followed by a few nights in Ylläs and then Levi.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148429495/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/2/1490/26148429495_885653ee53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A husky Tour in Hetta is a must in our opinion. It’s so relaxing and fun!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25333253494/in/album-72157665518007610/" title="Powder turns on Kesänki"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1649/25333253494_d679a86349_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Powder turns on Kesänki" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While Ylläs is known as the XC Ski Mekka of Finland I loved the ski-touring, too. Imagine finding perfect snow and you can make the first turns!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28044201296/in/dateposted/" title="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7797/28044201296_a750b77c3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Santa’s Cabin on Levi is a wee bit off-piste and was built for the Finnish Santa movie from a few years back. It’s a beautiful cabin with a great view.</p>

<h2 id="april">April</h2>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/lyngen.html">Lyngen</a> with Henryk scores high as the most memorable ski-touring trip of the year. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25455047716/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Going down."><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/2/1445/25455047716_5a5b16aa20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Going down." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With sunsets like these it is easy to understand why Northern Norway is a photographers paradise, and equally popular amongst climbers &amp; skiers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148754883/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="What a view!"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/2/1694/26148754883_8441890563_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="What a view!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And also the skiing is pretty awesome, as Henryk here shows.</p>

<h2 id="may">May</h2>

<p>In may I was on the AdventureNEXT Conference in Macedonia, and went afterwards to Meteora in Greece. The Balkans are a gorgeous region with untapped potential for hiking, climbing, packrafting, bikepacking and will enchant you with the lovely people, tasty food and the pristine mountains and nature.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26965428300/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Climbing"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7295/26965428300_4a48114bb5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Climbing" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The climbing in Macedonia was great, and I am looking forward to sample more of it in the future.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26505575123/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Hiking in Meteora"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7060/26505575123_422cb17f12_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Hiking in Meteora" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The same I can say about Meteora in Greece. What an outstandingly beautiful place! </p>

<h2 id="june">June</h2>

<p>In June we went on summer holidays with the family to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/impressions-from-the-bregenzerwald-in-vorarlberg-austria.html">Vorarlberg</a> in Austria. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27700551721/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Sunrise on the Kanisfluh"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7180/27700551721_12abb83624_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise on the Kanisfluh" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That one morning where the sun shone, everything came together on the sunrise hike on the Kanisfluh.</p>

<h2 id="onwards">Onwards</h2>

<p>The next six months look pretty good too. Next week I am off to my annual <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/outdoorfn-2016-is-a-go.html">OutDoor pilgrimage</a>, then it is likely to Ireland and Wales, a visit to the south in November, dozens of research trips in Finland and in December I hope to be hunting some snow again. So, <strong>how has your outdoor year been thus far?</strong> What was the most memorable trip, and which trip in the second half of 2016 are you most looking forward to! <strong>Let us know in the comments!</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 240]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/twir-240.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-03T23:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/twir-240</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“If you go away on a summer day.”</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19854192616/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Crossing snowfields on the Sorapiss Circuit"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/4/3731/19854192616_b23bd6a6d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Crossing snowfields on the Sorapiss Circuit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Stevie Haston’s take on the <a href="http://steviehaston.blogspot.fi/2016/06/post-brexit-your-climbing-gear-will.html">Brexit and why it is shite</a>.</p>

<p>The 840 g light <a href="http://bit.ly/28VXFPw">Sierra Designs Backcountry Quilt</a> is designed by Andrew Skurka and now available, starting at $199.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/aktuelles/freiheit-fuer-die-wisente-im-rothaargebirge/">Freedom for the Wisent</a>! [German]</p>

<p>Wanna go canyoning, climbing and rafting? Take part &amp; win a sweet <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/?pid=81">adventure weekend in Tyrol</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/29ffOff">Grand Canyon Trail Map T-Shirt</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tenkarausa.com/myportfolio/short-cast-entomology-and-tenkara/">Entomology and tenkara</a>.</p>

<p>A complete <a href="http://www.tenkarausa.com/shop/product_info.php/products_id/192">tenkara set</a> to get you started.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1558582611/psycho-vertical">Psycho Vertical Kickstarter Campaign</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.instagram.com/packraftingstore/">Packrafting-Store is on Instagram</a>.</p>

<p>Learn alpine climbing in Tyrol and <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/montura-alpinsommer-obergurgl/?pid=81">win a complete alpine climbing outfit from Montura</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.gehlebt.at/weitwander-rueckblick-juni-2016/">Long-Distance Backpacking Review of June</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Summer Stock-Up Sale</a> with up to 50% off on Gear &amp; Apparel.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=313709&amp;pw=73183">Sign up for Campsaver.com’s newsletter and receive 10% off your first order</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=151477&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10881/151477/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Part two of “<a href="https://fortheloveofclimbing.com/2016/06/28/i-am-not-a-big-wall-climber-part-two/">I am not a big wall climber</a>”.</p>

<p>Rich is <a href="https://runrideandsleepoutside.wordpress.com/2016/07/03/running-on-the-moors-and-sleeping-in-a-bag/">running on the moors</a> and sleeps in a bag.</p>

<p><a href="https://tozantales.wordpress.com/2016/07/03/myojin1/">A close call</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kristerjonsson.se/2016/07/voie-versant-satanique-bassin.html">Satanique</a> in the Bassin d´Argentiere looks like a fun route!</p>

<p><a href="http://blakeclimbs.blogspot.fi/2016/07/liberty-crack-firstthird-free-ascent.html">Liberty Crack</a>.</p>

<p>Stevie and friends enjoy <a href="http://steviehaston.blogspot.fi/2016/07/days-of-marvel-now-by-stevie-chilling.html">Days of Marvel</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JlZckv0hxcs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Jill is <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2016/06/all-drugged-up-to-go-outside.html">all drugged up to go outside</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/sprachcamp-allgaeu-outdoor-english-camp-fuer-kinder/">Be outdoors and learn English at the Sprachcamp Allgäu</a>. [German]</p>

<p>The 3610 m high <a href="http://idnu.ch/wordpress/auf-dem-hoechsten-wanderberg-europas/">Üssere Barrhorn is the highest hiking peak of Europe</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/brette-harrington-rituals/">Brette Harrington’s Solo Soul Serenity</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://hillplodder.com/2016/06/30/the-gathering-of-the-clan/">The Gathering of the Clan</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20243714383/in/album-72157656271111848/" title="Dinner is served"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/1/780/20243714383_17f5ced77a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Dinner is served" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Kathrin’s <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/packliste-trekking-grossbritannien/">LEJOG Gear List</a> is worth nerding out over! [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://seattlebackpackersmagazine.com/vegan-backpacking-tips-and-tricks-for-optimal-performance/">Vegan Backpacking Tips and Tricks</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/the-slap-bag/">The Slap Bag</a>.</p>

<p>Raf reviews the <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2016/07/review-five-ten-quantum-rock-shoes/">5.10 Quantum</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://lesserplaces.wordpress.com/2016/06/28/the-things-ive-carried-a-love-letter-to-every-pack-ive-hiked-with/">love letter to all the pack carried</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bikepackersmagazine.com/plus-bikes-27-5-vs-29/">Plus Bikes: 27.5+ vs 29+</a>.</p>

<p>Light things that bring smiles: <a href="http://quasiout.blogspot.fi/2016/07/tread-lite-gear-cuben-fiber-dyneema-x.html">Tread Lite Gear Cuben Fiber Dyneema X Grid Stuff Sack</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2016/06/crotch-guard-review/">Crotch Guard Review</a>.</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=135585&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/11565/135585/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 239]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/twir-239.html"/>
    <updated>2016-06-26T23:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/twir-239</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“You have brains in your head. You have feet in your shoes. You can steer yourself in any direction you choose. You’re on your own, and you know what you know. And you are the guy who’ll decide where to go.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/28VovvP">Dr. Seuss</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27109586615/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Salomon X-Alp GTX"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7526/27109586615_78051eab6d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon X-Alp GTX" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/outdoorfn-2016-is-a-go.html">OutDoor 2016</a> is less than three weeks away!</p>

<p>The Andrew Skurka designed <a href="http://bit.ly/28VXFPw">Backcountry Quilt</a> from Sierra Designs is now available.</p>

<p>It’s our duty as Americans to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2016/may/22/alex-honnold-opinion-protect-america-national-parks-environmental-threats">protect our national parks for the next hundred years</a>.</p>

<p>Very awesome: <a href="https://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2016/06/23/lael-wilcox-finishes-trans-am-bike-race-2016-in-18-days-10-minutes/">Lael Wilcox wins Trans Am Bike Race 2016</a> in 18 days 10 minutes.</p>

<p><a href="http://dirtbagdiaries.com/ultimate-weekend-warrior/">The Ultimate Weekend Warrior</a>.</p>

<p>The Last Bastion of <a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/2092301/no-restrictions-apply">Outdoor Outlaws</a> in the USA.</p>

<p>Three shirts, four pairs of trousers: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/20/three-shirts-four-pairs-of-trousers-meet-japans-hard-core-minimalists">Meet Japan’s ‘hardcore’ minimalists</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2016/06/quiz-are-you-spending-enough-time-outside/">Are You Spending Enough Time Outside</a>?</p>

<p>Sean Conway just finished the <a href="https://twitter.com/Conway_Sean">longest Triathlon</a>, 4200 miles around Britain. Congratulations!</p>

<p>Big <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/salewa-zelt-schlafsack/">Salewa Photo Contest</a> in which you can win a sleeping bag and tent!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2016/06/lili-marlene-and-misplaced-nostalgia.html">Lili Marlene and misplaced nostalgia</a>.</p>

<p>Discover innovative, ultralight gear from outdoor startups at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=489297&amp;pw=73183">Garage Grown Gear</a>. </p>

<p>Just today you can get <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/hagloefs/outdoor-bekleidung/?bfc-marke[]=peak-performance&amp;bfc-marke[]=bergans&amp;bfc-marke[]=norroena-bf&amp;">20% off on gear from Haglöfs, Norrona, Bergans and Peak Performance at Bergfreunde</a>.</p>

<p>Get <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=531991&amp;pw=73183">30% off on Patagonia gear at the Gear Coop</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Beautiful: <a href="https://fortheloveofclimbing.com/2016/06/21/i-am-not-a-big-wall-climber/">I am not a big wall climber</a>.</p>

<p>Gerald hikes through the <a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2016/06/durch-die-drakensberge-1.html">Drakensberge</a> [German]</p>

<p>Jackie returns to <a href="http://www.travelingjackie.com/on-returning-to-montana/">Montana</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/28ZqGNE">9 Tips to succeed on the PCT</a>.</p>

<p>Adam <a href="http://adamspictureblog.blogspot.fi/2016/06/goodbye-alaska.html">leaves Alaska</a> - I’ll miss his awesome photos.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/wandern/bayern/lamawandern-ammergauer-alpen/">Hiking with Lamas</a> in the Ammergauer Alps. [German]</p>

<p>Fun: <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/the-art-beneath-the-routes/">The art beneath the routes</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FC86MySgs8A" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Peter enjoyed the 4th part of hos <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2016/06/the-vigu-sea-kayaking-guide-course-pt-46.html">Vigu Sea Kayaking Guide Course</a>.</p>

<p>With the packraft on the <a href="https://mitsackundpackraft.wordpress.com/2016/06/22/per-packraft-auf-dem-tagliamento/">Tagliamento</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/backpacking-lake-aloha-june-2016/">Backpacking Lake Aloha</a>.</p>

<p>Mike hiked ths <a href="https://mbguiding.ca/2016/06/juan-de-fuca-marine-trail-juan-de-fuca-provincial-park/">Juan de Fuca Marine Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Nine days <a href="http://www.bergreif.de/2016/06/22/querweg-freiburg-bodensee-schwarzwald/">through the Blackforest</a>. [German]</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2016/05/dirt-bag-guide-skaha/">Dirtbag Guide to Skaha</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://longdistancehiker.com/pct-44-selden-pass/">Day 44 on the PCT</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/gear-outtakes-spring-2016.html" title="Probably my three favourite jackets!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7288/27800542106_7d13569e58_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Probably my three favourite jackets!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Big <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/gear-outtakes-spring-2016.html">Gear Outtakes</a> Spring edition post came out this week.</p>

<p>Lael’s <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/lael-wilcox-trans-am/">Trans Am Gear List</a>.</p>

<p>Check out Christy’s <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2016/06/21/sierra-high-route-here-we-come/">Sierra High Route Gear List</a>.</p>

<p>Raf reviews the <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2016/06/review-rab-nebula-belay-parka/">RAB Nebula Parka</a>.</p>

<p><em>Did this article make you want to go outside? Great! Be even more inspired more and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer:  There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear Outtakes Spring 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/gear-outtakes-spring-2016.html"/>
    <updated>2016-06-23T23:53:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/gear-outtakes-spring-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bite-sized gear reviews, spring edition.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733431412/in/dateposted/" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody, Patagonia Nano-Air Hoody and Satoro AR Zip Neck LS Mens"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7665/27733431412_03fe5b489c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody, Patagonia Nano-Air Hoody and Satoro AR Zip Neck LS Mens" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gear-outtakes/">Gear Outtakes</a> is a seasonal collection of kit and what I think about it.</p>

<p>★☆☆☆
Mediocre, I wouldn’t spend money on it.</p>

<p>★★☆☆
Good, but there are better options.</p>

<p>★★★☆
Great, worth your money.</p>

<p>★★★★
Outstanding, the benchmark of its category.</p>

<p>DISCLAIMER
<br />Some of these products have been sent to me for free by the manufacturer.</p>

<h2 id="black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody">Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733432342/in/dateposted/" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7231/27733432342_5a1586438c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />150€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28Ppl8b">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28PaWhk">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody-windjacke/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-alpine-start-w-039-s-hoody-amethyst-s/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a> (On Offer!), <a href="http://bit.ly/OcTdRJ">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28PVqiy">REI</a></p>

<p>I have reviewed the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody.html">Alpine Start Hoody</a> before, but I felt that after another two years of intensive use it’s time to highlight once more how much I love this wind jacket. I use it almost daily, when out with the kids, cycling, and it is the first thing that I pack when I go hiking &amp; backpacking. After so many years it is not so water-resistant anymore (even when I clean it regularly with special detergents), but it still holds the wind out like a king. There’s a little hole in the left sleeve where I was bushwhacking, its a bit dirty at the cuffs from the almost daily use, but other than that I still love this jacket heaps and I’d be my first recommendation if someone is looking for a wind jacket/ softshell. / 204 g in Size M</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-alpha-fl-jacket">Arc’teryx Alpha FL Jacket</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27222774004/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Alpha FL Jacket"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7377/27222774004_42916fc42b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Alpha FL Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />350€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28PH0js">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28PaW0A">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-alpha-fl-jacket-hardshelljacke-bf-1/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28OMnMn">Campsaver.com</a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;category=Shell_Jackets&amp;model=Alpha-FL-Jacket">Alpha FL Jacket</a> is an ultralight Gore-Tex Pro hardshell which is made for fast &amp; light alpinism, and hence is great also for ultralight backpacking. Sure, there are even lighter hardshells out there, but this is such a great fitting jacket for me that I don’t think I need to continue the hunt. It takes all the abuse I throw at it - from jamming myself into a crack in the rain to hiking through the undergrowth - which I like a lot. The sleeves are a wee bit longer and so keep the hands dry when gloves stayed at home, the one pocket is again useful for some small items like my <a href="http://amzn.to/28SNH4J">camera</a>, and if not needed it packs down to a volume of one litre and disappears in the pack. There’s noting superfluous on this jacket, it allows me all the crazy moves I could come up with and looks good - what else do you need from a hardshell? / 270 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="patagonia-nano-air-hoody">Patagonia Nano-Air Hoody</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733429172/in/dateposted/" title="Patagonia Nano-Air Hoody"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7449/27733429172_d070c46b73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Nano-Air Hoody" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/28OMBTX">Patagonia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/28ZvSyJ">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28ScK9X">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-nano-air-hoody-kunstfaserjacke/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-nano-air-hoody-underwater-blue-xl/?key=Patagonia+Nano+Air+Hoody+underwater+blue+XL&amp;cat=suggest">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28NXFTg">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28PW3ca">REI</a></p>

<p>I have used the <a href="http://bit.ly/28OMBTX">Patagonia Nano-Air Hoody</a> now over a year, from hiking the IAT in Ireland over ski-touring to spring and summer hikes across the globe. It’s in combination with the Alpine Start Hoody currently my most worn insulation layer, though it’s really a breathable insulation layer as it is made from Patagonia’s FullRange material (think Polartec Alpha). It’s a super-stretchy piece, not wind-resistant but in combination with a wind jacket a great layering piece. I have been sceptical about breathable insulation materials, but after a week-long autumn hike in the rain and sleet of Sweden I was convinced. It’s great to have a piece on that keeps you warm when you stop and doesn’t heat up too much when you’re moving, especially in wet and cold weather. In warmer weather (anything over 10°C for me) it’s too warm, though, and I’ll shed it as soon as I start to feel too hot. It’s not too warm on its own either, but with a wind jacket or hardshell on top it’s a good insulation piece. With four pockets it’s also good for keeping stuff close by (snacks, camera batteries and a gas canister when you get closer to camp). The shell material is pretty sensitive, though, so bushwhacking in it will destroy it in no time, as will intense rock contact. / 352 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-satoro-ar-zip-neck-ls">Arc’teryx Satoro AR Zip Neck LS</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733429992/in/dateposted/" title="Satoro AR Zip Neck LS Mens"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7390/27733429992_e1a5c94e06_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Satoro AR Zip Neck LS Mens" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />150€</p>

<p>The Arc’teryx Satoro AR Zip Neck LS isn’t available yet in the shops as it launches in the autumn. I was given one when I visited Arc’teryx in Vancouver for the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/arcteryx-procline-carbon-lite-ski-boot.html">Procline Ski Boot</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/arcteryx-voltair-avalanche-airbag.html">Voltair Airbag Launch</a>, and have used it ski-touring and hiking over the last six months. Made from Merino wool and a synthetic core it combines the benefits of the two materials. The baselayer has a great fit for me (as have all Arc’teryx pieces with an Athletic cut) and I like the feel of the material on the skin. It stays odour-neutral pretty long, five or six days is no problem. The little chest pocket is good for e.g. a camera battery and SD card, and the long front zipper is great to dump heat. The price is pretty steep, though. / 202 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="black-diamond-coefficient-vest">Black Diamond Coefficient Vest</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733434642/in/dateposted/" title="Black Diamond Coefficient Vest"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7316/27733434642_64692ed7e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Black Diamond Coefficient Vest" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />120€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28PptEU">Amazon.com</a> (for $60!)</p>

<p>The from Coefficient Vest Black Diamond is not easily available anymore and that’s a sad thing in my opinion. For ages I have been a fan of vests, and this fleece vest is a really great layering piece in all seasons. Ski-touring in winter, hiking in spring and mountaineering &amp; backpacking in summer, the Coefficient Vest has been a faithful companion. The Powerdry fleece ist toasty warm and wicks sweat further away to the outside, and it’s pretty warm for its weight, too. It’s a slim-fit piece that’s slightly longer so especially good in winter. / 225 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="norrna-falketind-longsleeve">Norrøna falketind longsleeve</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733435242/in/dateposted/" title="Norrøna falketind longsleeve"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7097/27733435242_3397c8157a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Norrøna falketind longsleeve" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />80€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/28OTDbg">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/norroena-womens-falketind-long-sleeve-shirt-longsleeve/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/norrona-falketind-ls-w-039-s-shirt-cool-black-xs/">Bergzeit</a></p>

<p>More of a urban outdoor piece for me is the <a href="https://www.norrona.com/en-GB/products/falketind/falketind-long-sleeve-shirt-m/">Norrøna falketind longsleeve</a>, a beautiful and super-comfortable longsleeve. Made of drirelease wool which is a mix of wool and Polyester it is soft on the skin, and the Polygiene finish ensures it stays odour-neutral for a while (two to three days in use, I’d say). It’s simply a pretty longsleeve that feels great to wear, and a basic for me when I’m on a business trip. / 162 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="eagle-creek-pack-it-spectre">Eagle Creek Pack-It Spectre</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733433952/in/dateposted/" title="Eagle Creek Pack-It Spectre"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7427/27733433952_b4a0eb5a31_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Eagle Creek Pack-It Spectre" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />14€ - 27€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/28Q5Vme">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/eagle-creek-pack-it-specter-cube-packsack/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/eagle-creek-pack-it-specter-compression-cube-strobe-green/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28Rb2WS">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28Q6ah0">REI</a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://shop.eaglecreek.com/pack-it-specter/l/231">Pack-It Spectre Cubes</a> ensure everything stays orderly in my pack or <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/one-duffle-to-rule-them-all-the-arcteryx-carrier-duffle.html">duffle</a> when I travel. Especially If I travel only with my backpack I love to take one or two of these, as I can fit all I need in them, compress the content even further and at the hotel can just pull all my clothes out in one go. The Silynlon cubes are highly-water-resistant and their different shapes and sizes mean you can get the ones that suit you best. I have a compression cube and a smaller half cube in which I can fit garments for ten days without problems (they help in packing less, but I still tend to come home with one or two shirts I didn’t wear). A useful organizing tool if you don’t want that your underwear is seen by everyone if you get something out of your backpack! / 19 g for the Half Cube, 57 g for the large Compression Cube</p>

<h2 id="marmot-mono-pant">Marmot Mono Pant</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733435662/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Mono Pant"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7448/27733435662_fe7330b779_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Mono Pant" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />90€, available at <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/marmot-mono-pant-kletterhose-bf/">Bergfreunde</a> (On Offer for 43€!) and <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/marmot-mono-hose-red-stone-d-steel-s/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a></p>

<p>I love climbing pants because they’re comfortable and allow for freedom of movement. And if they are as comfortable and cool-looking as the <a href="http://www.marmot.de/content/en/collection_28&amp;c=703">Marmot Mono Pant</a> you can’t go wrong really. The deep pockets are great for phone, wallet and keys and there’s also a brush pocket for when you’re working on your boulder project. Great for climbing and bouldering they also work very well in the city, and as my feel-good pants they have seen a lot of use during the last year. The material is breathable yet durable, and even super-hot summer days allow you to stay cool in these. The leg cuffs an be adjusted in width so you can see you’re foot placements, too. / 325 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-gamma-rock-pants">Arc’teryx Gamma Rock Pants</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27800541576/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Gamma Rock Pants"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7428/27800541576_9907eba673_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Gamma Rock Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />150€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28On5QP">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28OXq8o">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-gamma-rock-pant-softshellhose/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-gamma-rock-hose-black-s/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a> (On Offer!) and <a href="http://bit.ly/28Spu0i">Campsaver.com</a> </p>

<p>At the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-alpine-academy-chamonix-2015.html">Arc’teryx Academy in Chamonix</a> I got the <a href="http://www.arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=Mens&amp;category=Pants&amp;model=Gamma-Rock-Pant">Gamma Rock Pants</a> and immediately fell in love with them. They are light, durable, comfortable, water- and wind-resistant, have two zippered pockets, allow for great freedom of movement and even have an integrated belt. I have used this on pretty much every 3-season hike and climb in the last twelve months, from climbing and Via Ferratas in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/love-the-dolomites-tour.html">Dolomites</a> to mountaineering in Macedonia last month and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/impressions-from-the-bregenzerwald-in-vorarlberg-austria.html">hiking in Austria</a>. If you look for just one pant for all your activities take a good luck at these trousers, as they Rock! / 299 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-a2b-chino-pants">Arc’teryx A2B Chino Pants</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733436252/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx A2B Chino Pants"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7301/27733436252_7b442c61ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx A2B Chino Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />110€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28Zx1GI">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28SqqSn">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-womens-a2b-chino-pant-jeans/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-a2b-chino-hose-w-039-s-biome-biome-6/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28OYucp">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28O50SG">REI</a></p>

<p>Another more lifestyle oriented pair of pants, the <a href="http://www.arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=Mens&amp;category=Pants&amp;model=A2B-Chino-Pant">A2B Chino Pants</a> actually are made for the bicycle commuter. If you roll the trouser leg up reflective details appear, and the material is water-resistant. A zippered side pocket ensures something important like your phone doesn’t drop out of your pocket. The two hand pockets also are good for all the other stuff you carry along. It’s a good looking pants that is at home in the city, but thanks to the bicycle cut it also is alright for medium-length rides around town. If you need a business-like pants that also allows you to ride your bike, check this one out. / 305 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="buff-high-uv-buff">BUFF High UV Buff</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27222924663/in/dateposted/" title="BUFF High UV Buff"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7205/27222924663_d90e81bd56_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="BUFF High UV Buff" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />18€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28ZSbpz">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28O5KaK">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/buff-high-uv-buff-multifunktionstuch/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/buff-high-uv-protection-buff-stem/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28SrDJn">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28PmcKu">REI</a></p>

<p>The BUFF really shouldn’t need an introduction I reckon. I got the <a href="http://www.buff.eu/es_es/anton-blue-ink.html">Anton Krupicka High UV Buff</a> as I like the print of the Flatirons on it, but with hundreds of prints you will find one that suits just your taste. These are the UL multi-use items: From it’s intended use as a piece of headwear you can convert it into a pot holder, water filter and towel. It’s a super useful item, and in these sunny summer months the High UV version keeps you from burning your head. / 39 g</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-neutro-visor">Arc’teryx Neutro Visor</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733436722/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Neutro Visor"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7418/27733436722_17be01f64b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Neutro Visor" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />25€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/28Pn2Hk">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-calvus-visor-muetze/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-calvus-visor-black-l-xl/">Bergzeit</a></p>

<p>In case a Buff and shades are not enough sun protection, then a Visor is a good way to keep the sun out of your face. The Neutro Visor from Arc’teryx is flexible, light and a nice piece for more sun protection. I can roll it up to the size of an orange if not needed and pack it away into my running short’s back pocket, and it also keeps reliably the sweat out of my eyes. / 40 g in Size S</p>

<h2 id="vivobarefoot-gobi-ii-hopewell">VIVOBAREFOOT Gobi II Hopewell</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27800559366/in/dateposted/" title="VIVOBAREFOOT Gobi II Hopewell"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7408/27800559366_8783956e76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="VIVOBAREFOOT Gobi II Hopewell" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />150€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28Pq1dT">Amazon.com</a> (for $79!)</p>

<p>Sometimes there are occasions or seasons where trailrunners or sandals are not appropriate and I need to wear proper shoes. The Gobi II Hopewell from VIVOBAREFOOT are these shoes for me, and best of all: They are proper barefoot shoes, with a wide toe box, and medium to narrow heel, a grippy sole and they look the part. A lovely pair of shoes from the guys at VIVOBAREFOOT, sadly sold out at the moment, so if you see a pair somewhere try them on and see if they suit you. / 521 g for the pair in EU Size 42</p>

<h2 id="adidas-terrex-x-king">adidas terrex X-KING</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27222775894/in/dateposted/" title="adidas terrex X-KING"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7460/27222775894_79c69509ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="adidas terrex X-KING" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />160€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28ZxMQh">Amazon.com</a> and <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/adidas-terrex-x-king-schuhe-black-uk6/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a></p>

<p>New trailrunners with an awesome sole - YEAH! The <a href="http://adidasoutdoor.com/terrex-x-king/AF5996-6.html">terrex X-King</a> sport a sole from Continental, the car and bicycle tire manufacturer, and promise to give you superb grip. Well, I ran down muddy mountains in these and didn’t slip, sprinted over icy and snowy trails and walked up on rubble paths, always with great grip. The Speed Lacing is great (though I made the one shoe a wee bit too short almost) and also otherwise this trailrunning shoe with the low drop allows for a great feel on the trail. That’s thanks to the <em>Mountain-bike-inspired “tyres for your feet” design that’s directly moulded to the upper for added stability</em>. They’re great for hiking, too, if you’re into fast &amp; light shoes with great grip. / 567 g for the pair in EU Size 42</p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research-seamseeker-gloves">Outdoor Research Seamseeker Gloves</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27733433202/in/dateposted/" title="Outdoor Research Seamseeker Gloves"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7664/27733433202_fcd8567f6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Seamseeker Gloves" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />48€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28Onrqj">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28Ppq0z">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-research-seamseeker-gloves/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/outdoor-research-seamseeker-gloves-cairn-redwood-cairn-redwood-s/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a> (On Offer for 16€!) and at <a href="http://bit.ly/28O8btM">Campsaver.com</a></p>

<p>I have used the <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/mens-seamseeker-gloves.html">Outdoor Research Seamseeker Gloves</a> for belaying and Via Ferrata hikes and have found them great in 3-season use. Especially on hot days in the Alps the open finger tips and breathable upper are comfortable and preferable in my opinion over a normal glove. The gel padding in the palm does run hot on long rappels, but otherwise they do their job well. Useful side effect: Hands get less dirty! / 98 g for the pair</p>

<h2 id="black-diamond-magnetron-rocklock">Black Diamond Magnetron RockLock</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27222774294/in/dateposted/" title="Black Diamond Magnetron RockLock"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7300/27222774294_e1e9542aaa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Black Diamond Magnetron RockLock" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />25€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28Onpz4">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-magnetron-rocklock-hms-karabiner/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-magnetron-vaporlock-hms-karabiner/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28O9bOv">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28QhZDQ">REI</a></p>

<p>I bought a pair Black Diamond Magnetron RockLock carabiners about three years ago, and both have seen constant use in that time. One is connected to my PAS (see underneath) and the other one is with my belay device. I like that they’re easy to operate in any season with one hand, with our without gloves, don’t freeze when ice climbing and are big and hence lie good in the hand. The gate opens wide for easy clipping, too. I have a bunch of HMS carabiners, but these two are my favourites for their ease of use. / 82 g</p>

<h2 id="metolius-pas-22">Metolius PAS 22</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27222774764/in/dateposted/" title="Metolius Alpine PAS"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7617/27222774764_a76300b248_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Metolius Alpine PAS" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />50€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28TreEC">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28P5VAA">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/metolius-pas-22-standschlinge/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/metolius-personal-anchor-system-black/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28RmBNX">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28OaaOI">REI</a> </p>

<p>PAS stands for <strong>P</strong>ersonal <strong>A</strong>nchor <strong>S</strong>ysyem, and if you do Multi-pitch or alpine climbing then you probably know what this is. You clip into the stand (belay) with it, and the beauty of the <a href="http://www.metoliusclimbing.com/pas_personal_anchor_system.html">PAS from Metolius</a> is that the six loops all have a breaking load of 22 kN. The length is adjustable to your needs at the belay and can be long or short, and each loop having such a high breaking load means more security. It’s also light and stores compact when climbing, so for me a better system than a Daisychain or a 120 cm sling. / 76 g</p>

<h2 id="scarpa-furia">Scarpa Furia</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27222775074/in/dateposted/" title="Scarpa Furia"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7656/27222775074_32a0dbac13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Furia" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />145€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28Tew8J">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/28QkcPU">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/scarpa-furia-kletterschuhe/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/scarpa-furia-kletterschuhe-black-36/">Bergzeit</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/28PrYfm">Campsaver.com</a></p>

<p>The Furia from <a href="http://scarpa.it">Scarpa</a> is a climbing shoe for bouldering and sports climbing. I found the VIBRAM® XS Grip2 sole great for slabs and small holds alike, and friction climbing in them is a lot of fun. The toe is covered with rubber on top, too, which makes it great for toe hooks, and the heel is also covered in rubber for heel hooks. Inside it feels very comfortable and even in hot weather (25°C+ in Greece, for example) it remains comfortable. The two Velcro straps allow to adjust the shoe great to my foot, and the two straps in the back make it easy to pull the shoe on and off. It’s a more advanced shoe so beginners probably want a less aggressive shoe than this one, but if you’re climbing hard then this shoe is right for you and can help you to solve a hard boulder problem or succeed on a hard sports route. / 366 g for the Pair in Size 40 </p>

<h2 id="grivel-mega-k6g">Grivel Mega K6G</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27558333150/in/dateposted/" title="Grivel Mega K6G"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7265/27558333150_0bef887728_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grivel Mega K6G" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />18€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/28Pz3fN">Backcountry.com</a> and <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-twingate-mega-k6g-hms-karabiner/">Bergfreunde</a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.grivel.com/products/rock/carabiners/25-mega_k6g">Twingate carabiners from Grivel</a> are awesome, a real innovation in the climbing carabiner market. Grivel thinks they’re just as safe a a screwlock carabiner, and I think I agree. Things must be pretty dire for something to open this in a situation, but they’re easy to use with one hand (without gloves) on the other hand. I use the one I have in different situations, and Grivel suggests you could use it from building a belay to clipping into one. It’s a tad heavy for alpine use, but works well on Multipitch climbs et al. / 76 g</p>

<h2 id="scott-obsess-acs-sunglasses">SCOTT Obsess ACS Sunglasses</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27222775504/in/dateposted/" title="SCOTT Obsess ACS Sunglasses"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7242/27222775504_c8f74637d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SCOTT Obsess ACS Sunglasses" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />80€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/28PxZIC">Amazon.com</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/28PdJCh">Amazon.co.uk</a></p>

<p>I like sunglasses and use them year-around, almost every day. The <a href="http://www.scott-sports.com/us/en/products/2355124747192/SCOTT-Obsess-ACS-Sunglasses/">Obsess ACS from Scott</a> I can wear without problems for 12 hours straight, so comfortable they are. Made for small to medium faces they fit me very well. The mirrored glasses in red also are surprisingly scratch-resistant and they haven’t gotten a single one in the 9+ months I now have them in use. Developed as bicycle glasses they work equally well for skiing and hiking as well as strolling through town &amp; travelling. They’re pretty affordable, too, for such good shades. In some situations they do fog up a bit, but if I take them up it really just takes six seconds and they’re clear again. Great shades for just about any outdoor adventure. / 27 g </p>

<h2 id="montane-softflask-500-ml">Montane Softflask 500 ml</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27222776114/in/dateposted/" title="Montane Softflask 500 ml"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7201/27222776114_648d39f27b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Montane Softflask 500 ml" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>★★☆☆
<br />25€, available at <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/montane-softflask-trinkflasche/">Bergfreunde</a></p>

<p>At 25€ the 500 ml Softflask is far from being a bargain. It’s also not particularly light in terms of weight-to-volume. But it’s easy and convenient to use - both for drinking as well when storing the empty bottle, as it takes up just a wee bit of space. If you need a light-ish softbottle give the Softflask a look and decide if you want one. / 30 g</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Some of the gear was sent for free to me. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[#OutDoorFN 2016 is a go!]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/outdoorfn-2016-is-a-go.html"/>
    <updated>2016-06-21T23:28:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/outdoorfn-2016-is-a-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just three more short weeks until the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2015/">OutDoor</a> 2016 kicks off in Friedrichshafen, and I’m already pretty psyched for my fourth visit to the trade show at Lake Constance. Read more on why this year the OutDoor is set to be even more awesome than in the previous years!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653293216/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Tents!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5678/20653293216_721f13d920_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tents!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="where-to-go">Where to go?</h2>

<p>I have a short list of must-visit places &amp; companies I want to check out at the fair - from the Trend Lounge and Black Diamond over Petzl to Adidas Outdoor, as well as the usual suspects Arc’teryx, RAB and Scarpa, plus a few more. But is there a company you - <em>yes, you reading this!</em> - would like me to visit? With <a href="http://www.outdoor-show.com/od-en/index-of-exhibitors/index.php?navid=538007229630">960 exhibitors from 40 nations</a> the list is long, so if you’re curious about a specific company why not let me know in the comments which company you think I should check out and I will swing by them at the fair to check them out &amp; report on their kit!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20670323912/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Klättermusen booth"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/758/20670323912_39e2265786_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Klättermusen booth" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bloggers-are-welcome-at-the-outdoor">Bloggers are welcome at the OutDoor!</h2>

<p>The best thing for me at the OutDoor has always been meeting the people: The contacts you exchange emails with at the companies and PR Agencies, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">meeting athletes</a> and of course my fellow bloggers and Social Media mates. So I’m pretty excited about the <a href="http://www.outdoor-show.com/od-en/the-outdoor/outdoor-blogger-base.php?navid=545263545263">OBN Blogger Base</a>, which allows me to work &amp; meet fellow bloggers from across the globe. Best of all: OBN organizes every day an OBN_talk where you can learn about topics which are important to us, and the Blogger Walk across the fair promises to be a good way to meet new companies, too. </p>

<p>If you’re an outdoor blogger you totally want to <a href="http://www.outdoor-show.com/od-en/press/Blogger.php">get accredited as a blogger</a> for the fair, as it has a lot of benefits - from access to the Blogger Base to the Blogger Breakfast. And best of all: It’s free for us outdoor bloggers! Apply now for your <a href="http://www.outdoor-show.com/od-en/press/Blogger.php">Blogger Pass</a>, and then comment and lets meet up at the OutDoor! </p>

<p>And already now and during the fair you can follow the Hashtag #OutDoorFN on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/outdoorfn/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OutDoorFN">Twitter</a> for real-time updates on the fair. I’m sure it will be super busy once the 13th of July comes around!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20516112978/in/album-72157656356655229/" title="Vaude Citus 24 LW Backpack"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5643/20516112978_a85234b05f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude Citus 24 LW Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I am a co-founder of the <a href="http://en.outdoor-blogger-network.com/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Network</a> and am involved with the OBN activities at the fair. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
