<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-18T14:29:40+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Via Dinarica in Bosnia and Herzegovina]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/the-via-dinarica-in-bosnia-and-herzegovina.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-18T23:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/the-via-dinarica-in-bosnia-and-herzegovina</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I returned last Friday from a beautiful backpacking trip on the Via Dinarica in Bosnia and Herzegovina. It’s wild, gorgeous and has lots to offer to backpackers, packrafters, mountaineers and bikepackers alike. <em>A teaser of things to come.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17715452652" title="Looking towards Maglić by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7771/17715452652_19f6ddb3dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Looking towards Maglić" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’m a tad busy so a detailed write-up has to wait, but enjoy one photo of each day (and then book your flights to Sarajevo to experience your own Balkan adventure)!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17482619688" title="Snow Ridge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5446/17482619688_90251c50aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow Ridge" /></a>
Day 1 gave a taste of the snowy things to come. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17788651356" title="In the mist &amp; rain on Prenj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8837/17788651356_56418d585d_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="In the mist &amp; rain on Prenj" /></a>
Day 2 brought rain, mist and climbing 60° snow slopes without mountaineering gear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17194614483" title="Jezerce Mountain Hut in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7770/17194614483_2bf6ddcfb6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jezerce Mountain Hut in the background" /></a>
A relaxed lunch was had at the Jezerce Mountain Hut on Day three.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17192476044" title="Dubocani village by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8868/17192476044_a79da411f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dubocani village" /></a>
Nestled in the lush, green valley was the Dubocani village we passed on Day four.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17192470994" title="Upward to Maglić by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5467/17192470994_490c3fd46a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Upward to Maglić" /></a>
And on Day five we climbed up to Maglić, the highest summit of Bosnia and Herzegovina.</p>

<p><strong>Stay tuned for more shortly!</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 03/2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/trekking-magazin-03-slash-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-15T23:28:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/trekking-magazin-03-slash-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The newest trekking Magazin is available and has great trip reports, tips on outdoor photography and several specials by yours truly!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17502601540" title="trekking Magazin 03/2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8867/17502601540_54e73fc0df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 03/2015" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The new issue has a very lengthy special on Via Ferratas by me, as well as hiking in dangerous terrain. The latter gives tips on what to do when there’s no blue bird weather but you’re confronted by hail, snow and strong winds, how to cross rivers and what to consoder when you’re in the mountains and on glaciers. In my gear column I talk about approach shoes and review five pairs of approach shoes from <a href="http://bit.ly/1zDfoq6">adidas</a>, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/arcteryx-acrux2-fl-gtx.html">Arc’teryx</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/lowa-laurin-gtx-lo-approachschuhe/">Lowa</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/five-ten-guide-tennie-schuhe-ca-sun-ca-sun-uk4/">Five Ten</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/salomon-x-alp-gtx-approachschuhe/">Salomon</a>. There’s also great tips on outdoor photography and plenty of great trip reports in Germany, Austria, Italy and Romania.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17069819103" title="trekking Magazin 03/2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7721/17069819103_accddc1e6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 03/2015" /></a></p>

<p>There’s still plenty more in there so pick up your copy today on the way home or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> to not miss any future issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/arcteryx-acrux2-fl-gtx.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-07T20:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/arcteryx-acrux2-fl-gtx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Acrux² FL GTX from <a href="http://arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a> is the Canadian brand’s entry into the approach footwear business. Made of an hydrophobic outside and a Gore-Tex slipper with a Vibram MegaGrip sole, it is a unique shoe. How it performed in the outdoors, you can read here.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17203304149" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Side and Sole by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7794/17203304149_daccb18e5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Side and Sole" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The Acrux² FL GTX arrived in late March and has been along on the International Appalachian Trail in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ireland/">Ireland</a>, where I wore it for seven days straight in rain and sunshine. I usually review gear only after a long period of time - often a year or longer - but as there’s a lot of interest in this shoe I wrote this initial review. I will update it after more use in the future. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16767071834" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX at the coast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8700/16767071834_2caf372641_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX at the coast" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX is two shoes in one: A Gore-Tex liner (blue) and a Hydrophobic shell shoe (black). For simplicity’s sake I will refer to them as the liner and shell. As an approach shoe it’s function is to allow you to get easily to the crag and back and for that it has a grippy sole with a climbing zone in the toe area which allows you to do easy scrambles in them. The shell does not absorb water and the liner has a Gore-Tex lining, which makes it highly water-resistant.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Technical alpine approach footwear for multiple days spent in variable weather &amp; terrain.</em> - Arc’teryx</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17389527535" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Liner bootie and its insole by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5329/17389527535_206647f76f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Liner bootie and its insole" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>As from Arc’teryx’s website:</p>

<p>Sole: 
<br />- 3D moulded Ortholite™ footbed
<br />- Vibram® MegaGrip™ sole
<br />- 14 mm Heel Drop
<br />- Sharp heel brake and mountaineering heel tread</p>

<p>Shell:
<br />- Seamless one piece upper with thermolaminated construction
<br />- EVA foam midsole
<br />- Hydrophobic material</p>

<p>Liner:
<br />- Tongue free liner
<br />- Low height, light weight
<br />- Arc’teryx Adaptive fit is an independent liner that conforms to the foot for a custom fit with no pressure points
<br />- Stetchable GORE-TEX® liner
<br />- Completely removable, interchangeable liner
<br />- Rubberized sole</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EcIPgSWo_cA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Arc’teryx separated the shell and lining of a traditional shoe and made two separate ones out of it, while re-designing both. So the upper is made from a single-piece of fabric, with a TPU-coating on the non-perforated parts which make them abrasion-resistant and let them shed water easily. The shell is also not sewn, but all parts are laminated together for a seam-free feel, which minimizes the risk of blisters and chaffing.</p>

<p>While there might have been shoes like these before, Arc’teryx is the first brand in recent time that brings a shoe with a removable liner to market. What’s very special is that the liners of the Acrux² and the Bora² are interchangable - which means you can use the high, insulated liner of the Bora in your Acrux, or if you need more water-protection in the Acrux use the high Gore-Tex bootie liner - They all work together. The liner is also thought to increase the airflow inside the shoe, which should maximize ventilation. It’s made from stretchable materials which hug your feet for a comfortable feeling, all day long.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17363563336" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX 0.1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7789/17363563336_c26f9bc77a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX 0.1" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The quality of these shoes - both liner and shell - is superb as you expect from Arc’teryx. The whole construction is very tidy and clean, with no little threads hanging around. The laminated upper is super smooth and stylish, while the liner bootie has minimal seams and is very comfortable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17203302069" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Shell, insole and liner bootie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7762/17203302069_35755460e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Shell, insole and liner bootie" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX is a medium-weight shoe, in EU Size 42 they weigh:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Liner: 126 g</li>
  <li>Shoe: 371 g</li>
  <li>Total: 499 g</li>
  <li><strong>PAIR 998 g</strong></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17389527005" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 0.5 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8710/17389527005_3de2af25d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 0.5" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The Acrux² FL GTX is a stylish shoe. If you travel a lot to go climbing &amp; hiking and also will spend some time in civilization, airplanes, hotels and B&amp;Bs the Acrux FL² GTX are great beacause while they are functional approach shoes they also could pass as a stylish city sneaker. I used them as a scramble and approach shoe as I was <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">sea stack climbing</a> and there they worked fantastic. The Vibram MegaGrip sole had superb traction on the wet slabs at the coast, and the small climbing zones at the toes allowed for good foot placements on small ledges. </p>

<p>Also for hiking the shoes were very comfortable, even in hot weather (more on that underneath). I was a bit worried before flying to Ireland if the shoe would be too hot and might give me blisters, but the truth was that even on long, high kilometer days the shoes were comfortable and I finished the trip without blisters, even on those close to 20°C sunshine &amp; blue-bird days. The laces were very good and did not come undone, something which has been a problem with some other shoes. The shoe is comfortable all day long, the liner hugs my foot nicely and you can lace up the shell as loose or tight as you like. At 499 g per shoe they’re medium weight but I didn’t get tired feet in the shoes. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17203380689" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7681/17203380689_b77edb80bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX" /></a></p>

<p>Now one of the design ideas of this shoes was that you can take the Gore-Tex liner out if it gets wet and can dry it overnight in your sleeping bag or tent. In practice I am not sure if it works, to get the liners dry again I needed to place them close to a radiator so that they would be dry the next morning; if there was no heat source then they were still moist the next morning. It could be that if you take the moist liners into your sleeping bag at a bivy that they will dry out well, but in my limited tests I am not sure if it works. An alternative could be to carry a 2nd pair of liner booties - at 126 g they’re not too heavy - and so ensure always dry feet. What I missed in this respect was that the shell did not have some drainage/ ventilation holes at the sole-level, this would help to get water out faster when you wade through a stream (or bog!).</p>

<p>What the liners are really great for is being used as a camp shoe. I used them to stroll around and the grippy rubber sole and light weight made them excellent for that. I also can imagine them to work very well for <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/packrafting/">packrafting</a>, where you can use them as your bootie in the packraft and the complete shoe for hiking. I jumped from rock to rock over the Atlantic with them on my sea stack adventure and they gave good grip on the wet &amp; salty rocks at the Irish coast, which means for me that they should be good as a paddling booty. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17182072687" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 1.0 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7786/17182072687_852f3232fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 1.0" /></a></p>

<p>Fit-wise I found the liner and shell to be both spacious. The EU Size 42 shoe gave me plenty of space inside the liner bootie to move my toes around, and when laced tighly they gave me good control and feel on small ledges. The heel did feel a bit wider and could for me be more narrow, but with a sock that’s well-cushioned in the heel you will have a good feel and should be fine. Overall a good &amp; spacious fit for my normal feet with plenty of space for movement.</p>

<p>I have a couple of gripes thus far with the shoe: The black shell makes the shoe very hot. Even on the mild (+11°C) spring days we have currently here in Vaasa the shoe is getting very hot, very quickly. I wore <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/bridgedale-coolmax-liner-socke-doppelpack-black-black-36-39/?pid=81">Coolmax socks</a> which usually are good in warm weather, but in this shoe I got hot feet very quickly. I am not sure if another colour would mitigate this, or if the shell would just need more &amp; larger ventilation openings in the shell shoe so the ventilation is improved. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17203302519" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 2.0 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8702/17203302519_31521ebe12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 2.0" /></a></p>

<p>The second thing I do not recommend: Walk through a bog with them. Along the IAT in Ireland I crossed several swamps, and the combination of bog flora &amp; fauna + my own sweat created an unbearable smell in the shoes. It was absolutely terrible and I felt slightly afraid to go sit with them in a plane for several hours. At home I first tried the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grangers-universal-spray-cleaner-275ml/">Granger’s Universal Spray Cleaner</a> but that showed no success in terms of getting rid of the smell (probably should have used the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grangers-odour-eliminator-60ml/?pid=81">Granger’s Odour Eliminator</a>), so they went into the washing machine with <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/nikwax-tech-wash-pflegemittel-002/?pid=81">Nikwax Tech Wash</a> which got rid of the smell for the most part. So I would not recommend them for walking in swamps right now, unless there’s a good way to get rid of the smell. If you’re in alpine environments where there’s no bogs this will not be of concern, but in Ireland, Scotland, Wales, England and Scandinavia you’re likely to encounter swamps in the hills, so keep this in mind (It might be of course that your sweat germs in combination with a bog’s flora &amp; fauna creates an irresistible odour and it’s just my sweat that’s wrong!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17182071337" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7728/17182071337_162901961c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, I hope Arc’teryx will release at the coming <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor</a> an membrane-free bootie liner. It really is missing for me in their bootie line-up, and I think it would make the shoe even more attractive for those of us who don’t need a Gore-Tex or Insulated bootie. Make it highly breathable with good drainage, with a material that’s odour-neutral, and it could be a winner.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17387539812" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Shell Inside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7721/17387539812_572df856b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Shell Inside" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>I am not aware right now if there’s similar shoes that are made of a liner + shell, but I have no doubts that there could be. For ultralight backpackers and weight-conscious alpinists a combination of a unlined approach shoe + a <a href="http://bit.ly/1F5m1op">Gore-Tex sock</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1F5lXVO">Neoprene Sock</a> could also create this combination of a quick-drying shoe and a waterproof liner that you can dry easily over night. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17387540382" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Made for approaches by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7786/17387540382_19e7fb9a24_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Made for approaches" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Acrux² FL GTX is a shoe that brings fresh wind into the approach shoe market. A comfortable, removable liner paired with a hydrophobic, stylish shell and a grippy Vibram MegaGrip sole make this a great shoe for approaches, Via Ferratas and scrambles. The price of 250€ puts it at the high-end, but then you get essentially two shoes for the price of one. Add in the versatilty the Acrux² offers with the interchangable, removable liners and you have a great shoe for your mountain adventures, and you can get rid of a stinky liner bootie if you have hiked through a bog! Finally, as this is the first Generation of Arc’teryx footwear we can be curious to see what they will come up with the next Generations!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157651938930537">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-acrux-fl-gtx">Where to buy the Acrux² FL GTX</h2>

<p>You can get them directly from <a href="">Arc’teryx</a> or at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-acrux-2-fl-approachschuhe/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-alpha2-fl-gtx-schuhe-black-big-surf-uk6-5/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1F5uZCc">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1GOzXhD">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1GYO9XR">REI</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17182073947" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Side by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7713/17182073947_cbcd710c7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Side" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/jacks-r-better-high-sierra-sniveller.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-06T21:03:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/jacks-r-better-high-sierra-sniveller</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller</a> is the Multi-Tool amongst the winter quilts, as it not just is a toasty quilt for your autumn to spring backpacking trips but also works as a Poncho/ Serape and can be used with your hammock. Toasty times!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17375828181" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Reading/ chilling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5464/17375828181_01ce55ee52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Reading/ chilling" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller</a> arrived in December 2013 at HiF HQ and has seen several outings since, amongst others to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html">Lake District</a> in England.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376802441" title="Bed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5515/14376802441_7b2115dea3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller is not just a quilt. It is</p>

<ul>
  <li>A quilt</li>
  <li>A serape/ poncho</li>
  <li>A top quilt for your hammock</li>
  <li>Almost a sleeping bag</li>
</ul>

<p>Made for cold temperatures the High Sierra Sniveller is a winter quilt which should keep you toasty to around -5°C to -10°C, maybe even colder temperatures if you’re a warm sleeper.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17350199956" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Inside open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7785/17350199956_125178e9ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Inside open" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The High Sierra Sniveller can be used as a flat blanket, a sleeping bag/ quilt and a serape. A serape is like a poncho, and for that it has a Velcro head hole in the middle which you can open and put your head through. You then can tie it closed around your waist to minimize drafts. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376162885" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Closed in the back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8698/17376162885_dbf25b1de9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Closed in the back" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The JRB Sierra Sniveller Quilt is very well constructed, with clean seams, durable and high-quality materials. It uses a 1.1 oz., 30 denier ripstop nylon and 800 cuin fill power goose down. The shell &amp; lining material is soft and comfortable on the skin and the high-quality down keeps you toasty warm.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17375828531" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Tags by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7795/17375828531_440530fdf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Tags" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>679 g High Sierra Sniveller Quilt, Regular length</p>

<p>38 g Compression stuff sack</p>

<p><strong>717 g Total</strong></p>

<p>That’s a very good weight for a winter quilt, especially when set in relation to the price. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376164525" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Down under by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5450/17376164525_c009b7de26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Down under" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/quilt-comparison-chart/">Quilt Comparison Chart</a> is ideal in my opinion for anyone considering a JRB quilt. These kind of tables should be standard for any company offering many similar products within the same category, as it makes choosing the right product for a customer much easier. </p>

<p>The High Sierra Sniveller is unassuming. A green, stealthy shell blends in in forest environments, and the black inside helps with drying the quilt in the sun in the morning. The construction is clean and sturdy, and while being lightweight I didn’t have the feeling that I need to treat it with silk gloves. The cord locks and cords as well as the Velcro closures radiate sturdiness, too. </p>

<p>I have used the High Sierra Sniveller mostly as a quilt/ sleeping bag and a flat blanket, in both configurations I was very happy with it. The footbox is long enough for me and it is easy to take one leg out of it to <em>“cool down”</em>. The Regular length has a small taper, it’s 132 cm wide at the top and goes down to 96 cm at the foot end. It was a good size for my thin self and drafts where no problem, also when sleeping on my side. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376164655" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Chilling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8715/17376164655_8c5f7da7c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Chilling" /></a></p>

<p>I have used the JRB High Sierra Sniveller on autumn and spring trips where temperatures went down to around -2°C and it was too warm for me in those conditions, so I think it’s easily good to -5°C to -10°C as claimed by JRB. If you like to strap the quilt to your mat then there’s three pairs of webbing loops to allow you to do that. </p>

<p>Using it as a serape is only something for morning and evening use in Camp, I wouldn’t want to wear it while moving throughout the day - it’s not very ergonomic. If you’re out on a winter trip and want to minimize the puffy, space-consuming down jacket for camp and breaks, the High Sierra Sniveller will be a good solution for you. The draw-back is that you need to be more careful around campfires when wearing your High Sierra Sniveller, as you don’t want any holes from sparks or such in it. If saving weight &amp; space is a high importance, then the multiple use aspect of this quilt will be high. If not needed the head hole closes tightly and almost can’t be seen, and also has not been a source of drafts or similar. This is a good feature for people who want it, and if you don’t need it it’s easy enough to ignore that it’s there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17168694907" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole closed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8782/17168694907_cb451e5ed1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole closed" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188369558" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7774/17188369558_f630c2f75a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole open" /></a></p>

<p>I didn’t like the compression bag a lot - it does tend to get into a strange shape, and the biggest problem I have with that is that packing it in a backpack creates some unusable, empty space. Also the pull strap you can hold on to feels, while being sturdily sewn, that it could break. I much prefer super basic roll-top closure stuff sacks that are light. The storage <em>“sack”</em> is a plastic square bag with a zipper, which I also felt isn’t the best place to store a down bag. Here I prefer large (organic) cotton bags or at least a fabric that’s breathable. Organic cotton bags also would be more environmentally friendly, and look nicer if stored in plain sight. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17189931059" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Size comparison by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8728/17189931059_3b7cb85afd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Size comparison" /></a></p>

<p>With the sleeping bag I have no serious complaints. I saw that the head end got a push button in 2014 which allows you to close the quilt around your neck so it stays in place, this is a nice feature especially on more breezy, cold nights as it keeps drafts out and the warm air in. JRB also is now using a hydrophobic down, which is good for a quilt which is likely used in wet &amp; cold environments. The cord locks and cords are very durable and big, I imagine JRB could easily use smaller &amp; lighter versions of these without making them more difficult to use but saving a bit of weight. I also would put the top loops for attaching the quilt to a mat further down, though in use the two pairs in the middle should be enough if you use that feature.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193694557" title="Camp II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2898/14193694557_4fe213486b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Camp II" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>The quilt maker market has seen some influx in the last years, and also some big brands have started to make quilts. Directly competing with the JRB High Sierra Sniveller are for me, given it’s unique feature set, only the <a href="http://astucas.com/en/products/sestrals-poncho">As Tucas Sestrals Poncho</a> and the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=42&amp;products_id=133">MLD Spirit Quilt</a>, though both are synthetic insulation quilts. These have the option to wear it as a poncho. A warm winter quilt is also the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/01/katabatic-gear-sawatch-quilt.html">Katabatic Gear Sawatch Quilt</a>, and then there’s several other quilts &amp; sleeping bags which are fit for winter use.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188583110" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Top View by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7664/17188583110_59c95bb036_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Top View" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Ultralight-Sleeping-Bag-Reviews/Jacks-R-Better-Sierra-Sniveller">Outdoor Gear Lab</a> gave it 4 Stars and <a href="http://treadoutdoors.blogspot.fi/2014/11/love-sniveller-jack-r-better-sierra.html">T.R.E.A.D. Outdoors</a> rates it high, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188369208" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - A look from beneath by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8732/17188369208_47fa87f620_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - A look from beneath" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I like the Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller. The Multiple-use aspect of it is great: You can use it as an open blanket, a quilt, a poncho and also as a top quilt in your hammock, which is superb value for your money - if you need these options. If you don’t plan to use the High Sierra Sniveller as a serape you might be able to save some weight by getting a quilt without the head hole, though it probably is useful to have in an emergency - and does not add a substantial amount of weight. As a quilt it performs just as it should: Unpack, let it loft and then have a comfortable, un-restricted night’s sleep underneath it. It’s easy to vent when you run warm, and if you plan to use it as a serape it will save you money that you’d spent on a dedicated down jacket. If you’re looking for a multiple-use, lightweight, warm and affordable autumn to spring quilt, take a good look at the High Sierra Sniveller from Jacks ‘R’ Better - you won’t be disappointed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157652366367951">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>You can buy the <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">High Sierra Sniveller</a> at <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/">Jacks ‘R’ Better</a>. Right now it is on Sale and starts at $310 (regular price starts at $410).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188368038" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Sleeping by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7708/17188368038_aac28bc259_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Sleeping" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DMM Demon Cams]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/dmm-demon-cams.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T23:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/dmm-demon-cams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dragons and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">Demons</a> are not just part of any good fantasy novel, but also hang on the harness of many Trad Climbers. And because for longer routes you need more than just a set of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/dmm-dragon-cams.html">Dragon Cams</a>, a pair of Demon Cams has found their way into my climbing pack. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16743368694" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7688/16743368694_34f21b81ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">DMM Demon Cams</a> arrived last spring and have been along to Olhava, the local crag close to Vaasa, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">rock climbing in Poland</a> and Alpine climbing in Chamonix. But why would I need a 2nd pair of cams besides the Dragons? Well, longer routes need more protection, the Demon Cams have different size ranges than the Dragon, are a single axle design and are lighter. That was enough reason for me to get a pair from <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, and since they have free shipping on orders over 50€ in Europe it has gotten pretty easy to order from them.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/49821137?color=cc0033&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="600" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The Demon is a combination of two DMM Cams: It takes the single stem of the Dragon and the Cams of the 4CU. They are single axle, single stem, with the trademark extendable Dyneema sling. The cam lobes make use of the 13.75° camming angle, have an Active strength rating of 14 kN (and a Passive rating of 10 kN) and are Made in Wales.</p>

<p>As you might know, cams are active protection. While the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts.html">nuts and hexes</a> have no moving parts, cams do have moving parts - this allows them to suit a wider range of cracks - where you might need to carry one or more different nuts to place them in a crack, a cam’s lobes can be moved by pulling on the trigger which makes them narrower &amp; thus you can enter it in a crack. Release the trigger and the lobes will wedge themselves into the rock, being, if placed correctly, a solid piece of protection. They are also versatile in the sense that you can use them passively - that is that you just place the cam as it is into a crack, much like a Nut, without pulling the trigger. Unlike the DMM Dragon Cams the Demon Cam has a lower passive strength rating than active rating. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16743368334" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8774/16743368334_eff30e3137_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>The Demons come without a carabiner, so I got the colour-coded <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-alpha-trad-non-locking-carabiner/">DMM Alpha Trad ‘biners</a> and two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-phantom-non-locking-carabiner/">Phantom carabiners</a> with the cams. The Trad biners are very nice and easy to clip, quite large and at 34 g they’re still light. The Phantom is only 26 g but you can easily feel and note the difference in size, its gate is also a bit heavier to clip. If you get pumped or nervous and want to be sure you can easily and quickly clip the rope, take the Alpha trad carabiners, they have a far better handling. Cam Lobes, slings and Alpha Trad carabiners can (and should!) be colour-matched for easily finding the right cam when you’re on the wall.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365876125" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8824/17365876125_aaf623fb92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>Back to the Demon Cams, and lets look at their weights. Here’s the weight of the Demon Cam alone and with a Alpha Trad carabiner.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Size 4,0: 223 g (259 g)</li>
  <li>Size 3,5: 182 g (218 g)</li>
  <li>Size 2,5: 129 g (165 g)</li>
  <li>Size 1,5: 102 g (138 g)</li>
  <li>Size 1,0: 98 g (134 g)</li>
  <li>Size 0,5: 90 g (126 g)</li>
  <li>Size 0: 84 g (120 g)</li>
</ul>

<p>The whole rack of seven Demon cams with Alpha Trad biners is 1.160 g. That is a tad heavier than the Dragons (the six of them including carabiners is 819 g) but the size range of the Demons here speaks for them. For comparison:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Size 4 Demon Cam (223 g) has a lobe size range of 64 to 100 mm</li>
  <li>Size 4 Dragon Cam (149 g) has a lobe size range of 38 to 64 mm</li>
</ul>

<p>This difference can be seen throughout the two Cam lines. If you want to have a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/camming-devices/">Cam</a> with a large operating range, then the Demon is the way to go my opinion.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365533331" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8899/17365533331_95f25e7afa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>The 8 mm Dyneema sling is extendable to 23 cm which allows you to carry less slings and quick-draws to the hills. I love this feature of the DMM Cams and wouldn’t want to miss it. DMM also thinks along and offers a service to re-sling the cams when the Dyneema slings become worn out, which is a sustainable and environmentally friendly service and makes the cams long-lasting.</p>

<p>Which brings me to Quality. Which is fantastic. I guess you have expected this already, but I really value these cams - as all my other gear from DMM - very highly. The flexible stem, durable materials that are anodized makes them long-lasting, also at <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">sea stacks</a>. They have seen quite a bit of use but still look pretty good, and I expect them to last many more years.</p>

<p>If there’s something which I don’t like about them, well they are expensive - but then so are most cams. I also am wondering why DMM does repeat colours on the cams and ‘biners - Gold, Blue and Silver are used twice in the same series, and with there being hundreds of colours this is a bit odd. I would wish DMM would add more colours in the future, this makes it easier to choose the right cam and eliminates mix-ups. Imagine you want to grab the large blue 3.5 cam but grab the tiny blue 0 cam? Also the stem could be a tiny bit longer, which would make it easier to place them in deep cracks. I also think they could be offered as a complete set with a carabiner (preferably for a better price than buying them separately). And finally, if they’d be a <em>tiny</em> bit lighter, well, I wouldn’t mind that either!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17158410927" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8854/17158410927_28d89d8448_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I really like <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/brands/dmm/">DMM</a> gear. It’s well-designed and Made in Europe, which I value a lot. With the climbing trips this year I reckon the Dragons and Demons will both see plenty of use, especially in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html">Dolomites</a> and here in Finland. If you’re new to Trad climbing and in the market for some active protection then you might want to have a chat with your climbing partners and see what they recommend for your home crag, but eventually, and especially when you will travel to go climbing, you will likely end up with a complete rack or more. With the Demons you get a superb single stem, single axle cam. You’ll value the extendable sling pretty quickly as it allows you to leave some Quick-draws at the bottom of the crag. They are easy to place and equally easy to remove if you second. These durable cams will not make you a better climber, but they are so long-lasting that they will see you become better over time. </p>

<p>You can get the complete DMM Demon Cam package at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a> in Europe and <a href="http://bit.ly/1JLrstV">Backcountry.com</a> in North America. And <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157652287977376">more photos are on Flickr</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365531111" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7734/17365531111_16a28f5bf1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 201]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/the-week-in-review-201.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-04T20:34:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/the-week-in-review-201</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Because it’s there.”</em>
― <a href="http://amzn.to/1EJE6Fi">George Mallory</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16654145983" title="Willing model at a stormy coast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7657/16654145983_70016f9a89_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Willing model at a stormy coast" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>LAUFBURSCHE launched three new pack series, the Plus Line, the Core Line and the Lite Line. <a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/packs/">Check them out</a>!</p>

<p>Hydrophil offer <a href="http://www.hydrophil.biz/">ultralight &amp; sustainable bamboo toothbrushes</a>. Getting a light toothbrush has never been easier!</p>

<p>Hyperlite Mountain Gear <a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/bug-off-ultamid-mesh-inserts/">UltaMid Inserts are here</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.shaunacoxsey.co.uk/2015/05/time-to-break-the-silence/">Shauna breaks the silence</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bunterwegs.com/tipps-fuer-frauen-fernwanderung/">8 Tips for women on long-distance hikes</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Sherpa Adventure Gear has created the earthquake relief fund called <a href="https://www.crowdrise.com/helpsherpashelpnepal">“Help Sherpas Help Nepal”</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/everests-helicopters-couldve-been-used-elsewhere/">Everest’s Helicopters Could’ve Been Used Elsewhere</a>, some good thoughts in there.</p>

<p><a href="http://thatemilychappell.com/2015/04/how-to-host-a-cyclist/">How to host a cyclist</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ulligunde.com/2015/05/ist-das-gegenteil-von-abenteuer-eigentlich-langweilig/">Is “boring” the opposite of “adventure”</a>? [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com/choosing-life-ordinary/">Choosing a Life Less Ordinary</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/04/30/news-termine-mai-2015/">News &amp; dates for May 2015</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Lots of climbing gear up to 60% off at the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/outlet/climbing/">Bergfreunde.co.uk Outlet</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=259941&amp;pw=73183">Save 30% on popular Patagonia Jackets, Shirts, Pants &amp; more + Free Shipping at Patagonia.com</a>!</p>

<p>Up to <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=49133&amp;pw=73183">30% Off Patagonia, Big Agnes, &amp; Icebreaker during the Backcountry.com Spring Sale</a> + Free 2-Day Shipping over $50.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=197101&amp;pw=73183">Climbing Equipment Sale at CampSaver.com</a> - Get up to 30% off ropes, carabiners, harnesses and more.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>The guys from RolloMixed did it again, a recommended read: <a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2015/04/mattacorru-traverse.html">Máttačorru traverse</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p><a href="https://mitsackundpackraft.wordpress.com/2015/05/01/nochmal-weils-so-schon-war-der-donaudurchbruch-per-packraft/">Packrafting on the Danube wth kids</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Camping &amp; sketching at <a href="http://campillustrated.com/post/117919059101/big-sur">Big Sur</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2015/04/rode-trip-cottonwood-canyon/">Cottonwood Canyon Basecamp</a>.</p>

<p>Matthew hikes in the <a href="http://hillplodder.com/2015/05/02/the-valley-of-sluggishness/">Valley of Sluggishness</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://runrideandsleepoutside.wordpress.com/2015/05/03/something-simple/">Something Simple</a>.</p>

<p>Packrafting on <a href="http://injuringeternity.net/2015/05/03/shallow-waters-a-short-trip-to-nittalven/">Nittälven</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lvujuoDDh4Q" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Nick heads out for an overnighter to <a href="http://tms.nickbramhall.com/blog/2015/04/beinn-bhuidhe/">Beinn Bhuidhe</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/1825136/come-herd-or-high-water">Come Herd or High Water</a>.</p>

<p>Emma’s <a href="http://emmaamerikassa.blogspot.fi/2015/04/birthday-bingo-in-kustavi.html">28th Birthday Bingo in Kustavi</a>.</p>

<p>Tookie’s <a href="http://walkwithtookie.com/3-trips-thursday-37/">Three Trips Thursday #37</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://willsim.blogspot.fi/2015/05/the-nw-face-of-mount-deborah.html">The NW face of Mount Deborah</a>.</p>

<p>Winter is back on <a href="http://tarmachan.blogspot.fi/2015/04/blog-post_27.html">Fiacaill’s Ridge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17232192322" title="Inov-8 X-Talon 212 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8821/17232192322_08075a06cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Inov-8 X-Talon 212" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Peter’s <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/05/greenland-paddle-six-months-later.html">Greenland Paddle, Six Months Later</a>.</p>

<p>Alex takes a look at the <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/05/the-tarptent-notch-backpacking-tent.html">Tarptent Notch</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/das-jetboil-sol-kochsystem-im-test/">Jetboil Sol</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://gauperoar.blogspot.fi/2015/04/dehydrating-rice-pudding.html">Dehydrating: Rice Pudding</a>.</p>

<p>Sven reviews the <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2015/04/la-sportiva-hail-jacket-im-test/">La Sportiva Hail Jacket</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/womens-underwear/">Women’s underwear</a>!</p>

<p>Chad reviews the <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2015/04/28/exped-synmat-ul7-sleeping-pad-review/">Exped SynMat UL7 Sleeping Pad</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/sportsclimbing-in-the-dolomites-a-guidebook-review/">Sportsclimbing in the Dolomites</a> Book Review.</p>

<p>Kathrin’s <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/wanderapotheke/">travel &amp; hiking pharmacy</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pedalingnowhere.com/gear/maxxis-chronicle-29-review/">Maxxis Chronicle 29+ Tire Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pathlesspedaled.com/2015/04/bike-touring-to-bikepacking-re-learning-how-to-pack/">Bike Touring to Bikepacking: Re-Learning How to Pack</a>.</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Then please share this post with your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=28945&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/28945/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[David Flanagan | Rock Climbing in Ireland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/david-flanagan-rock-climbing-in-ireland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-01T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/david-flanagan-rock-climbing-in-ireland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ireland has more to offer than <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">Sea Stacks</a> - there’s superb crags across the country. David Flanagan’s “<a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a>” helps you plan your trip to the Emerald Isle - which has climbing on half a dozen types of rock to offer, at sea cliffs, in the mountains and beautiful crags!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17307673186" title="Rock Climbing in Ireland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7759/17307673186_e118d35b78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Climbing in Ireland" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Fellow climbers will easily be able to relate - get a new guide book into your hands and immediately you start thinking about a trip to the area the book presents. While I just returned from Ireland a couple of weeks ago browsing <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a> has me thinking about when I could again visit the island for some climbing - and plenty of awesome climbing there is in Ireland.</p>

<p>The book starts of with the basics you need to know about climbing in Ireland - Access and Conservation, Equipment, When to Visit, Accommodation and how to get around the island. A Crag Table lists all 22 crags and what sorts of routes you will find there, and then right away dives in with describing the different crags. These include a introduction, tips on accommodation in the area, what you could do on rainy or rest days, conditions and directions to the crag. A large overview photo often shows the crag and the different sectors, and a small, basic overview map helps with navigating. The Topos and Route descriptions are coming with good details and some great photos of the climbs will get you in the mood for a route. And finally, a Route Index at the end of the book lets you find a route quickly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17331763072" title="Rock Climbing in Ireland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8735/17331763072_7285ee4f9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Climbing in Ireland" /></a></p>

<p>I loved the clean, minimalistic and well-structured layout of the Guidebook. It was aesthetically very pleasing to read, with a nice &amp; clear typography and great topo photos - these are something that make a climbing guide book not merely good, but great. What I missed was that some crags didn’t have information on accommodation and rainy &amp; rest days tips, I think for many people visiting from abroad it would help to have a recommendation for where to stay and what to do when the weather is shite. This is my only complaint (<em>and something you can find out yourself with the help of an online search</em>), and overall I would highly recommend this book to anyone who is planning to go rock climbing in Ireland. The beautiful guide book will make you look forward to visiting this beautiful island with the fair weather and gives you with over 400 routes in it more than enough inspiration of where to go &amp; what to climb!</p>

<p>Buy Rock Climbing in Ireland at your local book store or climbing gym, order it directly from the author at <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Three Rock Books</a>, or your local taste of <a href="http://amzn.to/1GCHy2y">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1zkr3e1">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1bKkvdP">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review 200]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/the-week-in-review-200.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-26T23:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/the-week-in-review-200</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Five Years. 200 Issues. Hundreds of Trip Reports. A time to look back.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17088168259" title="Cnoc na Mara in front and Tormore Island in the background, Ireland&#x27;s largest sea stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7726/17088168259_2c411388e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cnoc na Mara in front and Tormore Island in the background, Ireland&#x27;s largest sea stack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="history">History</h2>

<p>Five years ago, on the 25th of April 2010, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/04/the-week-in-review.html">the first The Week in Review</a> saw the light. I had been blogging for a bit over a year by then, was following a growing number of outdoor blogs and felt it was difficult to <strong>separate the weekend hill walk from the epic adventures</strong> (there’s nothing wrong with weekend hill walks, btw - I love these myself!) - and so the first weekly outdoor-related curated post was born. The idea was pretty straight forward: Share with my readers the other great &amp; useful, fun and inspiring outdoor content on other blogs I read (and they maybe not (yet)). Hiking in Finland was back then already quite popular and as <strong>sharing is caring</strong> I thought it’s useful to give some other blogs some love, too. </p>

<p>It always has been pretty roughly 50% subjective and 50% objective content that found its way into TWIR, content that I liked a lot and content that I knew you, the readers will find useful. This often included skills, Tips &amp; Tricks and gear reviews - finding believable and high-quality reviews on ultralight gear has not been easy and still can be difficult. The same goes for inspiring trip reports - it can be hard to find some real pearls.</p>

<p>There have been a handful of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvii.html">Mystery Editions</a>, one <a href="https://flipboard.com/@hendrikmorkel/the-week-in-review-xxxvi-pfh7659jy">TWIR on Flipboard</a> and 199 other awesome TWIRs. You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">browse them all here</a> (<em>There’s some problems with the earliest TWIRs because of the URLs - happened when moving from Blogspot to Octopress - which I am working on a fix</em>).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17022136640" title="Swell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7688/17022136640_d5349517b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="blogs-blogs-blogs">Blogs Blogs Blogs</h2>

<p>From the beginning TWIR was <strong>highlighting content on outdoor blogs</strong>. The first blogs in my RSS Reader were probably from my fellow Nordic Lightpacking friends: <a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/">Roger</a>, <a href="https://thunderinthenight.exposure.co/">Joe</a>, <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se/">Martin &amp; Jörgen</a>, <a href="http://thebearablelightness.blogspot.fi/">Gustav</a>, <a href="http://www.backpackingnorth.com/">Mark</a> and <a href="http://goinglighter.blogspot.fi/">Thomas</a> followed by blogs from the UK, Germany, Europe, Australia, Asia and of course the USA. The number of blogs in my RSS reader started to grow quickly, though, and nowadays there’s close to 800 blogs in my subscription list. The last one I added is <a href="https://limitcamper.wordpress.com/">Limitcamper</a>, and each week a couple more are subscribed to.</p>

<p>While in the beginning it was a manageable task - blogging was just going down in popularity again in 2010/ 2011 - it quickly started to be a full-day task to keep track of all the superb content. Nowadays, if I don’t already browse during the week a bit in the RSS Reader, I easily can have 500 or more unread items on a Sunday waiting for me. I also try to vary the blogs I feature - even if some people create outstanding content each week (you should subscribe to their blogs to not miss a thing!) it is more interesting so find something fresh from someone new each week.</p>

<p>What RSS Reader I use has changed also, from the now-death Google Reader over Reeder I now am using the fantastic <a href="https://feedbin.com/">Feedbin</a>, which I highly recommend if you read blogs via RSS.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/125476007?color=ffffff&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="600" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="structure">Structure</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Photos</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst">Videos</a> have always been a part of The Week In Review. <strong>The internet is a visual medium</strong> and sharing great photos and videos not just loosens up the structure but also makes it more attractive. But more structure was needed and became gradually part of TWIR. It was <a href="https://twitter.com/rollofunk">Mikael</a> who suggested I number the issues for easier reference, and that’s the reason we can have a cake with two hundred candles on it today =)</p>

<p>While the superb content on other blogs is still the core of each TWIR, nowadays also news, gear deals and interesting announcements are part of it. This meant I needed to find a better way to separate News from Trip Reports and Gear Reviews - which gave rise to the sub-headers. This makes it also easier for the readers to go directly to the section they are interested in, or when looking something up to find it more easily. So besides great content from Outdoor blogs you now also can find interesting posts from major newspapers and other outdoor media.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>When you talk, you are only repeating what you already know. But if you listen, you may learn something new.</em> - Dalai Lama</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And because I follow blogs from across the globe and often include blogs in another language in the TWIR, it was <a href="https://twitter.com/korpijaakko">Jaakko</a> who suggested I add also a short [Language] tag behind those posts that are in another language than English. The final additions have been the last <em>“Share it with your friends”</em> sentence, encouraging you to let your friends know about the TWIR, and an inspiring, thoughtful quote as the intro. There have been suggestions to sort articles by activity - packrafting, hiking, climbing and cycling - though I feel that’s not needed right now. And clicking on an inspiring bike-touring article as a hiker certainly can’t harm, but only open the mind!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797321574" title="HMG UltaMid in a wet forest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5502/9797321574_0b9435d015_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG UltaMid in a wet forest" /></a></p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<p>Back in 2009 a bunch of mates set out on a <a href="http://www.tetongravity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=169211">33 days in Wrangell St. Elias National Park adventure</a> which still today is an EPIC in the truest sense of the word.</p>

<p>Joery’s adventures also are good in my memory, like his <a href="http://dzjow.com/2012/10/08/protect-the-peel-first-pics/">Peel Watershed Hiking &amp; Packrafting Trip</a>.</p>

<p>Also Willem’s <a href="https://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2014/01/25/greenland-part-iv-a-loop-into-cape-farewell-country/">Greenland adventure</a> ranks high in my memory.</p>

<p>And if I already mention Joery and Willem obviously Steve &amp; Katrijn can’t miss because they make the Belgian trio complete. Their world trip, especially their <a href="http://patagoniandreams.com/2013/05/06/patagonia-un-paseo-otonal-entre-la-roca-el-hielo-y-la-lenga/">trips in Patagonia</a>, have me looking up flights and thinking schedules for a trip there.</p>

<p>And finally, the <a href="http://distantranges.com/in-the-golden-mountains-of-altai-part-1/">In the Golden Mountains of Altai</a> trip report has me certain that I need to go to Russia for some hiking and packrafting.</p>

<p>But there have been many, many more memorable posts, so you really should <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">browse the past TWIRs</a>. Comment underneath and let me know which was your favourite story that you found via The Week In Review!</p>

<p><strong>A handful of fresh posts from this week:</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://mountainworldproductions.com/wp/2015/04/nepal-earthquake-updates-and-what-to-do-and-how-to-help.html">Nepal Earthquake: Updates, What to do and How to help</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://topofests.wordpress.com/2015/04/24/a-packrafting-apprenticeship/">A Packrafting Apprenticeship</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pcta.org/2015/congrats-to-the-2015-pct-photo-contest-winners-28872/">2015 PCT photo contest winners</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://ben-briggs.com/2015/04/16/mountain-equipment-ski-clothing-range/">Mountain Equipment Ski Clothing Range</a>.</p>

<p>Corinna aka the <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2015/04/4-jahre-outdoormaedchen-ihr-feiert-ich-verlose.html">Outdoor Mädchen</a> celebrates her 4th Blog Birthday! [German]</p>

<p>Chad shares his <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2015/04/25/back-2-back-with-cesar-thoughts-on-section-hiking-vs-thru-hiking/">Thoughts on Section Hiking vs Thru Hiking</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bonappetit.com/columns/my-morning-routine/article/alex-honnold-interview">Rock Climber Alex Honnold Loves Cookie Dough, Wants to Wash Your Dishes</a>.</p>

<p>Benjamin is back, and <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2015/04/flame-burns/">the flame still burns</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pedalingnowhere.com/plog/shooting-from-the-saddle-vol-01-tips/">16 bike photography tips from 6 great adventure cycling shooters</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/the-day-i-sent-golden-5-14b/">The Day I Sent Golden (5.14b)</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-future">The Future</h2>

<p>The Week In Review, 200 issues, five years old. As a friend asked this morning: Did I think this would happen? Nope. I’m also still surprised by the mass of people who read it and love it, for whom TWIR is their daily stop on a Sunday or Monday, where they <strong>find inspiring and beautiful outdoor stories</strong> and stay informed on what’s happening in the outdoor blog-o-sphere.</p>

<p>While there have been moments where I have felt like <em>Today’s not a TWIR day</em> these have been fewer and fewer thanks to effective management of how I write and organize them. Which means The Week In Review is here to stay, and I am looking forward to bringing you more inspiring outdoor stories in the years to come. And if I miss a Sunday - it’s usually because I’m out backpacking, packrafting, climbing or bikepacking myself =) </p>

<p><em>Liked this? Then please share this post with your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! And yes, <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">I do accept a coffee</a></strong> if you’d like to get me one!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/hide-and-seek.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-24T20:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/hide-and-seek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s weekend so its time to head outdoors, to the cabin. Got none? <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> will give you plenty of cabins to dream of over the weekend and inspire you to dream up your own.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17066651669" title="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7606/17066651669_6213274751_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Friday is the day where the mind starts to wander to a lonely log cabin in the woods, by the lake, heated by a wood stove, no electricity. Or is it more a luxurious cabin by the sea? Maybe a sleek mountain hut that looks old and ramshackle from the outside but that’s modern and cool inside? <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> has them all: Coastal cabins, mountain cabins, open range cabins and the wood cabin, nicely sorted into four chapters of the finest cabins the authors could find. And they have searched far and wide, from the Isle of Skye to New Zealand and Finland to Chile, there’s bound to be a cabin for everyone in this book, Gestalten’s 2nd Cabin book after <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/rock-the-shack.html">Rock the Shack</a>.</p>

<p>The book presents the cabins &amp; their interiors of people who don’t want to give up life in the city but want to be able to escape to nature. And as unique as we are as humans, so unique are the cabins, their surroundings and interiors in this book. The focus clearly is on small living spaces in nature, because the outside in front of the window is your living room in many cases, your entertainment, TV and internet. The book aims to inspire you to dream up your own cabin, but you’ll not find plans or construction tips in this coffee table book. However, in the index at the end of the book you can find out more about the architects of the cabins, so that gives you a good starting point.</p>

<p>Sadly we don’t have a own cabin by the sea or lake, so a book which inspires the mind for a more simple life away from home certainly is a good way to relax. I found the book interesting, though I saw a trend to very minimalistic, modern, almost similar looking cabins - with just the scenery changing from the coast to the mountains to the forests. There was a lot of wood, concrete, steel and stones used, all in similar shapes &amp; designs, often with straight lines. Standing out were really only Steve’s Thailand Dome House, the Tree Tent, the Cocoon and the Tree Snake Houses in terms of its design - that was fresh &amp; organic architecture. While I liked most cabins in the book, I missed more organic, natural and rustic cabins and interiors - which there shouldn’t be a shortage of. Personally I also would have liked a more inhabited look in the interior photos, many had the sterile-looking feel of a Modern Art Museum.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17065096818" title="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7601/17065096818_c322948cab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs" /></a></p>

<p>Despite this I would recommend this coffee table book to anyone who likes huts &amp; cabins and can’t get enough of them. You’re bound to have seen some of the featured hide-outs in the book if you follow <a href="http://cabinporn.com/">Cabinporn</a> but there’s a host of new &amp; fresh cabins featured which will get you dreaming about a weekend (or life!) away in them. It’s a beautiful book with high-quality paper and photographs, very legible typography and a clear layout which makes for a satisfying experience when reading &amp; browsing. There’s all in all 80 cabins and hide-outs in the book on 250 pages, and the nature &amp; scenery around the hide-outs and cabins is just as gorgeous as the huts themselves. I’m now off to dream up my own hut, if you need some weekend inspiration grab the book at your local book store or order it online from <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Gestalten</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1KbYSiH">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1duc68Y">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1ElTl8s">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Oh, and in case you’re wondering: My favourite hut probably is <a href="http://robinfalck.com/nido/">Nido</a> from Robin Falck.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bike &amp; Travel Magazine 01/2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/bike-and-travel-magazin-01-slash-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-21T17:30:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/bike-and-travel-magazin-01-slash-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bike &amp; Travel Magazine is a new bicycle magazine on the German market - lets take a look inside!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16603773563" title="Bike &amp; Travel Magazine 01/2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7611/16603773563_614d0ea74e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bike &amp; Travel Magazine 01/2015" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The <a href="http://biketravel-magazin.com/">Bike &amp; Travel Magazine</a> hit the shelves last week, but together with the publisher I have been working since spring 2014 on this new magazine. It was one of the reasons for me to get a couple of new <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">bikes</a> and it has been an interesting ride to see a new magazine being born. I will contribute to the magazine for at least the next two years, so if you like my writing you might want to <a href="https://ssl.topackt.com/trekkingmagazin.com/bikeabo/abo_eingabe.php?AboArt=ZweiJahresabo">take out a subscription</a> and don’t miss any issue. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17036201878" title="Bike &amp; Travel Magazine 01/2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7705/17036201878_11a7108d95_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bike &amp; Travel Magazine 01/2015" /></a></p>

<p>For this issue I contributed an article on comfortable sleeping along the trail/ road and lament that many people seem to be using massive tents and camping gear - the reasoning seems to be that many traditional bike-tourers think along the lines of <em>“I don’t need to carry it and have plenty of space”</em> - I showcase gear from the opposite side of the spectrum (so it’s light, compact and just as comfortable). Future articles will continue along these lines and also include a few nice bike tours in Europe. </p>

<p>The main focus of the magazine is on the adventures and tours you can do with your bike. The magazine has eight trip reports in the inaugural issue and is set to continue along these lines - there’s enough cycling gear magazines on the market already, and as <a href="http://www.fastcoexist.com/3043858/world-changing-ideas/the-science-of-why-you-should-spend-your-money-on-experiences-not-thing">research shows</a> - experiences are more valuable than the stuff you own. In that sense, grab the first issue of <a href="http://biketravel-magazin.com/">Bike &amp; Travel</a>, swing a leg over your bike and go for a ride!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sea Stack Climbing in Ireland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-20T23:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ashfall Quartz. Ebb. Tide. Swell. Mix it together, throw in a rubber dinghy and you have the stuff for a Sea Stack climbing adventure.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002240157" title="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/17002240157_6342150a0a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>From the distance Berg Stack looks like a wee little rock in the North Atlantic Ocean, just off the cost of An Port in County Donegal, Ireland. We - Iain, our guide, a photographer and an US American journalist - slept the last night in the Port Cottage and now a blue sky &amp; sunshine have us frolicking in the superb weather. <em>“Lets go and check out the swell and tide”</em> Iain announces. We pack up our climbing gear and the 40€ rubber dinghy, bought at a Toy Shop - three at a time, they’re not that durable and walk the <a href="http://www.walkni.com/iat/">IAT</a> path up to the sea stack.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589476163" title="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8697/16589476163_e1526639df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left" /></a></p>

<p>What looked like a wee sea stack from the lawn of the cottage turns out to be a 25 m high sea stack with a large ledge at the bottom, beautiful cracks and pin scars lining it from bottom to top and a Great black-backed gull with its nest on top. Oh, and an angry Atlantic Ocean with a two to four metre swell, making for not a good time to cross. We still inflate the unnamed dinghy, Iain gives me the instructions of how to assist him when he will board the sea worthy vessel to establish a tyrollean traverse on Berg Stack so I can get over, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17023512169" title="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8693/17023512169_4922bee743_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The we sit &amp; wait. Observe the swell. Finally Iain decides we’ll come back at high tide later in the afternoon, when the sea should be calmer. Adrenaline that was build up in anticipation disappears, shoes go back on and we go for a nice hill walk, checking out Cnoc na Mara - the Sea Stack we had originally planned to go up, but with this sea that would have been too much risk. The views are spectacular, the valley deserted and I can make out a dozen of superb spots for a wild camp.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021928808" title="A look up Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5322/17021928808_206ed924b5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look up Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>Sea stack climbing is less about climbing, really. Sure, it helps if you can climb well and know how to place gear - it’s all trad - but it is just as much about the skill set an Alpinist has: Patience, Risk Assessment, Speed &amp; Efficiency. Maritime skills &amp; knowledge are also essential, knowing when the tide is coming in, how high the swell is, if it is safe, being patient. Finally, a bit of daring for an adventure is also needed. After all, if you think paddling in a toyshop rubber dinghy on the Atlantic is insane, then sea stack climbing is nothing for you.</p>

<p>We’re back on the main land and observe the sea. It is high tide, the swell is still high but every now &amp; then there’s a calm moment - and one of these Iain uses to paddle over to Berg Stack. An euphoric cry echoes over the sea and you can see how a load is off his shoulders. He sets up an anchor for the tyrollean traverse, and during the next calm moment he’s back on the main land. We discuss the strategy and then it all goes quick: the dinghy is back in the water and Iain is in it, surfing the swell, a 240 cm sling connecting him to the tyrollean. A calm moment comes, he paddles in and I jump in - and just as quick out again off on Berg Stack. We both howl a cry of victory, a victory over the tide and swell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021935758" title="Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5343/17021935758_1ab7fb492e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>From here on it’s all basic rock climbing: Harness and rock shoes come on, Iain racks up and we tie into the rope. I stand barefoot on the ledge, the swell crashing on the rocks around. Iain leads up a variation the <em>Cormorant</em> which he probably has climbed a dozen times and before long an “Off belay” call echoes down to me. It is a nice route with great hand and foot holds up till the middle to the arête, then it goes around the arête and up a wet corner, which is also the toilet of the Great black-backed gull and its offspring which were kind enough to let us top out there. A moment later I stand on the top of Berg Stack next to Iain, high-fiving him, and again we both let out a howl of victory. But this is not a sports climb where you just clip into the chain and then rappel off. No, this is a sea stack. And the sea is angry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002250497" title="Roping up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7651/17002250497_95a7de41ea_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Roping up" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002062747" title="Me on Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8706/17002062747_44b293c870_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Me on Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17209684205" title="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5448/17209684205_822563f419_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The easiest way off the top back to the ledge is to down-climb a corner to about two meters above the rushing sea, and then traverse the sea stack on superb ledges &amp; holds back to where we started. We short-rope and five minutes later stand next to our dinghy. The sea is lower, more rocks can be seen as the ebb comes in, but the swell is still high. <em>“Lets wait till the tide is out and then walk off”</em> Iain says, and so we deflate the dinghy which has served us so well on the way here, pack up and wait. Wait for the water to retreat, for the swell to let us escape from this rock.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589483823" title="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5342/16589483823_e771dc38d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183741396" title="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8700/17183741396_a98415b910_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell" /></a></p>

<p>The sea does not see a reason for letting us off, it wants to keep us. The swell is high and white foam rushes over the barnacle-covered rocks, which would otherwise allow us to easily walk off. The sun throws its last rays on the main land, we can see the hut from our ledge and the comfort of the warm fire in the cozy cottage and slowly we’re getting cold &amp; hungry. Low tide arrives, but the swell still throws up large, foamy waves over the rocks we should have just walked off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183747146" title="Cold feet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17183747146_b904d8e834_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Cold feet" /></a></p>

<p>Iain goes first, jumps the large gap and makes it just to the top of a big rock when a wave comes in. He brings me my approach shoes and throws them over, as I do not fancy jumping barefoot on wet, slimy rocks and risking a broken ankle. Waiting for the right moment I too make the jump, and a final victory cry echoes from the rocks - the land has me again. We pack up and in the falling dusk walk to the cottage, where a warm fire and cool beer are waiting for us. My appetite for sea stack climbing is awakened, but first I’ll need to hike further on the International Appalachian Trail to Northern Ireland, to return another day for more sea stack climbing adventures.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17022143920" title="Patience by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17022143920_703730e92f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patience" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>
<p>There’s a <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/sea_stack_guide">free Sea Stack Guide book</a> if you want to go sea stack climbing - it has almost all sea stacks in it. A selection of sea stacks you also find in the <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a> book. I would suggest you do your first sea stack with Iain from <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/">Unique Ascents</a> and learn the ins &amp; outs from him about the sea and getting safely on and off the sea stack. He’s also a great guy and you’ll have a lot of fun on a day out with him. You’ll need a sea-worthy vessel - maybe <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Rentals:::34.html">loan a packraft</a>, but be sure you also know how to use it and have an idea about the tide, swell and weather forecast. If a sea stack is too much adventure, check out the <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/undiscovered_donegal">Donegal rock climbers guide</a> and visit one of the local crags, though there are also <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=CfM3DTcHcS8">calm days on Berg Stack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17208905321" title="Port Donegal Cottage by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8763/17208905321_de9c296ae9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage" /></a></p>

<p>If you plan to climb in the area around An Port stay in the <a href="http://port-donegal.com/">Port Donegal Cottage</a> - either book via their website or on <a href="http://www.ownersdirect.co.uk/accommodation/p8069109">Owners Direct</a>. It has a wonderful cozy feel and relaxing in the bathtub after a day out on the sea will be so good that you don’t wanna go out. It sleeps eight and with some luck Roland, the owner, will be around and delight you with his stories from far away places.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021740458" title="Port Donegal Cottage Inside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7725/17021740458_6b9517e048_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage Inside" /></a></p>

<p>The nearest village via a road is Ardara where you find several accommodation options like the <a href="http://www.bayviewcountryhouse.com/">Bayview Country House</a> and also shops and the <a href="http://www.nancysardara.com/">Nancy’s of Ardara Pub</a> for a after-climb pint, though it adds at least 45 minutes driving to your approach. For rest days go to Glencolmcille in the neighbouring valley and visit the <a href="http://glenfolkvillage.com/">Folk Museum</a> where you can see how people lived in the last centuries in the area, grab a good cup of coffee and a bite.</p>

<p>Gear wise you will need Trad gear as there are no bolts. Bring cord and slings if you want to abseil and need to build an anchor. Most of all, be patient with the sea and be open for the adventure!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear Outtakes - Winter 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/gear-outtakes-winter-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-10T19:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/gear-outtakes-winter-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bite-sized gear reviews, winter edition.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456421253" title="Snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7672/16456421253_762527c0c9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Snow" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gear-outtakes/">Gear Outtakes</a> is a seasonal collection of kit and what I think about it.</p>

<p>★☆☆☆
Mediocre, I wouldn’t spend money on it.</p>

<p>★★☆☆
Good, but there are better options.</p>

<p>★★★☆
Great, worth your money.</p>

<p>★★★★
Outstanding, the benchmark of its category.</p>

<p>DISCLAIMER
<br />Some of these products have been sent to me for free by the manufacturer.</p>

<h2 id="camp-supernova-womens-harness">CAMP Supernova Women’s Harness</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16903026838" title="CAMP Supernova Harness by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8823/16903026838_19e0f65480_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="CAMP Supernova Harness" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />65€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1IwzB4B">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/camp-klettergurte/">Bergzeit.de</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1yZb7IE">Campsaver.com</a></p>

<p>I love climbing, and the <a href="http://www.camp.it/EN/template01.aspx?codicemenu=1475">CAMP Supernova</a> was my try to get my wife fall in love with it too. With the Supernova Harness being a harness conceived by women, designed by women, and built for women I thought this will be the harness for her, and while she did like the lightweight and comfortable harness she isn’t as obsessed about climbing as me. M liked the padding and ease of adjustment of the harness, with a fully adjustable waist and leg loops, and the No-Twist belay loop came in handy when she was belaying me. / 360 g in Size M</p>

<h2 id="hestra-ergo-grip-outdry-dexterity-long">Hestra Ergo Grip OutDry Dexterity Long</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16470652683" title="Hestra Ergo Grip OutDry Dexterity Long by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8814/16470652683_e30779171a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hestra Ergo Grip OutDry Dexterity Long" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1yZdCe1">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/hestra/">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1Pp3DJv">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1IwC8M4">REI</a></p>

<p>Gloves, the eternal struggle. If all you need gloves for is that they keep your fingers warm and look good you’re a lucky person and won’t understand the “Search for the perfect glove” that outdoor enthusiasts, and especially ice climbers, conduct. The <a href="https://hestragloves.com/sport/intl/gloves/mountaineering/ergo-grip-outdry-dexterity-long-five-finger/100100/">Hestra Ergo Grip OutDry Dexterity Long</a> is as close to the perfect ice climbing and mountaineering glove I have come, me thinks. It is warm, waterproof with an OutDry membrane, offers superb dexterity and is very, very durable. I have used this fine glove for two winters now and some mountaineering and love it. It’s easy to clip ropes, open ‘biners, conduct fiddly work and keep warm fingers, even when water is running down the shaft of your ice tools. / 186 g for the Pair in Size 9</p>

<h2 id="suomi-tyres-gazza-extreme-294-a-54--622">Suomi Tyres GAZZA EXTREME 294 A 54 -622</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16903020858" title="Suomi Tyres GAZZA EXTREME 294 A 54 -622 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7614/16903020858_62a143f198_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Suomi Tyres GAZZA EXTREME 294 A 54 -622" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />90€, available at <a href="http://amzn.to/1Guc3gc">Amazon.com</a></p>

<p>294 in that name stands for the 294 steel studs with carbide pins on these tires, which makes these <em>the</em> cycling tires for icy conditions - and thanks to the triple thaw + freeze cycles we had this “<em>winter</em>” (and the last one, too) the <a href="http://www.suomityres.com/eng/tyres/">Gazza Extreme</a> have been very, very useful. Suomi Tyres is a small company from Eastern Finland and they know how to make some of the best bicycle tires on the planet - they are since 90 years in this business. They’re the only bicycle tyre manufacturer in Northern Europe (check this <a href="https://youtu.be/lxYa4Lb3VRI?list=UUl1rmXRFLvoJlm4E8UirZVw">video of how the tires are made</a>) and produce since ten years already environmentally sound tires from pure rubber compounds. I have ridden the Gazza Extreme on my 29er in the last two winters and didn’t slip once with them on icy roads and frozen lakes. These tires are on the bike a good five to six months a year and so far have yet to lose one stud! / 1090 g per tyre</p>

<h2 id="lundhags-bc-guide-boots">Lundhags BC Guide Boots</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17089310732" title="Lundhags BC Guide Boots by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8715/17089310732_5081e8c7db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lundhags BC Guide Boots" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />290€, available at <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/lundhags/schuhe.html">Unterwegs.biz</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/lundhags-guide-bc-hiking-shoes/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a> (On Offer - 30% off!) and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/lundhags/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk</a></p>

<p>Back to boots! Well, not really, but for Nordic Skating and Backcountry XC Skiing the <a href="http://lundhags.se/">Lundhags</a> BC Guide Boots have been fantastic. The shoe was out of the box comfortable, in part probably thanks to the 3 mm wool felt liner boot which can be removed. The boot itself is made from a Perwanger split leather on top which has been great in shedding water and snow and keeping my feet dry, and a Certech 4.5 cellular rubber as a midlayer, with a Rottefella® BC sole underneath which allows you to click into NNN bindings - be these on skis or Nordic Skates is up to you! The laces are long but allowed me to fit the boot well to my feet, and the boot is well insulated against the cold from below so that your feet stay toasty when you’re out on the ice. More on these in detail next year. / 1540 g for the Pair in Size 40</p>

<h2 id="rock-technologies-revive-creme">Rock Technologies Revive Creme</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17064847236" title="Rock Technologies Revive Creme by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8790/17064847236_2697e69e52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Technologies Revive Creme" /></a></p>

<p>★★☆☆
<br />5€, available at <a href="http://www.rocktechnologies.co.uk/order-online/">Rock Technologies</a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.rocktechnologies.co.uk/order-online/">Rock Technologies Revive Creme</a> is one of those products that I use to treat my hands after climbing. It helps to heal my hands and makes them fit for the next round on the gym wall or rock. It is a rather liquid creme with a nice smell that is quickly absorbed by the skin, and is also recommend to be used after chalk use. / 90 g for the full tube</p>

<h2 id="icebreaker-anatomica-boxers">Icebreaker Anatomica Boxers</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17090804855" title="Icebreaker Anatomica Boxers by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8757/17090804855_c3027366ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Icebreaker Anatomica Boxers" /></a></p>

<p>★★★☆
<br />45€, available at <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/icebreaker-anatomica-boxers-502598.html">Unterwegs.biz</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1NgbMl5">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/icebreaker-anatomica-boxers-funktionsunterhose/">Bergfreunde.de</a> <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/icebreaker-anatomica-boxers-stripe-metro-snow-s/">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1IOwl1e">Campsaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1Cv2hD9">REI</a></p>

<p>Can’t have enough underwear! The <a href="http://eu.icebreaker.com/en/mens-underwear/anatomica-boxers-w-fly/100472.html">Icebreaker Anatomica Boxers</a> were a present and I love them. I wore my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/03/finisterre-zephyr-boxer-shorts.html">Finisterre Boxers</a> till they were broken and the Anatomica have been a worthy replacement. The colours and fit are spot on, sometimes I find the waistband folds over (for example when cycling or climbing) but overall these have been great. The Merino wool makes these my choice of underwear on backpacking trips as you can wear them for several days and they stay fresh, and the flatlock seams &amp; thin material make them very comfortable on the trail. / 51 g in Size M</p>

<h2 id="exped-zip-seal-4">Exped ZIP SEAL 4</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16903250370" title="Exped ZIP SEAL 5.5 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7592/16903250370_8319f38b41_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Exped ZIP SEAL 5.5" /></a></p>

<p>★★☆☆
<br />20€, available at <a href="http://bit.ly/1Ng8wG4">Campsaver.com</a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.exped.com/switzerland/en/product-category/packsacks/zip-seal-4">Exped ZIP SEAL 4</a> was a gift at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor 2014</a> and has been used on and off since. I found it especially useful in winter when I need to wear my phone close to my body so it stays warm - the battery drains like nothing in the cold - but it can get wet from my sweat. The case has been 100% waterproof thus far and the transparent front lets me operate the phone in it without problems. There’s even a transparent back window so you can take photos through it, and as far as those go I do find the results are satisfactorily. If you need a waterproof case for your phone that’s also light, check this one out! / 23 g</p>

<h2 id="ecco-ulterra-ws-mid-gtx">Ecco Ulterra W’s Mid GTX</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17089314502" title="Ecco Ulterra W&#x27;s Mid GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/17089314502_38ff65d638_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ecco Ulterra W&#x27;s Mid GTX" /></a></p>

<p>★★★★
<br />170€ €, available at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/ecco-ulterra-mid-gtx-wanderschuhe/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/ecco-ulterra-mid-gtx-w-039-s-shoes-dark-shadow-37/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1CzUgMZ">Campsaver.com</a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://us.shop.ecco.com/women-boots/ecco-womens-ulterra-mid-gtx-823113.html">Ecco Ulterra W’s Mid GTX</a> is M’s winter boot since a year and she finds them excellent. She found them to be comfortable out of the box without needing to be walked in and appreciated the Gore-Tex membrane when she was out in the rain and snow so her feet stayed dry. The uppers are made from yak nubuck leather that’s super tough and allows for a good climate in the shoe. They’re reasonably light too and have good grip on forest trails and snow alike. / 872 g for the Pair in Size 40</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Family Adventures in Pyhä-Luosto]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-08T23:41:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The common human relationship with winter seems to go like this: As a child you love winter. In your twenties you could life without it. And from your thirties onwards you fall in love with winter &amp; snow again. In our family we’re all winter lovers, and as winter didn’t really visit us in Vaasa we decided to find it up north at <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/eng/">Pyhä Tunturi</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075087012" title="That one next, dad! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7599/17075087012_e945efd6da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="That one next, dad!" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="prologue">Prologue</h2>

<p>Climate change is a real bummer for winter lovers in Southern Finland. While I did get to ski and fatbike in the snow a bit back home, winter in Vaasa was a mix of snow + cold and then rain + warm temperatures which resulted in a less than nice winter. With a week of winter vacation that we could each take of, M and me decided to search winter in Lapland. After some discussions of what we wanted we quickly settled on the <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/eng/">Pyhä Ski Resort</a> as the best destination for us this year as it had plenty of fun winter activities to offer for all three of us, from skiing and hiking over sledding to ice climbing and fatbiking, with great <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/accommodation/">accommodation</a> options, too. </p>

<p>A car was rented, <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel?s=8">AirBnB accommodation</a> in Oulu was organized and the luggage was packed. It was a nice Sunday morning as we started the drive north, and it was around Oulu - 300 km from Vaasa - that we saw the first signs of Winter again. The next day we continued via a stop in Rovaniemi onwards to Pyhä, and already from a distance we could see the iconic fjells of the ski resort and <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/pyha-luostonp">National Park</a>, with lots of snow around us and a beautiful bluebird sky promising a great week of winter fun! We checked in to the <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1128&amp;submenu=3657">Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartment</a>, heated up the Sauna and enjoyed seeing the stars in the crisp, black sky.</p>

<h2 id="winter-fun-for-kids">Winter fun for Kids</h2>

<p>We found Pyhä a great location for our three year old. He loved the snow and we were daily at the sled hill, which was a five minutes walk from the <a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/pyha-luostonluontokeskus">Nature Centre Naava</a> (which is in the centre of the village and hence an easy reference point). The two sled hills were good fun and E didn’t get tired of sledding for many hours each day, with little rest breaks at the conveniently located open hut at the foot of the hill. Being allowed to throw another log of wood on the fire was equally nice as making snow angles and sledding together <em>superfast</em> with dad. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889011560" title="Pyhä Sled Hill by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7713/16889011560_3351fc57fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Pyhä Sled Hill" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076568685" title="Sled Hill break hut by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8752/17076568685_cb2b65aa11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sled Hill break hut" /></a></p>

<p>There’s a ski school for kids in Pyhä too, though we decided to wait for another year to put him on downhill skis. There were lots of kids skiing, though, and the Family slopes were full with parents and kids of all ages. Close to our apartment was also a reindeer enclosure and visiting Rudolph and his friends was every time again fascinating. E also enjoyed looking how other people skied down the hills so fast, and going up with the Polar Express to the top of the fjell made him smile from ear to ear. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075825821" title="Top of the fjell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8798/17075825821_e54ca475a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Top of the fjell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="skiing">Skiing</h2>

<p>M and me have the same shoe size, which was convenient as we loaned cross country skis and boots. M enjoyed skiing the tracks while I went a bit off-piste and explored the nearby National Park and swamp on skis. There’s surely a hundred kilometre or more of groomed cross-country skiing tracks at Pyhä and M liked the little huts and Laavus along the tracks, as they were ideal to have a short break and then ski back. The tracks vary in difficulty, from a super easy loipe that goes around a mire with zero elevations to more demanding loipes. You even can ski around the whole Pyhä-Luosto National Park on groomed tracks, which is - depending on the route you choose - between 70 or more kilometres. For early morning and late night skiers there’s also a pretty long illuminated track which is lighted up from 6 in the morning till 23 at night.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075080162" title="Skiing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/17075080162_2149394d66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Skiing" /></a></p>

<p>But of course cross-country skiing is just one sort of skiing you can do in Pyhä! It’s very well known in Finland to be <em>the</em> Backcountry destination, as you can take the lift up and then pretty much ski down where you please. Sadly my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">DPS Tour 1 skis</a> didn’t arrive in time otherwise I would have been out on the slopes and made some pretty turns after skinning up the hills. There are lots of great ski-touring options at Pyhä, so if that’s your kind of skiing make sure to take your gear along! Also for downhill and Freeskiers Pyhä is a great destination, with 9 lifts, 14 prepared slopes - the longest slope being 1800 m - and the same ski pass being valid at Ruka as well Pyhä is a great destination to go snowboarding and skiing. Add in that the lifts are working super efficient and queues were non-existent and you have the ingredients for lots of skiing and fun.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16890340699" title="Top of the fjell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8716/16890340699_d85b8eda66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Top of the fjell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ice-climbing">Ice climbing</h2>

<p>One of the reasons why Pyhä won for us as a destination is that you can go <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/ice-climbing/customized-ice-climbing/">ice climbing at Tajukangas</a> which is a short stroll from the slopes and the Pyhätunturi Hotel. My friends from <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/">Bliss Adventure</a> run the ice climbing crag there, and I was very happy that my friend <a href="http://aleksimehtonen.fi/">Aleksi</a> and his colleague Mikko were there with me and were the belay masters while I was whacking some ice. And whacking ice I did!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16454119254" title="My first ice lead at Tajukangas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7665/16454119254_4f6f3c878e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="My first ice lead at Tajukangas" /></a></p>

<p>After a couple of warm-ups and checking out the routes I did my first ice lead ever, and while I was a bit nervous while tying in to my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.fi/en/mammut-genesis-8-5-half-rope-red/?pid=81">Mammut 8.5 Genesis Ropes</a> and racking up the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/petzl-laser-speed-ice-screw/">Petzl Laser Speed ice screws</a> as soon as I was on the ice and put my mind on the task ahead the fear was gone, tranquility and enjoyment flowing through me. As far as ice leads go this wasn’t the most difficult route ever, though I found the company and encouragement from Aleksi &amp; Mikko superb and they helped me to trust myself and lead on ice. Now I’m hungry for more and hope that next winter will be much better than this one, so that there will be much more ice climbing and leading!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075086492" title="My first ice lead at Tajukangas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8723/17075086492_4b88107d6d_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="My first ice lead at Tajukangas" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hungry">Hungry?</h2>

<p><a href="http://pyhawurst.fi/">Pyhä Wurst</a> is a cozy little Restaurant/ Café at the bottom of the Northern Slope. They serve, as the name suggest, a variety of different sausages, and all three of us really found our food extremely tasty. Our son devoured a Hotdog - his first one! - and would have liked a second one, while M and me enjoyed a Bratwurst Hotdog and a Riistakäristys. They place was very popular with skiers &amp; snowboarders, walkers, cross-country skiers and families alike, so check them out when you’re in Pyhä and would like to taste some good Wurst!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050601976" title="PyhäWurst by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8732/17050601976_5f89cb12f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="PyhäWurst" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.cafeloimu.fi/en/">Café Loimu</a> was another Café which we enjoyed visiting almost daily as they served some super-tasty pancakes and good coffee. They’re located in the same building as the Nature Centre Naava so kids can even go and explore the museum on their own while the parents can enjoy a moment in the Café. Café Loimu is right in the middle of the village and also has an Á la carte Menu if you want to eat a bit more than pancakes or a sandwich.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/restaurants/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1019&amp;submenu=138">Hotel Pyhätunturi Restaurant</a> has a gorgeous Panorama view over the surroundings and is an ideal place to conclude a nice day outdoors, especially if the Northern Lights decide to show up and play a show over the forests and mires. M ate the best Sautéed reindeer (<em>poronkäristys</em> in Finnish) in her life at the Restaurant and found it so tasty that she still talks about how good it was. I enjoyed <em>The Poro</em> which was equally delicious, while E had problems finishing his kids meal of spaghetti and meatballs. The atmosphere and service at the Hotel Pyhätunturi Restaurant were excellent and if you stay in Pyhä we strongly recommend that you visit the restaurant.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16457137153" title="The Poro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8686/16457137153_4fe83a661d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="659" alt="The Poro" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.huttu-uula.fi/">Restaurant Huttu-Uula</a> has won an Chaîne des Rôtisseurs award and is located at the foot of the Polar slope. Every Thursday it serves a <a href="http://www.huttu-uula.fi/files/uula_puffee.pdf">Lappish Food Buffet</a> with lots of delicious dishes from Lapland. The friendly atmosphere together with the good buffet food make this a recommended visit on a Thursday evening, though you should reserve well in advance as the Buffet is very popular and was fully booked out when we were there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889741440" title="Leipäjuusto by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7681/16889741440_7557737323_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Leipäjuusto" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fatbiking">Fatbiking</h2>

<p>Since I got my <a href="http://salsacycles.com/bikes/mukluk">Fatbike</a> cycling has been a lot of fun in winter. Riding over the frozen Baltic Sea, shredding over the single track in the forest and doing laps on the groomed trails are just a lot of fun, so of course I took the opportunity to go on a <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/fatbikes/">Fatbike Adventure at Pyhä</a>. I was very lucky that my friend Artturi was my guide for the morning, and after familiarizing myself with bike and hearing what Artturi had planned for us we hit the trails.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16888790748" title="Fatbiking, skiing or hiking? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7676/16888790748_0235d89209_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fatbiking, skiing or hiking?" /></a></p>

<p>After some beautiful, flow-y single track trails we arrived at a large mire which was a lot of fun to ride across. We had a short break at a bird watching tower which allowed for wide views over the National Park, before continuing across the mire - fat tires rock in that terrain! Slowly narrow tracks brought us back to our starting point, and after a nice climb back up to the Hotel this little Fatbike adventure was done. You also can rent a Fatbike for half a day or longer from Bliss in case you want to explore the National Park on your own. Hats off to Bliss Adventure for offering this service, I think they’re spot on with it and I saw daily very happy fatbike cyclists riding on the trails and snow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076575735" title="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8797/17076575735_d5ec086d2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456411083" title="Selfietime! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7610/16456411083_2d9c29dd7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfietime!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076574115" title="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17076574115_7c29a3b793_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park" /></a></p>

<h2 id="snowshoe-hiking">(Snowshoe) Hiking</h2>

<p>There is a dedicated <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/video-msr-lightning-ascent-review.html">snowshoe</a> hiking trail in Pyhä, though it was so hard packed that one didn’t need snowshoes to walk on it. So we had a nice little family hike to the Isokuru gorge and back, which includes a steep descent and climb from the nice Isokuru Kota. The hike seems to take the route of the summer nature trail as we passed quite a few signs which gave information about the forest and land, and is ideal if you’d like to be outdoors for a couple of hours. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050611986" title="Danger! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8813/17050611986_396e0e5472_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Danger!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456419973" title="Family Hike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/16456419973_19757d8746_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Family Hike" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075086052" title="Fire by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17075086052_af66532256_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="nature--silence">Nature &amp; Silence</h2>

<p>Despite all the activities you can do in Pyhä, there are two things in Pyhä-Luosto everywhere, and they’re for free: Nature and Silence. Even with a Baltic Ski Cup going on while we were in the village, we just needed to walk for five minutes towards the <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/en/pyha-luostonp">National Park</a> and there was a calmness that was just once in a while interrupted by birdsong or the wind blowing through the trees. Pyhä-Luosto National Park is home to the southern most big fjells in Finland, beyond them towards the south starts the flat land. Though this does make them popular I had at no time the feeling that there were too much people around me, for example the lines at the lifts were pretty much non-existent despite there being a bunch of people, and also in the Cafés and Restaurants there were never masses of people. As someone who values silence a lot I found Pyhä a great place, with easy access to nature and the possibility to <em>“escape”</em> the main slopes and head into the National Park, where even on blue bird days I didn’t meet more than a handful of people. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16869172217" title="Silver by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7613/16869172217_7c288c4b9e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Silver" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050598466" title="Snow &amp; Birch by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8690/17050598466_e512ff6074_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Snow &amp; Birch" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p><strong>Where to stay?</strong></p>

<p>We stayed at a <a href="http://www.ski-inn.fi/majoitus.asp?prodtype=30&amp;lang=eng&amp;tunturi=&amp;day=&amp;endDay=">Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartment</a> which was ideally located right next to the slopes. The apartment was super family-friendly and had two bedrooms, a small kitchen, living room, balcony, a own Sauna and a drying cabinet to dry wet garments and gear (super handy with kids!). There are plenty more options in town, from the nice <a href="http://www.ski-inn.fi/majoitus.asp?prodtype=41&amp;lang=eng&amp;tunturi=&amp;changeMonth=">Ski-Inn Hotel Pyhätunturi</a> to many, many cozy <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=cabins&amp;submenu=3660">cabins</a> and even a <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1106">caravan site</a> if you’re coming with your own accommodation. You’ll surely find something to your liking, keep an eye out for deals, though, as at e.g. the Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartments ski passes can be included in the price saving you a bunch of money!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16869175557" title="PyhäSuites by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7703/16869175557_09002a90bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="PyhäSuites" /></a></p>

<p><strong>How to get there?</strong></p>

<p>As we don’t own a car we rented one for a week and drove up north. Vaasa - Pyhä is around 660 km and with a toddler along we decided to split the journey in two and spend a night in Oulu. If you come from abroad you might want to fly directly to Rovaniemi and take the <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/info/?file=content_exec&amp;id=2292&amp;submenu=3890">SkiBus</a> to Pyhä, or take the (overnight) train from Helsinki and then jump on the SkiBus. In the village you can walk pretty much everywhere within 15 minutes, and there’s a variety of shops to suit your needs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157651506091295/">More Photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16454124174" title="No sledding by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8787/16454124174_baa0f5cd6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="No sledding" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075081902" title="Aurora Borealis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7644/17075081902_4025b6fd68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p><em>Thanks to the Pyhä Ski Resort and their Partners which invited us up north.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CXCIX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/the-week-in-review-cxcix.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-05T23:40:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/the-week-in-review-cxcix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Spring is the time of plans and projects.”</em>
― <a href="http://amzn.to/1Igbh6X">Leo Tolstoy</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16853591559" title="Locus Gear Khufu eVent II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8816/16853591559_6a1fd6d95a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Khufu eVent II" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.thebmc.co.uk/may-2015-lets-make-this-the-outdoor-election">May 2015: Let’s make this the Outdoor Election</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.trailgroove.com/issue21.html">Trail Groove Magazine Issue 21</a> is out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/web_weit_wandern/outdoor-news-zum-1-april/">April 1st Outdoor Pranks</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/sporting-scene/selling-rock-climbing-in-the-social-media-era">Selling Rock Climbing in the Social Media Era</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.compasscaddy.com/">Compass Caddy</a> which is soon launching on Kickstarter.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorphotographer.com/how-to/shooting/get-perfect-exposure-every-time.html">Get Perfect Exposure Every Time</a>.</p>

<p>Apply for a <a href="https://www.woodsdreamjob.com/">Hiker’s Dream Job</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/04/01/news-termine-april-2015/">News and Dates for April 2015</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://radwegeplan.de/">radwegeplan.de</a>, a new tool to plan your cycle path tours. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://onehundredmountains.blogspot.fi/2015/03/story-of-review.html">Story of a review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Take 20% off one Full-Price Item at Backcountry.com with Coupon Code: SPRING20</a>.</p>

<p>60% off on Arc’teryx, icebreaker, Marmot, Mammut and Haglöfs at <a href="http://bit.ly/1IyUzfJ">Bergfreunde</a>. And best off all: European orders over 50€ ship for free!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=307857&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/307857/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Every so often I happen to find, or am made aware of, a trip report which is utterly outstanding. An epic adventure, beautifully described in words and gorgeous photos which want to make you pack up and head there immediately. <a href="http://distantranges.com/in-the-golden-mountains-of-altai-part-1/">In the Golden Mountains of Altai</a> is such a trip report. <em>A highly recommended read</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://teleturn.blogspot.fi/2015/04/alaska-mountain-wilderness-ski-classic.html">Alaska Mountain Wilderness Ski Classic 2015 Rohn Glacier route</a>.</p>

<p>Roger is <a href="http://www.rogerodoherty.com/2015/03/walking-colorado-trail-julyaug-2014.html">walking the Colorado Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2015/03/seccion-4-y-5-el-inga-nan-y-el-sur.html">Trans-Ecuador</a> Section 4 and 5.</p>

<p><a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/2015/03/29/e1-fjaras-to-jonsered/">E1: Fjärås to Jonsered</a>.</p>

<p>Nick enjoys <a href="http://tms.nickbramhall.com/blog/2015/03/north-monar-hills/">the North Monar Hills</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/121378956?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;badge=0" width="600" height="337" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.packgofind.com/springtime">Gravel grinding with the Kona Rove</a>.</p>

<p>Jost, a 22 year old Alpinist, is planning for <a href="http://www.abenteuersuechtig.de/index.php/der-lhotse-eine-expedition-zum-vierthoechsten-berg-der-erde/">Lhotse</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://ethanwalkerclimbing.blogspot.fi/2015/04/spain-coffee-pockets-and-chorizo.html">Spain! Coffee, pockets and Chorizo</a>.</p>

<p>A nice video from <a href="http://urbanpackrafter.com/Packrafting-Morocco">packrafting in Morocco</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://endor-fin.com/?p=296">Up. Down. Repeat.</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/mono-lake-black-point-fissures/">Mono Lake: Black Point Fissures</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/jetboil/?pid=81" title="Jetboil MiniMo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7590/16762845637_14b4caf332_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jetboil MiniMo" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Helen gives tips in an <a href="http://gauperoar.blogspot.fi/2015/04/easy-water-bottle-pack-modification.html">easy water bottle pack modification</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RDI9QyGtPEI">How to pitch the Hilleberg Enan</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pedalingnowhere.com/gear/crumpler-kashgar-camera-bag-turned-handlebar-bag/">Turn a camera bag into a handlebar bag</a>.</p>

<p>Dave reviews the <a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2015/03/30/the-mid-ive-been-looking-for/">Beyond Timberline 2 from Seek Outside</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2015/03/sierra-madre-research-nube-shelter-review/">Sierra Madre Research Nubé Shelter Review</a>.</p>

<p>Wes lets you know why he thinks <a href="http://indefinitelywild.gizmodo.com/why-hammocks-suck-1694839210">Hammocks Suck</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://thenewnomads.com/?p=2165">Sleeping Outside</a>.</p>

<p>Watch <a href="http://sticksblog.com/2015/03/29/post-hike-gear-talk-march-2015-carvers-gap-to-kincora-hostel-dennis-cove-rd/">Chad’s Post Hike Gear Talk: March 2015</a>.</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Then please share this post with your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=42809&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/42809/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tulikartta - A Map of Wilderness Shelters in Finland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/tulikartta-a-map-of-all-open-shelters-in-finland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-31T09:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/tulikartta-a-map-of-all-open-shelters-in-finland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Open Wilderness Huts, Laavus, Kotas and Fireplaces are something I dearly love about the outdoors experience in Finland. It’s just very sophisticated to be able to plan a backpacking trip and rely on laavus and huts for sleeping, or know that there will be a fireplace in the mid point of the hike for a nice lunch break by the fire. <a href="http://www.tulikartta.fi/">Tulikartta.fi</a> set out to index all public shelters - from Laavus and Kotas over Wilderness Huts to Fireplaces - in one easy to use map, which makes it an excellent tool to plan an overnighter!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16799797338" title="Lankojärvi Hut by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8690/16799797338_3621ec6343_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lankojärvi Hut" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="prologue">Prologue</h2>

<p>In the past and still in the present <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/">Outdoors.fi</a> and <a href="http://www.retkikartta.fi/">Retkikartta.fi</a> have been the digital services I have used to plan a trip in Finland. The former lists all National Parks, Wilderness and Hiking Areas in the country, with information on history, how to get there, history and services available. Retkikartta is a highly detailed map which you can use to create routes, measure distances and look up coordinates to huts up to a scale of 1:2500, save and print out directly from the browser or export to your <a href="http://bit.ly/1Dk1sCb">GPS device</a>.</p>

<p>Outdoors.fi overview of destinations in Finland
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16366737023" title="Outdoors.fi Destination Search by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7607/16366737023_517394ba86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="627" alt="Outdoors.fi Destination Search" /></a></p>

<p>Outdoors.fi “detailed” map of a National Park
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16799142908" title="Outdoors.fi Map by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8720/16799142908_3867f425e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="628" alt="Outdoors.fi Map" /></a></p>

<p>Retkikartta.fi detailed map overview of the same National Park as above. This one can be zoomed in up to a scale of 1:2500!
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16985510292" title="Retkikartta.fi Map of trails, sights and shelters by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8711/16985510292_60a38cdaea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="627" alt="Retkikartta.fi Map of trails, sights and shelters" /></a></p>

<p>This is a good way to plan a backpacking trip, but if you wanted to find a shelter for a day trip it would have been a bit too involved. Enter Tulikartta.fi which facilitates finding a shelter a lot!</p>

<h2 id="an-introduction-to-tulikarttafi">An introduction to Tulikartta.fi</h2>

<p>A couple of weeks ago I read a tweet with a link to <a href="http://www.tulikartta.fi/">Tulikartta.fi</a> and I was immediately intrigued. A map of fire? Click, and I was there.</p>

<iframe src="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16985487862/player/" width="1024" height="626" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>It didn’t take me more than a look and a bit of reading to figure out what I had in front of me: A superb tool to plan overnighters and backpacking trips in Finland where I don’t want to carry a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shelters/">shelter</a> or might, for extra comfort and because I love a nice fire, camp close to a hut, fireplace or laavu. I set out to experiment a bit with it and see what kind of outdoors infrastructure the map listed around Vaasa, my home town. </p>

<iframe src="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16364468064/player/" width="1024" height="640" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Plenty of options to take the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">bike</a> and head to one of these places, make a fire and sleep outside. I also saw that a few fire places, bird towers and laavus were missing on the map, but happily the people who developed Tulikartta also thought of that and you can add a listing yourself. </p>

<iframe src="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16985487622/player/" width="1024" height="628" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I need to say it is one of these services where you might think “Why has no-one thought of this before?”. I like it alot already and it has given me plenty ideas for adventures close to home in-between the bigger trips this year. Using the existing infrastructure allows me to go ultralight with the bike and leave a shelter and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/stoves/">stove</a> at home and make use of a nice Lavvu by a lake and grill a bread and sausage over a fire. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16366741123" title="Laavus in Finland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7647/16366741123_af56d6f95c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="628" alt="Laavus in Finland" /></a></p>

<p>Right now the service is only in Finnish but it should be easy enough to use also if you don’t speak this beautiful &amp; easy language. To get you started: Laavu = an open shelter, Autiotupa = a open, free-to-use Wilderness Hut, a Kota = a native Saami tent, similar to a tipi from wood, Päivätupa = A Day Trip Hut and Nuotiopaikka = a Fireplace. The shelters usually also have a fireplace and a dry toilet close by to them, too, along with a woodshed and the obligatory saw and axe. Now that you know where to find the next shelter &amp; fireplace head out and enjoy the Finnish nature!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16801327849" title="Fireplace by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7634/16801327849_43d2aa66b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fireplace" /></a></p>

<p><em>Liked this? Let your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> also know about Tulikartta and share this article!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CXCVIII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxviii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-29T23:38:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxviii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Simplicity is the ultimate sophistication.”</em>
― <a href="http://amzn.to/1NpwCuP">Leonardo da Vinci</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16908493456" title="A lightweight spring adventure by bike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8738/16908493456_24643fdd8e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A lightweight spring adventure by bike" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://willgadd.com/ten-training-thoughts/">Ten Training Thoughts</a> from Will Gadd.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/03/ditching-infinity-machine-five-months.html">Ditching the infinity machine — five months later</a>.</p>

<p>Honored to be in the Top Ten of the top <a href="http://www.theadventurejunkies.com/top-25-adventure-travel-blogs/">25 Adventure blogs</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=cc&amp;cpid=1&amp;target=http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/montane/">Montane</a> is now available at <a href="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=cc&amp;cpid=1&amp;target=http://www.bergfreunde.de/">Bergfreunde</a>!</p>

<p>A great video from the <a href="https://youtu.be/-_ltTbWfaVU">ISPO 2015</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://lightroomkillertips.com/10-things-tell-new-lightroom-user-10/">10 Things I Would Tell a New Lightroom User</a>.</p>

<p>Take 20% Off One Full-Price Item at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">Backcountry.com with Coupon Code: SPRING20</a>.</p>

<p>Great deals on the best outdoor gear and apparel at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=13889&amp;pw=73183">CampSaver.com</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/outdoor-welten/fahrradausruestung/produkte/?utm_source=PTID13002584"><img src="http://ad.globetrotter-partnerprogramm.de/8-fahrrad-728x90.gif" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2015/03/where-north-wind-blows-part-three.html">Where the North Wind blows</a>, a recommended read.</p>

<p>Winter is still going string in the <a href="http://tarmachan.blogspot.fi/2015/03/blog-post_27.html">Cairngorms</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://emmaamerikassa.blogspot.fi/2015/03/the-kentucky-reunion.html">The Kentucky Reunion</a>.</p>

<p>Krister and Martin enjoy some <a href="http://mountainpassion.blogspot.fi/2015/03/lunndorren-2015-4-days-3-climbs-and-2.html">alpine climbing in Sweden</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://tv.thebmc.co.uk/video/go-wild">Go Wild</a>.</p>

<p>Spring in the <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/03/26/fruehling-bluemchen-gipfelglueck-im-ahrtal/">Ahrtal</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/dtFpURLUO0I">Danny MacAskill’s Solar Eclipse Ride</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WmVLcj-XKnM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://sticksblog.com/2015/03/28/at-section-hike-carvers-gap-to-dennis-cove-rd-kincora-hostel/">AT Section Hike: Carver’s Gap to Dennis Cove Rd.</a></p>

<p>Lina enjoys <a href="http://linaluftig.de/fruehlingsanfang-lenggries-oder-die-tuecken-der-uebergangszeit/">the start of spring in Lenggries</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://dirtanddogs.blogspot.fi/2015/03/winter-or-so-they-said.html">Winter, Or So They Said</a>.</p>

<p>Micheal’s first Winter 4000er, <a href="https://www.storehouse.co/stories/r9a8n-cannon-mountain">Cannon Mountain</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2015/03/24/a-different-game-the-dru-couloir-direct/">A Different Game: The Dru Couloir Direct</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://kuus-aa.blogspot.fi/2015/03/josse.html">Olhava in Winter</a> (Spring).</p>

<p><a href="http://onehundredmountains.blogspot.fi/2015/03/masterclass-on-karamatsu.html">Masterclass on Karamatsu</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16736638817" title="Off to Ireland! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7586/16736638817_31e640a493_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Off to Ireland!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A glued <a href="http://www.pluennenkreuzer.de/001_Landgaenger/419_HexHex/hexhex_01.html">MYOG Laavu</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.planet-alpha.com/index.php?topic=84.0">Sony A7 II Rolling Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/gear-reviews/electronics/digital-nomad-processing-and-backing-up-images-on-the-road">Digital Nomad; processing and backing up images on the road</a>.</p>

<p>Erika likes <a href="http://ulligunde.com/2015/03/fair-und-nachhaltig-kletterhosen-von-jung/">climbing pants from JUNG</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/haglofs-l-i-m-essens-jacket-review/">Haglöfs L.I.M. Essens jacket review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2015/03/field-tested-crux-ak37-pack/">Crux 37 Backpack Review</a>.</p>

<p>Jens tests the <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/test/praxistest-icebreaker-helix-ls-zip-isolationsjacke-aus-merinowolle/">Icebreaker Helix LS Zip</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2015/03/dream-hammock-thunderbird-review/">Dream Hammock ThunderBird Review</a>.</p>

<p><em>Liked this? Then please share this post with your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Greg Grenzke, Apparel Designer at Arc'teryx]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/mountain-people-greg-grenzke-apparel-designer.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-25T18:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/mountain-people-greg-grenzke-apparel-designer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“There is no bad weather, only bad clothes.”</em> </p>

<p>That’s a popular saying here in the North, and it is easy to imagine that this saying drives <a href="http://arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a> Designer Greg Grenzke and his team forward to design the best possible apparel for their <a href="http://arcteryx.com/ProductFind.aspx?language=EN&amp;Collection=Ascent">Ascent Line</a>. What goes into designing garments that are lightweight, functional and durable enough to survive in the mountains but are timeless in appearance you can read in this <em>Mountain People interview</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com" title="Greg Grenzke, Craftsmanship"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7634/16923034802_92c6824283_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Greg_Craftsmanship_AM0W9770" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Greg, thank you for taking the time for answering my questions.  Could you please introduce yourself briefly so we have an idea  what’s  your background?</strong></p>

<p>I studied industrial design at the University of Cincinnati as part of the DAAP (Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning program). Part of this program is cooperative education where they require the students to rotate between school and internships every 3 months year round for the last 4 years of the 5 year program. I did various internships throughout school such as with companies like Salomon Sports, Specialized Bicycles, and design firms. Anytime I had the opportunity to select the type of product I could work on it was always outdoor/ sports related, pretty much to the point my classmates would make fun of me because that was always my focus. This really helped me get my foot into the sports industry as I started building a portfolio of concepts/ products that I was really passionate about. I was offered a job before I graduated University from Specialized Bicycles. I worked there for 8 years designing all sorts of products such as footwear, bikes, bike graphics, helmets, saddles, gloves, really a huge variety of different products utilizing both hard goods and soft goods. The design approach was very hands on at Specialized which is also how things work at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a>. I have been at Arc’teryx now for over 3,5 years where I am the Designer/ Design Manager of the Ascent Apparel category. It’s been a fun challenge resolving soft good problems with more of an industrial design approach and methodology.</p>

<p>I have been active outdoors for as long as I can remember growing up in Michigan. Once I could drive (age 16 back then) that was really my door to freedom. I would borrow my mom’s car and go on road trips with friends to bike, hike, climb, ski, any opportunity I could typically heading west to the mountains.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16898393366" title="Greg bootpackin' by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr'"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8694/16898393366_a4e282d544_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="gg bootpackin" /></a>
©Rich Kupskay</p>

<p><strong>As a Category Manager for the Ascent line I imagine you’re a mountaineer and climber yourself. What are some of your favourite  routes and places?</strong></p>

<p>I still feel like I’m on vacation living in Coastal Mountain Range in North Vancouver as it’s somewhere I would come for vacation if I didn’t live here. You know you live in a pretty incredible place when you are traveling to other naturally beautiful countries and you still just want to get back home.</p>

<p>Some of my favorite places are very local like the Tantalus Mountain Range for alpine climbing which is about a 45 minute drive near Squamish BC, Canmore Alberta where I just went for my first time ice climbing with some of our athletes, and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html">Chamonix</a> where there are endless options! One of my other passions is ski touring/ mountaineering where again BC continues to stun me with its vast space and mountains where you often don’t encounter another soul sometimes for days at end.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16301931724" title="Greg and Tanja Schmitt, photo credit Matthias Scherer"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7627/16301931724_253140ddc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Greg and Tanja Schmitt, photo credit Matthias Scherer_Austria" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy 2014</a> at the “Insulation  types  for alpine environments” Seminar, where you introduced us with your  colleague Jon to the synthetic &amp; down insulation garments from  Arc’teryx. Some of these garments just came out - but can you give  us  a brief glimpse at what we could expect in the next season from  Arc’teryx?</strong></p>

<p>Well, let’s just say you can expect to see more insulation from us building upon our current offerings. There is a lot happening in the insulation world with new technologies and manufacturing processes. We are pretty conservative until we can prove the technology is substantially better than what we currently use and that it can stand the test of time. However, we are always experimenting with new ideas and technologies.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14784519783" title="Heatgun by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3847/14784519783_f6aee8fa98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Heatgun" /></a></p>

<p><strong>The Arc’teryx down insulation line has been available since 2013,  has it been more popular than your synthetics line?</strong></p>

<p>I’m not a sales guy so I’m definitely not the one to ask about sales numbers. However, the down line was a huge success after the 2013 launch and it is really growing extremely fast.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16304283443" title="Design Room"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8702/16304283443_9a7406a0f8_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-45" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What’s your own favourite layering setup when you head out into  the  mountains for a day of mountaineering or climbing?</strong></p>

<p>This really depends on where I am, weather conditions, how long I plan on being out, etc. But if I were to take a versatile system that works in many different situations I prefer to use something like a <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;model=Solo-Hoody">Solo Hoody</a> using our very hydrophobic Thermatek insulation as a belay/insulation layer, an <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;model=Alpha-FL-Jacket">Alpha FL shell</a> as it is very light weight, durable, and very breathable utilizing Gore-Tex Pro, a mid layer with high air permeability that provides light insulation but can dump heat/ moisture when you are pushing hard, and a slight synthetic base layer.   </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16923318411" title="Greg in Canmore"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8740/16923318411_1906e7e4ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="greg_canmore" /></a>
©Jon Rockefeller</p>

<p><strong>How long do you on average work on designing a garment? Is it a  couple of weeks from idea to prototype to fabrication sample, or  can  many months or even years go by?</strong></p>

<p>This also depends on if the product is a new style or a redesign of an existing style. Sometimes all the answers are in your head and the design time could be very quick. Other times, yes it can take months or even years to validate a design and it may not even make it to the market.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16923316131" title="Craftsmanship in the Arc'teryx Design Room"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8754/16923316131_2288edaba7_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-90" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Can you walk us through the different steps that go into making e.g. a Alpine climbing jacket like the Alpha FL?</strong></p>

<p>The first step is always defining the users need for a product. The Alpha FL is for travelling light &amp; fast while trying not to sacrifice durability. We had a really good starting point with the previous Alpha FL but we knew we could improve the product by minimizing seams, seam tape width, unnecessary glue/ fabric, and using a more durable face fabric with the Gore-Tex Pro membrane. We had various prototypes we tested in the field as well as in a lab for breathability testing. We ended up with a much more durable product at almost the same weight, about 69% less surface area from seam tape, more breathable, and more ergonomic feature set.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16301928864" title="Design tools"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8743/16301928864_22360c83f6_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-63" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are you &amp; your colleagues inspired by ideas from other companies  that make alpine climbing lines, or do you try to work in a vacuum  and  insulate yourself from what the others are doing?</strong></p>

<p>Ha, well North Vancouver can be a bit of a vacuum. We have a pretty unique work atmosphere and designers often challenge each other to make better products. Just walking around seeing what others are working on can be very inspiring and that’s where a lot of ideas stem from. We like to look forward and think about what could be done and not what has been done.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16304283403" title="2014-Northwoods-HO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8752/16304283403_723db53bf1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="2014-Northwoods-HO" /></a></p>

<p>  <strong>What role do your athletes have in the design process? Are they  involved from the start or does their feedback first come in when  they  are using what you have designed?</strong></p>

<p>We have some pretty amazing athletes in that they are so down to earth and easy to work with. They are some of the best testers we have as they literally live in the product. If their needs aren’t being met they will let us know and we will work with them to fill that need. Sometimes they will have ideas and we will make some prototypes for them to test. We do typically try to involve them early in the design process. We spend as much time with our athletes as we can, especially in the field as it’s a good excuse to get out of the office. Many of them are more like friends, as we share the same passions.    </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14731353344" title="Self-arrest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/14731353344_f604fca9f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Self-arrest" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What are the three most important attributes when you’re setting  out  designing a garment?</strong></p>

<p>Designing for longevity is typically one of the most important attributes that is always on our mind. This is really in the dna of the brand and it’s always rewarding to hear the stories of how someone’s jacket has lasted them over a decade, you can just see their face light up when they are telling you about it. </p>

<p>Another element of designing for longevity is building in timelessness. The brand has a very strong design language and we continue to build off this strong foundation. Although the materials and constructions continue to improve we want a product we design today to still look modern in 5 or 10 years. If you look at the lineage of something like the Beta AR or SV jacket, you can look at one from ten years ago and see the commonality. When we build in this timelessness we are also building in value.  </p>

<p><strong>Arc’teryx is well known for not resting on its laurels and  pushing  the boundaries. You’ve developed better water-resistant zippers,  were  one of the first companies to laminate seams, minimizing cuts so  that  seams are at an absolute minimum and many other innovations. Can we  expect another such innovation breakthrough from Arc’teryx in the  next  years?</strong></p>

<p>Arc’teryx always strives to push the boundaries and challenge conventional thinking. We still have some of the genius minds that helped create what the brand is today, as well as many new additions. We are definitely working on various future concepts but first we need to validate that they are feasible.</p>

<p><strong>Greg, thank you for taking the time for answering my questions!</strong></p>

<p><em>Liked this? Then please share this post with your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://arcteryx.com/" title="Screen Shot 2015-03-25 at 14.00.13 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8711/16738448720_5cfc100c7d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="598" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-25 at 14.00.13" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CXCVII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-22T23:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Everything was beautiful and nothing hurt.”</em>
― <a href="http://amzn.to/19IQV8k">Kurt Vonnegut</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16894069562" title="Fast winter rides across the open mires. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7584/16894069562_f687c8b583_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fast winter rides across the open mires." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/aktuelles/outdoor-deals-relaunch/">OutdoorDeals</a> relaunched their website and now helps you find the best deals on the gear you’re searching. Ute did an great <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/relaunch-outdoordeals-im-test/">in-depth test of how the new website works</a> and how you can use it to find the gear you’re looking for.</p>

<p>An <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/03/alpine-dawn-ii-teaser.html">Alpine Dawn Teaser</a>.</p>

<p>Keith’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1IfXWso">Balancing on Blue</a> book is now available!</p>

<p>Join the <a href="http://offthegrid.jp">Off the Grid</a> Outdoor Experience!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorwomensalliance.com/2015/03/know-when-to-walk-away.html">When to Walk Away from the Adventure</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/ultralight-thru-hiking/">Stripped Down with Mike St. Pierre</a>.</p>

<p>Definition of an <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/verschiedenes/definition-outdoor-blogger/">Outdoor Blogger</a>.</p>

<p>Are you going to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a>?</p>

<p>Check out the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/e9/outdoor-bekleidung/?bfc-marke[0]=abk&amp;bfc-marke[1]=chillaz&amp;bfc-marke[2]=red-chili&amp;bfc-marke[3]=prana&amp;bfc-marke[4]=edelrid&amp;bfc-marke[5]=8bplus&amp;bfc-marke[6]=charko&amp;bfc-marke[7]=gentic&amp;bfc-marke[8]=nihil&amp;bfc-marke[9]=five-ten&amp;listorderby=oxinsert&amp;listorder=desc&amp;&amp;&amp;">climbing gear and garments</a> at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de">Bergfreunde.de</a>.</p>

<p>Get the new <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=371565&amp;pw=73183">Big Agnes MTNGLO tents ONLY at REI</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=259941&amp;pw=73183">Save 30% on Popular Patagonia Jackets, Shirts, Pants &amp; more + Free Shipping at Patagonia.com</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>It’s a nother MYSTERY Edition of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">The Week In Review</a>, so click wisely &amp; enjoy the surprise post =) </p>

<p><a href="http://riversanddeserts.com/en/stuart-highway-part-1/">1</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/ecuador/planet-frailejon">2</a></p>

<p><a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/03/21/als-ob-die-zeit-still-steht-das-safiental-in-graubuenden/">3</a></p>

<p><a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/wicklow-mountains-winter/">4</a></p>

<p><a href="http://bigbananamountains.blogspot.fi/2015/03/no-sunset-im-afaid.html">5</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/03/another-short-kayaking-overnighter.html">6</a></p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bOnBRguDZ1I" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://hillplodder.com/2015/03/15/finishing-off-the-northern-fells-part-1-souther-fell/">7</a></p>

<p><a href="https://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2015/03/15/new-zealand-trip-trailer/">8</a></p>

<p><a href="http://freedirtmonger.blogspot.fi/2015/03/state-of-wilderness.html">9</a></p>

<p><a href="http://universalklister.blogspot.fi/2015/03/chasing-winter-final-2015-winter-frolic.html">10</a></p>

<p><a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2015/03/transitioning.html">12</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16688050737" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8725/16688050737_74310a1eb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/bike-talk/touring-in-south-america-on-a-fat-bike">1</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoor-logs.de/laufbursche-packsack/">2</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2015/03/foodloose-die-etwas-anderen-bio-nussriegel-und-frucht-nuss-mischungen/">3</a></p>

<p><a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/jung-womens-fritzi-pant-review/">4</a></p>

<p><a href="http://seattlebackpackersmagazine.com/super-natural-base-175-baselayers-review/">5</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/testbericht-julbo-montebianco-cameleon/">6</a></p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Share this post with your friend &amp; Followers via <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> so that also they get to read the best outdoors stories of the past week!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn Mountaineering at the 2015 Arc'teryx Alpine Academy]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-17T11:39:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/">2015 Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> starts in less than three months, and enrolment for clinics starts today! So don’t ponder longer and sign up for one of the best Mountaineering Events of the year and come to Chamonix in June!</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html" title="ARCTERYX_ACADEMY_PiotrD_928A1578 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8611/16650270818_3c404c9f35_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ARCTERYX_ACADEMY_PiotrD_928A1578" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I wrote in detail about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">2014 Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> and just booked my flights for this year’s event. If you want to learn about mountaineering, alpine climbing and the skills needed to safely cross a glacier on a hike, then you should right now surf to the <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy website</a> as registration for the clinics opens today. Here’s the teaser to get you in the mood:</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ERdkz2ga_6s" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>As in 2014 the ‘Compagnie des Guides de Chamonix’, the ‘British Mountain Guides’ (BMG) and the Chamex Guides together with Arc’teryx Athletes like Ines Papert, Luka Lindic, Nina Caprez and Mina Leslie-Wujastyk will teach you the skills and know-how to enjoy the mountains. New this year is the Clean-Up-Day on Thursday, the 11th of June, where the athletes and participants clean the mountains from rubbish. I’ll be there for that occasion, and can highly recommend you are too so you can get acclimatized before you head up to the Aiguille du Midi =) </p>

<p>You can read about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">logistics of getting and staying there</a> in my article from last year, and check out the <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/shop/">2015 Clinics</a> now so you know what to book. I have no doubt that the most popular courses will be fully-booked in a matter of minutes, so act quickly! New courses this year are <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/clinic-06-sun-advanced-technical-alpinism/">Advanced Technical Alpinism</a>, <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/clinic-11-sun-traditional-climbing/">Traditional Climbing</a>, <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/clinic-19-sun-big-wall-climbing/">Big Wall Climbing</a> and <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/clinic-20-sat-ski-alpinism/">Ski Alpinism</a> and there’s again exclusive Women’s courses, too. And make sure to join the <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/ad-mountain-dinner/">Academy Dinner</a> on Saturday evening before the <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/movie-night/">Movie Night</a>. It’s going to be a superb event and I am super psyched to be going there again this year, and if will be there - be sure to <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">let</a> <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">me</a> <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">know</a> so we can have a chat! </p>

<p>See you in Chamonix in June!</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html" title="ARCTERYX_ACADEMY_PiotrD_928A1619 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7591/16650638390_d37631fe39_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ARCTERYX_ACADEMY_PiotrD_928A1619" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CXCVI]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvi.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-15T23:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“So much universe, and so little time.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1EfatbN">Terry Pratchett</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16612857791" title="(Hidden) Moon, Venus and Mars by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8632/16612857791_7ba793f41a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="(Hidden) Moon, Venus and Mars" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://rab.equipment/">Rab</a> has a brand-new website.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/photo-galleries/outside-lens/Google-Street-View-Goes-to-Everest.html">Google Street View goes to Everest</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2015/03/our-dwr-problem.html">Patagonia’s DWR Problem</a>.</p>

<p>A new Dirtbag Diaries Podcast is out: <a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2015/03/dirtbag-diaries-podcast-the-threshold-moment.html">The Threshold Moment</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://revolutionclimbing.blogspot.fi/2014/11/the-grand-finale.html">Cordless shut down</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://franzstraubinger.wordpress.com/2015/03/14/vogelstimmen-lernen/">Learn to identify bird songs</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Don’t Look Back. <a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-adventure/climbing/mountaineering/American-Alpine-Club-2015-Everest.html">Climbing Still Has Plenty of Glory Days Ahead</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://kidproject.org/2015/03/09/qa-deal-stubborn-toddler/">How do I deal with my stubborn toddler on a outdoor trip</a>?</p>

<p>April on <a href="http://staywildandtrue.com/2015/03/08/hiking-solo-as-a-woman/">hiking Solo as a Woman</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/11/magazine/the-heart-stopping-climbs-of-alex-honnold.html">The Heart-Stopping Climbs of Alex Honnold</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=77257&amp;pw=73183">Free Shipping at REI</a>! EVERYONE gets US standard free shipping on orders of $50 or more!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=197101&amp;pw=73183">Hiking Footwear Sale at CampSaver.com</a> - get hiking shoes and boots up to 50% off!</p>

<p><a title="Bergzeit.co.uk" href="http://apps.bergzeit.de/seo/ldyn?pid=81&amp;bid=13&amp;cat=9&amp;lang=en" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><img alt="Bergzeit.co.uk" title="Bergzeit.co.uk" src="http://apps.bergzeit.de/seo/bdyn?pid=81&amp;bid=13&amp;cat=9&amp;lang=en" width="728" height="90" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://onehundredmountains.blogspot.fi/2015/03/by-fair-means.html">Climbing the One Hundred Mountains of Japan without fossil fuels</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tonilund.fi/2015/03/iti-2015-race-report-beyond-words-part-3.html">ITI 2015 Race Report - Beyond Words</a> - Toni’s </p>

<p>A quick <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/ecuador/ecuadorian-news-catch-up">Ecuadorian news catch up</a> from Cass.</p>

<p>Peter was out for a <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/03/a-short-kayaking-overnighter.html">short kayaking overnighter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/03/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-15.html">In the Realm of Tigers &amp; Rhinos</a> in Western Nepal. [German]</p>

<p>Christina &amp; Körni went <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/fast-forward-the-spring-season-climbing-in-arco/">climbing in Arco</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/03/the-grand-route-forbes-long-distance.html">The Grand Route Forbes — a long-distance hike in the Alps</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/120156522?color=61bf84&amp;byline=0" width="1200" height="501" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://mountainpassion.blogspot.fi/2015/03/3-men-mooning-climb.html">3 Men Mooning</a>, a Swedish ice climb adventure.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.twistingspokes.com/siberia-a-journey-to-lake-baikal/">Siberia, a journey to lake Baikal</a>.</p>

<p>Karolin gives you five reasons why you should go on a <a href="http://linaluftig.de/mit-schneeschuhen-zu-den-skitourentagen/">guided snowshoe hike</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2015/03/08/bear-lakes-basin/">Bear Lakes Basin Loop Backpack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://kathmandustories.com/2015/03/09/balephi/">Packrafting in Nepal</a>.</p>

<p>Helen has a new blog and was hiking at <a href="http://gauperoar.blogspot.fi/2015/03/the-stmarka-mil.html">The Østmarka Mil</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://campillustrated.com/post/112843924741/recent-trip-to-yosemite">Recent Trip to Yosemite</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16608847307" title="Wanderlust Equipment &amp; Ogawand kit. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8648/16608847307_955788dc17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="833" alt="Wanderlust Equipment &amp; Ogawand kit." /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Nadine likes the <a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2015/03/12/produkt-testmountain-hardwear-thermostatic-jacket/">Mountain Hardwear Thermostatic Jacket</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/aether-apparel-elite-leggings/">Aether Apparel Elite Leggings</a>.</p>

<p>Jacob hikes with the <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2015/zpacks-arc-blast-60l-backpack/">ZPacks Arc Blast 60L Backpack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/2015/03/the-evolution-of-wool.html">The Evolution Of Wool</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ivovanmontfort.blogspot.fi/2015/03/blaasbalg-voor-exped-downmat-7.html">MYOG Inflation bag for the Exped Downmat 7</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://offroute.ca/2015/03/13/a-beginners-guide-to-bikepacking-chilcotin-mountain-gear-choices/">A Beginner’s Guide to Bikepacking – Chilcotin Mountain Gear Choices</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://luminous-landscape.com/mountain-climbing-photography/">Mountain Climbing Photography</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Share this post with your friend &amp; Followers via <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> so that also they get to read the best outdoors stories of the past week!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schneeschuhe/" title="Schneeschuhe kaufen bei Bergfreunde.de" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><img src="http://www.bergfreunde-partner.de/banner/winter/728x90_schneeschuhe.jpg" alt="Schneeschuhe kaufen bei Bergfreunde.de" border="0" /></a><img src="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=413&amp;cpid=1&amp;prid=1&amp;view=1" height="1" width="1" border="0" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
