<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-25T14:05:02+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Greg Grenzke, Apparel Designer at Arc'teryx]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/mountain-people-greg-grenzke-apparel-designer.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-25T18:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/mountain-people-greg-grenzke-apparel-designer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“There is no bad weather, only bad clothes.”</em> </p>

<p>That’s a popular saying here in the North, and it is easy to imagine that this saying drives <a href="http://arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a> Designer Greg Grenzke and his team forward to design the best possible apparel for their <a href="http://arcteryx.com/ProductFind.aspx?language=EN&amp;Collection=Ascent">Ascent Line</a>. What goes into designing garments that are lightweight, functional and durable enough to survive in the mountains but are timeless in appearance you can read in this <em>Mountain People interview</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com" title="Greg Grenzke, Craftsmanship"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7634/16923034802_92c6824283_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Greg_Craftsmanship_AM0W9770" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Greg, thank you for taking the time for answering my questions.  Could you please introduce yourself briefly so we have an idea  what’s  your background?</strong></p>

<p>I studied industrial design at the University of Cincinnati as part of the DAAP (Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning program). Part of this program is cooperative education where they require the students to rotate between school and internships every 3 months year round for the last 4 years of the 5 year program. I did various internships throughout school such as with companies like Salomon Sports, Specialized Bicycles, and design firms. Anytime I had the opportunity to select the type of product I could work on it was always outdoor/ sports related, pretty much to the point my classmates would make fun of me because that was always my focus. This really helped me get my foot into the sports industry as I started building a portfolio of concepts/ products that I was really passionate about. I was offered a job before I graduated University from Specialized Bicycles. I worked there for 8 years designing all sorts of products such as footwear, bikes, bike graphics, helmets, saddles, gloves, really a huge variety of different products utilizing both hard goods and soft goods. The design approach was very hands on at Specialized which is also how things work at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a>. I have been at Arc’teryx now for over 3,5 years where I am the Designer/ Design Manager of the Ascent Apparel category. It’s been a fun challenge resolving soft good problems with more of an industrial design approach and methodology.</p>

<p>I have been active outdoors for as long as I can remember growing up in Michigan. Once I could drive (age 16 back then) that was really my door to freedom. I would borrow my mom’s car and go on road trips with friends to bike, hike, climb, ski, any opportunity I could typically heading west to the mountains.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16898393366" title="Greg bootpackin' by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr'"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8694/16898393366_a4e282d544_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="gg bootpackin" /></a></p>

<p><strong>As a Category Manager for the Ascent line I imagine you’re a mountaineer and climber yourself. What are some of your favourite  routes and places?</strong></p>

<p>I still feel like I’m on vacation living in Coastal Mountain Range in North Vancouver as it’s somewhere I would come for vacation if I didn’t live here. You know you live in a pretty incredible place when you are traveling to other naturally beautiful countries and you still just want to get back home.</p>

<p>Some of my favorite places are very local like the Tantalus Mountain Range for alpine climbing which is about a 45 minute drive near Squamish BC, Canmore Alberta where I just went for my first time ice climbing with some of our athletes, and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html">Chamonix</a> where there are endless options! One of my other passions is ski touring/ mountaineering where again BC continues to stun me with its vast space and mountains where you often don’t encounter another soul sometimes for days at end.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16301931724" title="Greg and Tanja Schmitt, photo credit Matthias Scherer"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7627/16301931724_253140ddc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Greg and Tanja Schmitt, photo credit Matthias Scherer_Austria" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy 2014</a> at the “Insulation  types  for alpine environments” Seminar, where you introduced us with your  colleague Jon to the synthetic &amp; down insulation garments from  Arc’teryx. Some of these garments just came out - but can you give  us  a brief glimpse at what we could expect in the next season from  Arc’teryx?</strong></p>

<p>Well, let’s just say you can expect to see more insulation from us building upon our current offerings. There is a lot happening in the insulation world with new technologies and manufacturing processes. We are pretty conservative until we can prove the technology is substantially better than what we currently use and that it can stand the test of time. However, we are always experimenting with new ideas and technologies.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14784519783" title="Heatgun by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3847/14784519783_f6aee8fa98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Heatgun" /></a></p>

<p><strong>The Arc’teryx down insulation line has been available since 2013,  has it been more popular than your synthetics line?</strong></p>

<p>I’m not a sales guy so I’m definitely not the one to ask about sales numbers. However, the down line was a huge success after the 2013 launch and it is really growing extremely fast.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16304283443" title="Design Room"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8702/16304283443_9a7406a0f8_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-45" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What’s your own favourite layering setup when you head out into  the  mountains for a day of mountaineering or climbing?</strong></p>

<p>This really depends on where I am, weather conditions, how long I plan on being out, etc. But if I were to take a versatile system that works in many different situations I prefer to use something like a <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;model=Solo-Hoody">Solo Hoody</a> using our very hydrophobic Thermatek insulation as a belay/insulation layer, an <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;model=Alpha-FL-Jacket">Alpha FL shell</a> as it is very light weight, durable, and very breathable utilizing Gore-Tex Pro, a mid layer with high air permeability that provides light insulation but can dump heat/ moisture when you are pushing hard, and a slight synthetic base layer.   </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16923318411" title="Greg in Canmore"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8740/16923318411_1906e7e4ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="greg_canmore" /></a></p>

<p><strong>How long do you on average work on designing a garment? Is it a  couple of weeks from idea to prototype to fabrication sample, or  can  many months or even years go by?</strong></p>

<p>This also depends on if the product is a new style or a redesign of an existing style. Sometimes all the answers are in your head and the design time could be very quick. Other times, yes it can take months or even years to validate a design and it may not even make it to the market.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16923316131" title="Craftsmanship in the Arc'teryx Design Room"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8754/16923316131_2288edaba7_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-90" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Can you walk us through the different steps that go into making e.g. a Alpine climbing jacket like the Alpha FL?</strong></p>

<p>The first step is always defining the users need for a product. The Alpha FL is for travelling light &amp; fast while trying not to sacrifice durability. We had a really good starting point with the previous Alpha FL but we knew we could improve the product by minimizing seams, seam tape width, unnecessary glue/ fabric, and using a more durable face fabric with the Gore-Tex Pro membrane. We had various prototypes we tested in the field as well as in a lab for breathability testing. We ended up with a much more durable product at almost the same weight, about 69% less surface area from seam tape, more breathable, and more ergonomic feature set.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16301928864" title="Design tools"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8743/16301928864_22360c83f6_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-63" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are you &amp; your colleagues inspired by ideas from other companies  that make alpine climbing lines, or do you try to work in a vacuum  and  insulate yourself from what the others are doing?</strong></p>

<p>Ha, well North Vancouver can be a bit of a vacuum. We have a pretty unique work atmosphere and designers often challenge each other to make better products. Just walking around seeing what others are working on can be very inspiring and that’s where a lot of ideas stem from. We like to look forward and think about what could be done and not what has been done.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16304283403" title="2014-Northwoods-HO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8752/16304283403_723db53bf1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="2014-Northwoods-HO" /></a></p>

<p>  <strong>What role do your athletes have in the design process? Are they  involved from the start or does their feedback first come in when  they  are using what you have designed?</strong></p>

<p>We have some pretty amazing athletes in that they are so down to earth and easy to work with. They are some of the best testers we have as they literally live in the product. If their needs aren’t being met they will let us know and we will work with them to fill that need. Sometimes they will have ideas and we will make some prototypes for them to test. We do typically try to involve them early in the design process. We spend as much time with our athletes as we can, especially in the field as it’s a good excuse to get out of the office. Many of them are more like friends, as we share the same passions.    </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14731353344" title="Self-arrest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/14731353344_f604fca9f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Self-arrest" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What are the three most important attributes when you’re setting  out  designing a garment?</strong></p>

<p>Designing for longevity is typically one of the most important attributes that is always on our mind. This is really in the dna of the brand and it’s always rewarding to hear the stories of how someone’s jacket has lasted them over a decade, you can just see their face light up when they are telling you about it. </p>

<p>Another element of designing for longevity is building in timelessness. The brand has a very strong design language and we continue to build off this strong foundation. Although the materials and constructions continue to improve we want a product we design today to still look modern in 5 or 10 years. If you look at the lineage of something like the Beta AR or SV jacket, you can look at one from ten years ago and see the commonality. When we build in this timelessness we are also building in value.  </p>

<p><strong>Arc’teryx is well known for not resting on its laurels and  pushing  the boundaries. You’ve developed better water-resistant zippers,  were  one of the first companies to laminate seams, minimizing cuts so  that  seams are at an absolute minimum and many other innovations. Can we  expect another such innovation breakthrough from Arc’teryx in the  next  years?</strong></p>

<p>Arc’teryx always strives to push the boundaries and challenge conventional thinking. We still have some of the genius minds that helped create what the brand is today, as well as many new additions. We are definitely working on various future concepts but first we need to validate that they are feasible.</p>

<p><strong>Greg, thank you for taking the time for answering my questions!</strong></p>

<p><em>Liked this? Then please share this post with your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://arcteryx.com/" title="Screen Shot 2015-03-25 at 14.00.13 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8711/16738448720_5cfc100c7d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="598" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-25 at 14.00.13" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXVII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-22T23:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Everything was beautiful and nothing hurt.”</em>
― <a href="http://amzn.to/19IQV8k">Kurt Vonnegut</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16894069562" title="Fast winter rides across the open mires. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7584/16894069562_f687c8b583_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fast winter rides across the open mires." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/aktuelles/outdoor-deals-relaunch/">OutdoorDeals</a> relaunched their website and now helps you find the best deals on the gear you’re searching. Ute did an great <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/relaunch-outdoordeals-im-test/">in-depth test of how the new website works</a> and how you can use it to find the gear you’re looking for.</p>

<p>An <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/03/alpine-dawn-ii-teaser.html">Alpine Dawn Teaser</a>.</p>

<p>Keith’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1IfXWso">Balancing on Blue</a> book is now available!</p>

<p>Join the <a href="http://offthegrid.jp">Off the Grid</a> Outdoor Experience!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorwomensalliance.com/2015/03/know-when-to-walk-away.html">When to Walk Away from the Adventure</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/ultralight-thru-hiking/">Stripped Down with Mike St. Pierre</a>.</p>

<p>Definition of an <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/verschiedenes/definition-outdoor-blogger/">Outdoor Blogger</a>.</p>

<p>Are you going to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a>?</p>

<p>Check out the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/e9/outdoor-bekleidung/?bfc-marke[0]=abk&amp;bfc-marke[1]=chillaz&amp;bfc-marke[2]=red-chili&amp;bfc-marke[3]=prana&amp;bfc-marke[4]=edelrid&amp;bfc-marke[5]=8bplus&amp;bfc-marke[6]=charko&amp;bfc-marke[7]=gentic&amp;bfc-marke[8]=nihil&amp;bfc-marke[9]=five-ten&amp;listorderby=oxinsert&amp;listorder=desc&amp;&amp;&amp;">climbing gear and garments</a> at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de">Bergfreunde.de</a>.</p>

<p>Get the new <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=371565&amp;pw=73183">Big Agnes MTNGLO tents ONLY at REI</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=259941&amp;pw=73183">Save 30% on Popular Patagonia Jackets, Shirts, Pants &amp; more + Free Shipping at Patagonia.com</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=35465&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/35465/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>It’s a nother MYSTERY Edition of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">The Week In Review</a>, so click wisely &amp; enjoy the surprise post =) </p>

<p><a href="http://riversanddeserts.com/en/stuart-highway-part-1/">1</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/ecuador/planet-frailejon">2</a></p>

<p><a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/03/21/als-ob-die-zeit-still-steht-das-safiental-in-graubuenden/">3</a></p>

<p><a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/wicklow-mountains-winter/">4</a></p>

<p><a href="http://bigbananamountains.blogspot.fi/2015/03/no-sunset-im-afaid.html">5</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/03/another-short-kayaking-overnighter.html">6</a></p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bOnBRguDZ1I" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://hillplodder.com/2015/03/15/finishing-off-the-northern-fells-part-1-souther-fell/">7</a></p>

<p><a href="https://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2015/03/15/new-zealand-trip-trailer/">8</a></p>

<p><a href="http://freedirtmonger.blogspot.fi/2015/03/state-of-wilderness.html">9</a></p>

<p><a href="http://universalklister.blogspot.fi/2015/03/chasing-winter-final-2015-winter-frolic.html">10</a></p>

<p><a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2015/03/transitioning.html">12</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16688050737" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8725/16688050737_74310a1eb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/bike-talk/touring-in-south-america-on-a-fat-bike">1</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoor-logs.de/laufbursche-packsack/">2</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2015/03/foodloose-die-etwas-anderen-bio-nussriegel-und-frucht-nuss-mischungen/">3</a></p>

<p><a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/jung-womens-fritzi-pant-review/">4</a></p>

<p><a href="http://seattlebackpackersmagazine.com/super-natural-base-175-baselayers-review/">5</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/testbericht-julbo-montebianco-cameleon/">6</a></p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Share this post with your friend &amp; Followers via <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> so that also they get to read the best outdoors stories of the past week!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn Mountaineering at the 2015 Arc'teryx Alpine Academy]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-17T11:39:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/">2015 Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> starts in less than three months, and enrolment for clinics starts today! So don’t ponder longer and sign up for one of the best Mountaineering Events of the year and come to Chamonix in June!</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html" title="ARCTERYX_ACADEMY_PiotrD_928A1578 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8611/16650270818_3c404c9f35_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ARCTERYX_ACADEMY_PiotrD_928A1578" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I wrote in detail about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">2014 Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> and just booked my flights for this year’s event. If you want to learn about mountaineering, alpine climbing and the skills needed to safely cross a glacier on a hike, then you should right now surf to the <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy website</a> as registration for the clinics opens today. Here’s the teaser to get you in the mood:</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ERdkz2ga_6s" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>As in 2014 the ‘Compagnie des Guides de Chamonix’, the ‘British Mountain Guides’ (BMG) and the Chamex Guides together with Arc’teryx Athletes like Ines Papert, Luka Lindic, Nina Caprez and Mina Leslie-Wujastyk will teach you the skills and know-how to enjoy the mountains. New this year is the Clean-Up-Day on Thursday, the 11th of June, where the athletes and participants clean the mountains from rubbish. I’ll be there for that occasion, and can highly recommend you are too so you can get acclimatized before you head up to the Aiguille du Midi =) </p>

<p>You can read about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">logistics of getting and staying there</a> in my article from last year, and check out the <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/shop/">2015 Clinics</a> now so you know what to book. I have no doubt that the most popular courses will be fully-booked in a matter of minutes, so act quickly! New courses this year are <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/clinic-06-sun-advanced-technical-alpinism/">Advanced Technical Alpinism</a>, <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/clinic-11-sun-traditional-climbing/">Traditional Climbing</a>, <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/clinic-19-sun-big-wall-climbing/">Big Wall Climbing</a> and <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/clinic-20-sat-ski-alpinism/">Ski Alpinism</a> and there’s again exclusive Women’s courses, too. And make sure to join the <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/product/ad-mountain-dinner/">Academy Dinner</a> on Saturday evening before the <a href="http://arcteryxacademy.com/movie-night/">Movie Night</a>. It’s going to be a superb event and I am super psyched to be going there again this year, and if will be there - be sure to <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">let</a> <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">me</a> <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">know</a> so we can have a chat! </p>

<p>See you in Chamonix in June!</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html" title="ARCTERYX_ACADEMY_PiotrD_928A1619 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7591/16650638390_d37631fe39_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ARCTERYX_ACADEMY_PiotrD_928A1619" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXVI]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvi.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-15T23:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxvi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“So much universe, and so little time.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1EfatbN">Terry Pratchett</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16612857791" title="(Hidden) Moon, Venus and Mars by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8632/16612857791_7ba793f41a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="(Hidden) Moon, Venus and Mars" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://rab.equipment/">Rab</a> has a brand-new website.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/photo-galleries/outside-lens/Google-Street-View-Goes-to-Everest.html">Google Street View goes to Everest</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2015/03/our-dwr-problem.html">Patagonia’s DWR Problem</a>.</p>

<p>A new Dirtbag Diaries Podcast is out: <a href="http://www.thecleanestline.com/2015/03/dirtbag-diaries-podcast-the-threshold-moment.html">The Threshold Moment</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://revolutionclimbing.blogspot.fi/2014/11/the-grand-finale.html">Cordless shut down</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://franzstraubinger.wordpress.com/2015/03/14/vogelstimmen-lernen/">Learn to identify bird songs</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Don’t Look Back. <a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-adventure/climbing/mountaineering/American-Alpine-Club-2015-Everest.html">Climbing Still Has Plenty of Glory Days Ahead</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://kidproject.org/2015/03/09/qa-deal-stubborn-toddler/">How do I deal with my stubborn toddler on a outdoor trip</a>?</p>

<p>April on <a href="http://staywildandtrue.com/2015/03/08/hiking-solo-as-a-woman/">hiking Solo as a Woman</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/11/magazine/the-heart-stopping-climbs-of-alex-honnold.html">The Heart-Stopping Climbs of Alex Honnold</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=77257&amp;pw=73183">Free Shipping at REI</a>! EVERYONE gets US standard free shipping on orders of $50 or more!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=197101&amp;pw=73183">Hiking Footwear Sale at CampSaver.com</a> - get hiking shoes and boots up to 50% off!</p>

<p><a title="Bergzeit.co.uk" href="http://apps.bergzeit.de/seo/ldyn?pid=81&amp;bid=13&amp;cat=9&amp;lang=en" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><img alt="Bergzeit.co.uk" title="Bergzeit.co.uk" src="http://apps.bergzeit.de/seo/bdyn?pid=81&amp;bid=13&amp;cat=9&amp;lang=en" width="728" height="90" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://onehundredmountains.blogspot.fi/2015/03/by-fair-means.html">Climbing the One Hundred Mountains of Japan without fossil fuels</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tonilund.fi/2015/03/iti-2015-race-report-beyond-words-part-3.html">ITI 2015 Race Report - Beyond Words</a> - Toni’s </p>

<p>A quick <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/south-america/ecuador/ecuadorian-news-catch-up">Ecuadorian news catch up</a> from Cass.</p>

<p>Peter was out for a <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/03/a-short-kayaking-overnighter.html">short kayaking overnighter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/03/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-15.html">In the Realm of Tigers &amp; Rhinos</a> in Western Nepal. [German]</p>

<p>Christina &amp; Körni went <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/fast-forward-the-spring-season-climbing-in-arco/">climbing in Arco</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/03/the-grand-route-forbes-long-distance.html">The Grand Route Forbes — a long-distance hike in the Alps</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/120156522?color=61bf84&amp;byline=0" width="1200" height="501" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://mountainpassion.blogspot.fi/2015/03/3-men-mooning-climb.html">3 Men Mooning</a>, a Swedish ice climb adventure.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.twistingspokes.com/siberia-a-journey-to-lake-baikal/">Siberia, a journey to lake Baikal</a>.</p>

<p>Karolin gives you five reasons why you should go on a <a href="http://linaluftig.de/mit-schneeschuhen-zu-den-skitourentagen/">guided snowshoe hike</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2015/03/08/bear-lakes-basin/">Bear Lakes Basin Loop Backpack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://kathmandustories.com/2015/03/09/balephi/">Packrafting in Nepal</a>.</p>

<p>Helen has a new blog and was hiking at <a href="http://gauperoar.blogspot.fi/2015/03/the-stmarka-mil.html">The Østmarka Mil</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://campillustrated.com/post/112843924741/recent-trip-to-yosemite">Recent Trip to Yosemite</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16608847307" title="Wanderlust Equipment &amp; Ogawand kit. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8648/16608847307_955788dc17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="833" alt="Wanderlust Equipment &amp; Ogawand kit." /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Nadine likes the <a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2015/03/12/produkt-testmountain-hardwear-thermostatic-jacket/">Mountain Hardwear Thermostatic Jacket</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.littlegrunts.com/aether-apparel-elite-leggings/">Aether Apparel Elite Leggings</a>.</p>

<p>Jacob hikes with the <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2015/zpacks-arc-blast-60l-backpack/">ZPacks Arc Blast 60L Backpack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/2015/03/the-evolution-of-wool.html">The Evolution Of Wool</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ivovanmontfort.blogspot.fi/2015/03/blaasbalg-voor-exped-downmat-7.html">MYOG Inflation bag for the Exped Downmat 7</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://offroute.ca/2015/03/13/a-beginners-guide-to-bikepacking-chilcotin-mountain-gear-choices/">A Beginner’s Guide to Bikepacking – Chilcotin Mountain Gear Choices</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://luminous-landscape.com/mountain-climbing-photography/">Mountain Climbing Photography</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Share this post with your friend &amp; Followers via <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> so that also they get to read the best outdoors stories of the past week!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schneeschuhe/" title="Schneeschuhe kaufen bei Bergfreunde.de" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><img src="http://www.bergfreunde-partner.de/banner/winter/728x90_schneeschuhe.jpg" alt="Schneeschuhe kaufen bei Bergfreunde.de" border="0" /></a><img src="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=413&amp;cpid=1&amp;prid=1&amp;view=1" height="1" width="1" border="0" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-13T21:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>How do you go about planning a trip to the Dolomites with a mate who is currently in Australia?</em> Easy: You both get the same guide book, book the flights together and then start going via Skype through the book to pick the climbs you wanna do. And that’s exactly how we are planning our trip to the Dolomites this summer, with our guide book of choice being <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16614176108" title="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7607/16614176108_d918a4f9ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’ve been dreaming/ planning/ pondering/ almost-booking-flights-to-the-Dolomites since around four years. Vivid are the memories of driving through them as a child with mom and dad on the way to Southern Italy and back to Germany, then a <a href="http://www.rockandice.com">Rock &amp; Ice article</a> a few years ago re-kindled that love to go and visit one of the most beautiful areas in Italy. Sure, there would be some sweet hiking and cycling there, but it will still be there at another time. Now, this trip, it will be about climbing Multi-Pitch Routes and do Via Ferratas, visit a <a href="http://www.messner-mountain-museum.it">Messner Mountain Museum</a> and enjoy the good life with a great mate.</p>

<p>And with the <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata</a> Guide Book the good life already starts at home with the planning. I have been since a few weeks each evening going through the Guide Book and found it a superb resource to plan our trip. It’s so easy to send a short message á la <em>“Check out that sweet Multi-Pitch climb on page 384! Wanna do that?”</em> and literally be on the same page. It makes deciding on climbs a lot faster and easier, too, because opening a page in a book is faster &amp; more convenient than surfing to a webpage.</p>

<p>So how is this book lay out? Well, it starts with a bit of (climbing) history of the region and its geology, gives tips on other books and maps, and then tells you all you need to know about the Logistics of getting there, getting around, where to eat, sleep and what to bring. Then there’s a chapter each on Via Ferratas and Climbing, with explanations of grades, gear and how to plan a trip on the routes. Very useful and open pretty much all the time is the overview map of the Region (page 26/ 27 ;) before the book goes into the details.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16800637951" title="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7620/16800637951_e9fa1116c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata" /></a></p>

<p>And details means in this case detailed maps of the Region/ sector, photos with drawn-in topos and in-depth descriptions of the Via Ferratas and climbs. I found these descriptions very good, they give a bit of extra information on how hard the climb could be and how long it could take. What I like best about the <a href="http://www.rockfax.com">Rockfax.com</a> Guide Book is that you can download either the sectors/ climbs or the whole book onto your smartphone, allowing you to leave the 926 g Guide Book at home and don’t need to carry it up a climb - smart stuff. At the end there’s a Route Index and another map of the region with a General Index. </p>

<p>So, for me this has been a wonderful Guide Book thus far. The photos are top-notch and have me very much looking forward to this trip. What could be improved would be probably a larger fold-out/ take-out map as I feel I’m checking it all the time - we’re not staying in one Region/ Sector but plan to see a lot, though if you have more time and/ or stay in one Region you’ll probably be happy as it is. Overall I’d say you should get this Guide Book if you plan to visit the Dolomites for climbing and Via Ferrata hiking - or you should get it if you want to have a very good reason to visit them =) It’s a beautiful book with inspiring photos, all the information we needed to plan the trip logistics and it has in-depth information on the climbs and Via Ferratas of the region. It has been a source of joy for me in the last weeks and has me very much looking forward to visit this Region again - lets hope the weather will be kind for climbing!</p>

<p>Buy the book directly from <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">Rockfax.com</a>, at your local climbing or book shop or order it from your favourite taste of <a href="http://amzn.to/1x0WARt">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1GMfr5H">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1GMfYVk">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-4.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-10T23:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A bunch more new gear for the trailrunner, the backpacker, the climber, the skier, the cyclists and simply anyone who likes the outdoors, or gear, with a look at trends, a dozen other blogs that reported on the fair and a final conclusion of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">2015 ISPO</a> in München.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695647012" title="Audi &amp; Heimplanet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8581/16695647012_b34d002d69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Audi &amp; Heimplanet" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Late to the Party? Read the other updates for more Gear News: <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html">Part 1</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2.html">Part 2</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">Part 3</a>.</em></p>

<h2 id="petzl">Petzl</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578475520" title="Petzl Sitta harness by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8731/16578475520_e272aca434_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Sitta harness" /></a></p>

<p>There were four big news for me at <a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The new Sitta Harness</li>
  <li>The new RAD System</li>
  <li>The new positioning lanyards</li>
  <li>The updated headlamp line-up</li>
</ul>

<p>Lets look at these in detail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578288858" title="Petzl Sitta harness by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7609/16578288858_3e832e66ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Sitta harness" /></a></p>

<p>The new harness obviously immediately had my interest, as it’s lighter yet again as the Hirundos (that I have here and which is already damn light at 280 g in Size Medium) - the Sitta will be 250 g in Size Medium and a sweet 230 g in Size Small. The Wireframe Technology which this harness uses uses Dyneema strands in the waistbelt and leg loops and which replaces webbing and foam in normal harnesses. It’s a very compact harness with a beautiful design that’s slim but still packs all you need from a harness: Two rigid front gear loops, two flexible back gear loops, two Caritool slots and a rear loop for a haul rope. It’s made of Bluesign® approved fabrics, too. Psyched about this one!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764794052" title="Petzl RAD System by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8718/16764794052_1aa2dcaae5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl RAD System" /></a></p>

<p>The new RAD System, (<strong>R</strong>escue <strong>A</strong>nd <strong>D</strong>escent) is an all-in-one set for skiers that allows you to set up an crevasse rescue, rappel or rope up on a glacier. The set contains three Attache carabiners, one storage bag, one Tibloc, one Micro Traxion, one 120 cm sling and the 30 m RAD Line, a newly developed 6 mm cordage which allows you to do a crevasse rescue, rope up on a glacier or rappel. The whole set weighs in at 1.045 g which is quite a bit lighter as other options, and also very compact. The cord tips the scales at 660 g for the 30 m, that’s 22 g/ m. It’s a static cord with less than 2% stretch which makes it great for rappels and rescue actions and minimizes yo-yo effects. It’s something any backcountry skier usually will carry, though nothing yet packs down as compact and light as the RAD (4 l pack size!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143568884" title="Petzl Positioning Lanyards by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8580/16143568884_0dd68a1709_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Positioning Lanyards" /></a></p>

<p>The Positioning lanyards are interesting. They aim to replace your Daisychain/ 120 cm sling with which you clip into the belay station. The Connect Adjust is made for sports climbing and mountaineering, while the Dual Connect Adjust is for Multi-Pitch routes and mountaineering. You attach them with a girth hitch to your tie-in point and then clip them out of the way until you need them. The magic happens when you arrive at the belay. With the locking carabiner (not included in the sets) you clip in to the belay, and then can easily adjust the length of the lanyard with the Adjust ascender. The lanyard is a dynamic rope which can reduce the force in case of a short fall. The Connect Adjust tips the scales at 125 g and the Dual Connect Adjust at 160 g, and will need one or two locking carabiners respectively. Knowing how much discussions we have in our climbing club about slings/ daisy chains/ <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/metolius-personal-anchor-system-black/?pid=81">Personal Anchor Systems</a> I reckon these will be hotly discussed, too. Personally I think they are great ideas which can make adjusting the length at the belay a lot easier and possibly safer, though they’re a tad heavier than normal systems (which in turn are a lot heavier than just tying in with a Clove hitch).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578285888" title="Petzl Headlamps by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7593/16578285888_8def09b8d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Headlamps" /></a></p>

<p>The headlamps line got a refresh, and many models got more power (= Lumen) and there’s also a hole bunch of new, fresh colours. The Tikkina, Tikka and Zipka headlamps went up to 80, 100 and 100 Luen respectively, the Tikka + and the Tikka XP went to 160 and 180 Lumen and the Tactikka + and Tactikka +RGB are headlamps in more toned down colours (all black, desert and camo) are for hunters and fishermen. Both come with 160 Lumen output and have different light options which allow for stealth and keeping your night vision.</p>

<h2 id="scarpa">Scarpa</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765869135" title="Scarpa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8568/16765869135_77370356c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://scarpa.it">Scarpa</a> goes wild with the Mojito Wild. The upper is made of spotted or plain color “cavallino” leather and the sole is the Spider Trek sole in all black. They’re probably going to be wildly popular, as I imagine the Mojito Patchwork will be, where every shoe will be totally unique as they are hand-sewed, with each square being different thus making every upper completely unique. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578271698" title="Scarpa Alien 2.0 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7632/16578271698_070961ef9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Alien 2.0" /></a></p>

<p>On the other hand you have the Alien 2.0. It is a race boot that employs the Tronic technology – a ski/ walk mechanism that automatically blocks the cuff to the shell simply by inserting the boot into the binding which should give you an advantage during a race when every second counts. It has an internal gaiter and a full carbon shell and cuff and it is closed with the Alien Fast Buckle Closure and the Boa Closure System. </p>

<h2 id="the-omm">The OMM</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143535204" title="The OMM Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8646/16143535204_c40b372fa7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The OMM Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System" /></a></p>

<p>I really like to stop by at the guys from <a href="https://theomm.com">The OMM</a> as there is always cool gear to be seen. Take the Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System above. Both garments are filled with Primaloft Gold and weigh 390 g for the Jacket and 235 g for the half-bag. The Half bag connects via push buttons on the inside of the jacket to it to create one versatile sleeping system that weighs in at 625 g. The half-bag also has a draw string to pull it tighter and packs a mighty fine 16 x 11 cm when its in your pack. This will be a hot item for runners and (S)UL Backpackers alike I think, it’s a great execution of the <em>“Multi-use”</em> idea.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16739960016" title="The OMM Rotor Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7637/16739960016_563fa0f204_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The OMM Rotor Vest" /></a></p>

<p>The Rotor Vest tips the scales at 135 g and is filled with Primaloft Gold in a 40 g weight variation. It packs rather small as I show above when you don’t need it, but when you put it on you’ll be toasty. It has a zipper so you can dump heat, a hem drawstring and the chest pocket also functions as the stuff sack. The Purple colour above also looks superb!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764773562" title="The OMM Kamleika Race Smock II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7621/16764773562_ee7d0c4cd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The OMM Kamleika Race Smock II" /></a></p>

<p>The Kamleika Race Smock II above isn’t new but the colour combo is and I’m totally in love with it. </p>

<h2 id="extreme-food">Extreme Food</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765859435" title="Extreme Food Booth by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7599/16765859435_dae4ba6952_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Extreme Food Booth" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.extreme-food.eu">Extreme Food</a> had one of the most fun booths on the show. It was simple, but the juxtaposition of fine porcelain, sterling cutlery and wine glasses with a fine course of freeze dried food in a bag was just great. The food is made in the UK from high quality natural ingredients with no artificial colourings or preservatives, and I have seen some UK tweeps already tasting it and finding it delicious. And what’s pretty awesome about these meals is that breakfasts, mains and desserts all have a superb weight-to-calorie ratio: A minimum of 4.8 kcal per g! That means each pouch weighs 102 g and gives you 500 kcal, which is pretty lightweight. Best of all, they’re <a href="http://www.extreme-food.eu/stockists.html">available already</a>!</p>

<h2 id="salomon">Salomon</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076604673" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8673/16076604673_f38509f1e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.salomon.com/">Salomon</a> had so much new stuff on the show that it’s hard to narrow it down. Lets start with the shoes, shoes at Salomon are always worth checking out, because they’re damn good.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510388979" title="Salomon X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8640/16510388979_1e088bcaa5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe" /></a></p>

<p>The X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe is the small sibling of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-4.html">Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX</a>, the mountaineering boot I already found awesome at the OutDoor 2014. It also employs a carbon midsole that is laterally stable but otherwise flexible, so should be great on these Approach shoes. They should arrive for test this week, so keep an eye on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for some tidbits on them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076575143" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8664/16076575143_c4dd257abc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074215914" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16074215914_94ffd2974a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>The Salomon S-Lab gear is probably some of the most advanced kit on the market and Kilian Jornet’s thoughts and feedback go into it. The S-Lab Wings above is a universal shoe for your trail runs that excels on the way down. This gives you more protection on the downhill and has a great fit in the heel thanks to the combination of Descent Control and the SensiFit-System, so that your foot doesn’t move to the front or sides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509153630" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16509153630_8f0df0d707_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510408099" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8623/16510408099_88b6153059_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>Shoes for less serious trailrunning were abound, too. The Speedcross Vario is the shoe for harder trails in dry weather, while the Speedcross Pro is great on wet and soft terrain (= MUD!). They’re built on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/salomon-speedcross-3.html">Speedcross 3</a> model with different soles and thus if you love the Speedcross 3 but need a shoe that’s better in soft and moist terrain, grab the Pro, or if you run usually in dry, desert-like terrain on hard trails the Vario will be for you. Why? Well, the Vario’s profile is larger and hence gives more friction on the ground, and there’s also more cushioning. The Pro on the other hand has the Mud &amp; Snow Contragrip sole, with smaller and more aggressive cleats. In the Pro your foot sits deeper in the shoe for a better ground feeling, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510422379" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8648/16510422379_2fff5b2640_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>The Carbon Ski enthusiast will be delighted by this combo. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696559455" title="Salomon Skitracer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8620/16696559455_15231a99b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon Skitracer" /></a></p>

<p>And the Freerider/ Powder enthusiast might consider a Skitracer the next time he drops into 3 meters of fresh pow and loses a ski. Because with the skitracer he’s able to find the ski again when it has hidden in that sweet powder.</p>

<h2 id="klttermusen">Klättermusen</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558580277" title="Klättermusen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8641/16558580277_eba0b13136_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Klättermusen" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://klattermusen.se/">Klättermusen</a> now entered the leguminous plants business. I think that’s rather smart, beans are after all super tasty and if you can make shell material out of them instead of oil - hey, that might mean some idiot oil company might not need to go and ruin the Arctic for us and the polar bears! The Nylon in their new insulation garments is made of Castor Seeds, which Toray and Klättermusen have developed together. At the moment the Nylon is made out of 60% plant-based raw materials but both companies work hard to bring this up to 100%. The plant-based nylon is supposed to have the same qualities as crude oil nylon, and at least trying them one and checking them out I wasn’t able to tell a difference, which is positive. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695481312" title="Klättermusen Castor Seeds Nylon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8595/16695481312_0f6ac6ec97_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen Castor Seeds Nylon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695203101" title="Klättermusen Bore 2.0 Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8583/16695203101_27fc10abf2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen Bore 2.0 Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Bore 2.0 Jacket that Malin models above packs 300 g of 800+ cuin goose down and Primaloft Silver ECO in the shoulders and back of the arms. Its shell is made from the new “Bean Nylon” and has a PFOA-free DWR finish on it, is made in a box wall construction and to minimize seams and cold spots the pockets have been moved in line with the side seams. It’s a super-toasty jacket that has a very nice cut, though the price tag of 500€ is pretty steep. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509118970" title="Klättermusen Frö 2.0 Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/16509118970_cfb512ab41_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Klättermusen Frö 2.0 Vest" /></a></p>

<p>The Frö 2.0 Vest is a midlayer piece for winter use with an Primaloft Silver Active insulation. At 250€ it’s more affordable than the Bore 2.0 Jacket but of course not nearly as warm! The high collar keeps chilly winds from your neck and throat, you can adjust the arm openings to be closed for keeping the warmth inside or open them for a bit of ventilation. The asymmetric zipper is perfect (all zippers should be asymmetric at the top in my opinion) and if you’re not a Vest-kind-guy-or-gal then you also can get the Frö 2.0 as a jacket. </p>

<h2 id="onoo">onoo</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764802102" title="onoo Jackets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/16764802102_60c5935639_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="onoo Jackets" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://onoo.de">onoo</a> is a young start-up from Munich which gathers to the urban cyclists. It was a bit of luck that I met them and I did like what they had to show. The three jackets all have a cycling specific fit and are from materials that are not worried if rain, dirt and abuse is coming its way. I had fun trying them on and speaking with the founder, and do agree with what he said: People know which jacket will suit them. I tried that one above on first and really like how it looks and feels, and while <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558587877/">this one</a> is pretty swell as well it’s maybe a tad less my style?! <a href="http://onoo.de/collection/">Check their collection</a> and pick the jacket which suits yours!</p>

<h2 id="vibram">Vibram</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695377681" title="Vibram Megagrip by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8681/16695377681_42a821081c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vibram Megagrip" /></a><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510345879" title="Vibram Megagrip by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/16510345879_0724a351fc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Vibram Megagrip" /></a></p>

<p>Getting a meeting at <a href="http://vibram.com">Vibram</a> has been on my agenda for a looooong time, so I was happy that after three years of trying I finally was deemed worthy. The big news at Vibram was their Megagrip sole, which has apparently pretty awesome grip on wet granite. At least they had a nice test parcours built up where you could try that out, but as I was already running around for six hours on the fair I was a bit shy in sharing my sweaty feet smell with others and so kept my shoes on. I’m sure some Megagrip shoe will appear at HiF HQ some day in the future, though, and as we have lots of granite in Finland and also no shortage of rain I will see if it performs as claimed =) If you too want to have Megagrip, you’re in luck: A whole bunch of shoe companies, from Scarpa to Salewa &amp; Arc’teryx, have used the soles in their 2015 shoes which are just hitting the stores, so go and get a pair!</p>

<h2 id="vaude">Vaude</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16145939523" title="Vaude Alphapro Bib Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8743/16145939523_9186a9abb6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude Alphapro Bib Pants" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.vaude.com">Vaude</a> is the “small” Family business which still turns out a lot of new gear. Not everything is ultralight though what Vaude really knows is environmentally friendly production. Lots of good stuff they are doing, and either I’m getting older or they’re getting younger in their styles because I did like quite a few pieces from them. The Alphapro Bib Pants above are Winter Cycling insulation Pants with Polartec® Alpha insulation in them and an Vaude Eco Finish DWR. Mesh suspenders keep the bib in place and a Men’s Advanced Cycling seat cushion ensures you can sit long in the saddle. It will weigh around 440 g and is an ISPO Award winner.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16579728219" title="Vaude Primasoft Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7627/16579728219_bb717ea6e7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude Primasoft Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Primasoft Jacket is a ISPO Gold Award winner and another cycling jacket. It combines Primaloft insulation materials with softshell materials in 3 different zones and is aimed at mountain bikers who like to ride in winter (Wait, aren’t they called Fatbikers?!). It has Primaloft Silver in the front and back, breathable inserts under the arms and in the back, a softshell material with a membrane in the front and kidney area and reflective details so you’re seen between dusk &amp; dawn and tips the scales at 485 g. </p>

<h2 id="hestra">Hestra</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578458280" title="Hestra Gloves Moon Mitt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8740/16578458280_8c9da35550_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hestra Gloves Moon Mitt" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://hestragloves.com">Hestra Gloves</a> make awesome gloves. The Moon Mitt above has a Primaloft insulation, a lambskin palm so you can pick up the kettle and has a liner, too. Toasty hands guaranteed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373244439" title="Hestra Gloves - Bark Powder Tanning by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7436/16373244439_7e472f0544_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Hestra Gloves - Bark Powder Tanning" /></a></p>

<p>New too is their vegetable tanned leather. It has been tanned using natural tannins such as bark powder. The method produces a supple leather with a unique brown colour and is the oldest known way of tanning. As the Press Release reads, <em>“The look and feel of a vegetable tanned leather is hard to beat and it ages naturally in a beautiful way.”</em> and yes, I agree. These vegetable tanned gloves were pretty, and the Abisko and Helags Junior Mitt above were very sweet indeed. </p>

<h2 id="madshus">Madshus</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764783932" title="Madshus IntelliGrip Skin by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8610/16764783932_451518694e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus IntelliGrip Skin" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://madshus.com">Madshus</a> has been making the IntelliGrip Skins, a special climbing skin for XC skis, since five years. Other than the full-length skins for alpine touring skis, IntelliGrip has the climbing skin only in the grip zone of the ski – just like wax or klister. The entire front part is made from polyethylene, the same material as the base itself, and since it worked so well, Madshus now integrates IntelliGrip into the base of skis. The first model is the Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic, a ski made for ambitious cross-country skiers eager to take advantage of a high performance waxing ski but who want to avoid the disadvantages of a conventional NoWax-ski. It
never requires the application of grip wax and avoids the typical disadvantages of NoWax-skis: the glide is much better than on any kind of fish-scale patterns and there is no rattling noise in an icy track.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143559784" title="Madshus Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic Ski by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7283/16143559784_7e473db14e_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Madshus Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic Ski" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143551434" title="Madshus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8677/16143551434_31fa052024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143540654" title="Madshus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7619/16143540654_56f8d9dda7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764801372" title="Madshus Glittertind BC Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7631/16764801372_d8c8563f68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus Glittertind BC Boot" /></a></p>

<p>More interesting for the ski-touring/ backcountry cross-country skiing enthusiast, the Backcountry skis from Madshus got a face-lift and now looks freshers as <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">my old ones</a>. Also the Glittertind BC Boot got a small update as the cuff is now a lot higher and is made of MemBrain® softshell material, which I think is a good development. </p>

<h2 id="millet">Millet</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765840625" title="Millet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7650/16765840625_8e13df02a9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Millet" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.millet.fr/en/">Millet</a> showcased their Triology Series, which is made for alpine pursuits in winter: Ice climbing, mountaineering, winter ascents, mixed climbing. Inspiration for the line comes from the winter ascents of the Eiger, Matterhorn and Grandes Jorasses North Faces of Eric Escoffiers in 1987. The garments are made of the most modern materials available and the “ingredients list” reads like a who-is-who: Polartec® Power Wool™, Polartec® Thermal Pro® Highloft, Tecnowool®, Gore-Tex® Pro, Gore-Tex® Helios Stretch, PrimaLoft®, Windstopper®, Schoeller® Wool Naturetec and K DRY™ - you see these garments will be made for cold, harsh weather and will keep you toasty and dry. Just climbing you need to yourself!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764693751" title="Millet Trident Winter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7598/16764693751_001e6b1e7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Millet Trident Winter" /></a></p>

<p>The Trident Winter Mid from Millet is an ISPO Gold Award winner and a lightweight winter boot for all you winter activities - from snow shoeing to glacier hikes, the Trident does it all and keeps your feet toasty thanks to a Primaloft insulation. It’s waterproof and breathable, too, with a DRYEDGE Membrane, and a Vibram sole to give you grip. It is crampon compatible and should be ideal for snowshoeing. </p>

<h2 id="trends">Trends</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509125580" title="Klättermusen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16509125580_3756bb738e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074209864" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8606/16074209864_6e71e31b71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16701345681" title="Montane by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8635/16701345681_59f8599c6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Montane" /></a></p>

<p>I think about half of the garment manufacturers I visited had these cuffs where the stretchy rim which keeps the sleeve in place was a few centimetres inside, and not at the end of the sleeve. This does make a lot of sense: It’s easier to put gloves on, or have “free” hands when the gloves are off but at the same time they bring the insulation point further down over the wrist and make the end of the sleeve straighter. The cuffs themselves also should get less dirty and it also might mean warmer wrists as he puffy layer covers them rather nicely. I think it’s a nice development and I’m curious to see if it is better than the traditional cuffs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558575287" title="Scarpa Alien 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8568/16558575287_a6c24294df_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Alien 2" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16592948772" title="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8572/16592948772_a6ec53441e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557739541" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8580/16557739541_ecb01807ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.boatechnology.com">Boa Closure System</a> has found its way at this ISPO into a lot of shoes, ski and mountain boots. I tried it on a few shoes and it was indeed very nice to get a good, tight fit and easy to “open” the shoe again. Kamik even used this technology in kid’s boots, which could make it easy for kids to close their shoes on their own. But also trailrunners, hikers, Cross Fitters and Skiers will be able to use the Boa technology, and I reckon it will increase even more in the coming year.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696398812" title="Ortovox Merino Fleece &amp; 260 Merino Ultra Net Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16696398812_bcc607ff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox Merino Fleece &amp; 260 Merino Ultra Net Hoody" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936837154" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7449/15936837154_b9fb3230a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a></p>

<p>Body Mapping isn’t really anything new, but quite a few companies have made some nice efforts with their garments. It just makes a lot of sense that some garments are windproof in the front and super breathable in the back, with stretchy sides for freedom of movement and warm, toasty hoods. There was, however, still a lack of aymmetric zippers in the face area. Lets hope a designer or two reads this and pleases me with asymmetric zippers in the 2016/ 2017 line-up!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557706791" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8660/16557706791_2827d34acb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937067704" title="Salewa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7421/15937067704_fac8cdc72c_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salewa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16372133760" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16372133760_09e8029623_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533491386" title="Haglöfs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7445/16533491386_7bcbb1c691_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs" /></a></p>

<p>The development of Urban (Outdoor) Styles and collections also is on the rise. As I’m myself am getting more interested in this area you might be able to see some more articles on this topic in the future, but for now: If you’d like to wear a Gore-Tex coat because it pours cats &amp; dogs, there’s a handful of outdoor companies which make those - and many more casual outdoor garments - in urban styles, so you don’t need to wear your bright green hardshell to the next client meeting. This will only be of interest to those who really need to look the part when they go to clients, or those who simply don’t want to wear their “outdoor uniform” in the city. Although, then fellow citizens might not think you’re an <a href="http://www.der-postillon.com/2014/12/mann-mit-jack-wolfskin-jacke.html">Extreme Mountaineer</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074253404" title="Petzl Sitta by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8682/16074253404_1884e493af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Sitta" /></a></p>

<h2 id="other-ispo-reports">Other ISPO Reports</h2>

<p>There was a host of other great bloggers at the ISPO and I was fortunate to meet many of them. Here’s in no particular order the outdoor bloggers who also wrote about the ISPO 2015: <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2015/02/weltgroesste-sportmesse-ispo-2015-bunt-wars.html">Outdoor Mädchen</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Wandervideoblog">Wander Video Blog</a>, <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/ispo-2015-munchen-trends-and-happenings/">Klimbing Korns</a>, <a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/outdoor-ausrustung/auf-der-ispo-2015/">Auf-den-Berg.de</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoor-blog.com/ispo-2015-eindruecke/">Outdoor Blog</a>, <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/tag/ispo/">Zwerg am Berg</a>, <a href="http://linaluftig.de/impressionen-von-der-ispo-2015/">Lina Luftig</a>, <a href="http://www.uptothetop.de/2015/02/06/ispo-2015-fuer-trailrunner/">Up to the Top</a>, <a href="http://www.wusaonthemountain.at/2015/02/ispo-2015-neuheiten-und-bewahrtes-ein.html">Wusa on the Mountain</a>, <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/ispo-2015-die-gipfelglueck-highlights/">Gipfel Glück</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoor-blog.org/ispo-2015-meine-erlebnisse/">Outdoor-Blog</a>, <a href="http://wandersuechtig.de/outdoor-news-neuheiten-aus-dem-outdoor-bereich/item/1056-die-ispo-2015-das-top-thema-war-die-nachhaltigkeit">Wandersüchtig</a> and <a href="http://www.airfreshing.com/messe/ispo">airfreshing.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696486635" title="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8565/16696486635_d884e3755a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ispo-2015-conclusions">ISPO 2015 Conclusions</h2>

<p><em>“Have you seen something new yet?”</em> / <em>“No, pretty much all the same just with a new marketing twist on it”</em></p>

<p>I had close to 40 meetings in three full days, so you get slightly blind to the stuff you’re being presented. Some stuff is really nice, innovative and cool, while other things are just the same old in a new colour. There are these companies who are honest about that fact, while others do as if they re-invent the wheel every year anew. This can get rather tiring if you get to see yet another synthetic/ Merino wool fabric mix that’s supposed to be the best thing yet and hasn’t been done before. Strangely I have been wearing that kind of garments since a while, though they didn’t have the XYZ Logo on it but were from ABC. Ah well, better take another sip of that good Espresso so I have enough processing power for the rest of the meeting(s).</p>

<p>Similar feelings I get with <em>“Our Responsible Down Standard”</em> being flavoured in yet another new name you haven’t heard of before and a totally fascinating story, which, thanks to the coffee you just had, happily doesn’t make you yawn. I’m not working for one company, so I get to see a bit more. I also read (BOOKS! Magazines! Imagine, death trees) and am curious, trying to question some things. So that’s why I don’t make somersaults if presented the best new thing for 2015 since, ähem, yeah, wait, since when exactly?</p>

<p>Four weeks after the ISPO closed it’s gates I’m hard-pressed to tell you what super-duper awesome new gear should be on your must-watch list - but to be honest, already on the fair I had difficulties with that, as the intro sentence maybe showed. Nevertheless, looking back through my <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157650454379737/">ISPO photos</a> and re-reading my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">ISPO 2015 posts</a> I can say that yes, there has been some interesting new outdoor gear on the show and my top five would be (in no particular order):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ortovox SAM 3D</li>
  <li>The DPS Tour 1 ski touring skis</li>
  <li>The Arc’teryx gloves that can be layered</li>
  <li>The Petzl Sitta harness</li>
  <li>The OMM “sleep system”</li>
</ul>

<p>Except the first one - the Ortovox SAM 3D - nothing utterly blew my mind, but as I wrote in my post about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">Ortovox</a> news and the SAM 3D, I think this is a superb invention which was - when you see it - so obvious that one can but wonder why something like this hasn’t been thought of before. It’s a very nice executed thing that brings the outdoors indoors and makes your time in the mountains more safe and fun. And that’s what it’s all about, in the end, isn’t it? </p>

<p>And if you liked The ISPO News articles, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> and then share it with your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, because <strong>sharing is caring</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16372182530" title="VAUDE by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7362/16372182530_d165a44357_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="VAUDE" /></a></p>

<p><em>Ah ja, wait: I was handed a prototype of a fluffy thing that my ideas and feedback has been going in to since last year and which I have tested sicne I’m back home. That is a pretty neat thing, which definitely should be on your list of “things to watch” if you like fluffy warm things.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXV]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxv.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-08T19:30:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Let us go forth, the teller of tales, and seize whatever prey the heart long for, and have no fear. Everything exists, everything is true, and the earth is only a little dust under our feet.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/1Efavk3">W.B. Yeats</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16528392290" title="Off/ Width by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8649/16528392290_24b2149f95_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Off/ Width" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Today is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Women%27s_Day">International Women’s Day</a>. </p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.sisugirls.org">SisuGirls</a>.</p>

<p>Helen is <a href="http://walkingwomad.com/2015/03/02/fighting-the-storm/">fighting the storm</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.therussianabroad.com/the-16-least-visited-countries-in-the-world/">16 least visited countries in the world</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://thenewnomads.com/?p=2149">The Story and the Lens: Why I Put My Camera and my Pencil Down</a>, a recommended read.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/05/opinion/nicholas-kristof-you-think-your-winter-was-rough.html">You Think Your Winter Was Rough</a>?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.wsj.com/articles/calvin-and-hobbes-americas-most-profound-comic-strip-1425656199?KEYWORDS=calvin+and+hobbes">‘Calvin and Hobbes’: America’s Most Profound Comic Strip</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin continues to make <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/fehler-beim-wandern/">a handful of errors when she goes hiking</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://adventureblog.nationalgeographic.com/2015/03/04/video-yosemite-climbers-tommy-caldwell-and-kevin-jorgeson-on-making-history/">Yosemite Climbers on Dealing with Their New-Found Fame</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ifyouhave.org">if you have</a> is a Japanese cottage that’s worth checking out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/blog/stories/brotherhood-searching-and-loss-in-the-chinese-karakoram">Brotherhood, searching and loss in the Chinese Karakoram</a>.</p>

<p>Angelica’s <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/03/06/news-termine-marz-2015/">News &amp; Dates for March 2015</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://eveningsends.com/climbing/the-return-of-climbing-porn/">The Return of Climbing Porn</a>.</p>

<p>Marmot Closeouts: <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=136727&amp;pw=73183">Soft Shells Up to 50% Off at RockCreek.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=313709&amp;pw=73183">Sign up for Campsaver.com’s newsletter and receive 15% off your first order!</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/winterausruestung/" title="Skitouren Ausrüstung kaufen bei Bergfreunde.de" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"><img src="http://www.bergfreunde-partner.de/banner/winter/728x90_skitouren.jpg" alt="Skitouren Ausrüstung kaufen bei Bergfreunde.de" border="0" /></a><img src="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=415&amp;cpid=1&amp;prid=1&amp;view=1" height="1" width="1" border="0" /></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Emma and her girl friends go <a href="http://emmaamerikassa.blogspot.fi/2015/03/ice-climbing-in-finland.html">ice climbing in Korouoma</a> - a recommended read!</p>

<p>Jill <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2015/03/finding-winter.html">finds winter</a>.</p>

<p>Stefanie goes on a <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/12-h-schneeschuhwandern-im-berchtesgadener-land/">12 h hardcore snowshoe hike</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.latvianalaskan.com/la-paz-to-puerto-vallarta/">La Paz to Puerto Vallarta</a>.</p>

<p>Dawn goes <a href="http://hikerdawn.blogspot.fi/2015/03/flying-with-friends-and-into-blue-hole.html">flying with friends</a>.</p>

<p>Christy is chasing rain on her <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2015/03/01/crag-peak/">Crag Peak Climb</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorwomensalliance.com/2015/03/skiing-silverton-mountain-colorado.html">Skiing Silverton’s Steeps</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AN5CDewKVdk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://gregboswell.co.uk/index.php/2015/03/01/one-of-your-five-a-day/">One Of Your Five-A-Day</a>.</p>

<p>Chris enjoys <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2015/03/a-wild-winters-day.html">a wild winter day</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://gypsybytrade.wordpress.com/2015/03/02/to-the-dead-sea-on-the-hlc-israel/">To the Dead Sea on the HLC, Israel</a>.</p>

<p>Willem is in <a href="https://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2015/03/01/in-te-anau-and-floating-to-the-end/">Te Anau and floats to the end</a>.</p>

<p>Jacob enjoys a <a href="http://urbanpackrafter.com/Weekend-on-Krokan">weekend on Krokån</a>.</p>

<p>Ryan’s <a href="http://ryangrayson.blogspot.fi/2015/03/last-miles-in-spain.html">last Miles in Spain</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16670558316" title="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16670558316_728f9a6fd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://vintageone.blogspot.fi/2015/03/gettin-fat.html">Gettin’ Fat</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2015/03/05/buchtipp-berggenuss-statt-hoehenangst/">How to not fear the fear of heights</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Amy tries some tasty <a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/2015/03/patagonia-provisions-organic-fruit-almond-bars.html">Patagonia Provisions Organic Fruit + Almond Bars</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://backpackingtechnology.com/knives/building-a-2-oz-knife-for-backpacking/">Building a 2 oz knife for backpacking</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoor-logs.de/patagonia-nano-puff-jacket/">Patagonia Nano Puff Jacket</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/test/the-north-face-chilkat-2-winterstiefel/">The North Face Chilkat II Review</a>.</p>

<p>Dave find’s the <a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2015/03/07/altra-lone-peak-1-5-half-brilliance-half-crap/">Altra Lone Peak 1.5 half brilliant, half crap</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Share this post with your friend &amp; Followers via <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> so that also they get to read the best outdoors stories of the past week!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/gaston-rebuffat-starlight-and-strom.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-06T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/gaston-rebuffat-starlight-and-strom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A book review of Gaston Rébuffat’s classic “Starlight &amp; Storm” - a <em>Must Read</em> for anyone just remotely interested in going outdoors.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16730495671" title="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8629/16730495671_870bcfb3e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I ordered Starlight &amp; Storm and a bunch of <em>“Classic Mountain Literature”</em> last autumn, probably after getting just another recommendation that it’s a superb book. Getting a book recommended several times sometimes makes me hesistant, but well, I love to read and as the mountains are far away at the moment reading about them is pretty much the next best thing (after browsing <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html">photography books</a> of the mountains). Rébuffat’s most well-known book is likely this one or <a href="http://amzn.to/1MbylRU">The Mont Blanc Massif: The Hundred Finest Routes</a>, and I think both books will be found on the bookshelf of a well-read mountaineer, alpinist or hill walker.</p>

<p>The book starts of with a short biography blurb on Rébuffat’s life which is followed by an introduction from Jon Krakauer, which is followed by yet another introduction, a Foreword and then finally you get to read Rébuffat’s words. Puh. Well, the good thing is that the good stuff starts right there with Rébuffat’ story of his ascent of the Grand Jorasses. This and the following chapters, where he descibes his adventures with friends of the great North Faces of the Alps is what really makes this book worth reading. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everything about the climbing of it was a joy, and as we climbed I seemed to understand the meaning of our exploit. It was not the increasing nearness of the summit,
or the climb in itself, that filled us with a quiet joy, but the feeling that mind and muscles were fulfilling their intended function. Somehow we were “in the right place.”
- Gaston Rébuffat, Starlight &amp; Storm, The North-east Face of Piz Badile</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16111754843" title="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8595/16111754843_88fc5b01dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm" /></a></p>

<p>I loved the accounts of how he tied up with clients and friends, how they spend nights on these big faces and enjoyed the starlight and peace of the night but welcomed the first rays of sunlight in the morning after a cold bivy, or how they turned around to come back another time because of bad weather. The Brotherhood of the Rope is strong in this book, and you feel that the people Rébuffat was climbing with were more than just climbing partners - they were brothers, sharing a single objective, living together on the rock, between the sky, ice, snow, wind and rain. </p>

<p>The chapters are short enough so that it’s easy to read them before going to bed or commuting to work in a week, and every Mountain chapter is accompanied by a Black-White photo of the mountain in question. What bothered me slightly was that the height and distance measurements where given in illogic feet, but apart from that I loved every part of the book. It’s a fascinating read, not just for alpinists and mountaineers, but also for people who wonder why one would climb a steep, inhospitable rock face. If you can not get to the mountains any time soon, I recommend you pick up this book and dream of having a bivy on one of these Northfaces! Buy the book at your local book shop or order it online from <a href="http://amzn.to/1NoHTMW">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1DRShVx">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/18WyyMF">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 02/2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/trekking-magazin-02-slash-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-05T16:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/trekking-magazin-02-slash-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>trekking Magazin 02/2015 is out today - grab a copy to read about my favourite hoodies, how to care for your outdoor jackets and plenty of great trip reports!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16697081426" title="trekking Magazin 02/ 2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8602/16697081426_79f9f6c488_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 02/ 2015" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I had a lot of fun writing for the second trekking Magazin issue of 2015. It included getting a lot of outdoor garments dirty and then learning about how to make them clean and functional again with the help of a bunch of outdoor detergents. Then I had fun taking photos for my hoody round-up and reviewing six hoodies, which should allow anyone who doesn’t have a hoody yet to find one for his needs! And finally I penned a story about my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/tatra-mountains/">Polish Tatra</a> trip which you already could read about on these digital pages in the past. As usually that’s not all: My colleagues went out sleeping in <em>Biwakschachteln</em> (bivouac booths) in the Alps, while others went went exploring the Swiss Engadin and hike to an volcano that was erupting. A lot of really inspiring trip reports which certainly will get out in the mood for spring hikes!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16721723161" title="trekking Magazin 02/ 2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8598/16721723161_dc4e00f3bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 02/ 2015" /></a></p>

<p>There’s still plenty more in there so pick up your copy today on the way home or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> to not miss any future issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-03T21:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Where there is gear, there will be gear nerds.</em> ISPO News 3.0 - enjoy this edition responsibly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695183181" title="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/16695183181_479778a57b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rab">Rab</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076720273" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/16076720273_ea53aff4b5_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://rab.uk.com">Rab</a> had a bunch of really excellent kit on display. The eye-catcher at the start of the booth was the new Expedition 8000 Suit which comes as a Jacket &amp; Salopettes combination (1.340 g and 850 g respectively) or as a suit (1.990 g). Kit for seriously high peaks or when the next ice age comes, but not for this rubbish winter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509074268" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16509074268_1bce8e8408_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>Kit that is more suitable for this winter is the new Rock/ Lifestyle collection which comes with a mighty fine Rab hoody, cool shirts and nice trousers for climbing and chilling at the crag. Women and men will be equally able to dress up in these garments, which already now are very popular with the Rab athletes. The Headwall Hoody above (539 g) feels great, but I liked even more the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076700173/">Elevation Pull-On</a> which had a really nice hood design. The Rockover Pant (305 g) could also become popular with hikers, but it’s made for climbing and allows for freedom of movement.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695361681" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8639/16695361681_19203731d9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>But lets move on to more technical garments, and there was no shortage of these. A big news was that Rab now uses Fluorocarbon-free Hydrophobic Down in all their down garments, which is good news for those of us who use their down garments in cold &amp; wet environments. I tried on a handful of them and they had the Rab-typical great, alpine fit. Many down-garments also now get a body-mapping construction with using different baffles constructions in different areas, like the Electron Jacket pictured above (470 g) which has a Pertex Endurance shell and has Stitch-through Midi baffles in the torso, back and hood and smaller Stitch-through Mini baffles on the side and arms - if you look closely you can see the different baffle sizes in the photo. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16670728016" title="Rab Paradox Pull-On by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16670728016_2d12aeb551_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab Paradox Pull-On" /></a></p>

<p>But it ain’t all down. The Paradox Pull-On uses Polartec® Alpha™ insulation  with a super-stretchy lining and shell. A deep zipper helps with dumping heat on fast ascents or runs, and if you don’t need it the 360 g top packs away small. This was a really nice piece and would be great as a autumn layering piece or on its own on cool days.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509065258" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16509065258_987eed6411_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695337601" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/16695337601_74ef7c6005_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509251460" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8676/16509251460_80916e78a3_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076708763" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8591/16076708763_f2d4130b34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>There was a bunch more really innovative backpacking/ hillwalking/ climbing/ mountaineering &amp; lifestyle garments to be seen, so you can start saving your $€£ for the coming winter because you’ll want to pick up some of these.</p>

<h2 id="dps-skis">DPS Skis</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16670544676" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8617/16670544676_b52b5f54f1_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a></p>

<p>What I love about these trade fairs is meeting the people who love what they can do with their products. At <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com">DPS Skis</a> I asked my contact which of these he’s riding. <em>“I love the <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com/en/skis/all-mountain-mixed-snow/wailer-99.html">Wailer 99</a> with <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/dynafit-tlt-radical-st2-anniversary-touring-binding-90mm/?pid=81">Dynafit Radical bindings</a> and a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/la-sportiva-syborg-tourenskischuhe/">La Sportiva Syborg</a> boot”</em> he told me, and then and there I knew that we’d get along just fine! That’s a pretty awesome and lightweight setup, and best of all: You too could get it! Because unlike other manufacturers DPS Skis sells their brand-new and ISPO Award winning <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com/en/skis.html">Tour 1 Skis</a> already now. So the Tour 1 are lightweight (1.350 g for the 176 cm Wailer 99!) backcountry touring skis which also perform very nicely on the way down the mountain. Because you shouldn’t invest energy in long tours if you can not enjoy the descent!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076525313" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16076525313_102f653bcf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509082860" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16509082860_2ee66fff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a></p>

<h2 id="patagonia">Patagonia</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695584932" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8650/16695584932_5080e45b2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a> Backcountry Experience collection is divided into five lines: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Lift Access, for quick-strike, done-in-a-day missions</li>
  <li>Free Tour, for more committing powder missions that require traveling a little deeper into the backcountry</li>
  <li>Steeps, for descents extreme enough to require technical climbing skills</li>
  <li>Alpine Touring, for traveling deep and extensively through the snow-covered backcountry</li>
  <li>Approach, for when climbing is the primary objective and skis are necessary tools for access</li>
</ul>

<p>These lines have been developed in cooperation of the Snow and Alpine Teams from Patagonia, and what I saw at the fair looked really swell. Technical fabrics, functional fit and design, all made with the Patagonia-typical environmental thoughts in mind. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076667093" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8588/16076667093_4063b2fdd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia" /></a></p>

<p>Another big news is the completely renewed baselayer line-up. The collection is structured into four categories: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Daily, for the stuff you wear each day to the office or grocery shopping by bike in winter</li>
  <li>Lightweight, having the lightest-weight, fastest-drying and best-wicking baselayers</li>
  <li>Midweight, being the most versatile baselayer with the greatest comfort range</li>
  <li>Thermal Weight, the warmest, most breathable baselayer with minimal bulk</li>
</ul>

<p>This is applicable to both the Merino and Capilene® baselayers. Capilene® got an updated fabric that is made from recycled Polyester with better odour control and wicking. The fit has been made the “Slim Fit” across the last three categories (Lightweight, Midweight, Thermal Weight) and everything is recyclable through the Common Threads recycling programme. The baselayers felt soft and nice to the touch, but of course only wearing them one could start to make an opinion on them. The Merino line is made from Patagonian wool and has very nice stripe designs and also felt great. And as you can see above - the whole packaging has been renewed. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510473569" title="Patagonia Denim by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8658/16510473569_ae4d2de148_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Denim" /></a></p>

<p>And then there are Jeans. I haven’t worn a jeans in probably five years but it’s still the de-facto pants for many people. I know that Jeans/ Denim manufacturing is a filthy business, so it’s good to see that Patagonia is setting out to change that. Patagonia® Denim uses 100% organic cotton grown without polluting fertilizers, poisonous pesticides or herbicides. A low-impact dyeing process enables them to dramatically reduce water, energy and chemical use and produce less carbon dioxide. Patagonia also never distress their denim with harsh chemicals or other methods. And the garments are Fair Trade Certified™ for sewing, which makes Patagonia Denim the way denim should be made. Here you can read more about the <a href="http://www.google.fi/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;ved=0CCAQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.iswa.org%2Findex.php%3FeID%3Dtx_iswaknowledgebase_download%26documentUid%3D3184&amp;ei=RW71VPe1D-LXyQOetoDACA&amp;usg=AFQjCNHqwl6f-JkE2wcteEE4OLckX1xvWA&amp;sig2=PCCiF7jMnwRhXQBpOAYj9A&amp;bvm=bv.87269000,d.bGQ">Environmental impact of denim product</a>.</p>

<h2 id="marmot">Marmot</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16489359707" title="Marmot Cerro Torre Jacket, Quasar Hoody &amp; Alpinist Bib by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/16489359707_25edc395ba_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Marmot Cerro Torre Jacket, Quasar Hoody &amp; Alpinist Bib" /></a></p>

<p>The Cerro Torre Jacket from <a href="http://marmot.de">Marmot</a> got a full technical revamp and now promises even better performance than its predecessor. Made from the new 3-layer Gore-Tex® C-Knit fabric the jacket is super-light and stays durably waterproof and windproof. The C-Knit gives it a soft feel and an improved breathability rating, which means even better wear comfort. A snug fitting hood, pockets positioned above the level of a backpack waist belt or climbing harness, extra-long Pit-Zips and a two-way front zipper make this a versatile jacket that’s equally well-suited for hiking, trekking, all mountain skiing and freeriding.</p>

<h2 id="lundhags">Lundhags</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510378169" title="Lundhags Cobbler Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8680/16510378169_b0dc6473cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lundhags Cobbler Boot" /></a></p>

<p>It was my first visit at <a href="http://lundhags.se">Lundhags</a> and it was very nice. I got a pair of their superb <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/lundhags-guide-bc-backcountry-skischuhe/">Guide BC Boots</a> last year for Nordic Touring Skating and skiing and really like them, so it was good to see more of their gear. The big news at the Swedish company was their introduction of casual footwear. I like the look of the Cobbler Boot above, which has a mid height shaft that’s very flexible. I would have liked a more minimalist sole myself, but I reckon the majority of people will like it just as it is - after all, The Beatles wore shoes like this! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509112040" title="Lundhags Termik Jacket and Termik W&#x27;s Anorak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8674/16509112040_77a9bb082c_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Lundhags Termik Jacket and Termik W&#x27;s Anorak" /></a></p>

<p>The Termik Jacket and Termik W’s Anorak above are made of Lundhags Polycotton material that has a parafin wax layer. The material has a 16.000 g/ m2/ 24h breathability rating (minimum) and a 20.000 mm hydrostatic head. The Anorak has a separate inner pocket in the large chest pocket, and a long zipper for easy entry/ exit as well as ventilation. It’s a classic-looking garment made of modern fabrics (well, Polycotton has been around a bit under other names) that surely will find a lot of fans.</p>

<h2 id="ortovox">Ortovox</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16671498646" title="Ortovox SAM 3D by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8598/16671498646_6178105b7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox SAM 3D" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://ortovox.com">Ortovox</a> is a company I also really like. Creative &amp; innovative products, great materials and colours, friendly and passionate people - what’s not to like? Take the <a href="http://www.ortovox.com/accessories/e_329113">SAM 3D mountain model</a>: It’s a 3D mountain model for avalanche education that they created after a Mountain Guide contacted them and said <em>“Look, I have an idea”</em>. This model allows you to recognize and interpret topography, understand contour lines, lets you estimate slope steepness and and and. It comes with a map, a set of water-based markers, a handbook and a Clinometer. This is such an awesome and much needed product that one can actually just winder: Why hasn’t anyone thought of this before? That’s what the ISPO also thought and made it a Gold Winner!</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Kbok5Ie4Z4o" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696398812" title="Ortovox Merino Fleece by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16696398812_bcc607ff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox Merino Fleece" /></a></p>

<p>Alright, that’s not all though. The Merino Fleece Plus Jacket on the left use 350 g/ m2 of wool fleece and is mighty warm and looks stylish, too! Then there’s the Merino Ultra Net Hoody on the right above is a finely woven Merino shell and a large-mesh lining this should be bomber warm in really cold weather as it will trap a lot of air next too skin. The hoody will tip the scales at 300 g and because I love hoodies this one is high on my list of <em>“Wanna try!”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077491093" title="Ortovox Piz Palü Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8622/16077491093_50ab54c97a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Ortovox Piz Palü Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Piz Palü Jacket rounds out the layering system from Ortovox and is a super-technical jacket. It uses Pertex Microlight, schoeller naturetec, Swiss Wool and Merino wool to create one athletic touring jacket. It weighs 424 g and has a body-mapping construction which places the mentioned materials there where they make the most sense.</p>

<h2 id="black-diamond">Black Diamond</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509300620" title="Black Diamond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/16509300620_330b2ab9c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond" /></a></p>

<p>Since <a href="http://eu.blackdiamondequipment.com/en/homepage">Black Diamond</a> entered the apparel market they have been going from strength to strength, refining each season their line and making the garments better and better. This kind of approach is rewarded, and so their Misson Pants with Pieps Pocket won an ISPO Gold Award. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509299980" title="Black Diamond Viper Ice Tool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8599/16509299980_c69edd9bde_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Viper Ice Tool" /></a></p>

<p>I did like the Viper Ice Tool which weighs 570 g with the Hammer or 595 g with the Adze and has an adjustable FlickLock Pommel - which, yes, employs the same FlickLock system as you already know it from BD Poles. It has a Titan pick and the head is modular, so on days where you need two Hammers or Adzes you can leave the other one at home (saving 80 g/ 105 g respectively, which yes, means, the “naked” tool weighs 490 g). This makes it the lightest BD ice tool yet, and being made from hydroformed aluminium these will last, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695655422" title="Black Diamond Vapor Carbon 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8565/16695655422_8091aeb8cd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Vapor Carbon 1" /></a></p>

<p>The Vapor Carbon 1 poles weigh 310 g for the pair which makes it one of the lightest ski poles on the market. It’s a one-piece pole that’s made for ski-mountaineering - but that shouldn’t hinder the dedicated gram-weenie to use them for backpacking and pitching his shelter! Available in lengths of 115 to 145 cm in 10 cm steps they can be equipped with Powder Baskets and Freeride Baskets.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696687575" title="Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 32 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8634/16696687575_5c7ae756d5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 32" /></a></p>

<p>The Dawn Patrol 32 is a mid-sized lightweight ski pack that can accommodate either skis or a snowboard and is AvaLung-Ready. The AvaLung Element is a streamlined, modular AvaLung unit that attaches to AvaLung-Ready packs and is a lightweight, affordable avalanche safety technology that significantly increases your fresh air supply in the event of a burial. The <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-avalung-brg/?pid=81">AvaLung</a> almost triples the air supply when you’re in an avalanche and at 100€ it is substantially cheaper than ABS packs et al.</p>

<h2 id="haglfs">Haglöfs</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939316493" title="Haglöfs Hellner Gear by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7407/15939316493_bcfe6cd8b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs Hellner Gear" /></a></p>

<p>The new gear from <a href="http://www.haglofs.com/">Haglöfs</a> was interesting. The skiing gear developed with Marcus Hellner will delight the cross-country readers. Lots of Windstopper garments which keep cold wind out but are highly breathable, with body-mapping constructions and smart details like magnet closures. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373587917" title="Haglöfs Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/16373587917_55fcaed82a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket won an ISPO Gold Award and is a belaying jacket that’s mighty warm - too hot for me to wear indoors, so I quickly put it off again. Filled with QuadFusion™ Pro that has a windproof and waterproof membrane it keeps in the warm air generated by the body but is breathable enough to not be uncomfortable. The fit is to be worn over a Hardshell/ Softshell which is in my opinion also a great way to wear your insulation jacket during hiking/ skiing breaks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939328973" title="Haglöfs Mountain Pro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7454/15939328973_0e1627983c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs Mountain Pro" /></a></p>

<p>The Mountain Pro will only be available for Mountain Guides and SAR Employees - people who work in the mountains. Developed in cooperation with mountain professionals and the Swiss Alpine Rescue the garments are super burly and consists of the ROC Rescue Jacket, BARRIER Rescue Jacket, ROC Rescue Pants and ROC Rescue 40 backpack and are made to be
functional twelve months a year and be adaptable, not just to different weather conditions and temperatures, but also to different types of rescue missions. </p>

<h2 id="montane">Montane</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16080317554" title="Montane Primino Baselayer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8562/16080317554_d85f3c7c29_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Primino Baselayer" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.montane.co.uk">Montane</a>’s big news were the new Primino Baselayers, which combine Primaloft® yarns with Merino wool. These baselayers come 220 g and 140 g weights, with gloves, long johns and boxer shorts accompanying the tops. The idea is that the Merino wool draws vapour sweat away from the body whilst the Primaloft® yarns wick liquid sweat across the outer surface, allowing it to dry quickly. I got one here and will put it to the test so expect an update on them before next winter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16495352457" title="Montane Black Ice 2.0 Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8564/16495352457_026e758e44_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Black Ice 2.0 Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Black Ice 2.0 Jacket is Montane’s warmest down jacket and weighs 679 g in Size M. It is filled with 250 g of Primaloft Gold Insulation Down Blend and has a Freeflow Ultralite 38 g/m2 shell. The torso has a Boxwall construction while the sleeves have a Stitch-through construction. The hood has a wired peak and fits over a helmet. Toasty warm it was!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16701343571" title="Montane Hi-Q Luxe Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16701343571_986c395d26_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Hi-Q Luxe Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>Equally warm was the Hi-Q Luxe Jacket, which is filled with synthetic Primaloft Gold Luxe. Primaloft Gold Luxe is a new twist on the Thermoball technology of The North Face (which also was developed by Primaloft) I feel, which should be just like down but keeps you warm even when wet (unlike normal down, which collapses). The Hi-Q Luxe tips the scale at 575 g in Size M so isn’t too light, but it packs small and would make a good layering piece on cold days - but thanks to the Pertex Quantum shell you also can wear it on its own!</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXIV]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxiv.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-01T20:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-week-in-review-clxxxxiv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Whenever I see an adult on a bicycle, I have hope for the human race.”</em>
- <a href="http://amzn.to/1N4Sg8w">H.G. Wells</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/gabrielamadeus/9100832215" title="Expansive view of Fort Rock and our route through the basin. by Gabriel Amadeus, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2887/9100832215_520f0a7bfc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="678" alt="Expansive view of Fort Rock and our route through the basin." /></a>
©<a href="http://limberlost.co">Gabriel Amadeus</a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.wired.com/2015/02/voormi-core-technology/">new Fabric Tech that could be Outerwear’s Biggest Advance in 40 Years</a>.</p>

<p>When <a href="http://www.tetongravity.com/story/snowboard/ski-bums-grow-up.-then-they-start-kickass-businesses">Ski Bums grow up they start great businesses</a>.</p>

<p>Toni gets ready to race <a href="http://www.tonilund.fi/2015/02/iditarod.html">Iditarod</a> - good success mate!</p>

<p>The <a href="http://simon-willis.blogspot.fi/2015/03/podcast-first-to-kayak-all-scotlands.html">first person to Kayak to all of Scotland’s Islands Podcast</a>.</p>

<p>Neil listed the <a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/win-stuff-online-competitions-for-hikers-march-2015/">Online Competitions for Hikers in March 2015</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=101189&amp;pw=73183">Join Today and get a REI Membership - A lifetime membership at REI is just $20</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/what-is-fatigue">What is fatigue</a>? =&gt; <a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/fitness/bodywork/the-fit-list/Train-Your-Brain-to-Feel-Less-Fatigued.html">The Stranger-Than-Fiction Way to Cheat Fatigue</a>.</p>

<p>Casey on how he <a href="http://greenecasey.blogspot.fi/2015/02/how-i-design-adventure.html">designs Adventure</a>.</p>

<p>Vroni has a chat with Walker Ferguson, <a href="http://www.airfreshing.com/portrait-patagonia-field-testing-manager-walker-ferguson-traumberuf-outdoor-tester-interview.html">Field Testing Manager</a> for <a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://universalklister.blogspot.fi/2015/02/compromise-fine-art-of-giving-and.html">The fine art of giving and taking from an advocates perspective</a>.</p>

<p>Haglöfs is searching for <a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/outdoor-ausrustung/moechtest-du-eine-neue-outdoorjacke-testen/">Testers for a new Insulation Jacket</a>.</p>

<p>Check the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1328&amp;pw=73183">Men’s Clothing Outlet at Backcountry and Save Up to 70%</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/ski-ausruestung/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc&amp;&amp;">Get skis, boots and bindings up to 50% off at Bergfreunde</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/?utm_source=PTID13002584"><img src="http://ad.globetrotter-partnerprogramm.de/1-globetrotter-728x90.gif" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Stefanie reviews the <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/buchtipp-das-schmankerlbuch/">Schmankerlbuch - Where Bavaria Tastes Best</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/blog/stories/what-does-an-alpinist-eat">What does an Alpinist eat</a>?</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.fastpacking.de/wordpress/icebreaker-helix-ls-modische-merino-jacke-mit-funktion/">Icebreaker Helix LS Review</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Jake reviews the <a href="http://www.barefootjake.com/2015/02/bobcat-kovea-stove-review.html">Bobcat Kovea Stove</a>.</p>

<p>Veit tests <a href="http://www.airfreshing.com/testbericht-mawaii-wintercare-face-hands-lips-hautschutz-kosmetik-hautpflege-wintersport.html">mawaii WinterCare for Face, Hands &amp; Lips</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Amy on <a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/2015/02/pizza-in-a-pouch-the-squeezable-real-food-trend.html">the Squeezable Real Food Trend</a>.</p>

<p>Axel has reviwed the <a href="http://outdoorseite.de/zajo-alpamayo-hardshelljacke/">Zajo Alpamayo Hardshell Jacket</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Shane’s <a href="http://www.shanecycles.com/packing-list-3-weeks-bikepacking-in-spain/">Packing list 3 weeks bikepacking in Spain</a>.</p>

<p>John takes a look at the <a href="http://hikelighter.com/2015/02/28/zpacks-duplex-tent-2/">ZPacks Duplex Tent</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qzTwXGO9Km4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2015/02/rappafossen.html">Rappafossen</a>. [Finnish]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.minimallyminimal.com/blog/portland-mm-travel-guide-15">Portland MM Travel Guide</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin hikes the <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/winterwandern-baumgartenschneid/">Baumgartenschneid</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Heather goes <a href="http://heatherclimbs.com/2015/02/24/all-in/">all in</a>.</p>

<p>Gerald is <a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/02/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-14.html">snowed in</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://talusfield.net/blog/2015/2/12/climbing-finger-rock-santa-catalina-mountains">Climbing Finger Rock, Santa Catalina Mountains</a>.</p>

<p>The Beuteltiere are having <a href="http://www.beuteltiere.org/2015/02/beuteltiere-im-gipfelfieber.html">Summit Fever</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://nickbullock-climber.co.uk/2015/02/27/shine-on/">Shine On</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://climbjapan.blogspot.fi/2015/02/mitsutoge-ice-climbing-shijuhataki-sawa.html">Ice-climbing – Shijuhataki-sawa</a>.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FgjoFv33kKk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://outlivingblog.wordpress.com/2015/02/23/more-fold-ramblin/">More Fold ramblin</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2015/02/23/lynxes-dont-grocery-shop-lidl/">Lynxes dont shop at Lidl</a>.</p>

<p>Roger hikes the <a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/2015/02/21/e1-fjaras-to-varberg/">E1 in Sweden from Fjärås to Varberg</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cumbriafellraven.blogspot.fi/2015/02/estanhets-deth-port-to-port-de-ratera.html">Estanhets deth Port to Port de Ratera de Colomers</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.hochtourist.at/skitour-piz-buin/">Piz Buin 2.0</a>.</p>

<p>A snowshoe hike on the <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/touren/schneewanderung-auf-dem-kindelsbergpfad-im-siegerland-wittgenstein/">Kindelsbergpfad in Siegerland-Wittgenstein</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Raf takes a step to far an hence wrote this <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2015/02/accident-report-one-step-far/">Accident Report</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2015/02/24/hunting-divine-valley-part-2/">Hunting divine valley</a>.</p>

<p>Jonathan is <a href="http://www.jstarinorbit.com/2015/02/in-transit.html">in Transit</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then I’d be grateful if you share this post with your friend &amp; Followers via <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> so that also they get to read the best the digital outdoors had to offer in the past week.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=42809&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/42809/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Joe Grant, Mountain Runner]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/mountain-people-joe-grant.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T21:05:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/mountain-people-joe-grant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Running is a wonderful activity to enjoy the outdoors, push yourself and stay fit. Joe Grant is an Ultrarunner who has run in the Copper Canyon, on the Annapurna trail and around Mont Blanc. Why he loves to run, especially in the mountains and on long Ultras races, you read in this <em>Mountain People interview</em>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16457882128" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8660/16457882128_e0db3343aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Joe, thanks for taking the time to answer my questions =) Could you please briefly introduce yourself and tell us what you do?</strong></p>

<p>I have a pretty eclectic background having studied international management with a focus on nonprofit work. I worked in nonprofits for several years after college, but started my own business <a href="http://alpine-works.com">Alpine Works</a> about 4 years ago which encompasses my work as a mountain runner, coach, writer and photographer. I’ve been running consistently for about 10 years and started racing Ultras 7 years ago. </p>

<p><strong>You have been changing location often, living a semi-nomadic life. Do you foresee that you’ll continue to be a nomad, living where you like it, or that you settle down once you maybe have found a place you want to call home?</strong></p>

<p>I travel a lot, mainly for races, but own a home in Gold Hill, Colorado just outside of Boulder. I was born in the UK, grew up in France and have been living in the US on and off for the past 10 years. Most of my travel is related to work and I call Colorado home.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16459281759" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8576/16459281759_2ca7c495f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Well, lets move away from standing still and take a run. You’ve run across the globe - is there a trail that really stands out for you?</strong></p>

<p>I’m partial to the San Juan mountains in Southern Colorado, but it’s hard to really pin point one particular trail that really stands out. Any trail in a unique, wild environment is appealing to me. </p>

<p><strong>And is there a trail that you still want to run?</strong></p>

<p>I’d like to spend more time in Alaska and the Himalayas. The grandeur of both places is very inspiring to  me. </p>

<p><strong>Tell us please how you plan for a race like the one you ran in Costa Rica - how does it start, what all needs to be done before you leave home?</strong></p>

<p>Well, <a href="http://alpine-works.com/2015/02/the-coastal-challenge/">The Coastal Challenge</a> is a tough race to prepare in Colorado in the winter.  I did my best to get into reasonable shape mainly skiing and biking and some running to get the legs moving a bit. My specific preparation was far from ideal. Since the race transports all of your gear from camp to camp, I did pack judiciously to have enough food, clean clothes and books to really recover well between stages. Recovery during the event is a key piece to stage racing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16619534966" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8622/16619534966_a3e484fe4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Do you have a FKT Attempt planned this year?</strong></p>

<p>I have a quite a few FKTs I want to attempt such as Nolan’s 14 or The Bob Graham Round to name a few, but the race calendar this year is pretty full for me to fit any of these into the season. After The Coastal Challenge, I’ll be racing TransGrancanaria, Ultra Fiord 100 in Patagonia, Western States 100 and UTMB.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16644042711" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8620/16644042711_bec1f586b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Besides running you also like ski-mountaineering, fastpacking and riding a Fatbike as I saw on your <a href="https://instagram.com/alpineworks/">Instagram</a> stream. Are these 100% pleasure or also part of your training?</strong></p>

<p>Both. I enjoy doing self-propelled activities in the mountains and in the winter for example skiing is most of the time a much more suited activity to where I live than running. All these activities do help my running though whether for strength, endurance or just taking a break from the pounding. Fastpacking is a great way to really immerse myself in nature for more extended periods of time. </p>

<p><strong>Any other past-times in the outdoors that you enjoy?</strong></p>

<p>I like climbing and scrambling a lot, often as an extension of running in the mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16644452922" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8614/16644452922_83e6dd8995_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Trailrunning is a trend sport across the globe right now and though the majority of trailrunners enjoy it because they can be running outside in the forests &amp; mountains only a small percentage also participates in races. Do you think taking part in a race should be on every trailrunners list? If so, what’s a good start?</strong></p>

<p>I think runners should do whatever motivates and inspires them. Most races have a great community aspect and provide a relatively safe environment to push oneself. Races can be limiting too because of permitting and other restriction so it’s sometimes better to just create your own adventure. I’d suggest choosing a race that inspires you, but that you can also adequately prepare for so I can enjoy your time.  </p>

<p><strong>As a coach you help runners to train for a race or event. If a complete novice runner would ask you for (free) advice on training, nutrition and gear, which three tips would you give him?</strong></p>

<p>Be consistent, eat real food and keep it simple.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16619535406" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/16619535406_3e0351394f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What does your own training at home look like?</strong></p>

<p>During the running season, I run an average of 2-3 hours a day in the mountains with longer runs once of twice a week that are more specific to the race I’m preparing. In the winter I don’t run as much, but stay in shape skiing, biking and climbing.  </p>

<p><strong>Do you pursue a special diet?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t. I try to eat mainly whole, organic foods. My wife and I cook most of our meals. We also like eating out and don’t worry about occasional indulgences. </p>

<p><strong>Joe, thank you so much for taking the time to answer my questions. Any parting words?</strong></p>

<p>Thank you very much for featuring me on your site.</p>

<p><em>Joe writes at <a href="http://alpine-works.com">Alpine Works</a> and has a column at <a href="http://www.irunfar.com/category/columns/from-my-doorstep">iRunFar</a>. He is sponsored by <a href="http://www.inov-8.com/">inov-8</a>, <a href="http://arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a>, <a href="http://www.buffwear.com">Buff</a>, <a href="http://www.drymaxsocks.com">Drymax</a>, <a href="http://www.julbousa.com">Julbo</a> and <a href="http://www.tailwindnutrition.com">Tailwind Nutrition</a>. You can follow him on <a href="https://twitter.com/@AlpineWorks">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Alpine-Works/188901357810995">Facebook</a>.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bikepacking Framebag Manufacturer List]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-24T18:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fatbikes, Mountain Bikes, 29er, Road Bikes and Bikepacking go hand-in-hand. So that you are ready for your next bikepacking adventure and don’t need to rely on old panniers which make riding Singletrack simply not fun, here’s an up-to-date list of people and companies which produce framebags.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410128705" title="Dawn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/10410128705_2ce65c655f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Dawn" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Framebags allow you to explore trails and tracks with all your gear packed in a lightweight, streamlined and rack-less method, without any panniers which hang off the back and front wheels and which make navigating singletrail tracks not pleasueable - if not impossible. With your camping gear in framebags - which covers handelbar bags, seatbags, top tube bags and (half) frame bags - you have a possibility to carry all your gear on your bike and are able to explore trails far off the beaten track, with your bike behaving as responsive and ergonomic as usual. </p>

<p>But not just for off-road travel by bike framebags are a smart choice, also for cycle-touring and commuting a half frame bag and top tube bag are great choices to store essential gear on the go. You easily can carry a pump, patch kit and more in a half frame bag, and the top tube bag stores snacks, your camera and phone with easy access during your ride. Both my bikes sport frame bags and I wouldn’t want to miss them on bikepacking adventures and commutes to town.</p>

<p>For easier reference I sorted the makers into locations - Europe, North America and the rest of the world. Know someone who should be on this list? <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Email me</a>.</p>

<h1 id="north-american-makers">North American Makers</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16439818958" title="Porcelain Rocket Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8573/16439818958_87688c7c3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="620" alt="Porcelain Rocket Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="revelate-designs">Revelate Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.revelatedesigns.com">Revelate Designs</a> is probably the first framebag maker which many come across. Eric and his team have been making framebags in Alaska since 2007 and nowadays also make framebags for Salsa and other bike companies. They produce the whole setup and also offer custom work. You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/11/interview-eric-parsons-from-revelate-designs.html">read my interview with Eric here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="porcelain-rocket">Porcelain Rocket</h2>

<p>I own a complete set of <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com">Porcelain Rocket</a> Framebags for my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/driving-in-the-mud-rain.html">29er</a> and love them. Scott and his team make a lot of custom bags and also have many great standard bags which will fit your bike. You can get your whole setup from PR as well as Salsa Anything Cage Bags. <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/interview-scott-felter-of-porcelain-rocket.html">Read the interview with Scott here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bedrock-bags">Bedrock Bags</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.bedrockbags.com">Bedrock Bags</a> are from Colorado. All bags are custom order and you can get a whole set from them.</p>

<h2 id="becker-gear">Becker Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.beckergear.com">Becker Gear</a> is another Alaskan framebag maker that offers custom work.</p>

<h2 id="jpaks">J.Paks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jpaks.com">J.Paks</a> packs are made in Denver, Colorado. They have besides the standard flavours of framebags also many special versions available, like an insulated stash bag.</p>

<h2 id="nuclear-sunrise-stitchworks">Nuclear Sunrise Stitchworks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nukesunrise.com">Nuclear Sunrise Stitchworks</a> packs are made in El Paso, Texas. Get every framebag possiblity from them.</p>

<h2 id="oveja-negra">Oveja Negra</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.ovejanegrathreadworks.com/">Oveja Negra</a> offers the whole bikepacking setup, from stock half frame bags to full custom bags. Based in Salida, Colorado.</p>

<h2 id="wanderlust">Wanderlust</h2>

<p><a href="http://wanderlust-gear.com">Wanderlust</a> is the former <a href="http://hansbagworks.com">Hans Bagworks</a> and you can get Framebags and Handlebar bags as well as some accessories from them. They’re based in Harrisonburg, Virginia.</p>

<h2 id="rogue-panda-designs">Rogue Panda Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://roguepanda.com">Rogue Panda Designs</a> is from Flagstaff, Arizona and makes seatbags, handlebar rolls, framebags and also lightweight panniers.</p>

<h2 id="bolder-bikepacking-gear">Bolder Bikepacking Gear</h2>

<p><a href="https://bolderbikepacking.wordpress.com">Bolder Bikepacking Gear</a> has been making bikepacking gear in Boulder, Colorado since 2010. You can get the whole bikepacking setup from them.</p>

<h2 id="andrew-the-maker">Andrew The Maker</h2>

<p><a href="http://atmhandmadegoods.com">Andrew The Maker</a> is a new framebag maker tht currently only offers a handlebar bag.</p>

<h2 id="phantom-pack-systems">Phantom Pack Systems</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.phantompacksystems.com">Phantom Pack Systems</a> are a maker from Canada and also offer the full bikepacking framebag setup.</p>

<h2 id="crater-packs">Crater Packs</h2>

<p><a href="http://craterpacks.com">Crater Packs</a> are made in Telluride, Colorado. They make frame bags, seat packs and handlebar bags from cuben and vinyl.</p>

<h2 id="cleaveland-mountaineering">Cleaveland Mountaineering</h2>

<p><a href="http://cleavelandmountaineering.blogspot.fi">Cleaveland Mountaineering</a> is located in Grand Junction, Colorado and makes custom frame packs, handlebar bags, Everything bags and top tube bags.</p>

<h2 id="jandd">Jandd</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jandd.com/bikes.asp">Jandd</a> has been making bags since 1983 (!) and offers a wide variety of bikepacking bags.</p>

<h2 id="lone-mountain-innovations">Lone Mountain Innovations</h2>

<p><a href="http://lonemountaininnovations.com">Lone Mountain Innovations</a> has been making framebags. They’re currently re-designing their products and will be back in a few months, so keep an eye on them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855481330" title="Pimpin&#x27; at the beach by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8429/7855481330_49fdb544f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Pimpin&#x27; at the beach" /></a></p>

<h1 id="european-makers">European Makers</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16007444033" title="Apidura Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8662/16007444033_7343c4d374_b.jpg" width="1024" height="617" alt="Apidura Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="apidura">Apidura</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.apidura.com">Apidura</a> is a British company which makes frame bags, seat bags, handlebar bags and top tube bags - the whole shebang thus - in standard sizes. Measure your bike, pick the bags and your ready to go!</p>

<h2 id="inuvik-studio">Inuvik Studio</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.inuvik.es">Inuvik Studio</a> produces their framebags and Top Tube bags in beautiful Spain.</p>

<h2 id="spk-werks">SpōK Werks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.spokwerks.com/bikepacking-gear.html">SpōK Werks</a> is a German maker of framebags, with the whole setup available.</p>

<h2 id="bike-pack">Bike Pack</h2>

<p><a href="http://bikepack.pl/en/">Bike Pack</a> hails from Poland. They make all sort of frame bags and do so for a very good price.</p>

<h2 id="parsley-bags">Parsley Bags</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.parsleybags.com/">Parsley Bags</a> is another German maker. The main business is for classic cycle-touring gear, but there’s also a seatbag available.</p>

<h2 id="alpkit">Alpkit</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.alpkit.com/bikepacking">Alpkit</a> nowadays also make the whole setup. Framebags are custom-made while seatpacks, top tube bags and handlebar bags are standards.</p>

<h2 id="wildcat-gear">Wildcat Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.wildcatgear.co.uk">Wildcat Gear</a> are from Wales and offer the whole framebag setup, both basic and custom options.</p>

<h2 id="bikebag">BikeBAG</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.buggybags.co.uk/pages/BikeBagOptions.htm">BikeBAG</a> is another UK maker of framebags. Only custom framebags are available.</p>

<h1 id="rest-of-the-world">Rest of the World</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16440220550" title="Wanderlust Equipment Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/16440220550_f24609baa9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="609" alt="Wanderlust Equipment Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="wanderlust-equipment">Wanderlust Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/products/g219-blade-frame-bag/">Wanderlust Equipment</a> from Japan makes a half frame bag to order. They look pretty neat and the craftsmanship should be superb!</p>

<h2 id="bike-bag-dude">Bike Bag Dude</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bikebagdude.com">Bike Bag Dude</a> is from Australia and offers standard bags and custom work, the whole range of framebags as well as Anything Cage Bags and Chaff Bags. They’re also a dealer for <a href="http://www.bikebagdude.com/#!oveja-negra-accessories/c1jyy">Oveja Negra Threadworks</a> framebags in Australia.</p>

<h2 id="myog">MYOG!</h2>

<p>Don’t want to spend money on a framebag? That’s not needed if you can use a sewing machine. Here are a couple of Guides to get you started:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pedalingnowhere.com/gear/how-to-make-a-bikepacking-framebag-krampus/">Making a simple frame bag for the Krampus</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/oWDRiexLA0I">How to make your own frame bag for bikepacking Video</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tourintune.com/constructing-my-diy-frame-bag/">Constructing My DIY Frame Bag</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.shanecycles.com/make-your-own-gear-myog-bikepacking-frame-bag/">Make your own gear (MYOG) Bikepacking frame bag</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15923653420" title="Salsa Mukluk on the ice by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8605/15923653420_5b51d86efe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salsa Mukluk on the ice" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-23T20:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">ISPO 2015</a> gear bonanza continues with sweet new hardware and soft goods for backpackers, climbers, skiers and hikers!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557811671" title="Dynafit Khion Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7367/16557811671_d2d2a49edc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit Khion Carbon" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html">Read Part 1 here</a></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research">Outdoor Research</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371946330" title="Outdoor Research M&#x27;s Diode Hooded Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16371946330_4138aba056_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research M&#x27;s Diode Hooded Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>At <a href="http://outdoorresearch.com/">Outdoor Research</a> a whole lotta new gear was to be tried on and tested indoors, like the M’s Diode Hooded Jacket up there. A jacket made with Body Mapping technology it uses DWR-treated down and Primaloft Gold. The latter is on the shoulders, hood, top of the sleeves and hips - areas which usually get more wet - while the core is filled with warm down to keep your torso toasty. All that is under a Pertex® Endurance 2L shell where the Primaloft is and the down is protected by Pertex® Quantum. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533381316" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/16533381316_95ee1e8e2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a></p>

<p>The Uberlayer Hooded Jacket (the blue on on the left) on the other hand trusts Polartec Alpha insulation completely to keep you warm, but not too hot. It has a stretch mesh lining which wicks sweat quickly away form your baselayer, where it meets on the Polartec Alpha insulation which further transports it to the outside. There’s plenty of pockets on the Uberlayer, a helmet-compatible hood and the shell is also wind and water resistant. The Men’s Uberlayer is 563 g in Size L, the Women’s is 472 in Size M.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558277002" title="Outdoor Research Furio Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8582/16558277002_3d65a62968_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Furio Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Furio Jacket uses the new Gore-Tex® C-Knit fabric in the shoulders, hood and hip, Paclite in the rest of the jacket and is fully seam taped. It has a Standard Fit and is 535 g light and is made for your alpine adventures where it will keep you dry, warm and protected in case the weather turns nasty. I do like OR’s TorsoFlo™ technology which are hem-to-bicep side zips that offer ventilation when the going gets steep. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936813154" title="Outdoor Research Luminary Sensor Glove by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7299/15936813154_921a82e670_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Luminary Sensor Glove" /></a></p>

<p>The Luminary Sensor Glove is an alpine climbing and skiing glove that allows you to take <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> photos without taking the gloves off. The indoor test the glove mastered without difficulties as you can see above. Made from Windstopper the shell gloves are windproof and water-resistant while the warm, removable wool blend liners keep your fingers toasty. The dexterity was good in these and with removable liners you’re able to dry them in your quilt during the night. The pair in L will weigh 236 g. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371894050" title="Outdoor Research Extravert Glove by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16371894050_52555e3dc0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Extravert Glove" /></a></p>

<p>The Extravert Gloves have a stretch nylon shell outer, a durable goat leather palm with textured fingertips and a warm wool lining. These ski-touring gloves will keep you warm when you’re skinning up and shed the powder on your turns down. The pair in L will be 165 g light.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559340835" title="Outdoor Research Untold Balaclava by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7427/16559340835_8430a96a97_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Untold Balaclava" /></a></p>

<p>The Untold Balaclava is made from acrylic and weighs 51 g. It’s a convertible balaclava that can be transformed into a cap when you roll the lower part up. It’s probably a very nice piece for winter use when the conditions change from cold and shady to sunny.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533325976" title="Outdoor Research Toasty Beanie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/16533325976_46f3f6dbcb_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Toasty Beanie" /></a></p>

<p>And then there were literally about a dozen new hats and even more gloves - after all that’s what Outdoor Research does very well. I did like the stylish hats and beanies which would be functional on the trail and stylish at the Aprés Bar after your hike. Lots of nice stuff coming from them, so keep an eye out for them.</p>

<h2 id="vertical-life--zlagboard">Vertical-Life / Zlagboard</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16588486191" title="ZlagBoards! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7336/16588486191_5df67be72b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ZlagBoards!" /></a></p>

<p>I’m pretty psyched about the news from <a href="https://www.vertical-life.info">Vertical-Life</a> and especially <a href="https://zlagboard.com">Zlagboard</a>. The latter I tried already at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/outdoor-2014-wrap-up-and-conclusions.html">OutDoor</a> and liked it but was wondering if the price was too high. Well, it seems my ideas were heard and the Zlagboard Team not just dropped the price on the Zlagboard Pro to 250€ but also introduced the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-mini">Zlagboard Mini</a> which will retail for 150€ and also the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-vario">Zlagboard Vario</a> which sells for 190€ and which allows you to attach a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/trainingsboards/">training board</a> you already have (like a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beastmaker-2000-series-trainingsboard/">Beastmaker</a>) to it. That’s not all, though, as the Team also has updated the App and there’s now a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html">Gimme Kraft!</a> training plan available and the option to create your own. I really love this and you can stay tuned for a review of the Zlagboard on these digital pages soon.</p>

<p>Vertical Life is the publishing arm of the business and they do have some <a href="http://guide.vertical-life.info/en/publications/">superb Guidebooks</a> available. Add to that already good line-up are four more guides in 2015: Sportclimbing in Südtirol, Bouldering in Südtirol, Arco Plaisir and Zillertal Multi-Pitch. Besides the dead tree versions they also will be coming as a digital app which you can download to your phone. </p>

<h2 id="salewa">Salewa</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371948468" title="Salewa North X Ice Axe, Speed Ascent shoe &amp; Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16371948468_fbfd3529e8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salewa North X Ice Axe, Speed Ascent shoe &amp; Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.salewa.com">Salewa</a> had equally interesting hardware and soft good news. Lets start with the hard goods: The North X ice axe is a 52,5 cm long and 540 g light technical ice axe for technical mountaineering. It has a steel head and blade, a 7075 aluminium shaft and a steel spike which makes it both light and durable. The hand rest can be precision-adjusted to the correct height with one hand without tools. The pick is interchangeable and the lower shaft is insulated and it has a integrated belay loop which has a 5kN breaking strength. It’s an ISPO Award Winner, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939441043" title="Salewa Ice screws by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/15939441043_ccedddc1a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Ice screws" /></a></p>

<p>I tried the new Salewa ice screws and did like them. They are an all-in-one solution: The come equipped with a Quickdraw and cap to protect the sharp points and thread, have an integrated crank and they rack very efficiently on your harness. They will be available in three lengths if I remember correctly and will start at 80€. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558505442" title="Salewa Vert Helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8636/16558505442_2232827397_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Vert Helmet" /></a></p>

<p>The Vert helmet is certified as both a climbing and skiing helmet, which makes it an ideal choice for ski-mountaineers. It has an heat-dissipating insulation and removable ear pads, the total goggle integration ensures a clear view and works together with anti-fog systems in modern ski eyewear. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533605556" title="Salewa Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/16533605556_0027b98732_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket is part of the Sesvenna Ski Touring Collection which Gore-Tex, Polartec and Windproof fabrics with Schoeller fabrics and Tyrol and merino wool for garments that combine functionality and traditional looks. They’re made with ski mountaineers in mind and are wind- and water-resistant, warm and breathable. The jacket above also won an ISPO Award and looked pretty good, a fresh design. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939447073" title="Salewa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8647/15939447073_322dfecf19_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa" /></a></p>

<p>And then there were several other new things coming from the Italian company. The Speed Ascent shoe won an ISPO Award, the climbing &amp; bouldering line gets some fresh new designs, there’s a line of products which are 100% made in Italy.</p>

<h2 id="garmin">Garmin</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15967528014" title="Garmin fēnix 3 Sapphire by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7357/15967528014_ed75eaba99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Garmin fēnix 3 Sapphire" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.garmin.com/">Garmin</a> presented the <a href="http://fenix3.garmin.com/en-US/">fēnix 3</a> and fēnix 3 Sapphire which had some major updates on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">fēnix</a> I have. The major difference between the two models is that the latter comes with a scratch resistant sapphire lens and a steel wristband (in addition to a normal plastic one) which allows you to wear your outdoor watch to the office. The watch is made for a host of activities, from backpacking to trailrunning to Triathlon. I think it’s a great looking watch, but that ain’t all of course: Under the hood the watch got some major updates: A color display that can be read in the sun (although I had major difficulties getting a good photo under them lamps indoors =), a stainless steel EXO™ antenna with GPS + GLONASS support for fast fix and accuracy, a host of Fitness training features &amp; Outdoor navigation features and Connect IQ™ compatibility for customized apps, widgets, watch faces and data fields. The fēnix 3 should be available in about a month or two, and retails for 500€ to 600€.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16620722281" title="Garmin epix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8599/16620722281_eb4fc2167b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Garmin epix" /></a></p>

<p>The Garmin epix on the other hand is a GPS watch which comes with a European Freetime Map pre-installed. It also has a Chroma colour display, an EXO Antenna for GPS &amp; GLONASS reception, several sports profiles and connects with several accessories. The  idea is that here you really have a high-resolution, color, touchscreen GPS/GLONASS mapping watch with worldwide, shaded relief basemap and 8 gb memory for further maps. I do like the classic look and the epix will be 500€ and also available in about two months. </p>

<h2 id="mountain-equipment">Mountain Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557871341" title="Mountain Equipment Compressor ¾ Pant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8655/16557871341_a8f03e3708_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Compressor ¾ Pant" /></a></p>

<p>Filled with PrimaLoft® GOLD between a Helium 30 fabric that’s windproof is the Compressor Pant and the Compressor ¾ Pant which I model above. The ¾ Pant version tips the scales at 240 g and the length is chosen so it stays above your skiing boots. It’s easy to put on with a full-length zippers on each side, and it packs into its own seat pocket. The ¾ Compressor will be 160€ will the full length version will set you back a tenner more and you’re able to carry 95 g extra, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373263039" title="Mountain Equipment by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7416/16373263039_e615d2d75a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment" /></a></p>

<p>The Switch Vest is a hybrid garment that combines Polartec® Alpha® in the front and Polartec® Power Dry® 225 Fleece at the sides and back. The idea is that the breathable and warm Alpha® insulation keeps away the headwind while you can lose the sweat and heat via the back when you’re skinning, running or climbing up a mountain. At 240 g and 100€ it’s looks like an interesting piece for the fast &amp; light readership. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373271959" title="Mountain Equipment Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/16373271959_9154aec292_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant" /></a></p>

<p>The Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant is <a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.co.uk">Mountain Equipments</a> foray into the Ski-touring market. Both garments are made from burly GoreTex Pro 80D. The Super Alpine Hood has been developed further for ski helmets and has an integrated collar, and the Alpine Fit with articulated sleeves ensures you have the freedom of movement you need when you earn your turns. The jacket also has a removable snow-guard while the pants have removable gaiters &amp; suspenders. A pocket on the thigh stores your avalanche beacon. The combo weighs together 1.335 g and will set you back 1100€. </p>

<h2 id="la-sportiva">La Sportiva</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16592940652" title="La Sportiva Ultra Raptor GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7410/16592940652_6b78d41f9e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Ultra Raptor GTX" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.sportiva.com">La Sportiva</a>’s News I’d divided in these Categories: Trailrunning, Mountaineering, High-Altitude News. Lets take a look at them in that order. The Ultra Raptor GTX weighs 410 g per shoe, has a 12 mm drop and a FriXion XF sole with the Trail Bite heel stabilizer which enhances the downhill grip. The shoe isn’t new, but the colour is =) </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16406374858" title="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7365/16406374858_8b978a4691_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX" /></a></p>

<p>The Crossover 2.0 GTX isn’t new either, but at 370 g light per shoe it’s worth a mention. This is the third shoe from La Sportiva in this round-up with an integrated gaiter, and considering this shoe is made for winter trailrunning (and hence is ideal to be “misused” as a backpacking shoe) and Winter being the sorry excuse it currently is I’m sure a few will be interested in it. Beneath the water-repellant gaiter you find a trailrunning shoe with 10 mm drop, a Ortholite Mountain Running Ergonomic footbed and underneath is a FriXion AT sole with Impact Brake System and AT Grip zone. La Sportiva offers a Grip Spike kit which allows you to get even more grip on ice. Good stuff.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15971418784" title="Trango Ice Cube GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7370/15971418784_e2534e7f0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trango Ice Cube GTX" /></a></p>

<p>The Trango Ice Cube GTX is a new boot and carries on the trend of integrated gaiters. Made for up to 4.000 m in terms of its warmth rating the 1.380 g heavy pair of boots comes with a Schoeller fabric gaiter that’s stretchy and water-resistant, a Gore-Tex Insulated Comfort lining, an insulated carbon Honeycomb Tech 3 mm insole and a La Sportiva Cube sole, made by Vibram® with the Impact Brake System lugs on the heel and a climbing zone at the toe. It’s so lightweight because of the seamless construction method on the uppers which use the Thermo Tech Injection™ technology. The boot is obviously fully crampon compatible and can be resoled.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16407729549" title="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7327/16407729549_3a1b2b283c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro" /></a></p>

<p>The G2 SM, which stands for Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro, is a sexy boot. Oh, its functional too. What I liked about it the most was the sense of adventure it communicates - Gasherbrum 2, Karakoram, 8.035 m, and of course the first winter ascent of Cory Richards, Denis Urubko and Simone Moro in 2011. It’s a very technical boot: Integrated Cordura gaiter, internal shell with BOA® quick lacing System, HoneyComb Tech midsole in carbon fibre, Vibram® Matterhorn sole with Impact Brake System lugs and a removable liner boot. It’s a super warm boot made for expeditions to the high ranges, and the pair will weigh 1.940 g. </p>

<p>Otherwise garments got some colour updates, there were a few rather nice new carbon skis and ski boots. </p>

<h2 id="grivel">Grivel</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16593580955" title="Grivel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/16593580955_e6acb0d845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Grivel" /></a></p>

<p>I do like what <a href="http://www.grivel.com">Grivel</a> does. Take the A&amp;D above: It’s an Ascender that also allows you to descend. Just thread the rope through the slit in the A&amp;D, clip it into a carabiner, open the Ascender part and you can abseil down. This allows you to use one less piece of kit, and the ascender is also easy to unlock when the teeth have dug deep into your rope. It works with ropes from 8,3 mm to 13 mm in diameter when going up and 7,3 mm to 13 mm when going down and weighs 259 g. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16001900693" title="Grivel Tech Machine Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8642/16001900693_54f2653a73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grivel Tech Machine Carbon" /></a></p>

<p>Then there’s the new Tech Machine which will be available as an aluminium and carbon version. The former is 660 g for the tool, the carbon version saves you 100 g - they work both just as good, as Stevie Haston ensured me - though the carbon one will be warmer. The interesting new development on these is the G Bone Shaft, which should allow for an ergonomic grip along the whole shaft. This technology will also be used in the Air Tech Evo ice axe (which also gets a Hammer Version next winter) and the North Machine ice tool. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15973805963" title="Grivel Mountain Runner Comp backpack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/15973805963_176c1e7bbe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Grivel Mountain Runner Comp backpack" /></a></p>

<p>The Mountain Runner Comp backpack is a 450 g light trailrunning pack with 5 l volume. These packs were designed with experience from the Tor de Geants Race, are one-size-fits-all, have multiple pockets to carry your gear and even allow you to carry your ice axes or poles on it. </p>

<p>Oh, and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-lambda-twin-lock-hms-karabiner/">Twin Gate carabiners</a> are now in stores. Get one to try them, I do quite like them.</p>

<h2 id="dynafit">Dynafit</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533475316" title="Dynafit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7431/16533475316_657af5fcd2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit" /></a></p>

<p>If I am at the ISPO a visit to <a href="http://dynafit.com">Dynafit</a> is always in order - gotta know what this company is up to if you like lightweight kit. The Chugach is a free touring ski which will launch for the 2015/ 2016 season and is for free riders who want to conquer new terrain by mountaineering means. Named after Alaska’s Chugach Mountains which represent untouched wilderness and awesome descents, the ski offers an optimal ratio of surface area to weight, which is 1.950 g. It has a double ellipse rocker construction and enables maximum edging on steep, icy terrain without losing the playful lightness when initiating turns. This is going to be a ski to watch if you like to play in big, wild mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373204349" title="Dynafit Khion Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7339/16373204349_020299b5ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit Khion Carbon" /></a></p>

<p>The Khiôn is a free touring boot which combines the rigidity and support of an alpine downhill boot with the comfort and lightness of a modern ski touring boot on the ascent. The boot will be available as a Khiôn MS model, a stiffer Khiôn Carbon version which adds more performance on the descent and also a Women’s version. The boot will give you performance and precision with direct power transmission and maximal support thanks to the new Precision Lock System which enables the various parts of the boot to work together as a torsionally stiff unit. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557822481" title="Dynafit Radical 2 Binding by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7302/16557822481_ab6d563ebc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Dynafit Radical 2 Binding" /></a></p>

<p>The Radical 2 Binding takes a step forward in safety and comfort 30 years after the invention of the frameless system. The Radical 2 weighs 599 g and the biggest update is the a pivoting toe piece combined with the Step in Side Towers. This has several advantages: It functions as an additional release mechanism and works to prevent early release from side impacts. It has a a precise release mechanism at the toe and heel piece with a release value between 4 and 10 for the Radical 2 ST version or up to 12 for the Radical FT.</p>

<h2 id="mountain-hardwear">Mountain Hardwear</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937000064" title="Mountain Hardwear HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8650/15937000064_16b2b942f8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com">Mountain Hardwear</a> HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag and it’s sibling Spark are synthetic sleeping bags which employ a central zipper for you to get in and comfortably sit in your bag during your morning coffee. The Spark will be 737 g and the Flame 1106 g with temperature ratings to 0°C and -6°C respectively. The bags are made with MH’s Lamina™ construction which welds the Thermal.Q™ insulation to the shell and lining, eliminating the cold spots caused by traditional stitching. Bodymapping technology was employed throughout the top of the bag to concentrate warmth where you need it most – around your core and feet. The bags will set you back 220 or 240€.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXIII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxiii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-22T21:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxiii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“There are always two people in every picture: The photographer and the viewer.”</em>
- <a href="http://amzn.to/19RTIM4">Ansel Adams</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6961553731" title="Sunset II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7176/6961553731_903b678b97_b.jpg" width="1024" height="480" alt="Sunset II" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://semi-rad.com/2015/02/dear-winter/">Dear Winter</a>.</p>

<p>Always felt like your feedback should be heard when developing a new outdoor jacket? Now’s your chance: <a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/aktuelles/prototyp-tester-hagloefs-isolationsjacke/">Test a Haglöfs Insulation Jacket Prototype</a> and let Toray &amp; Haglöfs know what should be improved!</p>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/1zWgNSX">Adobe Lightroom</a> 6 comes March 6th. Conincidence with the date? </p>

<p>Bunyan Velo Issue 5 is out. <a href="http://bunyanvelo.com/issues/">Read it for free</a> or <a href="http://bunyanvelo.myshopify.com/collections/all/products/bunyan-velo-issue-no-05">buy it</a>.</p>

<p>Win a warm &amp; waterproof <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/66-north-raffle/">66° North Snafell Down Parka</a> at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/walking-el-camino-year-camino-companion-smartphone-app/">The Camino Companion Smartphone App is Out</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nationalparks.org/ook/every-kid-in-a-park">Every Kid in a Park</a>, a great iniative in the USA.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alpinist.com/doc/web15w/wfeature-searching-for-jensen">Searching for Jensen</a>.</p>

<p>Antti’s <a href="https://longdistancetrail.wordpress.com/2015/02/18/gr5-book-now-available/">GR5 Book is now available</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://gizmodo.com/a-beginners-guide-to-doing-drugs-in-the-outdoors-1686617842">A Beginner’s Guide To Doing Drugs In The Outdoors</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.groundtruthtrekking.org/blog/?p=3472">Sixth Year in the Woods (Musings of a Wilderness Parent)</a>.</p>

<p>Aender &amp; Sven visit <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/2015/02/caspers-climbing-shop-ein-besuch/">Casper’s Climbing Shop</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/22/opinion/sunday/mountaineerings-greatest-climb-unravels.html">Mountaineering’s Greatest Climb Unravels</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/">Outdoorline.sk</a> has 20% off all <a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/26_westcomb">Westcomb Gear</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=313709&amp;pw=73183">Sign up for Campsaver.com’s newsletter</a> and receive 15% off your first order!</p>

<p>At the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=371565&amp;pw=73183">REI OUTLET Odds &amp; Ends</a> you can save 70% or more!</p>

<p>And the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/?refID=hif">trekking-lite-store.com</a> celebrates it’s fifth birthday this weekend with 10% off everything.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=45773&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10083/45773/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="145" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://easyhiking.exblog.jp/20910655/">天狗岳 2日目</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikeovernights.org/post/sources-of-inspiration-fat-bikes-canyon-country">Fat Bikes &amp; Canyon Country</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://chamconditions.blogspot.fi/2015/02/skiing-in-kosovo-and-macedonia.html">Skiing in Kosovo and Macedonia</a>.</p>

<p>Tips for a <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/roadtrip-baltikum-tipps/">Roadtrip through the Baltic States</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2015/02/los-volcanes-seccion-2.html">The Volcanoes</a>. </p>

<p>Part 13 of Gerald’s Trip Report takes him <a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/02/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-13.html">along ridges with great views</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Peter heads out for a <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/02/levaneva-ski-overnighter.html">Levaneva Ski Overnighter</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/119981667?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.bushwalkingblog.com.au/blue-mountains-valley-of-the-waters-and-the-national-pass-tread-lightly/">A week in the Blue Mountains</a> – Part 2.</p>

<p>Stefanie hikes to the <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/winterwanderung-herzogstand/">Herzogstand</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.carbon-monkey.co.uk/wp/index.php/2015/02/south-downs-way/">UK Bikepacking Trip</a>.</p>

<p>Ski-touring to the <a href="http://biwak.blogspot.fi/2015/02/chli-bielenhorn-2940m.html">Chli Bielenhorn</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A Winter hike to the <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/rotwand-1884m-in-spitzingsee-a-winter-hike/">Rotwand 1884m in Spitzingsee</a>.</p>

<p>Skiing on the <a href="http://www.kulturnatur.de/2015/02/18/uebers-wasser-laufen/">Königssee</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Linda visits <a href="http://photomomlinda.blogspot.fi/2015/02/smith-rock-in-winter.html">Smith Rock in Winter</a>.</p>

<p>Dave &amp; M go <a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2015/02/17/the-harsh-fiords/">sea kayaking in New Zealand</a>.</p>

<p>Dr. Tomás is back with <a href="http://www.scandinavian-hiking.com/2015/02/Ph.D.html">Piled Higher &amp; Deeper</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://becausetheyrethere.com/2015/02/17/arkengarthdale-moor-and-the-death-of-sods-law/">Arkengarthdale Moor and the Death of Sods Law</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/primus-winter-gas.html" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7452/16577006692_b45cdfda48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Corinna’s <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2015/02/weltgroesste-sportmesse-ispo-2015-bunt-wars.html">ISPO Impressions</a> were colourful. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://coastkid.blogspot.fi/2015/02/diy-fatbike-pvc-pipe-washstand.html">DIY Fatbike PVC pipe washstand</a>.</p>

<p>Will Gadd explains the <a href="http://willgadd.com/bd-spray-ice-hooks/">Pectre Ice Hooks</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://ivovanmontfort.blogspot.fi/2015/02/zelfbouw-gtx-regenjas.html">MYOG Gore-Tex Rain Jacket</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.alpin-blog.com/leichter-hochtouren-gurt-blue-ice-choucas/">Blue Ice Cou­cas Harness</a> reviewed. [German]</p>

<p>Roger prefers <a href="http://nielsenbrown.com/2015/02/15/why-i-prefer-klymit-mattresses/">Klymit Mattresses</a> and explains why.</p>

<p><a href="http://seattlebackpackersmagazine.com/clif-shot-bloks-energy-chews-review/">Clif Shot Bloks – Energy Chews Review</a>.</p>

<p>Derek reviews the <a href="http://theultimatehang.com/2015/02/antigravitygear-quicksilver-ultralight-hammock-review/">AntiGravityGear Quicksilver Ultralight Hammock</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outlet/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" title="Zum Winterschlussverkauf 2015 bei Bergfreunde.de"><img src="http://www.bergfreunde-partner.de/banner/wsv/af_wsv_728x90.jpg" border="0" alt="Zum Winterschlussverkauf 2015 bei Bergfreunde.de" /></a><img src="http://partner.bergfreunde.de/go.cgi?pid=10239&amp;wmid=402&amp;cpid=1&amp;prid=1&amp;view=1" height="1" width="1" border="0" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Primus Winter Gas]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/primus-winter-gas.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-19T13:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/primus-winter-gas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.primus.eu/winter-gas-230-g">Primus Winter Gas</a> Test. In real Winter™ conditions. Answering the age-long question: <em>Does it really work?</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16018424719" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8657/16018424719_cbbf145d70_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>A cartridge of <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Primus Winter Gas</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1DrYz2T">Primus Power Gas</a> arrived in December on my porch, courtesy of <a href="http://www.primus.eu">Primus</a>. With Climate Change being a reality in Finland and the winter 2015 turning out to be as shite as <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/the-four-week-winter.html">last year</a> I was eagerly waiting for the temperatures to drop to see if the gas really works as claimed. On a magical day which combined sunshine with -13°C (which felt like -18°C my Weather App ensured me) it was so far and I <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">dressed up in layers</a>, took my two MSR Reactor stoves and headed out to conduct my sort of <em>scientific outdoor test in Finnish Winter conditions</em>. Before we watch a video of me talking and playing with fire, here’s what Primus says about the Winter Gas: </p>

<p><em>“Everybody who has used a gas cartridge stove in cold conditions knows this: The lower the temperature, the poorer the performance of the stove. Even though the cartridge might be brand new! Why? Liquefied gas doesn’t evaporate properly the colder it gets. In addition, the evaporation process has a self-cooling effect on the cartridge, so
conventional LP gas canisters perform poorer and poorer during use.</em></p>

<p><em>Primus Winter Gas improves the performance of LP gas cartridge at temperatures down to –22°C. After 60 minutes of cooking, a Winter Gas cartridge is approximately 9 % more powerful than one without Vapor Mesh. After 120 minutes of use it delivers about 15 % more power. The reason for the even better performance over time is that the Vapor Mesh works better the emptier the cartridge gets, because more of its surface is exposed.”</em></p>

<p>Good, lets look a bit at that in detail. </p>

<ul>
  <li><em>The lower the temperature the poorer the performance</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Yeps, I can sign that for gas stoves. See my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/primus-omnilite-ti.html">OmniLite Ti Review</a> and scroll down to the video at the bottom. Took quite a bit to boil that water and that was with an inverted canister (Canister, cartridge, they’re the same in case you’re wondering).</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Primus Winter Gas improves the performance of LP gas cartridge at temperatures down to –22°C</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Lets call this the hypothesis, which I am trying to prove. </p>

<ul>
  <li><em>The reason for the even better performance over time is that the Vapor Mesh works better the emptier the cartridge gets, because more of its surface is exposed</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Are you wondering HOW that Vapor Mesh looks like? I surely was. Happily Primus made the effort to cut one of their canisters in half so we can look inside and have an idea:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557911141" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7411/16557911141_182ddf4be5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<p>Some more information on the Vapor Mesh is in order, me thinks. It’s a type of paper that absorbs the liquid gas. When I went to school and learned to write with a fountain pen I always had a sheet of <em>Löschpapier</em> - Blotting Paper - next to me in case of a mistake. So <em>Vapor Mesh</em> seems to be working like blotting paper, but what’s the idea of putting that paper in there? </p>

<p>As you saw, the Vapor Mesh paper is on the sides of the canister, from the bottom till almost the valve on top of the canister. The liquid gas in the canister is <em>liquid</em> and so the paper absorbs the liquid gas which then travels to the top, which widens the surface area of the gas. More surface area means more gas can evaporate from liquid to gas which also increases the pressure in the canister. How it works, according to Primus, is:</p>

<p>a) Faster phase transition from liquid to gas
<br />b) Burner receives more fuel
<br />c) Boiling times in low temperatures become shorter</p>

<p>This should get even better the less liquid gas is in the canister, as this makes the Vapor Mesh surface area larger. Gas goes down = more Vapor Mesh paper becomes exposed, sucking liquid gas up = more surface area for the liquid gas going from liquid to gas. OK, done, lets go outside.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16576488681" title="Primus Power Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8592/16576488681_80fd9c23be_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Power Gas" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-test">The Test</h2>

<p>So lets get down to testing. The conditions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Outside temperature was -13°C</li>
  <li>Two identical stoves, the <a href="http://bit.ly/1ilDgDz">MSR Reactor 1.0 l</a></li>
  <li>Valves were opened at the exactly same time</li>
  <li>Stoves were lightened up at the exactly same time <em>x¹</em></li>
  <li>Both pots were filled with exactly 500 ml of cold water</li>
  <li>Both pots were put on the stoves at exactly same time</li>
  <li>Power Gas Operating Temperature is -15°C to +25°C</li>
  <li>Winter Gas Operating Temperature is -22°C to +10°C</li>
</ul>

<p>This is how that looks in moving pictures: </p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mj-vaft7hF8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<p>Or watch it on <a href="http://youtu.be/Mj-vaft7hF8">Youtube</a>.</p>

<h2 id="the-result">The Result</h2>

<p>Look, I made a nice table to present my initial findings! </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td> Power Gas</td>
      <td> Winter Gas</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> Weight 1</td>
      <td>369 g</td>
      <td>374 g</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> Weight 2</td>
      <td> 351 g</td>
      <td>356 g</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> Time</td>
      <td>2:50 min</td>
      <td>2:20 min</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br />Both canisters ignited equally well at -13°C and there wasn’t a winner - the temperature was well within the capabilities of the Power Gas, which might get problems if the temperature drops down to -20°C and more. Both the Power Gas and the Winter Gas used the same amount of fuel (18 g) to boil the 500 ml of water, but the Winter Gas was 30 seconds faster. This means at least the <em>a), b) and c)</em> points above hold true. I wouldn’t go as far as proving the hypothesis right as this was after all only <em>one</em> short test with two new canisters. The real test would be to repeat these tests until both canisters are empty, and then draw conclusions. <em>x²</em> As I usually don’t cook food on the trail and just melt snow and boil water in winter, I’d do this long-term test like the above one, just several times in a row till the canisters are empty. This represents the real-world conditions for backpackers much closer than letting the stove run for as long as possible in one session.</p>

<h2 id="what-it-means-in-the-real-winter-outdoor-world">What it means in the Real-Winter-Outdoor-World</h2>

<p>Obviously my test is just starting to show the possibilities of the Primus Winter Gas, and I didn’t even touch on their claims of better performance over longer time. I’m happy to do that (<em>x²</em>) if time and responsibilities permit, but right now it’s either way to warm outside to test it and it will need to wait till I go north and chase winter. However, it did show that the Winter Gas did perform better than its sibling Power Gas, which was the de-facto gas most of us used in Winter (usually with an inverted canister stove). Now most often people that are serious about winter backpacking use a gas stove that allows them to invert the canister where the pre-heat tube at the stove lets the liquid gas vaporize to gas before it arrives at the burner, so I don’t know if Winter Gas is a must-have for them (the gas compositions of both Power &amp; Winter Gas seem to be the same, only the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-summer-gas-gaskartusche/">Summer Gas</a> uses a different gas mix).</p>

<p>However, many of us don’t want to buy an inverted canister stove just for the few times we go out in winter. And that’s where I see the possibilities of the <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Primus Winter Gas</a>: For all those people who use an upright gas stove like the <a href="http://bit.ly/1LgbO86">Jetboil MiniMo</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1AJrnU6">MSR Windboiler</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1A8sdHY">MSR Reactor</a> or <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-eta-lite-sturmkocher/">Primus Lite+</a> and who want to try winter backpacking but <strong>not</strong> buy a new stove. The Primus Winter Gas is around 2,50 € more expensive than the Power Gas but allows you to use the gas stove you have in cold winter temperatures. Which is a pretty neat thing, because usually upright gas stoves start to perform badly when the temperature drops and the canister gets emptier - the Winter Gas with its Vapor Mesh liner promises that your stove now will function just as good as in warm weather. I for one liked what my initial tests showed, and am looking forward to chase Winter up North and see if it performs also in the long run.</p>

<p>You can get the Winter Gas at your local <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/tuotemerkit/primus">Partioaitta Store</a> in Finland or online at the usual suspects like <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Globetrotter</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/primus/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16576491401" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7383/16576491401_01f554e0c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<p><em>I usually don’t do <strong>Disclaimers</strong> but here’s one: The Power Gas and Winter Gas have been sent to me for free and I was under no obligation to produce any content about nor endorse it. The statements represents my findings after using these items, at the time of testing and writing.</em></p>

<p><em>x¹</em> This needed several tries as either the Reactor stove with the Power Gas or the Reactor Stove with the Winter Gas didn’t catch a flame, so then I closed the valves and did the whole process from the beginning again
<br /><em>x²</em> If you’d like me to do just that, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> so I have something warm to drink while I’m standing outside in the cold.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16552157116" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7454/16552157116_c3ce614152_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-17T21:59:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The ISPO is the annual trade fair where outdoor companies present their autumn &amp; winter collections for the coming seasons. I travelled down to München once again to check out what new kit we can expect next winter and here is the first batch of my finds.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371800168" title="VAUDE by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7308/16371800168_23b1e71f13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="VAUDE" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="arcteryx">Arc’teryx</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557800531" title="Arc&#x27;teryx by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8579/16557800531_dab20040d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373187969" title="Arc&#x27;teryx by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7358/16373187969_85d819e367_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx" /></a></p>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> is that their glove line has been completely re-designed and like their clothing the gloves now work as a layer system. I tried on the different gloves and really loved them and found them better than the already great <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-alpha-sv-glove-black-xs/?pid=81">Alpha SV Gloves</a> I’m using right now. Most of the new gloves don’t use leather anymore which makes them more flexible and allows for better dexterity, and the liner gloves and shells also can be used completely on their own. For durability the gloves are made from a 3 layer Gore-Tex fabric with TPU laminates on the palm and fingers so that they’re highly abrasion resistant (and waterproof!). The Beta Shell Glove (110 g in M) &amp; Atom Glove Liner (90 g in M) are for the climbers and mountaineers while the Lithic Glove (an ISPO Gold Award Winner) is an insulated glove for backcountry skiers &amp; snowboarders that uses three kinds of PrimaLoft® synthetic insulation in the construction. Also the Mittens I tried on where fantastic and I imagine if you’re a lot out in really cold winter then these gloves will be high on your list.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558836791" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7363/16558836791_9d2067f3a3_b.jpg" width="751" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Canadians also will be using the new Gore-Tex® C-Knit™ fabric in their new Zeta LT Jacket which will weigh in at 335 g for a Men’s Medium and the even lighter Norvan Jacket (215 g in M). C-Knit from Gore should be ideal for hikers &amp; backpackers as it combines the durable Gore-Tex Pro membrane with an extremely thin, dense &amp; lightweight circular knit backer on the inside. The result makes the jacket much softer next to the skin and also less noisy and stiff. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15940472133" title="Nuclei AR Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/15940472133_4b223c94fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="536" alt="Nuclei AR Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>And the new Nuclei AR Jacket (also an ISPO Gold Award Winner) is an all-round belay parka that combines 100 grams/m2 of Coreloft synthetic insulation with a seam taped Windstopper exterior, making it a warm, windproof and water-resistant insulation piece that you can put on when you’re hanging in the middle of a frozen waterfall and are belaying your mate. The Nuclei in Medium will tip the scales at 465 g and set you back 475 €.</p>

<h2 id="primus">Primus</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557911141" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7411/16557911141_182ddf4be5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<p>Lots of good stuff coming from <a href="http://www.primus.eu">Primus</a>. <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Winter Gas is now available in stores</a> (and expect a spot review from me this week on it, too) which is good news for winter adventurers. It was announced at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor 2014</a> and now helps you to cook, melt snow and boil water in cold temperatures. Seriously good stuff.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559583855" title="Primus Silencer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7421/16559583855_94195b900f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Silencer" /></a></p>

<p>Have you seen my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/primus-omnilite-ti.html">Omnilite Ti with Gas in Winter Video</a>? Do you remember how LOUD the stove was? That’s a thing of the past with the Primus Silencer. The Silencer is mounted in a few seconds by unscrewing the upper part of the OmniLite Ti burner and replacing it with the Silencer and only adds 17 g to the stove weight but doesn’t reduce fuel efficiency or power output. It is not suitable for diesel, kerosene or jet fuel and will set you back 60 €, but the silence it gives you is well worth that in my opinion.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16374728849" title="Primus Stove Paw Ti by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7281/16374728849_9d0556f5f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="941" alt="Primus Stove Paw Ti" /></a></p>

<p>Serious winter backpackers usually take a plate of sort along for their stoves when they’re cooking and melting snow, as stove feet tend to sink into the snow or melt it and two litres of melted snow tipping over in your tent is inconvenient. Enter the Stove Paw Ti, a baseplate that supports stoves when cooking in snow or on other soft, slippery surfaces. The Stove Paw Ti folds super-compact and weighs in at 55 g and is made from Titanium as the name suggests. It fits with the Primus’ OmniFuel, MultiFuel, OmniLite Ti, EasyFuel and Express Spider stoves and the different stove’s feet attach quickly and securely to the slots in the plate, making cooking safer and easier. Again a rather simple yet smart accessory that makes your winter adventure a tiny bit more convenient.</p>

<h2 id="therm-a-rest">Therm-A-Rest</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373717847" title="Therm-A-Rest Voyager Mattress by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7440/16373717847_b3bc02c271_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Therm-A-Rest Voyager Mattress" /></a></p>

<p>There was only one new item at <a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/therm-a-rest/">Therm-A-Rest</a> at the ISPO, and that was their Voyager Mattress. It’s a mattress for the camper as the Regular length model weighs in at 650 g (R-Value 2,2) with a length of 183 cm and a width of 51 cm. The selling argument for the mat is its thickness of 6,3 cm and the WaveCore construction, which will make it a nice, warm camping mat for 3 Season use. </p>

<h2 id="jetboil">Jetboil</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559537985" title="Jetboil by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8563/16559537985_bf898d2a54_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Jetboil" /></a></p>

<p>You’ve likely seen some of the pre-ISPO Press Releases about the new <a href="http://www.jetboil.com">Jetboil</a> Flash Lite and I too got the Press Release well before the fair and so knew what was waiting for me. Like usual at Jetboil I asked for 500 ml of cold water and then made the indoor fair test, in which the Flash Lite boiled that half litre in 2:15 minutes to a rolling boil. The whole stove system weighs 312 g and measures 104 mm x 165 mm, with a suggested Retail Price of 100€. It’s a well-constructed little stove that replaces the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti.html">Sol Ti</a> and like its predecessor you can fit the stove, legs and a 100 g cartridge inside of the pot. Unlike the Sol Ti it shouldn’t have any problems with the flux ring and bottom of the pot dissolving as everything is made from aluminium. </p>

<h2 id="rjk">Röjk</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939424333" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7399/15939424333_ac073dca09_b.jpg" width="1024" height="654" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://rojksuperwear.com">Röjk</a> goes Inca Patterns in 2015. The designs are growing on me, from an initial <em>Hmmm, interesting</em> my opinion has matured into a <em>I think they’re onto something there</em> and give it a few more weeks and I’m sure I’ll totally love it. Except those T-Shirts. Those I love already:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558486002" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/16558486002_83f89b2252_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533585186" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8598/16533585186_31807106c9_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p>The Röjk crew partners with different artists each season who develop the designs and I yet have to see a SuperTee I didn’t like. They’re great. As I’m on a hyperbole train already, let me continue with the sweet packaging Jan has designed for the SuperBase baselayers: </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533597336" title="Röjk Packaging by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/16533597336_8c74017d91_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Röjk Packaging" /></a></p>

<p>As a former sustainability consultant this totally hit home with me. Flat packaging allows you to ship more SuperBase baselayers in one box which minimizes unused space and so brings the efficiency up and the fuel used down. The packaging can be recycled by the end user very easily and it’s pretty, too. Awesome! But back to them garments:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937025654" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7452/15937025654_b507853293_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p>Another new garment the Swedish company brought back is their ChillOut Pant. I saw it on the mannequins and Linus and wanted one immediately. It felt very comfortable with laces at the cuffs and waist that keep the pants in place. It looks stylish and I would have no problem heading to a Café in it, but most likely I’d be wearing them when heading to the climbing gym or chilling at home. Because style and comfiness are häftigt =)</p>

<h2 id="inov-8">inov-8</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559448265" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7409/16559448265_2d0b13a067_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.inov-8.com/">inov-8</a> had several ISPO Winners in their line-up but the best news for the backpacking inov-8 community is that their much-loved X-Talon 212 will come in 2015 besides the good old Regular version also in a Version with a Wide Toebox called Standard Fit. Both have the great close-fitting heel which locks the shoe into position but the wide toebox allows your toes to splay, which probably will make this already popular shoe even more, yeps, popular.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936887794" title="Inov-8 TerraClaw Line-Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/15936887794_ec1e7fdff4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8 TerraClaw Line-Up" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373527077" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7358/16373527077_56bc3bfcef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>New in the inov-8 Line-Up is the TerraClaw family. It comes in 220 and 250 g versions (per shoe) for Men and Women (left &amp; right on the above photo). The TerraClaw 220 is the stripped-down version for super-fast racing, while the TerraClaw 250 adds more protection and comfort and I reckon this could be a good ultralight backpacking shoe. inov-8 sees these shoes as their most versatile yet which should perform well on loose, rocky trails as well as hard-packed paths. It’s an ISPO Award winner and the judges valued the Multi-Directional Lugs which provide traction when climbing, descending and contouring alike. The Dual-C™ Outsole uses two types of sticky rubber - the darker one is more durable and is in areas of high wear while the lighter rubber maximizes grip. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558347592" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8648/16558347592_f873320966_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Inov-8" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936858314" title="Inov-8 RaceUltra Shell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7325/15936858314_45095e2823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8 RaceUltra Shell" /></a></p>

<p>Then there’s the garments. High on the list for Ultralight backpackers and Ultra Racers alike will be the Race Ultra Shell, a 125 g shell anorak that has a 10.000 mm hydrostatic head (the minimum requirement for many Ultra races nowadays), taped seams, a long venting zipper and the material is also breathable. The fabric is transparent so that race numbers can be seen underneath it and the fabric is stretchy, and best of all: When not needed it packs to the size of an orange. There’s a Race Ultra Pants, too, which tips the scales at 95 g and probably packs down o the size of an apple.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371756968" title="inov-8 Race Elite Merino LSZ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7361/16371756968_f81da06d79_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="inov-8 Race Elite Merino LSZ" /></a></p>

<p>The Race Elite Merino LSZ (yeps, also an ISPO Award Winner =) is a 263 g Merino wool hoody that uses a lighter fabric in the back and under the arms while at the fron there’s a heavier Merino wool. It has a close fitting hood and built in hand mitts (yes, REAL mitts) that fold into the cuffs when not needed. Add in a long zipper for venting and you got a new Merino hoody on the block which should delight not just trailrunners!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936852414" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/15936852414_486098ef3b_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>And finally there was the RaceUltra 10 backpack, an ISPO Gold Award Winner, which also has a little 5 l sibling. I tried this pack on, jumped around like a rubber ball and concluded my indoor test that the zero bounce claim holds true. The pack has several hydration options and ten pockets, which makes it a good choice for 100 miles and longer Ultras where you need to carry more mandatory kit and food. Both packs come with two 500 ml soft flasks with tubes and there’s a compartment for your hydration bladder, too.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> The <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>

<p><em>Check back on Thursday for Batch II!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week In Review CLXXXXII]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxii.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-15T21:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/the-week-in-review-clxxxxii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Snow falls/ water freezes/ air floats.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15909703263" title="Winter Bliss by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8641/15909703263_1634276c02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Winter Bliss" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.gourmetguerilla.de/2015/02/ein-blog-im-monat-kostet-und-warum-die-leser-das-wissen-sollten/">What a blog costs per month</a>. [German]</p>

<p>David &amp; David announce their <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/blog/2015/1/29/c2c4k">C2C4K</a> in aid of the John Muir Award.</p>

<p>Ulrich’s <a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/outdoor-ausrustung/auf-der-ispo-2015/">ISPO Impressions</a> and Ute’s <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/ispo-2015-outdoorbekleidung-kinder/">ISPO Kids Trends</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A interview with <a href="http://www.outdoorwomensalliance.com/2015/02/charlotte-austin-mountain-guide-adventure-writer.html">Charlotte Austin, Adventure Writer and Mountain Guide</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2015/02/11/pepper-and-trauma/">Video Interview with Pepper and Trauma on their Winter PCT Thru-Hike</a>.</p>

<p>And the third interview is with Luc Mehl: <a href="http://www.thebicyclestory.com/2015/02/luc-mehl/">Life, Death, and Philosophy in the Alaskan Wilderness</a>.</p>

<p>Alex <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2015/02/i-forgot-i-was-backpacker.html">forgot he was a backpacker</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.massdrop.com/buy/5394/?vendor_key=d02488acd6a84620c688c207d702d645">BlackRock Gear had a Flash Sale on MassDrop</a> - request a 2nd sale via the website for your chance to get a Down Hat for a great price!</p>

<p>What happens when <a href="http://www.powderguide.com/magazin/report/artikel/was-passiert-wenn-freeriden-volkssport-wird.html">Freeriding gets more popular</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A tidy &amp; cool <a href="http://www.outsideonline.com/outdoor-gear/The-Ultimate-Gear-Storage-Facility.html">gear shed</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-25-bis-die-sohle-qualmt/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #25</a> is out! [German]</p>

<p>And the <a href="http://bit.ly/1Ew04tP">Bergfreunde Wintersale</a> is coming to an end. Order some warm garments or gear for your summer hikes today while you still get up to 60% off!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/cheese-grouse-pricey-socks/">Cheese, grouse and pricey socks</a>, a recommended read.</p>

<p><a href="http://hematula.vsco.co/journal/antarctica-2">Antarctica</a>, inspiring photos from a beautiful summer down south.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://hillplodder.com/2015/02/04/dartmoor-a-north-eastern-backpack/">North-Eastern Dartmoor Backpack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://eltaraumara.blogspot.fi/2015/02/guarapo-y-mortinos-con-cafe-trans.html">Trans Ecuador, Seccion 1</a>.</p>

<p>Mike &amp; friends are <a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2015/02/finding-flow.html">finding flow down the Grand Canyon</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.rockandice.com/lates-news/tnb-my-first-epic">My First Epic</a>.</p>

<p>Joe on <a href="http://alpine-works.com/2015/02/the-coastal-challenge/">the Coastal Challenge</a>.</p>

<p>Watching the moon set at the <a href="http://geraldtrekkt.blogspot.fi/2015/02/durch-das-land-der-namenlosen-berge-12.html">Saipal Chuli</a>. [German]</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/118996487?color=ffffff&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="1200" height="634" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.pureoutdoor.de/reisen/usa-westen-reise-camping">Travelling two months in the USA with a baby &amp; Toddler</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://tomripleyclimbing.blogspot.fi/2015/02/no-tfa-on-mount-kenya.html">No T.F.A on Mount Kenya</a>.</p>

<p>Peter goes <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/02/vigu-ice-skiing.html">ice skiing</a> around Vaasa.</p>

<p><a href="http://fuusora.blogspot.fi/2015/02/snowshoe-hiking-in-kitayatugatake.html">Snowshoe Hiking in Kitayatugatake</a>. [Japanese]</p>

<p>Angelica is in love with <a href="http://wandernbonn.de/2015/02/10/schneeschuhwandern-eine-liebeserklarung/">Snowshoe hiking</a>. [German]</p>

<p>A <a href="http://ulligunde.com/2015/02/unbeschreiblich-bloggertreffen-amberger-hutte/">ski-touring blogger meet at the Amberger Hütte</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://surfnslide.wordpress.com/2015/02/13/winter-in-snowdonia-with-the-junior-sherpa/">Winter in Snowdonia with The Junior Sherpa</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16508620976" title="After a good wash this hardshell&#x27;s DWR again functions as it should by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7397/16508620976_fa486c326c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="After a good wash this hardshell&#x27;s DWR again functions as it should" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/XjRxUfQAfHw">Tips for hiking with a child carrier (backpack) in winter</a> - a great, informative video! [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://briangreen.net/2015/02/review-paleo-meals-go.html">Paleo Meals To Go</a>, reviewed.</p>

<p>Very cool <a href="http://woodtrekker.blogspot.fi/2015/02/msr-xgk-exreactor-hybrid-cold-weather.html">MSR XGK EX/Reactor Hybrid Cold Weather Stove System</a> from Ross.</p>

<p><a href="https://joecruz.wordpress.com/2015/02/09/folding-bike-touring/">Folding Bike Touring</a>.</p>

<p>John updated his <a href="http://hikelighter.com/2015/02/12/lightest-fully-enclosed-shelters/">Lightest Fully Enclosed Shelters</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Want more news and trip reports?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/">Flickr</a>, <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=42809&amp;pw=73183"><img src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10008/42809/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Said Belhaj, Climber]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/mountain-people-said-belhaj.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-11T22:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/mountain-people-said-belhaj</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Travelling, climbing, family and training - how do you fit that all into a year well spent without going to a nine-to-five job? If you’re Said Belhaj, a professional climber from Sweden, it’s easy. You train three months at home and then travel the world and climb each day! <em>A <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mountain-people/">Mountain People Interview</a>.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16504232795" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7299/16504232795_1aab6675e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Said, I know you a bit - but my reader’s don’t. Could you please briefly introduce yourself and tell us what you do?</strong></p>

<p>I was born and raised in Göteborg, Sweden to a father from Morocco and mother from Finland. I have 2 brothers and I live with my girlfriend. I’m 33 years old and have been climbing for over 20 years, 14 years as pro. We have an appartment in Stockholm with my girlfriend but are renting it out as we are travelling so much for the moment. Right now I’m staying in Santiago, Chile. Tomorrow - who knows?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15881673364" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7396/15881673364_1af82e9851_b.jpg" width="1024" height="658" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the Abisko Ice Climbing Festival in Sweden in February 2014 - was that the first time for you to climb ice, or have you been secretly planning your alpine climbing career and soon will stand on an 8.000 m peak in the Himalayas?</strong></p>

<p>I’ve ice climbed a little bit in my life, when I’ve gotten the chance. I like to try a bit of everything but unfortunately there is not always time. I don’t see myself on top of a 8000 meter peaks in the near future but at the same time who knows? I started climbing because I was seeking the adventure and the unknown, a 8000 meter climb would probably be both!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16316772330" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7375/16316772330_bac20af718_b.jpg" width="1024" height="698" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>In your “20 years as a climber” presentation you highlighted how you started climbing - from “free-soloing” as a kid to trad climbing to sports climbing - all outdoors. Nowadays most people start climbing indoors at gyms, and just a small percentage of them head outside to climb on rock. How do you feel about that?</strong></p>

<p>For me it’s strange to do an outdoor activity indoors - it’s impossible. My life and climbing has always been about beeing outdoors. Indoor climbing is good for training, comps and meeting people sometimes. I can totally see why people who start indoors stay indoors and it’s the easy access to indoor walls that have made climbing grow. At the same time it’s starnge to be out climbing in areas that used to be packed with people 20 years ago and find them almost empy now. But I wonder what would happen if all those indoor climbers went out on real rock?!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16318319937" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7320/16318319937_067a5137ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="752" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You are nowadays - thanks to the great <a href="http://www.rockandice.com/lates-news/the-seeker-said-belhaj">Rock &amp; Ice portrait</a> - probably best known for hard sport climbing, but you also do some bouldering. Is bouldering for you something to keep fit for rock climbing, or do you see bouldering as an art of climbing in itself that you enjoy?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t categorize myself as a certain type of climber; all my climbing life I’ve been doing trad, sport, boulder, big-wall, comps and even some ice. I just love to climb and like all types. I think this is what makes climbing so unique: all types, their all fun, I never get bored, always something new to learn and discover. I do more of some dicipline during certain periods of the year but would never say no to any of them - they are all climbing and thats what we do every day.</p>

<p><strong>You’ve climbed across the globe - is there a route or crag that you did that really stands out for you, and that you would recommend to any climber to visit?</strong></p>

<p>It’s almost an impossible question as I’ve climbed in hundreds of different places in about 40 countries. I think you can’t compare them, they are just different. I’ve had amazing experiences in one way or another in all of them exept some boring days of training in the gym maybe.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16478236376" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7457/16478236376_a8611e0c60_b.jpg" width="685" height="1024" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Is there a rock climbing route somewhere that you look forward to on leaving behind for others to enjoy?</strong></p>

<p>Well, I’ve put up quite a few routes on the Swedish Westcoast that people are climbing, some of them yet looking for a 2nd ascent. But because of the stupid political bolting situation in the area I’ve stopped for the moment. I’ve also put up trad routes and boulders but they never get mentioned. Anyway, I thinks it always destroys creativity when there are people who only criticize when we are trying to do something for everybody. We still have many things to learn as  humans and this can especially be said about climbers!</p>

<p><strong>How do you go about planning a climbing trip, how much time does it take to plan nine months of travelling and climbing?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t need so much time to plan these days. Usually I have some fixed plans for the year and leave some parts open. I usually do trips between 2 weeks - 3 months.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16503220012" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7302/16503220012_b10df947ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Who are your sponsors and how do they support you?</strong></p>

<p>My main partners are <a href="http://www.haglofs.com/">Haglöfs</a>, <a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a>, <a href="http://www.sportiva.com">La Sportiva</a> and <a href="http://www.c2safety.com">C2</a> who support me with gear and money. Then I also have some other brands that support me with gear and food such as Clif Bar, <a href="http://hilleberg.se">Hilleberg</a>, <a href="http://www.primus.eu">Primus</a> and Nokia. With these partners I can do that I want and I have never really had a “normal” job in my life. I will never get really rich but I’ve always done what I wanted in life - the biggest wealth if you ask me.</p>

<p><strong>Where does your next trip take you?</strong></p>

<p>For the moment I’m climbing in Perú, Bolivia and Chile in South America. In the spring I’m planning to go back to Spain &amp; France which I do every year. I also have plans for next summer and autumn but let’s first see what happens in the near future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16502501731" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8561/16502501731_ddcbbf1351_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Your family is living across the globe - your father is from Morocco, your mother from Finland and you grew up in Sweden. You travel a lot and speak six languages fluently. How do they see your career, and is it hard to see them not that often?</strong></p>

<p>I think my family didn’t like my choise in life at first, mainly because they were afraid. But they have accepted and realized I’m taking care of myself. Not seeing my family &amp; friends as often as I’d like it’s the prize I’ve had to pay to do what I do. All great things in life come to a high prize.</p>

<p><strong>You wrote on your blog that your usual yearly schedule is to train January to March at home and then travel the rest of the year. What does your training at home look like?</strong></p>

<p>I follow a 12 week training program that we’ve put together with Carlos Cabrera. I do about 10 sessions per week indoor and if possible I try to get outside on rock once a week -to stay sane. This might sound crazy but it’s totally worth it, then I can climb on rock for the rest of the year. Also, it gives me time to be in Sweden and see my family and friends. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15881673704" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/15881673704_cd8efa54fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="734" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Andy Kirkpatrick, a mountaineer from the UK, made in his essay “How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche” his first point to not have kids. You’re not yet a father, which makes climbing hard and travelling a lot easier. But do you think that at some point in time you will settle down and start a family?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, of course I’d love to have a family and get married soon. I don’t want to end up being this dirtbag dude who lives out of his van alone when I’m 50! But this doens’t mean I will stop climbing, climbing is for life.</p>

<p><strong>Said, gracias for taking the time to answer my questions.</strong></p>

<p><em>You can follow Said via his <a href="http://www.said-belhaj.com">blog</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/darsaidbelhaj">Facebook</a>.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16503220122" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7456/16503220122_9084374669_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony RX100III Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T18:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You want to go lighter than a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Full Frame Camera</a> but still want to have superb images for online and print? Then the Sony RX100III is what you want - an Ultralight Backpackers &amp; Climber’s Dream.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033934580" title="Sony RX100III Size Comparison with a Field Notes notebook by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7571/16033934580_a455c13d76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III Size Comparison with a Field Notes notebook" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’m still looking for the <em>Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> in terms of photographic equipment. It’s the camera which has only advantages, satisfies all my needs and is good enough for all my requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Print-quality photographs</li>
  <li>Nightshots possible</li>
  <li>Video capable</li>
  <li>Tiltscreen</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
</ul>

<p>That are <strong>MINE</strong>. Yours might be different. Mine are from a perspective of someone who needs high-quality photos for articles in magazines and online, likes to shot videos once in a while and does not like to carry heavy. I have plenty of colleagues who think like me, while others prefer something more substantial in terms of cameras. There’s no wrong or right and it always depends on your needs, and add in that I like to experiment and you can see why I was happy to give the <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/cyber-shot-kompaktikamerat/dsc-rx100m3">Sony RX100III</a> a spin when Sony asked me to. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033806418" title="Sony RX100III with EVF open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/16033806418_f4324c7d8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III with EVF open" /></a></p>

<p>Like usual this is no pixel-peeping review. <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-cybershot-dsc-rx100-m3">DP Review</a> does a good job looking at all the tech inside, I prefer to take the camera along outdoors and see how it performs in the field. So, 80% of the photos in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">Höga Kusten Trip Report</a> where shot with the RX100III, which means I got a full four days of photos out of the RX100III, or a total of 632 photos on one fully charged battery. That’s significantly above what is claimed (that would be 320 on one battery charge), and given that the weather on the Högakustenleden was cold and wet I find it a superb performance. It ticked one need of my list, so lets see how the others fared.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601476623" title="Sony RX100III in Selfie Mode by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8646/15601476623_65c5770695_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III in Selfie Mode" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033910680" title="Sony RX100III side with screen open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7476/16033910680_49c341d4d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III side with screen open" /></a></p>

<p>Tilt-able screen? ✓</p>

<p>The screen can be tilted fully up, great for Selfies, or at an angle, which is great if you want to shoot very low or from above your head. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033949750" title="Sony RX100III handling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7462/16033949750_519d7a2c36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III handling" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219705131" title="Viewing the view stop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7514/16219705131_dd6c0e5321_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the view stop" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601446823" title="Sony RX100III with Flash open and EVF on by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7573/15601446823_fea0a0e911_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III with Flash open and EVF on" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601438203" title="Sony RX100III taking a photo with the EVF by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7479/15601438203_b4d5205bc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III taking a photo with the EVF" /></a></p>

<p>Easy to use? ✓</p>

<p>Yeps, it is. Give it a mate in the hand who is not a camera geek and he will be able to make a great photo of you &amp; be delighted about the lightweight and easy to use camera. Sun is shining? No problem: Pop up the EVF and use it to take a photo. Although it does look a bit funny if you put that tiny camera up to your face to take a photo. </p>

<p>Print-quality photographs? ✓</p>

<p>Yes, it does produce stunning photos which have and will be printed in magazines from me. It can shoot in Sony’s Raw format which is fully supported by <a href="http://amzn.to/1LLfGPC">Lightroom</a> which makes it a great choice for professional photographers, too - I even have colleagues which only use this camera for all their photos. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15598868014" title="Sony RX100III front with open battery compartment and battery &amp; SDHD Card out by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/15598868014_e442886a44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III front with open battery compartment and battery &amp; SDHD Card out" /></a></p>

<p>Lightweight ✓</p>

<p>The RX100III is 290 g with the battery inside, with an extra 9 g for the <a href="http://amzn.to/1LLgc01">SanDisk Extreme 16GB Memory Card</a> I use. Which tips the scales at less than 300 g. Which is superb. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034258558" title="Night Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8603/16034258558_8d5ccdb6a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night Selfie" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15306067413" title="Helsinki Adventure Night by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15306067413_6fb9848e71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Helsinki Adventure Night" /></a></p>

<p>Nightshots possible ✓</p>

<p>You might think that a small and lightweight camera like the RX100III might need to have some things it does not excel at. Low light and night time photography is difficult already, usually requiring high ISO capabilities and large sensors. I wasn’t sure what I could expect from this little camera, but was positively surprised at the photos it produced in low light and at night. That Night Selfie was just after dusk, and while it’s not 100% sharp it’s a fine image, capturing the rain well, giving it a nice atmosphere. Also the indoor shot at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/helsinki-adventure-night.html">Helsinki adventure Night</a> came out superb, which ticks this point for me. Sadly I wasn’t able to try star photography with it, though I am positive that it should be possible.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220528902" title="Sony RX100III back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8624/16220528902_74fa472068_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III back" /></a></p>

<p>Video capable ✓</p>

<p>Yes, the RX100III also shoots some crisp, fine videos. It’s a bit counter-intuitive to shoot video after you took a photo, as you need to turn the dial on top into the Video mode to be able to record something. I also found the Record button at a strange location, and operating it with anything else than super-thing liner gloves is something where you can learn patience. Once it is rolling you can make adjustments to settings, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220497942" title="Sony RX100III handling with index finger on trigger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7524/16220497942_678635c6ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III handling with index finger on trigger" /></a></p>

<p><strong>And then for some further usability thoughts on it.</strong> I used the RX100III with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> and the <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/leash?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Leash</a> which I found a superb combo. I bought the <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/microplate?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Micro Plate</a> for it which is ideal with it and allows me to have the small &amp; lightweight camera securely attached to me. Speaking of small &amp; light: If you’re used to large &amp; heavy cameras this will be quite a change. I use usually cameras which are slightly bigger in size so having such a tiny camera, which easily fits in even the smallest chest pockets, is something I first needed to get used to. But then it was great.</p>

<p>Because the camera is so small people with large hands also might it difficult to operate. I have probably Medium-sized hands and found it OK to use with one hand, but usually used two. One with the finger on the trigger, the other to slightly stabilize it. Taking Selfies with the camera is easy as pie, and the Flash and EVF which can be stored away are good, too. The Focal length is 24–70 mm and the Aperture is a magnificent F1.8 - F2.8 which I liked a lot. The lens is from ZEISS which means it’s high-quality, take a look at the photos in some of the mentioned articles above or Albums underneath and you’ll see. </p>

<p>I found the battery life superb, sadly you can charge the battery online inside the camera via an USB cable, which is crap if you want to take photos with it while it loads. There’s an external Sony car charger available so at least if you’re on the go you can charge it, as well as several third-party chargers. For longer trips I’d always take an extra battery or two along, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033758968" title="Sony RX100III top and On by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16033758968_295fa5532c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III top and On" /></a></p>

<p>But are there problems with it? Well, I’m again hard-pressed to say something negative about the camera. Sure, looked at some things in isolation you could find some errors. But if I keep in mind that this is a 290 g, super-compact camera which produces superb images and has a long battery life then complaining about things like little buttons seem senseless. At 900€ the RX100III isn’t cheap, either, but there’s only a handful of cameras which play in the same league than it, and those all are a tad heavier and more expensive. </p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong>. If weight is at a premium in your pack or on your harness, but I still want to take great photos, then the RX100III would be my choice. I have <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/the-sony-rx100/">discussed with Jacob</a> about the different iterations of the RX100 before and agree that the high price might be what might keep most people getting it. But once you have it and take it on a trip, see how it performs on the trail and on the rock, in sunshine and rain, and the fine photos it takes you’re very unlikely to leave it at home. If only the lightest and best image quality does the job for you, consider the RX100III. For me it is the closest to an <em>Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> yet. </p>

<p>View <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157649751997029/">more photos of the Sony RX100III on Flickr</a> and more photos shot with it in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157648982512379/">Höga Kusten Album</a>.</p>

<p>You can support Hiking in Finland and buy the RX100III at your flavour of <a href="http://amzn.to/1BUbRPZ">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1DESZa3">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1DET2Ta">Amazon.de</a> or get it from your local <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/sony-dsc-rx100m3-kompaktikamera.html">photography shop</a> or directly from <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/cyber-shot-kompaktikamerat/dsc-rx100m3">Sony</a>. And if you think that you won’t need the latest Sony RX100 camera then you’re in luck: The <a href="http://amzn.to/1BUdbCp">RX100II</a> can be found in a tasty bundle for as low as $600 and the still great <a href="http://amzn.to/1yGsLAC">RX100</a> I found in a sweet bundle for as low as $400. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035685067" title="Views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8682/16035685067_1c22604b18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
