<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Laufbursche | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/laufbursche/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-18T11:02:08+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Leg for LAUFBURSCHE]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/a-leg-for-laufbursche.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-23T23:26:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/a-leg-for-laufbursche</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mateusz, backpacker and manufacturer of the ultralight <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">LAUFBURSCHE</a> backpacks, lost a leg in his battle against cancer. With this fundraiser I want to help him pay his medical bills and hopefully get a prosthesis that allows him to go hiking again. [<strong>Updated with winner!</strong>]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/" title="ILoveLAUFBURSCHE.com"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7176/26188616394_48ddfab21e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="615" alt="ILoveLAUFBURSCHE.com" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Mateusz and I met the first time six years ago when he joined a group of ultralight backpackers who followed my invite for an <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/02/tufwt-1-0-trip-report.html">Ultralight Winter trip</a>. We hiked, laughed, camped in the snow, went to Sauna and jumped into the ice hole together, and have been in contact ever since. I was lucky enough to get one of the very first 40D black Silnylon huckePACKs, a design which was back then and still today is revolutionary. As an Architect Mateusz has a great eye for functional design, and his backpacks are considered far and wide works of art. My “Packing your framless backpack - LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK” video is probably my most-watched video on Youtube, and it is that backpack which I today will to raffle off in support of Mateusz. </p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MDF26eJ2sqU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>As a fellow entrepreneuer I know that should sickness strike then shit hits the fan, and it’s sadly not different for Mateusz. Many other’s have written about his condition so I do not want to concentrate on it here, but instead send good vibes and support his way and a one-of-a-kind LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK your way. The pack is in great condition without any damage, is made of black 40d Silynlon with an XPAC floor, is Size L (which fits me at 175 cm very well) and weighs with all the straps attached 343 g. I guesstimate the volume at around 35 to 45 l, so it’s a great size for a week long trip in the mountains or woods.</p>

<p><em>So, how do you get a chance on winning this backpack AND help Mateusz?</em> </p>

<ul>
  <li>One lottery ticket costs 5€, and you can buy as many as you’d like. More tickets obviously increase your chances to win this unique pack and help Mateusz more!</li>
  <li>You Donate for each lottery ticket you’d like to buy 5€ to Mateusz via <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">this website</a> (<em>you can donate via PayPal or bank transfer, please follow the simple instructions given over there for your donation</em>)</li>
  <li>You send an Email with a screenshot of the confirmed donation to <em>laufbursche[ät]hikinginfinland.com</em> with your name and the amount of lottery tickets you purchased</li>
  <li>If you like, comment underneath to let others know how many tickets you have bought =)</li>
  <li>You can buy lottery tickets till the 22nd of May, Midnight Finnish time</li>
  <li>On the 23rd of May I will put all tickets in a hat and my son will pull out one lucky winner who gets the backpack!</li>
</ul>

<p>If you just like to help and have already enough huckePACKs, just head over to <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">I Love LAUFBURSCHE</a> and donate. Every donation is appreciated and helps Mateusz on the long trail of rehabilitation and getting back outdoors. <em>To read more about Mateusz condition head over to <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2016/04/crowdfunding-laufbursche.html">Outdoormädchen</a>, <a href="https://limitcamper.wordpress.com/2016/04/27/i-love-laufbursche/">Limitcamper</a> or the <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3737-ein-laufbursche-für-den-laufburschen/">various</a> <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3626-die-gute-tat-für-laufbursche-frühling/">threads</a> on <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3495-laufbursche-genesungswünsche/">Ultraleicht</a> <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3504-schulterschluss-für-mateusz/">Trekking</a>.</em></p>

<h2 id="update-23052016">Update 23.05.2016</h2>

<p>Wow, what a great effort! There were donations for a total of 201 lottery tickets, with some donations which didn’t want to enter, which raised a grand total of 1.295 € for Mateusz! I imagine that helps him with getting a ultralight carbon or titanium part for his prosthesis! The winner of the huckePACK has already been contacted and I hope she will enjoy hiking with the pack =)</p>

<p>Of course we don’t need to stop now - Mateusz is still battling with the complications of his sickness, and you can still <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">donate</a> to support him. Every small donation helps, so just drink one less fancy coffee and donate that sum instead =)</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I have no financial benefit in this campaign. Mateusz is a friend of mine and I want to help him pay his medical bills &amp; hike again in the future.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
