<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Velbon V-Pod | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/velbon-v-pod/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-02T12:08:14+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Velbon V-Pod - Worlds Lightest Tripod]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T15:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For years the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/04/joby-gorillapod-slr.html">Joby GorillaPod</a> has been my “tripod” of choice. And while I certainly still use it and often have it along on trips, in above tree line environments or when a real tripod would be more convienent than a GorillaPod, I needed something that’s still light enough to carry but can get high enough for photos, timelapses and video. Enter the Velbon V-Pod, probably the Worlds Lightest Tripod.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8570950041/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8374/8570950041_bf2f8aa725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I first read about the Velbon V-Pod a few year’s ago on Dave’s, the <a href="http://www.armchair-adventurer.com/">Armchair Adventurer</a>, blog. But it still has taken me an unreasonably long time to purchase a V-Pod, which I now, with hindsight, regret. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8572168042/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8091/8572168042_0c9f8fe4c1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>My Velbon V-Pod weighs 279 gram, has a transport length of 29 cm, is fully extended 100 cm tall and has a minimum height of 28 cm. It carries my <a href="http://amzn.to/ZXzy8j">Sony NEX-5r</a> with a <em>heavy</em> Pentax Asahi 55mm lens (body + lens = 570 g) without problems, though if you go outdoors with a Canon 7D or similar you might want to use something more substantial as a tripod. But for the M43 crowd and Point-and-Shoot photographers, the Velbon V-Pod is a superb tool. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8572072576/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8383/8572072576_14246b0ebd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>I used it since for shooting <a href="https://vimeo.com/60198868">timelapse movies</a>, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">aurora borealis and stars</a>, videos and stills. It is small enough to go inside the backpack or put it under a strap or a mesh pocket on the outside, and is ready to use in less than 30 seconds. It has a ball head which allows for great fluid movements and picking almost any position you’d like. If it is windy you can attach a weight (your backpack) to the centre strut of the V-Pod to pull it down and keep it in place.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8570973041/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8247/8570973041_b7a3a01d23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>It comes with a carrying pouch (12 g) and a holder for smartphones (25 g). Especially the latter is pretty neat (unless you have a <a href="http://amzn.to/10cFigF">Glif</a>) as it allows you to use your smartphone for videos, stop-and-go animations and photos. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8571075403/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8098/8571075403_e11c051320_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>In short: I’m sorry that I waited so long to buy the Velbon V-Pod. It’s a superb tool for photographers who use lightweight cameras, and nowadays the V-Pod finds its way into my pack on pretty much each trip, long or short. If you’re searching for a lightweight tripod for your Micro Four Thirds or similar camera, look no further. The Velbon V-Pod is the answer for us lightweight backpackers &amp; photographers.</p>

<p><strong>Get a Velbon V-Pod</strong> at <a href="http://amzn.to/XdRZGO">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/145x1P0">Amazon.de</a> (they’re not available at Amazon.com, sorry). <em>If you buy via these Affiliate Links, I earn a few cents. Don’t worry, it doesn’t cost you anything extra =)</em></p>

<p><em><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633031907155/">More photos of the Velbon V-Pod</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
