<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: backpacks | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/backpacks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-02T21:49:45+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-08T11:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What if <a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a> would go and build an alpine climbing pack that is minimalistic, comfortable, highly water-resistant and durable? Would it work also for backpacking?</em> These and other questions I answer in this review.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193953927" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/14193953927_5201bcbb49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l-505024.html">Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L</a> landed here in March 2014 and has been used various times at the local crag and in Chamonix, a week backpacking in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/lake-district/">Lake District</a> and a week climbing &amp; hiking in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/poland/">Polish Tatras</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193760149" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2916/14193760149_8ba4f829a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>This is a streamlined alpine climbing backpack with more space than it’s litte brothers (there’s a <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-25-l-505021.html?farbe=tailored%20grey">25 l</a> and <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-505022.html?farbe=electric%20orange">35 l</a> version available), made to carry more climbing gear for big ascents and/ or an overnight kit. It carries very well thanks to the Aluminium frame and easily can be used for week-long ultralight backpacking strips.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14378961872" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2926/14378961872_aeec0f6d90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>This is what Patagonia says about their pack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Light and durable nylon ripstop with excellent tear and abrasion resistance </li>
  <li>The spindrift collar opens wide for easy packing; drawcord simultaneously cinches collar and closes lid for a secure seal; additional spindrift collar deploys to protect your gear when you have overstuffed your pack</li>
  <li>Aluminium stay frame with tensioned mesh center gives the pack structure and helps to support heavy loads and can be removed for Fast &amp; Light adventures</li>
  <li>Padded hip belt can be removed to create a simple webbing hip belt</li>
  <li>Center sheath ice axe carry system accommodates a wide assortment of axes</li>
  <li>Daisy chains on front and side panels provide lashing options; compression straps on sides help manage different size loads; zippered pocket on lid provides easy access to small items</li>
</ul>

<p>What they fail to mention is that this pack is the brain-child of Steve House, one of the world’s top alpinists. This pack won’t make you climb like him, but at least you can carry your gear like him =)</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/FnWap_pZ3YU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Something I haven’t seen before is the internal frame system that Patagonia uses in this pack. It’s an aluminium frame that’s covered by mesh and that’s super flexible - you can twist it 180° so it gives the pack great freedom of movement. The DWR on the material is also very good and kept my gear inside dry during hikes in sustained, heavy rain from all angles. Also the inside rain-cover is a nice way to not need an external one when you carry more gear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624434903" title="Patagonia Ascensionist internal frame by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5530/14624434903_5969025411_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist internal frame" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After over two weeks of backpacking, climbing and scrambling with it it still shows no tears or signs of weakness. The DWR also still holds up very well, and all seams - despite some heavier loads and being fully packed - are still perfect like on day one. I think this pack will be with me for many hikes and climbs to come.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624459203" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3918/14624459203_a9bd18b0f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Patagonia Ascensionist is available in two lengths and I have the S/ M length of the pack. </p>

<p>Stripped Pack: 847
Frame: 151 g
Hipbelt: 140 g</p>

<p>TOTAL: 1138g</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417796848" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3838/14417796848_c8389e3d6c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="770" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>It’s Patagonia who made this pack so you know it has top-notch environmental credentials. ‘Nuff said!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602382524" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2939/14602382524_dd6979ab34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a wide variety of <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/kletterrucksack.html">climbing backpacks</a>, very good ones are the <a href="http://bit.ly/1qR0yaH">Crux AK-47</a> and the <a href="http://www.campsaver.com/speed-22-pack">Black Diamond Speed</a> packs. <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/">Cilogear</a> also makes top-notch climbing packs, as does <a href="http://www.mchalepacks.com/ultralight/index.htm">McHale</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14581386756" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3904/14581386756_39bdddd491_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The closure of the pack is really nice. It is easy to open and close, even if it seems like an old-fashioned closure it is a smart system in my opinion. You can close it with one hand, opening with both. You pull the cord to close it, and then put the aluminium hook through the webbing loop. Even when fully packed it’s easy to open and close and most important - it stays closed. The front aluminium hook can be moved up if it’s really fully loaded. </p>

<p>The elastic loops to tie down straps are a very nice detail. This way webbing does not dangle around when the straps are pulled tight - if you’re anal-retentive about straps and stuff dangling around on your pack and like things to be orderly you will really like this small addition to all the straps.</p>

<p>Your ice axes or <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools.html">ice tools</a> are connected to the pack via a small and durable ice axe pocket with a buckle at the front pocket and the shafts are held in place by the side compression straps. It’s a safe, good system for transport to the mountain and when you really won’t need it. For in between sections where you won’t need the tools you can store the ice axe He-Man style between your shoulder blade and strap.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14581388176" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2903/14581388176_f817a9ed5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<p>The top pocket is surprisingly spacious and I can fit a large amount of stuff in there. Map, compass, sunscreen, lip balm, snacks, shades, extra camera lens - and still room to spare. It’s fairly weatherproof too, so in case you forgot your phone’s rain cover it’s safe in there (but even safer inside the pack!).</p>

<p>For a 45 l pack the Ascensionist is super spacious. Food and UL kit for six days + 2 l water were no problem for it, and there would have been even more space - that large opening + inside rainflap makes it a very large backpack. But also a full trad kit, helmet, harness, crampons and rope + UL sleeping gear and snacks fit in there with some room left. I really like the form of the pack with the narrow bottom and the wider top - it makes for easy packing. Food or climbing gear go in the bottom, followed by down garments and rain clothes, kitchen, quilt, bivy, shelter and helmet. Water bottles I store on the top of everything for easy access.</p>

<p>So is the Ascensionist better with the frame or without? That’s a difficult question to answer. In the Lake District I had the frame in the pack and found it worked superb. In the Polish Tatras I left the frame at home and also found it excellent. Subjectively I feel with the frame it carries slightly better and transfers weight more effectively to the hipbelt. The pack has what feels like a closed cell foam pad in the back which does a good job of keeping the shape of the pack when the frame is removed and also gives a bit of extra cushioning against your back. </p>

<p>Moving with it - climbing, hiking, scrambling - is wonderful. It rides high on the waist and does not limit movement at all. As it is a streamlined pack it you also have no stuff at the sides in your way, and low chances of the pack snagging something along the route or trail. As the pack is narrow and not very deep it’s close to the body so you can squeeze through tight passages, and your centre of gravity is close to where it’s supposed to be. The thickly cushioned shoulder straps are comfy also on long days, as is the hip belt. The gear loops on the hip belt are solid and a welcome addition to rack gear on long routes.</p>

<p>Oh, and you also can attach the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Designs Capture PRO</a> wonderfully to the shoulder straps!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417878278" title="Hiking in the Polish Tatras by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5507/14417878278_ff97606b7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking in the Polish Tatras" /></a></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>When climbing with the frame in the pack I often would hit my head on it when looking up, which is not good. Removing the frame solves this, but it’s better with the frame inside for carrying heavier loads. If it’s possible I’d imagine making the internal frame shorter would solve this, as would a gap for the helmet when climbing/ looking up. </p>

<p>You can remove the padded hipbelt (and save 140 gram weight) but it’s too complicated - mainly because the wide webbing belt is sewn to the pack and can’t be removed. So you need to thread the webbing through the padding loops to take it off. I’d wish that everything could have been removed easily - I don’t see much sense in using the webbing as a hipbelt.</p>

<p>Water Management is not as straight forward as I’d like it to be. There’s no hydration system exit and no side pockets, so you need to take the pack off to drink. When climbing this is fine as you likely take the pack off at the belay and then can drink, but when hiking it’s not convenient to stop every 30 minutes to take the pack off to access your water bottle. You could attach your water bottle with a carabiner to the gear loop on the hipbelt, though I think that would be annoying if you have a bottle dangling in front of your legs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417828779" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3924/14417828779_643901874a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>At the moment the Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L is my favourite backpack. It carries very well, is large enough for week-long trips - be it climbing or backpacking - and can take a lot of abuse. It’s weatherproof, easy to pack, the big haul loop makes it easy to grab the pack &amp; put on, and the cushioned shoulder straps and hip belt make it comfortable to carry also on 30 km days with 2000+ m of ascent. Most importantly it does not bother me when climbing or scrambling and gives me freedom of movement to go to those high places I enjoy so much! If you’re in the market for a large-volume alpine climbing backpack I can really recommend the Ascensionist 45L from <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia.html">Patagonia</a>.</p>

<p>Oh, in orange it also looks great - Hup Holland Hup!</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Get your Ascensionist pack at <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l-505024.html">Unterwegs.biz</a> if you are in Europe, from <a href="http://bit.ly/1qG5cXo">CampSaver</a> if you’re in the USA or directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1lPYO9Z">Patagonia</a> everywhere else. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602411384" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3917/14602411384_f4f4f02911_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Packing your raft]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/packing-your-raft.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-17T10:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/packing-your-raft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I really like the <a href="http://bit.ly/WUaRuk">ULA EPIC</a> for packrafting, though I never liked how they suggested to pack your packraft on it. Until I figured out a much better way to carry it.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/packing-your-raft.html" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2820/10324096124_daec431087_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/WUaRuk">ULA Equipment EPIC</a> was made for packrafting, and I have been using it for over three years. It’s a great pack for that activity, the possibility to use it with dry sacks of different volumes is excellent. However, I did not like how the packraft was supposed to be carried in the pack: Rolled together at the bottom of the pack, even strapped underneath it. Even when packrafts are light, 2,5 kg at the bottom of a pack isn’t comfortable for me. So I started to experiment to find a better way to carry the packraft, with the weight further up.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9534961449/" title="Wet packraft &amp; paddle"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7432/9534961449_d2ae90436e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wet packraft &amp; paddle" /></a></p>

<p>My first tries saw me using a mat (a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-z-lite-sol-isomatte/">Z-Lite</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-ridgerest-solite-isomatte/">RidgeRest</a> usually) at the bottom to push the rolled packraft further up. That worked OK, but wasn’t perfect. Then, on a packrafting trip it hit me: Why roll the raft at all - it could just as well be laid out double against the backpanel of the EPIC, and the dry sack goes in front of it. The thought was implemented, and I was surprised about how much better the whole pack carried in an instant! With hindsight this isn’t surprising - traditional packing of a backpack suggests you pack heavy items in the centre of the pack, close to the back. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10324280143/" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3706/10324280143_ce55d2e92d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10324123586/" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2830/10324123586_04e4a399b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10324133366/" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3733/10324133366_eb1368e674_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a></p>

<p>So how to pack it? After the raft is dry, I fold my packraft twice - the two sides are folded into the middle (the seat area). This makes for a more compact package than folding it just once in the middle and makes it only slightly wider than the backpanel of the EPIC. I then open the EPIC completely up, fold the packraft twice and lay it down. Dry sack on top, close the side and top buckles, slide in the paddle and pull the straps tight, and you’re done! With longer rafts - I got the small Alpaca - you might need to fold it maybe four times, but it still should result in a fairly flat package.</p>

<p>This works especially well with the <a href="http://www.alpackaraft.com/">Alpacka packrafts</a>, but also should work just fine with rafts from <a href="http://bit.ly/ZDiyFO">Klymit</a>, <a href="http://flyweightdesigns.com/">FlyWeight Designs</a>, <a href="http://www.supaiadventuregear.com/">Supai Adventure Gear</a> and others, even if these packrafts are lighter and more compact to pack. You could employ this technique also with another backpack, as long as the pack has enough volume and is wide enough. You also can pack it inside a dry sack this way, though both of these options are a bit more fiddly. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10324127325/" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2888/10324127325_ee111960fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hyperlite Mountain Gear IcePack]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/hyperlite-mountain-gear-icepack.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-18T21:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/hyperlite-mountain-gear-icepack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ice climbing does involve a fair bit of gear. There’s tools and crampons, ropes, screws, a helmet and belay jacket as well as safety gear. You could start each approach wearing all of that gear, or you just could use a lightweight backpack and hike in comfort to the base of your climb. The <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/2400-ice-pack.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear IcePack</a> is such a lightweight backpack. <em>A Living Review</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595259281/" title="HMG-IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8243/8595259281_55c7b2c11e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG-IcePack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>
<p>I have used the HMG IcePack for six days of ice climbing and dozens of days of walking, hiking and cycling. One of the ice climbing trips was even a fast &amp; light trip, in which I was able to fit all my camping gear plus ice climbing gear in the pack! Overall I have used the IcePack well over a year.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8536787938/" title="The @HyperliteMGear Ice Pack also works very well as a filming bag. #photography #videography by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8386/8536787938_9ca7ced992_o.jpg" width="612" height="612" alt="The @HyperliteMGear Ice Pack also works very well as a filming bag. #photography #videography" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>
<p>The IcePack allows you to carry all your ice climbing gear, and includes dedicated attachment possibilities for crampons, ice tools, and ropes. It also works very well for backpacking with camera gear, as the crampon attachment can hold a heavy tripod (mine is 2,5 kg) without problems, and the ice tool straps can hold trekking poles.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659088153/" title="041713_1842 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8106/8659088153_c84555e7ba_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="041713_1842" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Exterior Dyneema patch with elastic straps for attaching crampons</li>
  <li>Two shock cord systems for securing axe shafts</li>
  <li>Two removable, shaped aluminium stays</li>
  <li>Padded back panel</li>
  <li>Roll-top closure</li>
  <li>Top Y-strap compression system designed to keep pack contents tight as well as to hold other gear and equipment</li>
  <li>Two side compression straps with side release buckles</li>
  <li>Padded shoulder straps</li>
  <li>Padded, removable hip belt with gear loops for racking carabiners</li>
  <li>Adjustable sternum strap with self-tensioning elastic</li>
  <li>Double-reinforced pack bottom</li>
  <li>Internal mesh pocket</li>
  <li>Haul loop handle</li>
  <li>Bar tacked reinforcements on all stress points</li>
  <li>100% rainproof</li>
</ul>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/65279320?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>
<p>I’m 175 cm tall and my Size M pack fits me perfectly. If you’re ordering a IcePack it is worth to take the time to measure your back to get the correct length.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659092873/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8111/8659092873_514deec3df_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>
<p>It’s a completely stripped down pack, which can be modified to suit your needs. It uses Hyperlite Mountain Gear’s Cuben Fiber/ Polyester hybrid material, and the crampon attachment is unique, too. Overall the innovations in this pack is more in what is NOT there. </p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>
<p>It’s a high quality pack, though some stitching could use a bit more attention to detail - it decreases the overall impression of what is otherwise a good backpack. The material is super durable and besides some cosmetic blemishes (mud and tree sap) the pack is still in top condition after over a year of use.</p>

<p><strong>Update May 2013:</strong> Hyperlite Mountain Gear informed me that the stitiching has been improved on the newer packs and shouldn’t disappoint anymore. Furthermore, they are now taping the seams of the body of the pack with cuben fiber tape, this further reinforces the stitching and enhances the already very good water resistance of the pack.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659090579/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8121/8659090579_da374d3ef5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660188178/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8109/8660188178_2ab7933695_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>
<p>The complete pack in Size M weighs 900 g on the spot. Here’s the breakdown of the weight</p>

<ul>
  <li>114 g removable stays</li>
  <li>152 g removable waist belt</li>
  <li>634 g backpack</li>
</ul>

<p>My preferred setup is without the waist belt, which brings the weight down to 748 gram.</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>
<p>The pack is made of HMG’s Cuben Fiber/ Polyester hybrid material and hence is made of oil based materials. Thus it shouldn’t be thrown in the garbage like ordinary rubbish, you could try to either recycle it via your local outdoor shop or inquire from Hyperlite Mountain Gear how to recycle the IcePack at the end of its life cycle.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659117043/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8101/8659117043_577b1d7105_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660218174/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8126/8660218174_6b1ed763f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659117449/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8116/8659117449_58ba259742_b.jpg" width="1024" height="428" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>
<p>I have used the IcePack more for hiking and cycling than for ice climbing, though it certainly excels for the latter activity. I have an <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/gregory-alpinisto-50-rucksack-alpine-gold.html">Gregory Alpinisto 50</a>, which should have a larger volume than the IcePack, though it is the other way around: The IcePack with its about 40 l of volume fits more gear, and more easily, than the Alpinisto. The IcePack also has a large opening and it is easy to pack and unpack. </p>

<p>Because there’s no separate internal pocket for small-ish stuff (at least not in my version, it looks like this might have been addressed in the newer packs) it’s not easy to organise in case you want that kind of stuff. The inside mesh pocket is “Meh” and while I haven’t yet cut it out I don’t see much use for it. But packing is rather straight forward: You just pack your gear bottom to top into the pack, close the velcro and roll it closed. Crampons and ice tools fit easily to the front and are very easy to attach, and a CCF pad or ropes can be attached via the top or side compression straps. This makes packing fast and convenient, though if you want a place to store your keys, wallet and cellphone you either should take a small stuff sack for them, or keep them on you.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660209450/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8110/8660209450_47065266dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659120151/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8659120151_8cb1afc771_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8659119769/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8108/8659119769_e98ffc3bc7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<p>I rarely use the hipbelt, because I feel that even with a heavy rope and a full pack it’s not needed, hence I detached it. The pack carries with the stays very well, and while with a light load and without the stays it still is good to carry you gain a lot of extra carrying comfort with the stays, so I always have them in. On the trip to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html">Korouoma</a> I carried about 10 kg of gear in it, and it was still perfectly fine to carry without the hipbelt and just using the padded shoulder straps. </p>

<p>HMG advertises that the gear loops on hip belt can be used for racking carabiners or ice screws, but for ‘biners the loops are rather tight and wide so I wouldn’t bother with it - they’re too difficult to get in or out, unless you want to attach them permanently for racking gear or use Ice Clipper ‘biners - then . If you use the Petzl ice screws with the flute storage, then racking them on the hipbelt is easy, though I prefer to rack all gear on my harness. I haven’t climbed with the backpack on, though, so if you climb very long multi-pitch routes you might find the hipbelt’s storage possibilities useful, though on the other hand the hipbelt might get in the way with your harness.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660197492/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8124/8660197492_79db1d095d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660199762/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8109/8660199762_ef098a88e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>
<p>There are heaps of ice climbing specific packs available, but only a few which are truly lightweight. <a href="http://www.mchalepacks.com/">McHale</a> makes exclusively custom-made backpacks which are raved about by their owners, and <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/packs.html">CiloGear’s WorkSacks</a> also have been very positively reviewed. The <a href="http://www.ks-ultralightgear.com/p/ks-alpisack.html">KS Alpisack</a> is an ultralight climbing pack Made in Japan, and also some European companies like <a href="http://www.camp.it/EN/template01.aspx?codicemenu=1170">CAMP</a>, <a href="http://grivel.com/products/ice/rucksacks/">Grivel</a> and <a href="http://www.crux.uk.com/en/rucksacks.php">Crux</a> produce lightweight backpacks. From the big players <a href="http://www.blackdiamondequipment.com/">Black Diamond</a> and <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com/">Mountain Hardwear</a> make very good and light climbing specific backpacks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587936563/" title="All packed up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8365/8587936563_6ac57e172b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="All packed up" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>
<p>Nick has put his <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/?p=563">HMG IcePack</a> through a lot of climbing and hiking, and finds it superb. <a href="http://www.thegearcaster.com/the_gearcaster/2011/12/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ice-climbing-pack-review.html">Amy likes the IcePack</a> for its major reduction in weight, and <a href="http://larsonweb.com/blog/?p=296">Kai liked his pack</a> so much that he bought a 2nd one. Finally, the <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Alpine-Climbing-Pack-Reviews/Hyperlite-Mountain-Gear-Ice-Pack">Outdoor Gear Lab gives it 4 Stars</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>
<p>Overall it’s a great pack in use: At the base of a climb or the start of the approach you easily can get your crampons and tools off the pack, and they’re as easily attached back to the backpack after a climb. The rather big storage of the 2400 cu model is big enough for fast &amp; light climbing &amp; camping weekends as well as for backpacking trips and the pack carries extremely well thanks to the stays. While the padded back is minimal it does the job well. The IcePack is very durable and takes the abuse from sharp tools and crampons without problems, and the material is thus far 100% waterproof - in neither rain nor snow the gear inside got wet. It is easy to attach gear to the outside to the backpack: The side compression straps with their buckles can hold a Z-Lite or thin CCF pad, and the top Y-Strap keeps your rope and helmet in place.</p>

<p>A couple of points of improvement would be to pay attention that the stiching is top everywhere, the option for a side pocket to easily store a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos flask</a>, and a zippered inside pocket for small items. Other than that the IcePack is my top choice for ice climbing trips, as I value its great carrying capabilities while still being lightweight.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633269353761/">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-hyperlite-mountain-gear-icepack">Where to buy the Hyperlite Mountain Gear IcePack</h2>
<p>Buy it at <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/index.php?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a> | <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/2400-ice-pack.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8660188966/" title="HMG IcePack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8109/8660188966_81cb96b5b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG IcePack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>
<ul>
  <li>In the next season I will add more on how the pack performs when climbing, if there were any failures, and more overall experiences</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Disclaimer</em><br />
Trekking-Lite-Store.com provided me the IcePack free of charge for testing, and paid me 1 kazillion € to review it.*</p>

<p><sub><sup><sub><sup>* One of these statements is not true.</sup></sub></sup></sub></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
