<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ireland | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ireland/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-10T11:40:56+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Ireland's Wild Atlantic Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T22:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is the Wild Atlantic Way on your bucket list? Then you want to grab this travel guide to Ireland’s wild west coast!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183102302/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Cover"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7074/27183102302_ee6f87d84a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Cover" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last year I was lucky enough to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">explore Ireland</a>, hike the IAT and go sea stack climbing. What caught my interest and brought me to the Green Isle, however, was the Wild Atlantic Way: The world’s longest coastal touring route which goes from south to north along the west coast and is over 2.500 km long. There’s all kind of adventures to be had along the WAW, from visits in picturesque Irish villages and their pubs to bigger towns and their cultural offerings. However, <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</a> helps you find the off-the-beaten-track gems and takes you outdoors into the fresh, Irish air (and occasional rain shower!). </p>

<p>On 224 pages <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> takes you from the south in Kinsale to the far north of Malin Head along the coast. In seven chapters - divided by county - you can start to explore the Wild Atlantic Way. Do you fancy surfing, sea stack climbing and lots of remote wilderness? Then head to Donegal in the north. Do you prefer a cable car ride to an island, trying your luck fishing or going cycling? Then Cork in the south is a good place to start your adventures! Wherever you decide to go, <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> will have an insider tip ready for you. The seven county chapters are further divided into sections, each coming with their own little overview map to give you a feel of the land. Hundreds of gorgeous photos will get you in the mood to explore, while the detailed introduction chapter gives tips on when to come, what to bring and any other question you may have.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101542/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Inside"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7529/27183101542_ffe5d299bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Ireland is beautiful, and <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> helps you discover the green isle beyond the hustle and bustle of Dublin and the other big towns. Jam-packed with beautiful photos that inspire to visit the described places on Ireland’s west coast this book helps you plan your ultimate outdoor adventure itinerary. Three Rocks Books has created another stunning book which showcases some of the best scenery, sights and places in Ireland, and no matter if you plan to explore the Wild Atlantic Way on a roadtrip, by bike or public transportation, it will make sure you will see the true Wild Atlantic Way. <em>My tip: Book a flight to Ireland the same time you order this book!</em></p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Three Rocks Books</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/25pjt1d">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i48S">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUK3G">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[David Flanagan: Rock Climbing in Ireland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/david-flanagan-rock-climbing-in-ireland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-01T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/david-flanagan-rock-climbing-in-ireland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ireland has more to offer than <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">Sea Stacks</a> - there’s superb crags across the country. David Flanagan’s “<a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a>” helps you plan your trip to the Emerald Isle - which has climbing on half a dozen types of rock to offer, at sea cliffs, in the mountains and beautiful crags!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17307673186" title="Rock Climbing in Ireland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7759/17307673186_e118d35b78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Climbing in Ireland" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Fellow climbers will easily be able to relate - get a new guide book into your hands and immediately you start thinking about a trip to the area the book presents. While I just returned from Ireland a couple of weeks ago browsing <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a> has me thinking about when I could again visit the island for some climbing - and plenty of awesome climbing there is in Ireland.</p>

<p>The book starts of with the basics you need to know about climbing in Ireland - Access and Conservation, Equipment, When to Visit, Accommodation and how to get around the island. A Crag Table lists all 22 crags and what sorts of routes you will find there, and then right away dives in with describing the different crags. These include a introduction, tips on accommodation in the area, what you could do on rainy or rest days, conditions and directions to the crag. A large overview photo often shows the crag and the different sectors, and a small, basic overview map helps with navigating. The Topos and Route descriptions are coming with good details and some great photos of the climbs will get you in the mood for a route. And finally, a Route Index at the end of the book lets you find a route quickly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17331763072" title="Rock Climbing in Ireland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8735/17331763072_7285ee4f9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Climbing in Ireland" /></a></p>

<p>I loved the clean, minimalistic and well-structured layout of the Guidebook. It was aesthetically very pleasing to read, with a nice &amp; clear typography and great topo photos - these are something that make a climbing guide book not merely good, but great. What I missed was that some crags didn’t have information on accommodation and rainy &amp; rest days tips, I think for many people visiting from abroad it would help to have a recommendation for where to stay and what to do when the weather is shite. This is my only complaint (<em>and something you can find out yourself with the help of an online search</em>), and overall I would highly recommend this book to anyone who is planning to go rock climbing in Ireland. The beautiful guide book will make you look forward to visiting this beautiful island with the fair weather and gives you with over 400 routes in it more than enough inspiration of where to go &amp; what to climb!</p>

<p>Buy Rock Climbing in Ireland at your local book store or climbing gym, order it directly from the author at <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Three Rock Books</a>, or your local taste of <a href="http://amzn.to/1GCHy2y">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1zkr3e1">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1bKkvdP">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sea Stack Climbing in Ireland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-20T23:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ashfall Quartz. Ebb. Tide. Swell. Mix it together, throw in a rubber dinghy and you have the stuff for a Sea Stack climbing adventure.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002240157" title="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/17002240157_6342150a0a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>From the distance Berg Stack looks like a wee little rock in the North Atlantic Ocean, just off the cost of An Port in County Donegal, Ireland. We - Iain, our guide, a photographer and an US American journalist - slept the last night in the Port Cottage and now a blue sky &amp; sunshine have us frolicking in the superb weather. <em>“Lets go and check out the swell and tide”</em> Iain announces. We pack up our climbing gear and the 40€ rubber dinghy, bought at a Toy Shop - three at a time, they’re not that durable and walk the <a href="http://www.walkni.com/iat/">IAT</a> path up to the sea stack.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589476163" title="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8697/16589476163_e1526639df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left" /></a></p>

<p>What looked like a wee sea stack from the lawn of the cottage turns out to be a 25 m high sea stack with a large ledge at the bottom, beautiful cracks and pin scars lining it from bottom to top and a Great black-backed gull with its nest on top. Oh, and an angry Atlantic Ocean with a two to four metre swell, making for not a good time to cross. We still inflate the unnamed dinghy, Iain gives me the instructions of how to assist him when he will board the sea worthy vessel to establish a tyrollean traverse on Berg Stack so I can get over, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17023512169" title="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8693/17023512169_4922bee743_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The we sit &amp; wait. Observe the swell. Finally Iain decides we’ll come back at high tide later in the afternoon, when the sea should be calmer. Adrenaline that was build up in anticipation disappears, shoes go back on and we go for a nice hill walk, checking out Cnoc na Mara - the Sea Stack we had originally planned to go up, but with this sea that would have been too much risk. The views are spectacular, the valley deserted and I can make out a dozen of superb spots for a wild camp.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021928808" title="A look up Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5322/17021928808_206ed924b5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look up Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>Sea stack climbing is less about climbing, really. Sure, it helps if you can climb well and know how to place gear - it’s all trad - but it is just as much about the skill set an Alpinist has: Patience, Risk Assessment, Speed &amp; Efficiency. Maritime skills &amp; knowledge are also essential, knowing when the tide is coming in, how high the swell is, if it is safe, being patient. Finally, a bit of daring for an adventure is also needed. After all, if you think paddling in a toyshop rubber dinghy on the Atlantic is insane, then sea stack climbing is nothing for you.</p>

<p>We’re back on the main land and observe the sea. It is high tide, the swell is still high but every now &amp; then there’s a calm moment - and one of these Iain uses to paddle over to Berg Stack. An euphoric cry echoes over the sea and you can see how a load is off his shoulders. He sets up an anchor for the tyrollean traverse, and during the next calm moment he’s back on the main land. We discuss the strategy and then it all goes quick: the dinghy is back in the water and Iain is in it, surfing the swell, a 240 cm sling connecting him to the tyrollean. A calm moment comes, he paddles in and I jump in - and just as quick out again off on Berg Stack. We both howl a cry of victory, a victory over the tide and swell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021935758" title="Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5343/17021935758_1ab7fb492e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>From here on it’s all basic rock climbing: Harness and rock shoes come on, Iain racks up and we tie into the rope. I stand barefoot on the ledge, the swell crashing on the rocks around. Iain leads up a variation the <em>Cormorant</em> which he probably has climbed a dozen times and before long an “Off belay” call echoes down to me. It is a nice route with great hand and foot holds up till the middle to the arête, then it goes around the arête and up a wet corner, which is also the toilet of the Great black-backed gull and its offspring which were kind enough to let us top out there. A moment later I stand on the top of Berg Stack next to Iain, high-fiving him, and again we both let out a howl of victory. But this is not a sports climb where you just clip into the chain and then rappel off. No, this is a sea stack. And the sea is angry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002250497" title="Roping up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7651/17002250497_95a7de41ea_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Roping up" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002062747" title="Me on Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8706/17002062747_44b293c870_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Me on Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17209684205" title="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5448/17209684205_822563f419_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The easiest way off the top back to the ledge is to down-climb a corner to about two meters above the rushing sea, and then traverse the sea stack on superb ledges &amp; holds back to where we started. We short-rope and five minutes later stand next to our dinghy. The sea is lower, more rocks can be seen as the ebb comes in, but the swell is still high. <em>“Lets wait till the tide is out and then walk off”</em> Iain says, and so we deflate the dinghy which has served us so well on the way here, pack up and wait. Wait for the water to retreat, for the swell to let us escape from this rock.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589483823" title="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5342/16589483823_e771dc38d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183741396" title="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8700/17183741396_a98415b910_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell" /></a></p>

<p>The sea does not see a reason for letting us off, it wants to keep us. The swell is high and white foam rushes over the barnacle-covered rocks, which would otherwise allow us to easily walk off. The sun throws its last rays on the main land, we can see the hut from our ledge and the comfort of the warm fire in the cozy cottage and slowly we’re getting cold &amp; hungry. Low tide arrives, but the swell still throws up large, foamy waves over the rocks we should have just walked off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183747146" title="Cold feet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17183747146_b904d8e834_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Cold feet" /></a></p>

<p>Iain goes first, jumps the large gap and makes it just to the top of a big rock when a wave comes in. He brings me my approach shoes and throws them over, as I do not fancy jumping barefoot on wet, slimy rocks and risking a broken ankle. Waiting for the right moment I too make the jump, and a final victory cry echoes from the rocks - the land has me again. We pack up and in the falling dusk walk to the cottage, where a warm fire and cool beer are waiting for us. My appetite for sea stack climbing is awakened, but first I’ll need to hike further on the International Appalachian Trail to Northern Ireland, to return another day for more sea stack climbing adventures.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17022143920" title="Patience by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17022143920_703730e92f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patience" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>
<p>There’s a <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/sea_stack_guide">free Sea Stack Guide book</a> if you want to go sea stack climbing - it has almost all sea stacks in it. A selection of sea stacks you also find in the <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a> book. I would suggest you do your first sea stack with Iain from <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/">Unique Ascents</a> and learn the ins &amp; outs from him about the sea and getting safely on and off the sea stack. He’s also a great guy and you’ll have a lot of fun on a day out with him. You’ll need a sea-worthy vessel - maybe <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Rentals:::34.html">loan a packraft</a>, but be sure you also know how to use it and have an idea about the tide, swell and weather forecast. If a sea stack is too much adventure, check out the <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/undiscovered_donegal">Donegal rock climbers guide</a> and visit one of the local crags, though there are also <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=CfM3DTcHcS8">calm days on Berg Stack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17208905321" title="Port Donegal Cottage by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8763/17208905321_de9c296ae9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage" /></a></p>

<p>If you plan to climb in the area around An Port stay in the <a href="http://port-donegal.com/">Port Donegal Cottage</a> - either book via their website or on <a href="http://www.ownersdirect.co.uk/accommodation/p8069109">Owners Direct</a>. It has a wonderful cozy feel and relaxing in the bathtub after a day out on the sea will be so good that you don’t wanna go out. It sleeps eight and with some luck Roland, the owner, will be around and delight you with his stories from far away places.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021740458" title="Port Donegal Cottage Inside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7725/17021740458_6b9517e048_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage Inside" /></a></p>

<p>The nearest village via a road is Ardara where you find several accommodation options like the <a href="http://www.bayviewcountryhouse.com/">Bayview Country House</a> and also shops and the <a href="http://www.nancysardara.com/">Nancy’s of Ardara Pub</a> for a after-climb pint, though it adds at least 45 minutes driving to your approach. For rest days go to Glencolmcille in the neighbouring valley and visit the <a href="http://glenfolkvillage.com/">Folk Museum</a> where you can see how people lived in the last centuries in the area, grab a good cup of coffee and a bite.</p>

<p>Gear wise you will need Trad gear as there are no bolts. Bring cord and slings if you want to abseil and need to build an anchor. Most of all, be patient with the sea and be open for the adventure!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
