<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mountaineering | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mountaineering/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-10T11:25:44+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/gaston-rebuffat-starlight-and-strom.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-06T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/gaston-rebuffat-starlight-and-strom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A book review of Gaston Rébuffat’s classic “Starlight &amp; Storm” - a <em>Must Read</em> for anyone just remotely interested in going outdoors.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16730495671" title="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8629/16730495671_870bcfb3e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I ordered Starlight &amp; Storm and a bunch of <em>“Classic Mountain Literature”</em> last autumn, probably after getting just another recommendation that it’s a superb book. Getting a book recommended several times sometimes makes me hesistant, but well, I love to read and as the mountains are far away at the moment reading about them is pretty much the next best thing (after browsing <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html">photography books</a> of the mountains). Rébuffat’s most well-known book is likely this one or <a href="http://amzn.to/1MbylRU">The Mont Blanc Massif: The Hundred Finest Routes</a>, and I think both books will be found on the bookshelf of a well-read mountaineer, alpinist or hill walker.</p>

<p>The book starts of with a short biography blurb on Rébuffat’s life which is followed by an introduction from Jon Krakauer, which is followed by yet another introduction, a Foreword and then finally you get to read Rébuffat’s words. Puh. Well, the good thing is that the good stuff starts right there with Rébuffat’ story of his ascent of the Grand Jorasses. This and the following chapters, where he descibes his adventures with friends of the great North Faces of the Alps is what really makes this book worth reading. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everything about the climbing of it was a joy, and as we climbed I seemed to understand the meaning of our exploit. It was not the increasing nearness of the summit,
or the climb in itself, that filled us with a quiet joy, but the feeling that mind and muscles were fulfilling their intended function. Somehow we were “in the right place.”
- Gaston Rébuffat, Starlight &amp; Storm, The North-east Face of Piz Badile</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16111754843" title="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8595/16111754843_88fc5b01dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm" /></a></p>

<p>I loved the accounts of how he tied up with clients and friends, how they spend nights on these big faces and enjoyed the starlight and peace of the night but welcomed the first rays of sunlight in the morning after a cold bivy, or how they turned around to come back another time because of bad weather. The Brotherhood of the Rope is strong in this book, and you feel that the people Rébuffat was climbing with were more than just climbing partners - they were brothers, sharing a single objective, living together on the rock, between the sky, ice, snow, wind and rain. </p>

<p>The chapters are short enough so that it’s easy to read them before going to bed or commuting to work in a week, and every Mountain chapter is accompanied by a Black-White photo of the mountain in question. What bothered me slightly was that the height and distance measurements where given in illogic feet, but apart from that I loved every part of the book. It’s a fascinating read, not just for alpinists and mountaineers, but also for people who wonder why one would climb a steep, inhospitable rock face. If you can not get to the mountains any time soon, I recommend you pick up this book and dream of having a bivy on one of these Northfaces! Buy the book at your local book shop or order it online from <a href="http://amzn.to/1NoHTMW">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1DRShVx">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/18WyyMF">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Top of the World - Herausforderung 8000er]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/on-top-of-the-world-herausforderung-8000er.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-30T14:56:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/on-top-of-the-world-herausforderung-8000er</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you like to know more about the history of the highest peaks on this planet, then <em>On Top of the World. The New Millennium</em> as <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/list?back=9db5a3e1b607eeefc414b4266862f7c2&amp;xid=11345923">Herausforderung 8000er</a> is called in English, should be on your bookshelf. Packed with detailed information and chronics from the first ascents to the newest route attempts, Herausforderung 8000er is required reading if you want to climb one of the highest mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16213778198" title="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7355/16213778198_ccd2dbe9e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="765" alt="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>After reading <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters.html">8000 Metres</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html">Alpine Exposures</a> Herausforderung 8000er from the <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/">Tyrolia Verlag</a> is the third book in the mountaineering corner on my bookshelf which is about the highest of peaks. Besides detailed topographic photos and lists of the first ascents on the different routes it are the captivating stories from the ascents and expeditions which are worth getting this book. </p>

<p>The book has 17 chapter - after an introduction each 8.000 m peak has its own chapter where stories about the first ascents, the different expeditions, tragic accidents and solo ascents are given, with lists on the first ascents on the many routes on the peaks. It gets interesting in the “The New Millennium” sections, where stories about more current ascents are told. So the book goes from Annapurna to Shisha Pangma and then finishes with an outlook on the next decade and all relevant statistics.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16399669221" title="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/16399669221_1d67e65f4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="796" alt="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World" /></a></p>

<p>Not just the stories are captivating, also the superb photos from the mountains &amp; expeditions will let you forget the time when you’re reading this book. It highlights how some 8.000 m mountains nowadays can be attempted by normal people while at the same time alpinists on the cutting edge still find new routes up these same peaks. If you dream about standing on the top of the world on one of these mountains, then you should get Herausforderung 8000er - <em>On Top of the World. The New Millennium</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/leseproben/9783702232948/leseprobe.pdf">View the sample</a> and then get the book in German directly from <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/list?back=9db5a3e1b607eeefc414b4266862f7c2&amp;xid=11345923">Tyrolia</a>, your local bookshop or <a href="http://amzn.to/1uIeFNA">Amazon.de</a> or buy the English Edition at <a href="http://amzn.to/1uIf6ay">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1CiQkpf">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jon Griffith: Alpine Exposures]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T16:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jon Griffith’s photo book <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/pages/book">Alpine Exposures</a> is the culmination of over ten years photographing in the Alps. Full of breath-taking images that depict some of the best ways to move in the mountains, this is the coffee table book you wanted for those days where you can not head out yourself or need some motivation to get up at 1 am.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16050375500" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/16050375500_2694d126ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I have been following Jonathan Griffith’s photography since many years via his <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/blogs/chamonix-conditions">blog</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Alpine-Exposures-Jon-Griffith-Photography/120793041299250">Facebook</a> so when word came out that he was working on a photo book I knew it would be superb. Jon regularly kept readers and Fans up to date about the process of producing and publishing this book, and just in time for the holidays the alpine exposures came out last November. </p>

<p>Alpine Exposures starts off with a Foreword by Ueli Steck which is one of the best forewords I have read in a while. Honest and appraising, highlighting why Jon takes such good photos (because he’s a mountaineer first, photographer second) Ueli sets the tone for the book and gets you excited to turn the pages. Jon follows that up with an equally touching Introduction before you meet some of Jon’s rope partners and then you can start to enjoy the photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16211793956" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/16211793956_541519cb26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<p>The book is written in three languages: English, French and German. This lingual trinity is well executed with a good layout that’s easy to read and follow throughout the book. It’s high-quality paper that depicts the superb images very well, and it’s a pleasure to read the book. The photos all are from real situations, so no fake “Lets go to the Aiguille Du Midi and do some shoots on the Cosmiques” kind of photos. The seven distinct chapters in the book show Jon’s favourite photos from Alpinism, Skiing, Climbing, Landscape, Ice Climbing, Flight (BASE and Paragliding) and Work. In between the photos are here and there short anecdotes from climbs and work trips, and some climbs are highlighted in longer photo essays which not just give you an idea of the route if you’re planning to climb it yourself, it also adds variation to the book and makes it very interesting for alpinists that want to attempt some of these routes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16050174968" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7517/16050174968_925b8dd4f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<p>This is the coffee table book you wished you would have gotten as a present from Santa last Christmas. Cover to cover it features breathtaking photos from the mountains and people having fun in them, and will inspire you to make a trip to Chamonix as soon as possible so you can experience the beauty yourself. It’s a book for alpinists, climbers and photographers and you’ll have a hard time putting it down once you start to read it. <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/kx49us95qxbuj0f/Alpine_Exposures_Sample.pdf?dl=0">View a 60 page sample online</a>, if you’re convinced (and you will be!) you can buy your copy of <em>alpine exposures</em> directly from Jon at <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/products/alpine-exposures-photo-book-10-years-of-photography-by-jon-griffith">Alpine Exposures</a>, your local book shop or order it online from <a href="http://amzn.to/1I10mLL">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1xYMvBb">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1APW8EE">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-05T10:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A shoe that lets you climb almost like <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">Ueli Steck</a>: The Rebel Ultra GTX from <a href="http://www.scarpa.it">Scarpa</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15890321735" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7570/15890321735_fac69de43c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received the Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX over a year ago in November 2013. I climbed ice in Korouoma, Vaasa and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html">Abisko</a> with them and was mountaineering in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Chamonix</a> and the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">Polish Tatras</a>. All in all they have seen over four weeks of use and have been used for ice climbing, mountaineering and hiking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14604399775" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX &amp; Grivel Air-Tech crampons by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3863/14604399775_16e2e604d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX &amp; Grivel Air-Tech crampons" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>Similar to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html">Scarpa Rebel Ultra</a> the Rebel Ultra GTX is made for technical mountaineering, rock climbing and speed climbing on ice &amp; mixed terrain with snow. It can be used with a wide variety of crampons.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15888352111" title="Grivel G20 Crampons &amp; Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7528/15888352111_9a89f61bba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grivel G20 Crampons &amp; Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Scarpa Sock-Fit plus</strong> is the tongue, flex-point and collar made from a single piece of S-Tech Schoeller® elastic fabric that’s both tough and breathable</li>
  <li><strong>Re-Active AC XT sole</strong> </li>
  <li>The <strong>KCN-Tech fabric</strong> is made from Kevlar®, Cordura® and Nylon that’s woven together to form a hard-wearing, waterproof &amp; breathable fabric</li>
  <li><strong>Carbon Fibre insole</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Y-Structure</strong>: Is the microfiber calf support with injected exoskeleton plates and a mesh endoskeleton for good structure and maximum lightness</li>
  <li><strong>Vibram® Mulaz sole</strong></li>
  <li>A <strong>Gore-Tex® Duratherm lining</strong> keeps your feet dry &amp; warm</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15704309739" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX and Grivel G20 Crampons by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7473/15704309739_0e40dcf6b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX and Grivel G20 Crampons" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Again Ueli Steck has helped to develop this boot, and you can see it from the weight and the technical features. While the sock-gaiter-construction isn’t new I have not seen a lot of mountaineering boots which use it. The Y-Structure, KCN-Tech fabric and Re-Active AC XT sole stand out on this booth, as does the very good fit &amp; the light weight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15889704852" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7473/15889704852_aecafa05ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The shoe is hand made in Italy and is from a quality point of view absolutely superb. The fit is impeccable and even after four weeks of hard use the boots still look like new. Only the reflective tape in the back of the shoe shoes some wear, otherwise boot and sole still look like new.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417800278" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5078/14417800278_0203ed722c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>773 g per boot in Size 42,5 or 1.546 g for the pair. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15704318359" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7499/15704318359_c268bdd03c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>The boots are hand made in Italy. If you have worn it out you could have it resoled at your local shoemaker or you can recycle it via your local recycling scheme.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15270675413" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX - Back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7567/15270675413_b4b29d5fe3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX - Back" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p><strong>Ice &amp; Mixed climbing</strong> I did with the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/grivel-g20-crampons.html">Grivel G20 crampons</a> to the boot and it’s a fantastic combination. The G20 are 424 g per crampon which means one shoe &amp; boot are 1197 g, which is about 150 g lighter than with the Phantom Ultra boots on. This might seem trivial but feels like a big difference. What I enjoy most with the Rebel Ultra GTX is, however, the freedom of movement my feet have in them. I can pretty much fully move my feet like I could in a trailrunner, with the difference that I can connect a pair of crampons to them and climb ice with them. This is especially useful for mixed climbing, but also on more tricky ice climbs in narrow places this freedom of movement helps in better foot placements. The high sock works like a gaiter &amp; keeps water and snow out and the carbon insert makes the sole nicely rigid for climbing. In short, the climbing in them is great, I really loved the freedom of movement they gave me. </p>

<p>The last winter was super mild and I wasn’t able to test the boots in severe cold weather, but the -5°C I used them in, often while standing around on snow and ice, where no problem for them and I had warm feet and toes in the boots. When constantly moving one might be able to wear them in even colder temperatures, say to -10°C, but beyond that I reckon they will be not warm enough and it’s better to put a warmer boot on. One option that I haven’t tried is using an overboot with them in colder weather for a little bit of extra insulation, though I almost think that just using a warmer boot would be lighter - though less versatile.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15864534166" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX in Chamonix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15864534166_7c1da26c08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX in Chamonix" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Hiking</strong> in these boots is possible but really wasn’t something I liked. While they allow great freedom of movement they are lined boots, so walking from the Chalet to the Cable Car in Chamonix, a 15 minutes walk, was not enjoyable as it was +35°C in the valley, which meant I had super-sweaty feet by the time I arrived at the house. In the Tatras I hiked on two occasions with the Rebel Ultra GTX boots, once in warm weather which again was not good, and once in the pouring rain, where they were fine. I had moist feet &amp; boots after hiking four hours in the rain in them, but they were warm so it was OK. They did also dry almost completely over night. However, when I know I need to hike long distances in the summer I would always take my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals OSO</a> along for it, as I much prefer to hike in warm weather in them.</p>

<p><strong>Mountaineering</strong> in the Alps and Tatras I did most of the time with the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-air-tech-new-matic-steigeisen/?pid=81">Grivel Air Tech New-Matic</a> (453 g per crampon) but I also tried the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-xlc-390-steigeisen/">CAMP XLC 390</a> (254 g incl. optional Antibot). The weight difference between these two crampons is almost 200 g so not trivial. I did climb more with the Grivel Air Tech New-Matics and do like them a lot, and these two crampons show that you can use the Rebel Ultra with either a plastic harness or a front bale. The light weight and freedom of movement of the boot of course are great for alpine climbs and the sole is sticky on rock and allows for precise foot placements. I still would switch to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/scarpa-stix.html">climbing shoes</a> for more demanding/ technical climbs, but if it are easy routes you’re doing the Rebel Ultra GTX are more than capable. Add in good grip on snow &amp; ice and you have a very efficient mountaineering boot.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083979134" title="Scottish Mixed, Swedish style by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3529/13083979134_05c1a80c5f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="877" alt="Scottish Mixed, Swedish style" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>The <a href="">Scarpa Phantom Ultra</a> is a warmer and heavier boot which might attract the same people who’re curious about the Rebel Ultra GTX. If we look at other brands the <a href="http://bit.ly/1xAiXwT">La Sportiva Trango Cube GTX</a> and the <a href="http://bit.ly/1AhNGww">La Sportiva Batura 2.0 GTX</a> are both lightweight mountaineering boots which can be used for the same activities as the Rebel Ultra GTX.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15889670892" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7471/15889670892_4fe3a5cbc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I’m hard-pressed to come up with something that could be better in this boot. I am sure Scarpa and Ueli had their reasons to use Gore-Tex® instead of OutDry® for this shoe, personally I feel OutDry® is slightly better at keeping moisture out, dries faster and breathes better, but I think the Gore-Tex® lining does a good job in this boot. So really nothing to complain.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15890337425" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX with Grivel G20 Crampons attached by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7497/15890337425_9735b0f75f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX with Grivel G20 Crampons attached" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX is a beautiful <em>and</em> ultralight mountaineering boot that is excellent for early and late season ice &amp; mixed climbing and summer mountaineering. It keeps your feet &amp; toes warm till at least -5°C even if you’re just standing around in the snow or hang in the belay, and with the Vibram® sole it is also well suited for easy alpine climbs. I think if you look to up your ice, mixed and alpine climbing by shedding weight and going lighter the Rebel Ultra GTX is the right boot for you. I love my pair and am always happy to put them on, because I know a good day in the outdoors lies ahead of me with them on my feet.</p>

<p>Some more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157645579555695/">Rebel Ultra GTX Album</a> on Flickr.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Buy your Rebel Ultra GTX Boots at <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/tuotemerkit/scarpa">Partioaitta.fi</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx-bergschuhe/">Bergfreunde.de</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/scarpa-rebel-pro-gtx-mountain-boots/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Backcountry.com</a> (<strong>Best Deal!</strong>), <a href="http://bit.ly/140EvFm">Campsaver.com</a>, <a href="http://camu.fi/pages/miesten_asusteet/kengat/kengat/rebellitegtxvuoristokengatpetrolorange.html">Camu.fi</a>, <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorstore.com/haku/?q=Scarpa">ScandinavianOutdoorStore.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1K6s7EI">REI.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15702812168" title="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7550/15702812168_3958206a3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T12:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ve probably seen a trend in my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">book reviews</a> in the last years: They’ve been more and more about mountaineering and climbing. Why that is so I’ll explain at another time, but now I want to take you along and tell you about the latest book I have read, <em>8000 Metres - Climbing the World’s Highest Mountains by Alan Hinkes</em>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15985413000" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8658/15985413000_e521caa7ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There’s 14 8.000 m peaks on this planet and Alan Hinkes is the first British Mountaineer to have successfully summited all fourteen of them. In his splendid coffee table book “<a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/tab/detail/iid/1/show/description#.VKZk6cbvR_0">8000 Meters - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</a>” he tells the stories and shares his fantastic photos with the reader. Its a chronological layout and after a Foreword, Preface and Introduction we start at Alan’s first 8.000 m summit, Shisha Pangma, which he climbed in 1987. </p>

<p>From that year one Alan has been almost every season in the Himalayas and Karakoram on a quest to climb 8.000 m peaks, even if climbing all 14 of them wasn’t something that he set out to from the start. His writing style is very enjoyable: Honest, down-to-earth and lacking hyperboles which easily could sneak itself in when writing about climbing the highest peaks on the planet. The thoughtful texts describe the experiences of climbing the high mountains, what kind of mental and physical difficulties one can face, from the waiting game in base camp while sitting out bad weather and passing frozen corpses high on the mountains to climbing difficulties and getting up and down these peaks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15986690559" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7463/15986690559_90c9064a27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World &#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<p>Alan’s climbing Motto is <em>“No mountain is worth a life, coming back is a success and the summit is only a bonus”</em> and throughout the book he also highlights the importance to have enough power reserves for the descent. What happens if you don’t have these Alan has seen in his friends on some expeditions, which burned themselves out on the ascent and then had no energy left for the descent, which often is even more dangerous than going up. </p>

<p>In between chapers there are small anecdotes from Alan’s encounters with fellow mountaineers like Reinhold Messner and Jerzy Kukuczka or the Trek-Ins to base camps and local cuisine. These loosen up the already enjoyable peak stories. A real highlight for me are the fantastic photos Alan has shot during his ascents and from his travels to these two mountain ranges. The photos were shot before the rise of automatic digital cameras and so one needed to know how to adjust ISO, Aperture and Shutter Speed to get great results, and the photos in this book are proof that Alan knows his trade. I have spent a lot of time just browsing the photos, tracing the lines described in the texts to the summit, and enjoy the vast views which you can have when standing on the top of the world. </p>

<p><em>8000 Metres - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</em> is a highly enjoyable book that shouldn’t be missing on your bookshelf if you like mountaineering, alpinism and are dreaming of the highest peaks of the planet. The honest &amp; evocative writing is on par with the superb images in the book, and if you ever hope to stand on top of a 8.000 m peak you will do well to read Alan’s book and follow his Motto!</p>

<p>Get the book at your local bookshop, directly from <a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/title/8000-metres#.VKZejsbvR_0">Cicerone</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/1wIIMnr">Amazon.de</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1xzM7fy">Amazon.com</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1yehuvP">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
