<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: International Wilderness Guide School | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/international-wilderness-guide-school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-24T15:03:42+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wilderness Guiding]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/wilderness-guiding.html"/>
    <updated>2011-08-04T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/wilderness-guiding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
Events aligned in a fortunate way yesterday. I will be out guiding on my first paid gig as a wilderness guide starting on Sunday for a whole week, returning to the beautiful &lt;a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalhikingareas/hossa/Pages/Default.aspx"target="_blank"&gt;Hossa Hiking Area where I spent two weeks earlier this year during the winter.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Hf8mUpR2b2fUL4xZvZwNPiBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-GvT436oSNm8/TYSFPZcmGWI/AAAAAAAAEK8/HgkvjG8OHLI/s640/_DSC1195.jpg" height="271" width="640" /></a><br />The last time I was in Hossa, there was plenty of ice and snow around.<br /><br />It was on pretty short notice - a text message yesterday afternoon asking me if I could jump in and guide a tour, starting this coming Sunday, for a whole week. A call to my wife, a look at the programme, a call to Urpo at &lt;a href="http://www.upitrek.com/"target="_blank"&gt;Upitrek, another call to my wife, and it was settled - I will be going Sunday up north to guide for Upitrek for a whole week! I was a bit skeptical, as I have &lt;a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1277447934/ultralight-a-z-the-video-guide-to-lightweight-back"target="_blank"&gt;a bunch of &lt;a href="http://korpiconsulting.com/index_en.html"target="_blank"&gt;work cut out for me at the moment, but after my wife encouraged me, I decided to go. A chance like this doesn't come along that often, so better take them when they appear! It is also a splendid opportunity to practice my guiding skills, and make these important connections in the very small guiding business circles in Finland.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/rBoSRh9HRiK8q76cKTDLszWiupv70N-RGKSfyQFBX78?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-q0hMBqBWJNg/TjqKViEGUcI/AAAAAAAAFD0/-fpltOoDVXA/s640/Screen%252520Shot%2525202011-08-04%252520at%2525203.01.58%252520PM.jpg" height="193" width="640" /></a><br />Weather-wise I hope it is a bit better than this longterm forecasts predicts.<br /><br />The tour I will be guiding will operate with a base camp, and small excursions in the surroundings of the Hossa Hiking Area will take place every day. Hiking, canoeing, a visit to a reindeer farm, bear watching and visiting 4000 year old rock paintings are on the itinerary, together with a warm Sauna (and swimming!) each evening. It will be quite the opposite to sitting in a office in downtown Helsinki, where I am this week.<br /><br />Best of all: I will be camping the whole week out under my new &lt;a href="http://gossamergear.com/shelters/shelters/cubictwinn-tarp.html"target="_blank"&gt;Gossamer Gear CubicTwinn and be sleeping in my new &lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/26912303"target="_blank"&gt;BPL Vapr bivy! As the weather will be wet but warm, I reckon the BPL Cocoon 240 quilt will be what I take, and I also will bring my &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/04/first-look-tenkara-fly-fishing-gear.html"target="_blank"&gt;tenkara fly fishing gear along - Hossa is a popular fishing destination, and I wasn't able to go out fishing a lot yet this year. Maybe even try &lt;a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Jetboil/"target="_blank"&gt;a new stove? Oh, and while I will be "roughing it" outside in bivy and tarp, the guests will sleep in a beautiful log cabin. Probably they more comfortable and smart way, looking at the weather forecast =)<br /><br />As you might guess, I am pretty excited about this! Being outdoors with guests, showing them the beauty of the Finnish forests and lakes which I love so much, is what I set out to do as I did the Wilderness Guide education. Most of all I am very proud and happy that my wife actually encouraged me to go - Kiitos rakkani!<br /><br />So, there will be some radio silence here while I am out, obviously. You always can browse past trip reports and articles, or take a peak at my &lt;a href="http://youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst"target="_blank"&gt;Youtube and &lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/hendrikmorkel/videos"target="_blank"&gt;Vimeo videos. Or, a really extreme proposition: You could go out hiking yourself ;) <br /><br />Happy trails!</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[International Wilderness Guide - Professional Examination]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/06/international-wilderness-guide-professional-examination.html"/>
    <updated>2011-06-23T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/06/international-wilderness-guide-professional-examination</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
Four weeks ago, right after we came back from the &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2011/06/jongunjoki-and-ruunaa-river-paddling_14.html"target="_blank"&gt;canoe trip, we had our Professional Examination. As I know that many readers are following this story of my IWG education, I thought to share it with you - also future students certainly will appreciate to know what is in store for them!<br /><br />The Professional Examination has three evaluators: A teacher from the school (non of our own teachers, obviously), an entrepreneur who has his own guiding business and a wilderness guide. All three where really cool guys, friendly, funny and with plenty of experience between them. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Hwy6t3bMCulAxVpGK6QsnnfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-DYh6JjmuiBE/TgJDVe7cbzI/AAAAAAAAErs/oKtyjL2ARjc/s640/P1020460.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />Nature knowledge session.<br /><br />So, the story starts on Tuesday morning at 8 o'clock. We each get a map, and will be told later on with whom and to where we need to guide. They went in alphabetical order, which meant I was somewhere in the middle. Our Aussie and Belgian classmates had the honours of going first and setting the benchmark. We jumped in the cars and drove off into the forest, where our two teachers would drop us and take the cars back. <br /><br />The task was to navigate to a point on the map, off-trail of course, and en route disclose some nature knowledge - be it about birds, trees, mosses or any other flora &amp; fauna is up to oneself. The rest of the class was instructed to be "good clients" and don't make trouble, and to top things of we were also seriously lucky with the weather - the thermometer was upwards of the 20°C mark and it was nice sunny. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/v_2f5nRwz7143e5PLQWa-HfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-y1fc8dlVgUs/TgJDcRR2g3I/AAAAAAAAEr4/7gcFAC4jkPM/s640/P1020466.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/i8Wcc7CjfisY_JQIHW3OunfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-JdX09gdODiI/TgJDhNgeHxI/AAAAAAAAEr8/oC1Zdik4yq0/s640/P1020471.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />Onwards through the woods.<br /><br />The navigation &amp; nature knowledge part was done fine by everyone, and the last part of the journey was to be traveled via canoe, paddling some three to four kilometer over the lake to our final destination. Once we arrived there, we loaded the seven canoes back to the trailer and immediately got our next tasks.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8G2yzpWbMZF9N07YlWEeBHfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-iJYsPFRr_rk/TgJDlHbya_I/AAAAAAAAEsE/s3SEtYvhDYg/s640/P1020476.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />Arrived at the canoes! <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/5BVMTIKPceFWSteELM3JZ3fAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-bbkHJjMyiGI/TgJDos4GDJI/AAAAAAAAEsM/8vZkpciyWUg/s640/P1020483.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Task I.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/5Cj_0TxflT3de7J7Br9_x3fAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-jd9fDCl0GiY/TgJDp8kzT7I/AAAAAAAAEsQ/tpp5KJT7w1c/s640/P1020484.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Task II.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/nwUmiWfHJxgrN-h2gZOvOnfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-9-W43NnFOGQ/TgJDnds8AkI/AAAAAAAAEsI/puqX_kjkpME/s640/P1020479.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />My camp.<br /><br />We had three hours to build our camp, the fireplace &amp; toilet, and start carving; while at the same time we were called in for additional tasks. It really was very fast paced, and the time flew by. I was testing the sharpness of my Gransförs Bruks axe and found out that it is sharp enough of to cut a good piece of skin of my hand, and thus made use of first my own First Aid kit and then consulted my classmate who's a nurse, who did a superior job than me. Continue with a bit of a dressing =) <br /><br />The "in-between" tasks were to explain fishing laws in Finland and setting up a rod &amp; reel for pike fishing, followed by demonstrating your knowledge about sharpening your puukko and knots, and finally using a GPS. The first three were no problem, and while I was able to use the GPS to get the location coordinates, I misunderstood the second part of the task and did poorly in it. In hindsight I found out what was wanted: We were giving coordinates and needed to locate these on a map. I was able to do this, but because I misunderstood and thought we should locate our current location, I failed this part (Future exam takers probably want to know that the coordinates given are not the coordinates of the current position, but of another place. If you know how to read GPS coordinates on a map it should be no problem to find the right spot =). <br /><br />This took a bit longer as expected (11 students doing all of the above), so at 21 o'clock we gathered around to hear the final task of the day: Prepare your own dinner with the given ingredients, on a wood fire, time is 90 minutes, evaluators will come by to sample your dish. Ingredients at our disposal: A complete perch which you needed to prepare, potatoes, onions, turnip, carrots, dill, half a lemon, some butter, oil and creme as well as several spices. As much as possible needed to be used, and I used all except the creme; and you needed to start your fire not before you had collected your ingredients. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/V2uzZfAwqW0y1hTVY2oCFHfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-SqeYQsulSE0/TgJDsE0IQaI/AAAAAAAAEsU/f4_XCfDGJpc/s640/P1020486.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/SGnk4DjaBkWFPKyqEnpVznfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-8Ta0pHEl23A/TgJDtY0MOXI/AAAAAAAAEsY/vq_hqi4ABa0/s640/P1020487.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />Cooking &amp; the finished meal. <br /><br />I opted to filet &amp; fry the perch, boil the veggies in water, salt &amp; butter and garnish the whole thing with a slice of lemon and some dill. I was the first to finish cooking and got good marks for my dish - it was a tad to salty they said, though I need to point out that Finns &amp; Central Europeans are on different saltiness levels. So all in all I was happy, and yes, it tasted fab - it was a smart move on my side to loan a frying pan from the school, as without that cooking would have been slightly more difficult!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/zFObhy9jFL55lVUXiyQjZ3fAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-24fGI20cILc/TgJDucG6iBI/AAAAAAAAEsc/-nb0oOdsUds/s640/P1020488.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Eating dinner with a fine view.<br /><br />After cooking and eating I continued to carve a bit, though as dusk was setting in, as did my tiredness - I got up at 5 o'clock that morning - I decided around midnight to go to sleep. I went into my lovely LAUFBURSCHE tyvek bivy, said good night to the army of mosquitos sitting on the no-see-um mesh and went dreaming. <br /><br />At six thirty I got up again, the sun already was shining since a few hours and at seven o'clock we needed to be ready for the next tasks. Yeps, more tasks, more cooking! Eggs, bacon, bread, salad, tomatoes, cucumbers, needed to be transformed into a palatable breakfast. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/c2deK5pIaDcy9LCGZwkzAXfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-Wigz-mhn9Gg/TgJDyvKNvaI/AAAAAAAAEsg/VeT8C5-Yq-o/s640/P1020496.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><br />I opted for a rather basic fried bacon &amp; eggs with veggies sandwich, which was well received. The evaluators came to check our camp, while we again went one-for-one through the task of explaining a Optimus Multifuel stove. After I successfully went through that I explained the teacher how my BushBuddy Ultra worked =)<br /><br />The next task was to break up camp. An evaluator came by to check if we were able to break camp and "Leave No Trace" - I was so good in hiding my fireplace that he didn't find it =) Then I needed to explain &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/05/packing-your-frameless-backpack.html"target="_blank"&gt;how to pack my rucksack, and show how and what I packed. No problem, though the evaluator looked and listened with interest as I was explaining about ultralight gear, frameless backpacks, sleep systems et al. <br /><br />The final half an hour I spent carving:<br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/C5V33JN798x9h_9LPR1A_XfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-KQThq6PUAM0/TgJD4MLDFkI/AAAAAAAAEsk/dOnEGiYM0xw/s640/P1020497.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />Not pretty but OK. Spoons are a pain if you don't have a lot of time or a curved knife. <br /><br />That were all tasks done, and being the first one packed and ready I was also the first to go and have the personal talk with two of the evaluators. They asked me how I think it went, and after I briefly stated how it was in my opinion, they gave me feedback on the different tasks. Everything was very good to excellent, except my GPS failure. We then had a short talk about why I wasn't on the Bear Ski, and after we had sorted that we shook hands and I walked off, having passed the practical part of the Wilderness Guide examination.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/mVdTM_869BgOumkNbExkeHfAqv-B7lrLSjHHz1K0beQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-1b3Mp0SaSdE/TgJD6SRqJlI/AAAAAAAAEso/0MdE-JeM10o/s640/P1020502.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Guess which one is mine ;) !</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jongunjoki and Ruunaa River Paddling Expedition - Part III]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/06/jongunjoki-and-ruunaa-river-paddling-expedition-part-iii.html"/>
    <updated>2011-06-14T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/06/jongunjoki-and-ruunaa-river-paddling-expedition-part-iii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
And the final installment of this rather long trip report!<br /><br />---<br /><br />On the way to the &lt;a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/page.asp?Section=5445"target="_blank"&gt;Ruunaa Hiking Area we stopped in a small village, where we shopped some groceries - that means German Bratwurst, bananas, apples and more chocolate for me! After this brief stint into civilization we continue to the next basecamp, the Siikakosi parking and fire site at the end of the Ruunaa river. The site was "meh" in regards to "Great places to pitch" but I found a halfway decent site with a nice view on the river, even though the wind was blowing mighty fine where I was located.<br /><br />The evening exercise was to scout the two last rapids which we would run tomorrow. Now Jongunjoki was a small river, and Ruunaa was quite a different ballgame. A good thirty or more meters across, deep and fast this was a big river, and so where its rapids. The last rapid was Siikakoski, a mere Class I - but because of its 1,2 km length, and being right after the Class II Murrookoski, quite different from the Class I rapids on Jongunjoki.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xPTTeGtoKkFDtvPSOec38-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-04C-SgK7egg/TeJ-v9TWg9I/AAAAAAAAEf4/BJfZjoJELIY/s640/P1020284.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Off you go.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/E3dYE67mY1PEINZCTiY4XeAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-bnt22B_51e4/TeJ-xiUYCOI/AAAAAAAAEf8/g1vleU5Allc/s640/P1020287.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Siikakoski bridge. In the Ruunaa Hiking area there were plenty of bridges for walkers to cross the river on dry feet.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/kfHShTuVRgzJTB5UoX18iOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-uSgG4nbAu6M/TeJ-_dTXwRI/AAAAAAAAEgM/ydfK6_rB8Vg/s640/P1020313.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/QLthVCECJqw9tLhnR5FnFeAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-zIOVWCVwDD8/TeJ-2WIWgxI/AAAAAAAAEgA/3kRbpEmQKS8/s640/P1020302.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />One of the surely dozens of laavus along the river, a fine view and great soundscape. Fishermen will love the installed smoke ovens where you can smoke your freshly caught trout and grayling!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/PH-ljsN3lIo4pP-9xLw5f-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hzwIcXgwW-g/TeJ-8WH11UI/AAAAAAAAEgE/O564NcHOkHY/s640/P1020312.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Jeq0xQF53F5LAMP3jZ-n4OAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-uZ3rZs9cWoU/TeJ_DG0b2CI/AAAAAAAAEgQ/x4NgQqM0pc8/s640/P1020315.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Murrokoski rapid, a fast Class II<br /><br />Tuesday, a full day paddling on Ruunaa. Wake up early, breakfast, pack the belongings needed for the day, hop on the car and drive up to Matkalahti. While we unpack and load the canoes and kayaks, and generally lounge in the sun, the cars depart back to camp and one comes back. A lot later than expected we start, happily the weather is brilliant, warm sunshine makes paddling a bliss and even makes the strong headwind less of a problem - at least on the first stretch.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ocZamQhY9bi9ZAbIcwMYm-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-yOgfOWs49jM/TeJ_QvxZi8I/AAAAAAAAEgk/as3PEXb0N1g/s640/P1020334.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Departure.<br /><br />Haapavitja was the first serious rapid that day, Class II, some two or three very deep haystacks, big rocks, more haystacks, several hundred meters long. Being with someone in a canoe I haven't paddled with before, this was a serious test for our teamwork. Despite some very different approaches (I was the bow paddler, my preferred position in a canoe) we managed to go down the rapid without capsizing, despite going sideways into the haystacks. Some miraculous saves on both ends were likely responsible for that, and down the rapid we went to collect the canoe of some classmates which were less lucky. <br /><br />As we had two capsizes at this rapid, and it already being fairly late, we had lunch at the Korpiniemi laavu before continuing. The wind picked up, and our traverse of the Neitijärvi lake was quite strenuous despite trying to stay in the wind-sheltered side of the lake. After a good hour of paddling into the headwind we reached the Neitikoski rapid, Class II that day due to the "low" water. A big stopper wave right there in the middle, followed by some deep haystacks.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/QmbRd3gHZtMC9KvB5gLD9OAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Gy8lB9BxVPc/TeJ_XDxkVAI/AAAAAAAAEgs/W-X18iErVOQ/s640/P1020346.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Neitikoski. <br /><br />Kayaks were to go first, with canoes to follow, one at a time. Daily leader in kayak: Pass. Petri: Pass. Teacher: capsize. Next kayak: capsize. First canoe: capsize. 2nd canoe: capsize (that was us). Third canoe: capsize. Fourth canoe: Pass! (That were our two 50 year old ladies - really awesome =). Final kayak: capsize.<br /><br />What a ride. The key success is simple: Either go full power forward for the stopper wave and paddle like a madman (or woman!) to get over it, or backwards ferry-glide on the right side of the deep stream in order to go down the right, easy side, bypassing the stopper wave. The latter was our plan, but our communication and different paddling techniques made short work of that plan - the main stream picked us and all I said was "Full power forwards" with my stern paddler saying "wtf? Oh no..." as we went diagonal for the stopper wave. For a moment it looked like we could make it over it, and possibly we were, but then we tipped backwards and took a bath in the cold stream, holding on to our paddles and canoe.<br /><br />Petri was there right away to tow our canoe, and us holding on to it, to the nearest shore. From there we saw how the other canoes and kayaks, one for one, capsized and were rescued. Our two ladies, who made it through, reported that they were sitting nearly knee-deep in water and that there wasn't much space left and they also would have capsized. But as it were, they were the only ones who made it through in a canoe - Congratulations again on this way! <br /><br />As nearly 80% of the class and a teacher took a dip, we stopped at the laavu not far away from the rapid, lighted a fire and dried ourselves. I grabbed some nuts, dried fruits and a Snickers Bar I had saved just for such an occasion (!) to warm myself up from the inside, while drying out my clothes by the fire. But we only had come half way, so soon we continued, over another lake into the headwind. <br /><br />Over the next few rapids - Kattilakoski, Murrookoski and finally Siikakoski - people started to shiver, lose motivation and concentration and hence we had quite a few more capsizes. My stern paddler and me, well, we had a few more miraculous saves from near-capsizes, conversations which are too foul to write down here (What happens on the river, stays on the river!) and picked up a few more paddles, canoes and swimmers until we made it to the campsite. <br /><br />After this long hard day, paddling on a big river, we all went off to our shelters, switched into dry clothes and grabbed our cooking gear to head back to the common fire, where everyone was cooking while we discussed the day gone by. Preparation for the final day. The day that my classmate and me would be daily leaders.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/T1ujSznxLWTkBiCeMFigv-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-IvDKCIQj6ac/TeJ_JyryTEI/AAAAAAAAEgc/B3hh4FArVNY/s640/P1020328.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />The end of the Siikakoski rapid. On the right side by the yellow speck (its a rowboat) was our camp.<br /><br />I wake up on Wednesday morning at 6.30 and the sound of rain on Spinnaker informes me of less than great weather. On my round to wake up the other people, the feeling that some are less motivated and interested in paddling is split pretty much in the middle. As we gather around 8.30 around the fire to discuss the day ahead, it becomes clear that we have a good 50% of "difficult" clients which don't want to paddle but would prefer hiking - the many capsizes from yesterday together with the rain and wind make makes this quite understandable. Negotiations with Petri and our teacher, and among my daily leader partner and me bring different possibilities to the front, and after we made one decision, some more thinking and discussing, and a final decision we decide to split the group in two - paddlers and hikers. This way we make everyone happy, a much better decision than the compromise we decided on earlier - it is good to be flexible in decision making =)<br /><br />Everyone grabs the gear and we drive off to Neitikoski, where the hikers started their day trip back to camp while the paddlers try their luck against Neitikoski again and then continue to paddle to camp. My daily leader partner, an additional driver (as I don't have a driving license) and me stay with with the cars and organize the afternoon and evening programme. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xqWrf_bVmvGIvwPkzdHTBeAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-2AMiHEy6oTM/TeJ_dkxirRI/AAAAAAAAEg0/qD4VrA184ew/s640/P1020375.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/YGTKU6iEFOafVdutfxLTmOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-WktlkdEvqEA/TeJ_f-FRNMI/AAAAAAAAEg4/OPOzbr0-mIE/s640/P1020376.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/UTTYeLRDoQ-beuwcDrSX4uAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-tVv-HT_V0Ss/TeJ_ikBXEwI/AAAAAAAAEg8/cjSBitXIiK4/s640/P1020377.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/7FUj2DaZfVvaakGyjJDEsOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-dEpHuzza_Wg/TeJ_mL20yjI/AAAAAAAAEhA/piQ2E-nPO08/s640/P1020401.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Also teachers and paddling instructors capsize sometimes at Neitikoski =)<br /><br />With watching the paddlers try their luck over Neitikoski (only one who made it over it!) and checking with them that they're OK, we head of to the nearby Nature Centre to pick up the key for the Sauna, have a look at the exhibition, a coffee and pulla before checking out a nearby bird watching tower. Back at camp I start a fire and not too soon at all, as the paddlers already arrive. They didn't take a lunch break and paddled all the way down, and hence are happy about the fire and being able to eat now. <br /><br />I check with Petri if it is OK for me to wander off and do Siikakoski in my packraft, on my own. Permission granted, I wander the 1,5 km up, inflate, motivate, put on my helmet and PFD and jump in. An interesting ride, and very different from the previous ones: Deep haystacks with headwind mean I need to give 110%, leaning forward and paddle strongly to not flip over and capsize. In the end I make it without problems, and even was able to practice a bit of eddy hoping and ferry gliding in the Alpaca. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/gk_EOse74Q5-7P72FNTbL-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-HqtLOUVIfCI/TeJ_spPAjJI/AAAAAAAAEhI/cVxk2We_Jx4/s640/P1020410.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Packraft vs. kayak!<br /><br />I arrive with a smile on my face back at camp, around the same time that the sun is making an appearance. A tad later our hikers arrive, and with the clients gathering their sauna gear we set off in the cars. We drop off my daily leader partner to start heat the sauna while I take the "clients" to a nearby bird watching tower at the Reposuo mire area, and after having a look around we head back to the warm sauna. Ladies first, men next (men just need a lot longer in sauna =), sausages, pancakes, banter, a rain shower, sunshine, happiness.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/E6U075k3AuqYaWE-EGN6pOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-wJKxcxrx_yY/TeJ_vPdPteI/AAAAAAAAEhM/fnB7nOc_giw/s640/P1020412.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/OlzM4u4toWnQxqrGrpQLhuAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-eq-iHgYYudE/TeJ_zGpZs5I/AAAAAAAAEhU/6W53mbxs9eE/s640/P1020421.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Reposuo info board and part of the mire. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/amjETY3UVsSkHO6CnDzWp-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-XCgYFwoeiuo/TeJ_2pUcAOI/AAAAAAAAEnw/s5XhHAikWm4/s640/P1020428.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />View from the Sauna.<br /><br />We get feedback on our daily leader performance, which was largely positive though a comment came up that none of us two daily leaders where actually with the "clients" but that on the other hand it would not have worked any other way. Everyone is happy, pancakes are shared and after that we leave the sauna and head back to camp. A final fire, instructions for the next day, and we head of to bed. <br /><br />The next day is getting up at 6.30 o'clock, packing, breakfast, loading the car and heading back home. A way too long nine hour drive and we're back in Kuru, unloading personal gear and heading soon after to the local pizza &amp; beer joint!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/gtkRTHxBd2aFOsQJQ4YLzOAMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-t7XEveuupxQ/TeKAH5Hif6I/AAAAAAAAEn4/wL00aMC8YDQ/s640/P1020450.jpg" height="640" width="480" /></a><br />Basecamp the last three nights.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Xl6Fil3xvj6ZcznIXpeRZ-AMDokLuBhQJU4joJoy3cQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-NYhpVlLb6RE/TeKAJYuUJUI/AAAAAAAAEh8/W8Rm9IGO-h4/s640/P1020457.jpg" height="480" width="640" /></a><br />Last morning - time to head home!<br /><br />So that was the final expedition-like trip of the Kuru International Wilderness Guide school, and in my opinion the best one. Responsible for that is largely Petri, who was an excellent teacher and who made paddling fun, interesting while also on land disclosing some useful tips &amp; tricks for us Wilderness Guides to-be. And of course, for me personally, for being so cool and supporting with the packrafting - not a given, and very appreciated. <br /><br />Reflections then? Well, canoeing is fun. While UL principles are not super necessary (canoes can carry plenty of gear without much influence on how the canoe runs), I think they allow for nicer paddling if you're lightly loaded. Paramount to good paddling is good communication and a similar paddling style - I only had that with one person, communication was perfect: It was without words. Whatever my action in the bow, I knew my partner in the back would do the corresponding strokes, resulting in a perfect paddle, be it on a lake or down a Class II+ rapid. Without a good partner canoeing is still fun, but adds a bit of unneeded stress - thoughts like "Will he/ she jump ship/ get nervous/ remember the right strokes/ clamber the railing?" will go through my head, and that's stuff I don't need. <br /><br />Kayaking is fun as well. It is fast - I imagine 60 to 80 km days under fine conditions are no problem, given that you're starting early and paddle late. Navigating the seakayaks on rapids was "meh" and I am not intending to do that again; however, play kayaks and white water kayaks like the red one next to my packraft above should be fun on rivers. <br /><br />Problem of both canoe and kayak is that they are made for paddling, and not hiking &amp; paddling (let alone cycling). That is fine if you want to paddle, but is a problem if you want to combine different activities. Yeah, portage is possible, but doing any serious distance with carrying/ pulling such a vessel on a trolley is not possible. Which brings us to the packraft.<br /><br />The perfect vessel for hiking AND paddling (AND cycling). Very forgiving on white water - it was by far the easiest vessel to run rapids with, and a lot more fun. But forget paddling lakes, especially if it is windy - that's where you roll it up, strap it to your pack and walk. It probably looks a lot more dangerous, (my teacher kept on referring to it as a "playboat" whereas Petri saw the options it opened for combined activities) but given that you're alone and it being a very forgiving vessel, I think even complete novices will find running up to Class II rapids no problem in it, and once you have experience even Class III and IV should be no problem - with and without a load. <br /><br />The packraft is pretty hard to capsize. I didn't yet once capsize in one, and a good friend, who paddles a lot more canoe &amp; kayak, had a very hard time to capsize in it (he managed it in the end =). However, going down those deep haystacks at Siikakoski, with headwind, I realized that if you just sit back and paddle in a relaxed way, capsizing is definitely possible and will happen. You need to concentrate, and you need to know how to read waterways. If you have gained that experience, then complete new adventures open up to you, in which you for a weight gain of some 3,6 kg (Packraft including a spraydeck and a paddle) gain endless new opportunities to explore and experience nature. <br /><br />So much for the moment. I shall follow up with the by now traditional &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/search/label/food"target="_blank"&gt;Food For Thought and a &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/search/label/Gear%20Talk%3A%20Gear%20that%20worked%20and%20gear%20that%20didn%27t"target="_blank"&gt;Gear that worked and gear that didn't posts in the near future =)</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wilderness Guide School Internship Wrap-up]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/03/wilderness-guide-school-internship-wrap-up.html"/>
    <updated>2011-03-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/03/wilderness-guide-school-internship-wrap-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
The internship is over, I got an excellent customer service evaluation, made great connections with people and got to see a new area. Time to wrap things up.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/e3fpiMQ683oVIfAjsSEcLCBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSIfTjxr9I/AAAAAAAAEL0/2n9bvjpxVhg/s640/_DSC1277.jpg" height="347" width="640" /></a><br />Yours truly enjoying the show.<br /><br />Obviously these kind of trips are very different from what I normally do, and will when I will be guiding in the future. It was, however, a superb experience. Seeing that there are highly efficient companies like &lt;a href="http://www.upitrek.com/"target="_blank"&gt;Upitrek, where things work smoothly like a clock work, is rewarding and a great asset for tourists coming to Finland, because they can be sure to have a wonderful holiday.<br /><br />I always believe that the customer is King (a remnant of my bachelor degree studies!), and hence tried to be very customer oriented as a guide, paying attention to the different needs and ensuring everyone had a good experience. While the guide work itself was not especially difficult in my opinion, it are long days - on average from 8.00 in the morning till 21.00 at night - in which one needs to be available, and "me time" is very limited. This ain't of a problem if the group you are with and your fellow guides are as great as on the two trips I was on, but might be more of a challenge if you get difficult clients. Other than that the work is good fun and rewarding to see the clients enjoying themselves on their holidays!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/0xYUmielZyOJo96pyHivpjWiupv70N-RGKSfyQFBX78?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TY3AnkgKaKI/AAAAAAAAEP4/b50r1oTO5eI/s640/_DSC1322.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a><br /><br />On the whole, the two weeks of internship were far more rewarding and enlightening than the time spent in class in Kuru. I will report on my growing frustration of the school separately in an update, but the internship really gave some joy and happiness, while I was able to learn a few things from my fellow guides along the way. <br /><br />Finally, in case you haven't guessed yet, the focus of &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/p/guiding.html"target="_blank"&gt;my guided trips in the future will be on lightweight and ultralightweight backpacking and packrafting; being off-trail expeditions in which we sleep outside and enjoy the beautiful Arctic scenary during the different seasons. I am currently planning one such trip, so if you are possibly interested, then you should stay tuned or <a href="mailto:hendrik.morkel@gmail.com?subject=Guide me in the Arctic!">get in touch</a> =)</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wilderness Guide Internship with Upitrek: Multiactivity Tour]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/03/wilderness-guide-internship-with-upitrek-multiactivity-tour.html"/>
    <updated>2011-03-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/03/wilderness-guide-internship-with-upitrek-multiactivity-tour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
And on to my second week of internship at Upitrek, the &lt;a href="http://www.upitrek.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=56:winter-fun-in-finland&amp;catid=21:other-winter-programmes&amp;Itemid=34"target="_blank"&gt;Winter Fun in Finland Tour. The idea of this trip was to give the clients an introduction to different winter activities, and hence tour is ideal for families with children and people who're not settled on one thing yet and like to try different ways to enjoy the snow and cold.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8GrGpJ_0ifMDns0R3skBxiBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TX-XlTYf-WI/AAAAAAAAEKM/QMzYE22XJgk/s640/_DSC1164.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a><br />Our dogs.<br /><br />It started on Sunday night as I met my fellow guide Tumppi and our seven clients from the Netherlands in a restaurant in Kuusamo. After a good dinner of typical Finnish cuisine we retired to the hotel in the centre, as the next day we would go direction Ruka for some Husky sleigh ride. This was the first time ever I went on a Husky trip, and it was quite enjoyable, even if it was short. I am a dog person, so this was quite exciting and I enjoyed the time with the dogs a lot. I can imagine to do a longer organized trip, of a few nights, with Huskies in the future - it must be quite something to travel with these great creatures through the white fjells and forests of Lapland.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/7Gab_MHRBSdo65AcVn953SBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TX-XixJC4fI/AAAAAAAAEKI/ABUPvZElGH0/s640/_DSC1158.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a><br />In the sleigh.<br /><br />After coffee, sausages and pulla (a Finnish pastry) we continued to Hossan Lomakeskus, our basecamp for the week. Following lunch we gave out snowshoes and some instructions, before some of our eager clients went for a walk to get familiar with snowshoes. <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/_oszNg9J-gKsTJd7vmFyeCBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSDgDdKkrI/AAAAAAAAEKk/Qemx-RlnSxw/s640/_DSC1168.jpg" height="277" width="640" /></a><br />Setting off over the lake.<br /><br />Tuesday morning I set off with the clients towards Hossan Luontokeskus (Hossa Nature Centre), where we would have a look at the Museum and enjoy lunch. It was good fun to go with the clients, after we climbed up the ridge via the skiing and snowmobile track we went along on top of the ridge, until we went in a zick-zack method the good 40 m in elevation down. For people who stood the first time on snowshoes this was a challenge, though everyone made it safe and sound down to the lake. And to top things off, we saw a few female Black Grouse taking off while going down!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/eaLYPPLfp3mUF87jhZuZEiBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSDy0_pikI/AAAAAAAAEKo/f38vHi3kJ2Y/s640/_DSC1172.jpg" height="427" width="640" /></a><br />Going down.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/irZQlU8HK3WUp2n4oY5MiiBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSD2uWXZnI/AAAAAAAAEKs/6fBOpF5TGaU/s640/_DSC1173.jpg" height="427" width="640" /></a><br />On the lake.<br /><br />We were faster than I thought so I did a few pranks (walking in circles, zick zack, getting lost =) before we climbed the small hill to the Nature Centre. Lunch time. The weather was very much on our side - which is always nice - so we set off towards the cabin at which we would spent the night. Now going through the National Park area we followed the summer trail markings, this was easier than going off-track - the sun meant that the snow was melting and becoming a mush which made it more difficult to walk on top of it - unless you're Legolas (See the &lt;a href="http://www.everytrail.com/view_trip.php?trip_id=992681"target="_blank"&gt;Everytrail Trip of this day)!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/OX0ICFfEtYm_jOP4vt89wiBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSEJuZY2iI/AAAAAAAAEKw/s9HlxXz4d44/s640/_DSC1182.jpg" height="427" width="640" /></a><br />Almost at the cabin.<br /><br />As we arrived early yet again, and there was plenty of daylight still, one of the clients and me went for a fine walk through the forest and back over the lake. We witnessed two Raven - in many parts of Europe very rare, here more common than crows at this time of the year - fly into the dusk, which was very beautiful - the photo doesn't do it justice.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/PmV14GDLqN1gA6sjXTlC0CBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSEtAfsgyI/AAAAAAAAEK0/UpFOSWnq7gc/s640/_DSC1188.jpg" height="303" width="640" /></a><br />Dusk.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Xfz0-mSwkkz1tjYl2aSSXiBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSE7RUnEyI/AAAAAAAAEK4/RM0rN285g4k/s640/_DSC1189.jpg" height="427" width="640" /></a><br />The warm glow of light from the sauna and cabin.<br /><br />Wednesday we snowshoed back to the Hotel in Hossa, with a lunch stop at a cabin. Groups separated, and while the Gentlemen and me made in a straight line through the forest the Ladies and Tumppi followed the skiing track to the cabin. The wind was blowing pretty hard over the ice, but it makes for a beautiful sight seeing the loose snow speed over the ice crust, swirling up in a little vortex. At the cabin I showed the clients how to start a fire just with birch bark, a fire steel and a puukko which resulted in some "Ahs!" and "Ohs!" and soon sausages were being grilled and the water for the coffee started boiling.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Hf8mUpR2b2fUL4xZvZwNPiBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSFPZcmGWI/AAAAAAAAEK8/EZZmCbHFtlo/s640/_DSC1195.jpg" height="271" width="640" /></a><br /><br />We continued on a easy route towards the hotel, though again we were so fast (Dutch people are the tallest people in Europe and hence have super-long legs =) that we made a little extra round over the lake, taking photos, making snow angles, and enjoying the winter sun (See the &lt;a href="http://www.everytrail.com/view_trip.php?trip_id=993553"target="_blank"&gt;Everytrail Trip of this day).<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/QIxjhkFze6WhalCHpFyURSBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSGFaBR7SI/AAAAAAAAELE/IQlIgZdl_hM/s640/_DSC1201.jpg" height="640" width="454" /></a><br />Rudolphina.<br /><br />Thursday was fairly relaxed, with a visit to the &lt;a href="http://www.hossanporopuisto.fi/"target="_blank"&gt;Hossa Reindeer Farm. Lovely creatures, and so tasty. After spending some time in the enclosure with them, feeding and petting them, the clients went for a short sleigh ride á la Santa before getting into the beautifully renovated house to warm themselves next to the fire and enjoy a good reindeer soup. A video about reindeer farming and history later we continued back to the hotel.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/AzC-MSwCURpfp1yM14hBICBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSGRTrhDjI/AAAAAAAAELI/dbcwFrMc4Zk/s640/_DSC1204.jpg" height="640" width="629" /></a><br />I found this little fellow a lot cuter than the reindeers =)<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/BZLUU7UsP0m8eivDGn5m2CBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSGXO3CV-I/AAAAAAAAELM/WF2EqyGRApY/s640/_DSC1210.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a><br />I was a bit &lt;a href="http://www.everytrail.com/view_trip.php?trip_id=994529"target="_blank"&gt;bored at the hotel, so I went for an extra skiing round.<br /><br />Friday was our skiing day. I am now totally hooked on skiing and looked very much forward to this day, so right after breakfast we started with some basic instructions - how to fall right, get up again, how to get forward, get up and down a hill, and break. A few rounds on the beginner circle before we moved to the advanced circle and hill, where I went with some of the clients for a small tour already - they stood the first time on langlauf (Cross Country) skis and did really well, very excellent!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/UfL31G1ETgProPIQRVUAxyBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSGpPfZNMI/AAAAAAAAELQ/GMi2hAIBJuY/s640/_DSC1222.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a><br />It had snowed a lot that night and morning.<br /><br />After lunch I went with a small group for an afternoon trip to the Hossa Nature Centre (&lt;a href="http://www.everytrail.com/view_trip.php?trip_id=995301"target="_blank"&gt;Everytrail Trip), which was very nice again. To see beginners so eager to go for a trip is very rewarding, and while there were some falls everyone arrived in one piece back at the hotel in the afternoon while feeling that they accomplished something great - I was pretty proud of them!<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/y3W1Up5oVs5WqP6B_In2pCBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSG8O3B6OI/AAAAAAAAELU/prxmDEKEUbc/s640/_DSC1230.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a><br />Off track with langlauf skis. Where there's a guide, there's a way.<br /><br />Saturday was our last day, and clients could choose an activity they'd like to try more or go for something new. So the morning was spent with ice fishing, while some went snowshoeing as well. I spent time packing and reading, as also I would travel back home on the following day.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/RyNgVfvcMhonUL_dFVQl4yBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSHDq6aIwI/AAAAAAAAELY/QvMhJqCfJPo/s640/_DSC1236.jpg" height="640" width="426" /></a><br />High endurance sport.<br /><br />Sitting around the dinner table the question for northern lights came up. While we saw some very weak ones on Monday night, our clients felt that they'd like to see "proper" northern lights on their last evening. While there is no switch to put Aurora Borealis on, a sacrifice to the pagan gods can help make them appear =) I put on my jacket to see if there's a show on, and much to the joy of our guests, there was. It was spectacular, with even red and yellow northern lights to be seen besides the green ones. Fantastic! <br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/zy9wE_8Zd65Ib_5gUjf7cyBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSHk1DtByI/AAAAAAAAELg/2vKEJE7tP70/s640/_DSC1251.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/hqHEEdqf_Ffsxxo1xtsxhSBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSH-J5stOI/AAAAAAAAELo/x0AIKkV0M_o/s640/_DSC1258.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a><br />Aurora Borealis.<br /><br />And so the week ended with a great show. Sunday morning a last breakfast together, collecting the gear the clients loaned, packing and jumping on the taxi bus to Kuusamo. I myself jumped on the bus and started my 10+ hour trip back south, planning routes for upcoming trips, reading, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/#!/hendrikmorkel"target="_blank"&gt;tweeting and looking forward to sleep to my loved one in our own bed.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/VoUxY7oKpPRg7E6VPyY9MyBBbHBQPEZAJ8vraTRirYA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TYSI4fy0i1I/AAAAAAAAEMA/R_S9N8BBmCI/s640/_DSC1298.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a><br />A guest enjoying the show.<br /><br />And so my internship ended. While it were long days it also was fairly easy and relaxing, as I was doing something I enjoy myself a lot. Having smart, funny and interested clients helps a lot as well to make this "work" seem less like work but more like having a good time with mates. I will wrap up this experience in a separate post and tell more about what happened at school in the meanwhile, so stay tuned =)</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
