<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Kids gear | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/kids-gear/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-09T13:57:49+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Fun with the Reima Mamid Jacket and Procyon Pants]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/winter-fun-with-the-reima-mamid-jacket-and-procyon-pants.html"/>
    <updated>2016-11-07T19:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/winter-fun-with-the-reima-mamid-jacket-and-procyon-pants</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Winter is coming!</em> And that means for us Families here in the North: Dressing the Kids up warmly and heading out into the snow! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30201863754/in/dateposted/" title="Up the Sled Hill"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5734/30201863754_12a9f5a583_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Up the Sled Hill" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The Reima Mamid Jacket and Procyon Pants have been our choice of winter garments for our son, and this down-filled jacket and the warm and water-repellant pants have been great in keeping our little boy warm when the temperatures drop low. And low were the temperatures, not just here in Vaasa but also up North in Lapland on our <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Family winter holiday in Pyhä</a> - which is a great place to take your kids for a relaxed &amp; adventurous winter holiday! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075087012/in/album-72157651506091295/" title="That one next, dad!"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7599/17075087012_e945efd6da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="That one next, dad!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Mamid jacket has everything you’d expect of your own jacket: Taped seams, windproof, water-proof and a toasty warm insulation of Reima 60 Down (that means there’s a mix of 60% Down to 40% feathers, which I found a good combination as when our son is a lot less careful when he is out playing, and the high feather percentage means the down can do its job and does not get compressed to easily). The hood with the fake fur is great when standing on a cold fjell top or at night when watching the stars and Northern Lights. It can be removed when not needed, which is useful for those chilly but sunny autumn and spring days. The waist can be adjusted by a drawstring on the inside so it is close to the body, and the sleeves have Velcro cuffs so no cold breeze or snow come in. </p>

<p>I don’t know what is the obsession with pockets on Kids garments, maybe the manufacturers just adapt adult designs and make them smaller? At least I feel that most <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/kids-gear/">Kids garments</a> have too many pockets. The Mamid for example would have been fine with just the two large flap pockets, eliminating the zippered pockets on the chest and inside. These just don’t get used by kids of the age 3 to 5 and add unnecessary material and costs to the garment. On the other hand, great are the reflective details on the jacket - though there could be possibly be some more, especially on the right sleeve there could also be a patch like on the left one. As for the freedom of movement, the Mamid was great for all our activities, from sledding to walking and climbing on rocks. The material is durable and abrasion-resistant and still looked like new after a season in the snow. </p>

<p>In short, if he’d not out-grown it so quickly he’d still be wearing it - also because he really liked his red winter jacket! Good thing his little sister will be able to wear it in a year or two and then I can go sledding with her =) The <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Koululaisten-lastenvaatteet/Ulkovaatteet/Ulkotakit/Talvitakit/Lasten-Reimatec®%2B--talvitakki-Serkku/p/531235-3830">Reimatec Serkku Winter Jacket</a> is the successor to the Mamid Jacket so if you’re still looking for a warm, durable and stylish jacket for your little one - we can recommend this one completely!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889011560/in/album-72157651506091295/" title="Pyhä Sled Hill"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7713/16889011560_3351fc57fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Pyhä Sled Hill" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That brings us to the pants which we got together with the jacket, the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Syysuutuudet/Lasten-toppahousut-Procyon/p/522207N-6980">Procyon pants</a>. These are also well-constructed, robust and still look very good after a winter season of abuse. While the suspenders are a bit tricky when our son was supposed to dress up himself, they ensured the pants stayed where they belong when we were outside, and the small bib added also a wee bit of warmth. There could have been some more reflective details on them (there are, but not enough in my opinion) as especially now in November it is so dark and more visibility is always good. </p>

<p>The pants have great freedom of movement, climbing and running in them was no problem, and the taped seams made them highly water-repellant and windproof. The stretchy inside trouser cuffs ensured no snow came into his boots and socks and are adjustable in width - together with the Velcro adjusters on the outside trouser legs these mean no snow or dirt has a chance. The two side pockets were again never used and could be eliminated, but otherwise these were great, warm pants when playing in the snow. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30201863854/in/dateposted/" title="Stay here!"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5346/30201863854_580e6c896f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Stay here!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Overall we were very happy with the two winter garments from Reima (and the many other ones we have bought!) and it is great to support &amp; work together with a Finnish Company which makes so good clothes for kids. Winter is arriving all over Europe, so now is a good time to get those warm, durable and stylish kids garments so the little ones can continue to play outside. <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/reima/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> have a wide selection of Reima garments, and you also can buy everything directly at the <a href="https://www.reima.com/">Reima Online Shop</a> or visit a <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/myymalat">local Reima Retailer</a>. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050611986/in/album-72157651506091295/" title="Danger!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8813/17050611986_396e0e5472_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Danger!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The Jacket &amp; Pants were sent for free to us and Reima asked me to have fun with it. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this . Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/marmot-space-walk-jacket-and-edge-insulated-pants-review.html"/>
    <updated>2016-03-29T23:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/marmot-space-walk-jacket-and-edge-insulated-pants-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Skiing, sledding, hiking and building an igloo: Winter is a great time for kids to be outside &amp; enjoy the snow. So that he does not get cold, our son wore the Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants - which we review here.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108799805/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1583/26108799805_df4fb92f57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Winter, also known to parents as the time where you need to get ready 15 minutes before you plan to leave - because your little ones need help dressing up in the multitude of layers we make them wear so they do not get cold. Because only when they’re not cold they actually enjoy being outdoors (much like adults, really). We tested the <a href="https://marmot.com/products/details/boys-space-walk-jacket">Marmot Space Walk Jacket</a> and <a href="https://marmot.com/products/details/boys-edge-insulated-pant">Edge Insulated Pants</a> during the last four months outside while alpine skiing, sledding, building snowmen and XC skiing, and here are our thoughts about them.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484248574/in/dateposted/" title="Sledding at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1538/25484248574_b0fe932edf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sledding at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25835958970/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1488/25835958970_4ab4a4766b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25506181673/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1536/25506181673_6ef459c4a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="space-walk-jacket">Space Walk Jacket</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.marmot.de/content/de/collection_26&amp;c=643&amp;show=5778">Space Walk Jacket</a> in Size XS equals size 110 and weighs 512 g. Our son loved the colour combination of orange and reds, and we too really liked it. Outside a waterproof &amp; breathable Marmot MemBrain® Fabric keeps snow and moisture at bay, while on the inside a Thermal R 100 g insulation ensures generated warmth stays inside. The hood is removable, and a really good fit, even over a bobble hat. The Powder Skirt keeps the snow out and is extremely useful for little skiers and playing in the snow. It has a silicone band on the inside which keeps it in place and has two levels of tightness. In the back, chin and neck a fleece lining makes it comfortable against the skin and likely helps with breathability, too. What we found overkill were the six pockets, we could have done easily with only the one large mesh pocket on the inside (which is great to store beanie, neck warmer and gloves!) and one of the outside pockets. Our son never used the Velcro hand pockets nor the other two pockets on the outside. The hem is adjustable, though with the toggles in the pockets it is difficult to do so - happily we never needed it. The sleeves have Velcro closures and also can be adjusted, and most importantly are wide enough so gloves can be worn underneath the sleeves to keep the snow out. The jacket closes high and our son found the area in the front of the face constricting, something we solved by leaving the zipper always a couple of centimetre open.</p>

<p>In terms of warmth, we feel the jacket (and pants for that matter) are warm till -10°C with a thin midlayer on (plus normal clothes), probably more with a thicker midlayer. The jacket has plenty of space underneath for layering, and our son never was cold in a variety of activities and weather conditions. It gives little skiers and climbers great freedom of movement, and the Powder Skirt ensures no cold and wet snow comes inside. After four months of use and a couple of washes the jacket also still looks like new, also at high-stress areas like the cuffs and back. Overall our son really liked his Space Walk Jacket - it is warm, has nice colours and is easy for him to put on and off on his own. </p>

<p>Get the Marmot Space Walk Jacket right now with great discounts at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/marmot-boys-space-walk-jacket-ski-jacket/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1Uq4bDm">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1Sh9qz1">Campsaver</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1ogTV1S">evo</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1Uq5jqD">REI.com</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108801235/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1637/26108801235_cfc707f7e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25506181033/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1478/25506181033_1c7630e710_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25504057124/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1685/25504057124_34e4c202fc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="edge-insulated-pants">Edge Insulated Pants</h2>

<p>In size XS the <a href="http://www.marmot.de/content/de/collection_26&amp;c=647&amp;show=5792">Edge Insulated Pants</a> weighs 444 g. They are, as the name suggests, insulated pants, made of the proprietary Marmot MemBrain® fabric on the outside which makes the pants water-resistant, while on the inside a Thermal R™ insulation keeps little winter lovers warm. We found the internal flex boot gaiters great to keep shoes &amp; socks dry from the inside, and the reinforced inside leg is useful for skiing as well as scrambling on rocks. The waist is adjustable via Velcros on the inside, but sadly the adjustment is only minimal - we feel a bit more adjustment in width or a stretchy waist could have been better and would possibly make it possible to use the pants two winter seasons. The removable suspenders are great, and the soft inside lining makes it easy to put the pants on over other pants. We never used the three pockets on the pants, so maybe it’d make sense to get rid of at least the two zippered pockets. </p>

<p>Putting the pants on is easy thanks to the smooth lining and it stays well in place with the adjustable suspenders and button closure. After four months of daily use outside the Edge Insulated Pants still looks like new after a couple of washes. The Marmot MemBrain® fabric kept the snow &amp; wetness always reliable outside and it was easy to brush dirt off the pants. They allow for great freedom of movement, be it scrambling up the snow hills along the streets, climbing on the playground or Alpine and XC skiing. The sizing is good for kids between 108 and 112 cm, though if your child is wearing more than one baselayer the waist might get tight (we just left the button open). Asides from these little things from us parents our son simply liked his Edge Insulated Pants a lot: They were toasty, allowed him to go sledding on his pants down steep snow hills and also looked cool!</p>

<p>Buy the Marmot Edge Insulated Pants at <a href="http://bit.ly/1URthuB">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/marmot-boys-edge-insulated-pant-ski-pant/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1RnGIAh">Campsaver</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1UxaV2z">evo</a> - all of them have great offers on the pants thanks to their winter sales!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108802745/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1705/26108802745_6e2c8c20c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26016281992/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1582/26016281992_7a9bd6e1ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The jacket and pants have been provided by Marmot for review. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
