<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Portugal | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/portugal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-21T20:52:42+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Biketouring Portugal: Lisbon to Porto]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/biketouring-portugal-lisbon-to-porto.html"/>
    <updated>2016-02-12T23:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/biketouring-portugal-lisbon-to-porto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year I was fortunate to escape the dreaded month of November for a week and enjoy sunshine &amp; cycling along the coast of Portugal, riding over 500 km from Lisbon to Porto.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23170406440/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Cabo da Roca"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5701/23170406440_011dc7899e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cabo da Roca" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>After thru-hiking the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">High Coast Trail</a> in November of 2014 and experiencing all the weather you can expect in November in Scandinavia - snow, sleet, rain, grey clouds as far as you can see and a tiny bit of sun - my mind was set on the south for outdoor trips in November. Last year it was so far: I boarded a plane in Vaasa with my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Pelago Stavanger</a> and flew to Lisbon, where +20°C temperatures and sunshine where waiting for me. During the following weeks I will share the adventure of riding in this beautiful country, but I already now want to get you in the mood for cycling in Portugal! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23380978901/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Hello Beach!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/720/23380978901_4d30838bf6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hello Beach!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Riding from Lisbon to Porto made a lot of sense to me while planning this trip. And there were even other people who have done similar tours. But being on the road for a week and cycling North, I quickly decided that I makes more sense to do this trip the other way around. The reason is the North-Westerly wind which I had every day, and while Headwind is to be expected when cycling, some days I was swearing so much about the f#€k!n6 headwind that I made a mental note to recommend this tour the other way around. It’s a lot nicer to cycle with tailwind than cycling against a headwind which slows you sometimes down so much that you’re almost standing still.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22835147394/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Lighthouse"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5762/22835147394_f5b1594fd6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lighthouse" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I rode from Cascais, a suburb of Lisbon, to Sintra on Day 1, an easy 40 km which also took me to Cabo da Roca, the most westerly point of the European continent. On day 2 I managed to ride a 20 km Detour so that I arrived in Peniche at dusk with over 114 km cycled, while Day 3 where only 90 km to São Pedro de Moel where the fine Lighthouse above was warning the ships out in the ocean. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23383680491/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="10% at 40 km/h please."><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5682/23383680491_027093f765_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="10% at 40 km/h please." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22839048623/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Aveiro"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/629/22839048623_5f79624a5c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Aveiro" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Day 4 I cycled to Coimbra which had me swearing the most about the headwind as I was cycling on a completely straight road to Pedrogão, though happily it got a bit less windy as I cycled inland. Cycling to Aveiro on Day 5 was more relaxed, though the cycling out of Coimbra in the fog with a visibility of less than 100 m had me scared about being crashed into a couple of times. On my last day to Porto I was cycling inland through tranquil little villages, up steep, steep cobblestone roads in the middle of the forest and then finally crossed the bridge into Porto, which put a big smile on my face. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22835148504/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Speed"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/734/22835148504_8867470aa2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Speed" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you want to escape November in Scandinavia &amp; Central Europe go cycling or hiking in Portugal, where it is a beautiful sunny month with nice temperatures. I had help from <a href="http://a2z-adventures.com/en/">A2Z Adventures</a> during the planning and execution of my trip, and if you don’t want to go to Portugal on your own or fly with your bike join one of their <a href="http://a2z-adventures.com/en/find-trip/biking">Biking Trips</a> - they have everything from self-guided trips to a guide cycling next to you and telling you all about the country. I cycled light and slept in B&amp;Bs and Hotels along the way, and traded the stove and freezer bag meals to Lunches and Dinners in Cafés and Restaurants - Portugal is very affordable for Scandinavians. More coming soon, so <em>stay tuned for my Day-to-Day account coming to your favourite Scandinavian Outdoor Travel Blog!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23463494785/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Cockpit bird&#x27;s eye view"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/709/23463494785_264b62b11f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cockpit bird&#x27;s eye view" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: This trip was made possible with the help of <a href="https://www.visitportugal.com/en">Visit Portugal</a> and <a href="http://www.flytap.com/">TAP Portugal</a> as a research trip for a story which will appear in the <a href="http://www.biketravel-magazin.com">Bike &amp; Travel Magazine</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
