<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sponsored Post | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/sponsored-post/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-06T12:00:52+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/swix-pro-trail-carbon-120-trekking-pole.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-06T23:37:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/swix-pro-trail-carbon-120-trekking-pole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking for a light carbon trekking pole which accompanies you through the day and stands tall when you pitch your shelter in the evening? Then take a peek at the new Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole from Swix!</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I got the Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 in July 2016 and have been using them on day hikes, a trail run and as poles for pitching my shelters on Microadventures. All in all they haven’t seen as much use as I usually would put a piece of kit through before I write about them, but this being a sponsored post I sadly didn’t have the freedome to test them for 12 months &amp; longer =) However, I intend to take them along to a trip to the ALps this autumn where I’ll be backpacking for a week and after that I will feel more confident about a final statement.</p>

<p>PHOTO</p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>As I highlighted in my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles.html">Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles</a> Review, trekking poles have many advantages outdoors:</p>

<ul>
  <li>They help you to keep your balance on difficult terrain</li>
  <li>Useful in fording rivers</li>
  <li>Can be transformed into a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html">tripod</a> or used with a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/03/interview-rod-java-from-thestickpic-com.html">StickPic</a> for photography</li>
  <li>They can pitch your tarp or shelter</li>
  <li>They train your upper body muscles when hiking and running</li>
</ul>

<p>PHOTO</p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon is available in fixed lengths from 100 to 135 cm in 5 cm intervals. All of the poles have the following features in common:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Compact folding system</li>
  <li>Comfort Connection system</li>
  <li>Multi grip from cork with EVA extension</li>
  <li>Flexi basket system</li>
  <li>Swix carbon technology Swix CT1 grade</li>
  <li>Folded pack size is 39 cm</li>
</ul>

<p>PHOTO</p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The quality is really great. The trekking poles make a solid impression, the construction of the segments is clean and smooth and they fit well together, and also the grip is very nice. </p>

<p>PHOTO</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My poles in 120 cm length weigh 153 g per pole including the little baskets, so the pair of them weighs 306 g. This makes them more heavy than my BD Poles, but I imagine this weight will reflect positively on the durability of the poles. On the plus side, that’s 29 g lighter as Swix claims they would be!</p>

<p>PHOTO</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>3-season pole because of cork</p>

<p>Very stiff</p>

<p>L &amp; R hand loops, not easy to remove</p>

<p>Flexi basket system</p>

<p>Pitching a Pyramide and Tarp</p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I really like the cork grip and would wish the Sonic Pro Trail Carbon pole would have a complete cork handle, so that the lower EVA part is also cork. It just feels more comfortable on the hand to me, and it’s a shame the lower part is made from EVA. I also would have wished that the strap would be easy to remove. I rarely use straps with poles in the summer and am sure I’d liked it better to save a few more grams than being forced to have it along. I also think that if one buys thes poles that it’d be nice to get a choice of baskets with them, because the small trekking baskets aren’t really great in summer snow, swamps and boulder fields where a larger basket would make it easier for the pole not to penetrate too deep. </p>

<p>PHOTO</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>The at the beginning mentioned <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles.html">Black Diamond Poles</a> are a worthy competitor which I know are very long-lasting &amp; robust, and if you can life with poles that have a larger pack size also the <a href="http://www.rutalocura.com/trekking_poles.html">Ruta Locura Yana poles</a> are great poles that I have used since many years very happily. If you need adjustable poles I’d check out the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/swix-sonic-x-trail-carbon-trekkingstoecke/?pid=10239">Swix Sonic X-Trail Carbon</a> which some of my friends will surely tell about in a while!</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Despite not having used them as much as I’d like to the Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120 Trekking Pole have made a good first impression on me. They are very light and comfortable when out hiking and backpacking, they allow me to pitch my Pyramide shelters and tarps and let me train my upper body when out for a hike. Keep in mind that I still am not a big trekking pole user when hiking although I almost always carry a pair because I need them for my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shelters/">shelters</a>. Because </p>

<p>Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon 120</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>You can get the pole in every length from <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/swix-sonic-pro-trail-carbon-trekkingstoecke/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> (On offer for 135€!) and <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/swix-sonic-pro-trail-carbon-trailrunningstock/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>. </p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The trekking poles were sent for free to me by <a href="http://en.outdoor-blogger-network.com/?noredirect=en_US">OBN</a> and Swix &amp; I got paid to write about them. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
