<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: climbing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/climbing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-23T17:29:14+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love the Dolomites Tour]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/love-the-dolomites-tour.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-17T23:53:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/love-the-dolomites-tour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friends. Good food. Wine. Three Guidebooks. No plan. Equals a fantastic time in the Dolomites.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19872954152/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19872954152_05a10af0d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In March I let you in on a well-kept secret: That I will be going to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html">Dolomites</a> in July. With four friends. A rental car. An obscene amount of climbing, camping, Via ferrata and backpacking gear. So obscene that I needed to ditch one of my twin-topes on my mate Stu, with whom I was flying out of Helsinki way to early on a Sunday morning. A good thing that a sweltering heat was welcoming us in Venice, as well as our three companions and a rental car. Packed to the brim with only a dim idea how to get to Cortina we directed our vehicle North. And somehow I was able to navigate us securely to the <a href="http://www.dolomiti.org/ita/cortina/laga5torri/ospitalita/CinqueTorri/index.html">Rifugio Cinque Torri</a>. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19259485003/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Cinque Torri Refugio in the morning"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/350/19259485003_a0a9541eef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cinque Torri Refugio in the morning" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Gorgeous, stunning, breath-taking, <em>I love it</em>, where words that were uttered after the engine was switched off. We lost no time and shouldered ropes and climbing kit and hit the first crag, Torre Quarta Bassa. An easy 6a/ 5 Multi-Pitch route was picked for warm-up by Stu and me, as well as popping our Multi-Pitch Cherries. Our vocabulary soon was enhanced by meaningful phrases like <em>Where’s the next bolt?</em> and <em>That’s not a 5a!</em> As the sun was making the five beautiful towers of the Cinque Torri draw long shadows on the meadows we were rappelling down, walking back to the Rifugio. Dinner was calling, and so was the wine. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692381198/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Abseil"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/365/19692381198_dfdebbbb20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Abseil" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20660448541/in/dateposted/" title="Cinque Torri"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/730/20660448541_7fb341c5b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cinque Torri" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It’s common for climbers to get up early, and so we decided on a 6 o’clock start to climb a route on Cima Grande’s Southwest Face, which gets backed in the sun during the day. Rosamunde was climbed by Sam, Stu and me, and then breakfast was calling us back. Yes, half-board at the Rifugios is mandatory and highly recommended. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19257749664/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Morning Session on Rosamund"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/19257749664_f16b5152cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Morning Session on Rosamund" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stu and me were the Multi-Pitch team, and as we were in the company of a battalion of Italian soldiers it was the Via Normale on Torre Inglese which we climbed. There was exposure, sweaty palms, smiles, running it out, more smiles, squeezes and a hard-earned summit with trad gear. More smiles, two abseils and then some Apfelstrudel and Cappuccino. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19885405791/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Stu at the summit of Torre Inglese"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/524/19885405791_0e4b6fb8af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stu at the summit of Torre Inglese" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A few easy climbs at the School of Rock sector on the way back to a hot shower and a slab attempt that ended with the rain. Doesn’t matter, because there’s wine, dinner, card games, laughter, sitting outside and taking in the view. The next morning it was up before sunrise at 5 o’clock and another attempt on the slab. Stu on-sighted it, I failed, and so it was back to breakfast, packing up and heading onwards.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692379838/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Stu in the early morning light after having topped out on the Trephor Slab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/386/19692379838_e315f1fc7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stu in the early morning light after having topped out on the Trephor Slab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A resupply in Cortina and we drove onwards. The Sorapiss Circuit was <em>The Plan™</em>. Car parked, backpacks with bivy gear shouldered and onwards we went. A coffee at the Rifugio on the way and up that lovely scree field in the 30°C heat. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19257748424/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="On the approach to the Sorapiss Circuit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/452/19257748424_cfb90f08d2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On the approach to the Sorapiss Circuit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20660450391/in/dateposted/" title="Lago di Sorapiss and a wonderful scree field"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5692/20660450391_04f879eb54_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Lago di Sorapiss and a wonderful scree field" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It was getting late, the clouds were closing in, and so we stayed put at the end of the world. A un-secured hike 1000 m over a valley on narrow ledges was to be done fresh &amp; full of energy. The thunderstorms hitting us shortly after the bivies were rolled out made us congratulate ourselves for our smart decision. It was early to bed, sleep in, lightning storms all night. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692405060/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="A break between Thunderstorms"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/309/19692405060_906ac422e5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="A break between Thunderstorms" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As the sky cleared in the morning we decided against the sketchy approach, strolled back and drove to mountains with fairer weather. We found it in the Val Gardena, where we rolled out our sleeping bags on the Parking lot, shared wine with other campers and were looking forward to the Via Ferrata Brigata Tridentina.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19693765169/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="After the rain on the Gardena Pass"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/545/19693765169_d3bb7e6da4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="After the rain on the Gardena Pass" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19854193206/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="The Bridge on the Brigata Tridentina Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3736/19854193206_49e12f1c1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The Bridge on the Brigata Tridentina Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning a cloud inversion in the valley (<em>yeps, the opening photo</em>) made us dally around, but we were still in good time on the Via Ferrata and topped out happy at the top. A Kaiserschmarn later Matt, Sam, Stu and me explored the high plateau before it was back to the valley, which involved more scree, steel cables, snow fields and the urge to run it all down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653770955/in/dateposted/" title="&quot;Easy&quot; Downclimb"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5717/20653770955_0e4089c4d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;Easy&quot; Downclimb" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I rolled out my bivy under a Boulder Problem called Sella benath Sassolunga that night, taking in the fine view of a star-filled sky. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19885410521/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Sassolunga at night"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3834/19885410521_a0c2b49e98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sassolunga at night" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Easy climbs ensued the next morning after breakfast, followed by a check in to the fine <a href="http://www.dolomitesrefugeandhut.it">Rifugio Carlo Valentini</a>. A private bunk room, warm showers and more climbing followed by more showers followed, topped by a delicious dinner which had us wonder if we understood the quoted price right. The next morning saw us drive our car to the start of the Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata, the <em>most difficult</em> Via ferrata yet. An inexperienced Via Ferrata-ist before us had us wondering if we weren’t pokering too high, but as climbers we dispatched the first difficult bit in no time and hence enjoyed in peace the rest of the Via Ferrata. Suspension bridges, views on the Marmolada, ridge walks and caves made for an atmospheric hike. Just the long, steep walk back, we could have done without it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20466763028/in/dateposted/" title="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/610/20466763028_99e525a09a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20645582602/in/dateposted/" title="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/639/20645582602_a3565a0977_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And that was it. A long, or rather short night later I was on my way to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-soa-jury-meeting.html">SOA Jury Meeting</a> and the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i.html">OutDoor 2015</a>, while my good friends travelled on to other parts of the world. But we were sure of one thing: That we loved the Dolomites, and that we will be back. And if you like mountains, good food &amp; wine, great climbing and fun Via Ferratas, you too should pay the Dolomits a visit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20465766490/in/dateposted/" title="At the End of the World, there is happiness"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5670/20465766490_422c576db0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="At the End of the World, there is happiness" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kelly Cordes: The Tower]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/kelly-cordes-the-tower.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-26T23:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/kelly-cordes-the-tower</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1BQVH0i">Kelly Cordes - The Tower</a> is a gripping book about the history of climbing on Cerro Torre. If you’re in love with Patagonia, it’s mountaineering history, and the Chalten massiv, read on to hear my verdict on this book.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19165133102" title="Kelly Cordes - The Tower by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/302/19165133102_bd1146bf09_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kelly Cordes - The Tower" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Oh Patagonia, how I long to see thee!</em> As <a href="http://bit.ly/1BR9bcu">Patagonia Books</a> asked me if I’d like to read Kelly Cordes new book about Cerro Torre, my answer was of course <em>Yes!</em> How would one who likes to climb and loves the mountains not read the book about one of the most beautiful mountains on this planet? Also history enthusiasts will enjoy this fine book, which is written in such a way that also non-climbers will find it fascinating and read chapter after chapter.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Climbing is not a democracy. It never has been. That’s one of the things we love about it. Climbing is about freedom, and just as Maestri scarred Cerro Torre when he put in all those bolt ladders, Jason and I removed about 120 of his bolts on our descent.”</em> - Hayden Kennedy</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In a nutshell the book chronicles the history of climbing on Cerro Torre and the controversy surrounding the claimed first ascent in 1959 and the 1970 Compressor Route of Cesare Maestri, an Italian climber who became world-famous because of these two routes. The book has four distinct parts, divided into 35 chapters on 400 pages. Cordes tries on these pages to uncover the truth about the claimed First Ascent in 1959 &amp; the death of Toni Egger, who died under unknown circumstances on the claimed descent. Cordes interviews supporters and opponents of Maestri, talks with Reinhold Messner, and many of the Alpinists which have climbed new routes on Cerro Torre. In the end he draws logical conclusions, but lets you, the reader, come to your own results. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19170902365" title="Kelly Cordes - The Tower by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/318/19170902365_ed1f2005d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kelly Cordes - The Tower" /></a></p>

<p>On the side he also looks at how modern technology and tourism has changed the landscape in El Chalten, the removal of 120 of Maestri’s bolts and the ensuing discussion, and then gives you in three Appendixes a Timeline of Cerro Torre Ascents, the people mentioned and a climbing glossary, as well as maps and a selected bibliography. It’s a well rounded book with gorgeous photos and will inspire many to climb in Patagonia, or at least visit the area and hike underneath these stunning peaks. If you’re an Alpinist, climber, mountaineer or just barely interested in mountains and Cerro Torre then you should read this book. It’s an enthralling read and you’ll fly through the chapters, eager to learn more about the history and climbing on this beautiful mountain &amp; it’s difficult history. You can order the book directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1BQVH0i">Patagonia</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1GBoCAZ">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Jngv26">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1Cy6NlF">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zlagboard Pro Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/zlagboard-pro-review.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-24T23:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/zlagboard-pro-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/outdoor-2014-wrap-up-and-conclusions.html">OutDoor</a> last year I stumbled on the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/">Zlagboard</a> for the first time and immediately thought it’s an awesome way to train at home. The Zlagboard comes with a Smartphone App and training plans for every level, which allows you to track your progress over months. I have been training with the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-pro">Zlagboard Pro</a> since February and this is my review of it. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18490892773" title="Start Screen II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/468/18490892773_d873e8b60c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Start Screen II" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>As a father &amp; entrepreneur it’s right now not as easy for me to go to the gym or outdoors for a round of climbing, but I feel bad if I can’t go. I’ve had a pair of <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/metolius-rock-rings-3d-trainingsgriffe/">Metolius Rock Rings</a> for several years but wanted something more - something that allows me to track my training, measure progress, set goals and let me get strong. Enter the Zlagboard and the great App. I’ll look at these two components and then the training with both.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19085360396" title="Workout Plans by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/388/19085360396_4af11ce9fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Workout Plans" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-zlagboard-app">The Zlagboard App</h2>

<p>The Zlagboard <a href="https://zlagboard.com/app">App</a> (available on iOS and Android) is the digital part of your training. Modern smartphones like the iPhone come with a lot of sensors, and the physical Zlagboard in combination with the App make use of these sensors to measure your training. On the Start Screen you probably first want to set up your Profile and then head to the Store to activate your Zlagboard - you’ll find the code on the back of the Zlagboard to do so, and it’s good for five users. In the Store you also can purchase additional training plans, for example from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html">GimmeKraft!</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19104282642" title="Training Plans for Purchase in the Zlagboard Store by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3886/19104282642_674d3f4bb5_c.jpg" width="451" height="800" alt="Training Plans for Purchase in the Zlagboard Store" /></a><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18922333978" title="Trainings Overview Screen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/368/18922333978_b38447bf2d_c.jpg" width="451" height="800" alt="Trainings Overview Screen" /></a></p>

<p>Once activated I did the Test which recommends you which Training Plan to follow, but I decided I start at the lowest Level and went with the Basic (free) Plan. The four Training Plans that are shown were developed by <a href="http://patxiusobiaga.com">Patxi Usobiaga</a> and all run 12 weeks. You’re not bound to stick to the scheduled days, but it of course would make sense to do so for the best training effect. And if you miss your Wednesday training you can just do it on Thursday.</p>

<p>I found the App well structured but missed some more instructions on some exercises, if not in the App at least on the website. This would have made it more beginner-friendly, as likely not every climber knows e.g. what’s the Full-Lock position. I think the prices for the Pro Plans are very fair and everything else in the App was very well designed. It worked without flaws on my old iPhone 5 (running iOS 8) and also should work well on any Android phone.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18923828330" title="Zlagboard! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3769/18923828330_68dca4328d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="454" alt="Zlagboard!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-zlagboard-pro-fingerboard">The Zlagboard Pro Fingerboard</h2>

<p>Fingerboard, hangboard, trainingboard - there’s many different names for this, but they essentially all mean the same. It’s a board made of wood or plastic with different sized finger holds for training at home. What’s different about the Zlagboard is that it’s a mounted on a separate frame - it is made of two (three if you count the steel) parts. The Nilo is attached to the wall and allows you to mount the Zlagboard Pro or <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-vario">Vario</a> to it, and you could even mount several Nilo boards in your house and then just move the fingerboards around to use them. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19105859642" title="Side view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/437/19105859642_12f9a67d68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Side view" /></a></p>

<p>The actual fingerboard is mounted on a steel frame, and so when you hang on the board the steel frame stays in place but the wooden part moves softly a centimetre down. It’s super stable (unless you mounted it sloppily!) and makes for a good feeling when training. The board self is made of Alder wood and weighs 7 kg, with a size of 70 x 16 x 6 cm. It has 24 different holds in 10 pairs with four holds in the centre. There’s two Jugs, one 10° Sloper and two 35° Slopers, and many Crimps &amp; Pockets with a depth from 10 to 45 mm. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19085367456" title="Holds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/437/19085367456_46d305b056_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Holds" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18923826010" title="Smartphone Mount by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/416/18923826010_7ecc16bee5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Smartphone Mount" /></a></p>

<p>Your smartphone is attached via the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/additional-equipment#smartphone-mount">Smartphone Mount</a>, which is an elastic gadget that attaches over the four corners of your phone and then you can slide it easily over the top metal part, so that you always easily can see what’s to be done next. These also can be bought separately and in different colours, in case you tend to missplace such things.</p>

<p>Besides the Zlagboard Pro which you see in my photos there’s also a <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-mini">Zlagboard Mini</a> and a <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-vario">Zlagboard Vario</a>. The former is, as the name suggests, smaller and optimized for GimmeKraft! workouts, while the latter allows you to attach a <a href="http://bit.ly/1LB72By">fingerboard</a> of your choice on it, be it a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beastmaker-2000-series-trainingsboard/">Beastmaker 2000</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1GHpW8s">Metolius Wood Grips Compact Training Board</a>, you can attach almost any board to it and then create custom workouts for it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18923837050" title="Hang-time by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/483/18923837050_0a8c1fd32b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hang-time" /></a></p>

<h2 id="training">Training</h2>

<p>Now that you know about the soft- and hardware, it is time to look at the training. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19111537695" title="Day 10 Trainings Plan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/473/19111537695_63664516c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Day 10 Trainings Plan" /></a></p>

<p>I choose the Basic Training Plan for starters and found it a good 50 minute workout three times a week. It’s organized in such a way that you first build up strength over the first month, in the 2nd month strength &amp; endurance and in the 3rd month you go for power. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19114895991" title="Break by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/312/19114895991_c041ac4566_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Break" /></a></p>

<p>In between exercises the App counts down your break time, tells you what’s next and also allows you to skip the break or pause the exercise if you gotta interrupt it. There’s a varied mix of exercises that makes use of increasingly difficult holds, for longer times, in more difficult positions. Pull-ups on the jugs are a good warm-up, and you can configure the App so that it either automatically counts them or that you need to touch the screen with your nose, as I so stylish demonstrate underneath. The breaks between exercises can go from 7 seconds to 5 minutes, which means you could read a book or answer some emails in between exercises - or just skip the breaks and continue in one go! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18490903563" title="Touch the screen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3678/18490903563_c7608b07c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="845" alt="Touch the screen" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If you can not get to the climbing gym or crag as often as you would like to or are tired of your non-interactive fingerboard, then you’ll love the Zlagboard. For me it is one of the best innovations in the climbing market in the last years and allows me to train efficiently at home, with professionally developed training plans, and it tracks my progress so that I can measure my results. The wooden fingerboard is very well made and the App easy &amp; intuitively to use. The training plans are fun and get increasingly difficult, helping to build up strength and techniques for real-world projects - like my trip to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html">Dolomites</a> next week. For me the Zlagboard is a great tool and I often just do a few pull-ups or hangs on it when standing in front of the computer gets too much. I really rate it very high and would recommend it to everyone who’d like to train at home with professional training plans &amp; measure the progress.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Lets get Strong!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can get your choice of Zlagboard directly from <a href="https://shop.vertical-life.info/products/zlagboard">Vertical-Life</a>, at the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/zlagboard-pro-trainingsboard/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/zlagboard-zlagboard-trainingsboard/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>. <em>And if you liked this post share it with your mates on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157655005832735">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19105861882" title="Pull-ups by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/517/19105861882_aecb349cd5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Pull-ups" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc'teryx Alpine Academy Chamonix 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-alpine-academy-chamonix-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-22T23:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-alpine-academy-chamonix-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A reflection on the fourth <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy in Chamonix</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18863780819" title="&quot;And over there...&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/518/18863780819_3527250da3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;And over there...&quot;" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>2015 was the 4th <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> overall and my second one to attend. I was lucky enough to be invited as a member of the Press this year so got a sneak peak at the cool new gear that will come next year from Arc’teryx, and like everyone got the chance to hang out with the athletes, try out cool gear from Arc’teryx, Petzl, Scarpa, MSR and LYO Food and have a great time in Chamonix with the other participants. Here’s a re-cap of the three clinics I visited, which should be interesting if you’re considering to visit the Arc’teryx Academy in 2016!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18860432990" title="At the Base Station by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/499/18860432990_234d5c5a7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="At the Base Station" /></a></p>

<h2 id="glacier-preparation-clinic">Glacier Preparation Clinic</h2>

<p>I haven’t been to Mer de Glace last year so decided that the <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/shop/a-beginners/clinic-03-glacier-preparation-clinic/">Glacier Preparation Clinic</a> would be a good start for the weekend in Chamonix. The Mer de Glace is also only at about 1.900 m height which makes for easier acclimatisation, which worked well for me - last year I went straight up to 3.800 m, and living at sea level that’s quite a bit of difference. </p>

<p>Our group of four were with BMG and IFMGA Mountain Guide <a href="http://stuartmacdonald.org/">Stuart MacDonald</a> which was a great guy which explained us everything we needed to know about walking on a Glacier. After taking the train up to the Grand Hotel Du Montevers we walked to the ladders and started the descent down to the Glacier. It’s an interesting thing, as less than 150 years ago you could walk onto the Glacier from where you embark the train - climate change is showing its ugly face here, and it will be interesting to see how much more the glacier will retreat.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19046370865" title="Grand Hotel Montevers Hotel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/474/19046370865_4085701c4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Grand Hotel Montevers Hotel" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18861943339" title="Down the ladders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/432/18861943339_3cebe64d02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Down the ladders" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19042575182" title="Boulder-hoping by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/396/19042575182_7cc12f1051_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Boulder-hoping" /></a></p>

<p>Once you’re down the ladders you walk over the moraine till you’re at the proper glacier. Here Stuart explained us how to put on our crampons and how to walk normally in them, which we did for a bit. Then we moved on to learn more crampon techniques, front pointing, and how to use our ice axe. If you haven’t used these ever before its a good clinic to get to know the basics, so that you can do for example glacier hikes in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18860391730" title="Rock &amp; Ice by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/296/18860391730_ff5a10a7f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rock &amp; Ice" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19042544702" title="Approach by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/255/19042544702_8efeb42fef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Approach" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19042558292" title="Jumping crevasses by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/284/19042558292_86aaae53c1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jumping crevasses" /></a></p>

<p>After that we went to a steep section where a glacial river has carved a deep gorge into the ice, set up anchors and started to first walk steep ice up, and then ice climb it. The latter exercise was great fun, as we went from two ice tools to one ice tool to no ice tool, which taught you about proper foot placement and keeping your balance. This was the most fun part for me and I could have done it all afternoon long. Alas, we wanted to catch the 15 o’clock train down so after everyone made a lap down and up we started the walk back to the train station. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18861939059" title="On belay by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/333/18861939059_bab394c014_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On belay" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18860454288" title="Stuart MacDonald, BMG &amp; IFMGA Mountain Guide by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/436/18860454288_fef1f40dd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stuart MacDonald, BMG &amp; IFMGA Mountain Guide" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19051268351" title="Ascending the ladders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/547/19051268351_a795791827_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ascending the ladders" /></a></p>

<h2 id="advanced-alpine-techniques">Advanced Alpine Techniques</h2>

<p>The Arête des Cosmiques has been on my Tick List for a long time, and I was a bit jealous when my mate did it last year in his Technical Mountaineering course while we did the Pointes Lachenal Traverse. Waking up on Saturday morning after maybe one Génépi too much I was sure that today I’d be going on the Cosmiques, and lo and behold: As I arrived punctually at the Aiguille du Midi base station <a href="http://www.chamonix-guides.eu/Trombinoscope/251/contact/jean_villard_guides/23-trombinoscope.htm">Jean Villard</a> told me with a smile that the weather is so good that he thinks we should do the Cosmiques today, because we can learn &amp; practice all the techniques on it that we should do in our <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/shop/c-advanced/clinic-06-sat-adv-tech-alpinism/">Advanced Alpine Techniques clinic</a>. We drove up in the first Gondola and met the two other clients who slept the night up on the glacier, roped up and started the approach to the Arête des Cosmiques. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053159461" title="The start of the Arête des Cosmiques by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/421/19053159461_dfe9b0da84_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The start of the Arête des Cosmiques" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19049953765" title="Jean Villard preparing the rope by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/559/19049953765_bf34d4de11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jean Villard preparing the rope" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19044428282" title="Blue-Bird weather by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/476/19044428282_6f2375c22a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Blue-Bird weather" /></a></p>

<p>At the Abri Simond hut we untied, roped up again and started up the route. It starts off with easy snow &amp; ice covered slabs which we protected with an occasional friend. At the Gendarme then came the first abseil, which had me a bit nervous - wrongly, though. Then it are a few more steps to the 2nd abseil, where you need to squeeze yourself backwards through a narrow chimney, which again was somehow feeling a bit dodgy to me, but again was no problem. After that followed some easy traversing to the 2nd tower, where we passed the <a href="http://www.chamonixtopo.com/digital-crack-aiguille-du-midi">Digital Crack</a>, the highest 8a in Europe. It looked like a beautiful line and should I ever reach that level, I’m sure to try it. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19023712866" title="Scrambling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/520/19023712866_9dcd627ea1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scrambling" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053150951" title="1st Rappel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/400/19053150951_91b1417a73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="1st Rappel" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18427455014" title="2nd Rappel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3931/18427455014_fb2865d367_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="2nd Rappel" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862277738" title="Follow the leader by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/488/18862277738_4b1a17e008_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Follow the leader" /></a></p>

<p>But our climbing, at a much lower grade, was coming: The 4a Crux pitch. Jean free soloed it up without problems - he probably does that route a dozen times per year, and he’s already very long a Mountain Guide! - and then we followed. It was very easy even with crampons on, so even if you’re not a climber this shouldn’t have you worried in my opinion. As we were the first rope team on the route that day and we lost our pursuers after the first rappel we had a leisurely lunch on top of the Crux pitch, enjoyed the Alpine Choughs which were sailing above us and the beautiful sunshine. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18863787319" title="The 4c Crux and Jean on belay! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/264/18863787319_bcc114fd65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The 4c Crux and Jean on belay!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862253370" title="Almost there by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/469/18862253370_a063ddcef1_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Almost there" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862284358" title="Jean having Johannes on belay by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/384/18862284358_8b84068d78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jean having Johannes on belay" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053145441" title="Alpine Chough take-off by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3925/19053145441_3139abbae2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Alpine Chough take-off" /></a></p>

<p>After the nice break we continued onto the North Face of the route, and it got a wee bit colder in the shadow. But the scrambling over large boulders and through chimneys kept us warm enough until we reached the final plateau before the Aiguille du Midi cable car station. I had Georg, Johannes and Jean walk up to a pillar to take a few photos, and the people on the view platform went completely mad =) As we climbed the wee ladder up we were welcomed like celebrities and had our photos taken with strangers!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053168201" title="&quot;And then you swing your leg over it like this!&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/391/19053168201_dd50af4a14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;And then you swing your leg over it like this!&quot;" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862276668" title="Final scramble by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3743/18862276668_b5f74731bb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Final scramble" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19053169731" title="The Aiguille du Midi Station by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3882/19053169731_e7d1eedeba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The Aiguille du Midi Station" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19044388832" title="A look back again by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/380/19044388832_4bd2b8c937_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="A look back again" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18862246870" title="And up the ladder to the station by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/343/18862246870_4104f5ecff_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="And up the ladder to the station" /></a></p>

<p>It was a four hour round trip for us four (three clients, one Guide) with one long break for lunch, if you go alone or just two you probably can do it in a couple of hours or less - when there’s not a lot of people on the route, as it is very popular! It definitely is worth a visit, as it is a very scenic route that’s great to practice alpine climbing and mountaineering skills.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19049977945" title="Arrived! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/474/19049977945_ff89f288f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arrived!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bigwall-climbing">Bigwall Climbing</h2>

<p>Sunday and <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/shop/c-advanced/clinic-19-sun-big-wall-climbing/">Bigwall Climbing</a> was a great combination. The Bigwall Climbing clinic was new this year and very popular, and I think for a good reason: With a Client to Athlete to Guide Ratio of 3:1:1 it’s a fantastic clinic to learn new skills, ask a lot of questions and practice a lot. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18863698930" title="On the way to the Gongola by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/562/18863698930_34a87765fc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On the way to the Gongola" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19025173796" title="Bigwall Clinic group by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3746/19025173796_f7399d1035_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Bigwall Clinic group" /></a></p>

<p>The Bigwall Climbing consisted of four stations: The Portaledge Station, Jumaring, and two Aid Climbing stations - one with friends and nuts, the other with pitons and skyhooks. Because of time constraints I only got to try the first three, but on the plus side I was able to practice how to ascend the rope with some of my own gear (<a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/wild-country-ropeman-mk2f-steigklemme/">Ropeman 2</a> + <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-micro-traxion-seilrolle/?pid=81">Micro Traxion</a> in case you’re wondering). <a href="https://www.facebook.com/marcandreclimb">Marc-André Leclerc</a> showed us how to jumar the traditional way, with two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/petzl-ascension-ascender/">Jumars</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/black-diamond-alpine-aiders-ladder/">Aider Ladders</a>. It was interesting to try this, as it always looks so easy in movies, but until you have found out the rhythm it wasn’t as easy as it looks!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18428873064" title="Marc-André explaining how to jumar by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3777/18428873064_d2a06da4f9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Marc-André explaining how to jumar" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19025176476" title="Me jumaring by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/366/19025176476_7e9f1d6c4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Me jumaring" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19045837982" title="Brett showing another way to jumar by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3892/19045837982_3aea9c2756_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Brett showing another way to jumar" /></a></p>

<p>After that <a href="http://arcteryx.com/Athlete.aspx?EN/PaulMcSorley">Paul McSorley</a> showed us how to set up a Portaledge Camp, keep the camp in order and haul gear up. It was super interesting and as Paul has slept a few nights in Portaledges it was cool to hear his stories and tips on how to camp comfortably on a Bigwall. Sleeping on a Portaledge in Yosemite is high on my list, and this clinic certainly has me psyched to make that dream come true some day soon.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18865219979" title="&quot;And that&#x27;s how you keep things tidy&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/316/18865219979_96ac17bd8d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;And that&#x27;s how you keep things tidy&quot;" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19045823222" title="Jasmine trying out the Portaledge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/523/19045823222_abc5ef9ff0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jasmine trying out the Portaledge" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18428878174" title="Knot Protector™ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/495/18428878174_8b0b55d11e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Knot Protector™" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19054563981" title="HAUL! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/373/19054563981_c69512dd4b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HAUL!" /></a></p>

<p>And then we went Aid Climbing. <a href="http://www.bigwall.ch/">Pesche Wüthrich</a> explained Hayden and me the ins and outs, and then we both scaled the crack on aid. Slowly. Because Aid Climbing, we learned, needs a lot of time. You place gear, clip in the ladder and Daisy Chain, slowly weigh it to see if it holds, then clip in your Fiffi hook, and repeat. The route we climbed was a super easy crack which we probably could have climbed half a dozen times without Aid gear on lead, but this was a cool way to try it out and learn about it. The beauty/ attractiveness of it is certainly that you can climb safely on your own.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18863695980" title="Pesche Wüthrich explaining Aid Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/496/18863695980_157b4b6db6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pesche Wüthrich explaining Aid Climbing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19051392185" title="Hayden about to try Aid Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/432/19051392185_ea1f897688_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hayden about to try Aid Climbing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18617727928" title="Hayden Carpenter Aid Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/424/18617727928_9a4196d5b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hayden Carpenter Aid Climbing" /></a></p>

<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>

<p>I arrived Thursday morning and left Sunday afternoon, but happily would have stayed a bit longer in this fine Alpine Climbing &amp; Mountaineering Playground. My 2nd Arc’teryx Alpine Academy was again a lot of fun &amp; very inspirational, where I met great people, learned new skills, and got to climb in Europe’s best alpine climbing destination. What made me very happy was that there were a lot of people from all skill levels who decided to come to the <a href="https://instagram.com/explore/tags/arcteryxacademy/">#ArcteryxAcademy</a> to learn mountaineering and climbing skills. I shared the rope with hillwalkers from the UK &amp; Malaysia, aspiring mountaineers from Austria and Bigwall Climbers from the USA, Canada and France, and met old friends from across the globe. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19045840552" title="Hiking into the fog by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3818/19045840552_36c47c9f90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hiking into the fog" /></a></p>

<p>Again I can only recommend aspiring mountaineers and alpinists as well as backpackers &amp; hikers who’d like to up their skills to visit the <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a>. This year there were less people which in my opinion improved the learning and safety on the mountains, and made the groups more cozy &amp; personal, with more time for asking questions and trying techniques. The price-to-quality ratio still is superb, and if you consider all the free stuff available - the <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/movie-night/">Movie Night</a>, the interesting <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/seminar-night/">Seminars</a> and the <a href="http://chamonix.arcteryxacademy.com/demo-gear/">Demo Gear</a> - it really is very affordable. I certainly will keep a weekend free for next year for the 5th Arc’teryx Alpine Academy - if you’re smart, you’ll too! </p>

<p>There’s a lot <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157654457553021">more photos on Flickr</a> and here are <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Tips on Accommodation &amp; Getting there</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19044416802" title="Rope team crossing Vallé Blanche by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/561/19044416802_c5d748fe08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rope team crossing Vallé Blanche" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DMM Demon Cams]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/dmm-demon-cams.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T23:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/dmm-demon-cams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dragons and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">Demons</a> are not just part of any good fantasy novel, but also hang on the harness of many Trad Climbers. And because for longer routes you need more than just a set of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/dmm-dragon-cams.html">Dragon Cams</a>, a pair of Demon Cams has found their way into my climbing pack. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16743368694" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7688/16743368694_34f21b81ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">DMM Demon Cams</a> arrived last spring and have been along to Olhava, the local crag close to Vaasa, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">rock climbing in Poland</a> and Alpine climbing in Chamonix. But why would I need a 2nd pair of cams besides the Dragons? Well, longer routes need more protection, the Demon Cams have different size ranges than the Dragon, are a single axle design and are lighter. That was enough reason for me to get a pair from <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, and since they have free shipping on orders over 50€ in Europe it has gotten pretty easy to order from them.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/49821137?color=cc0033&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="600" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The Demon is a combination of two DMM Cams: It takes the single stem of the Dragon and the Cams of the 4CU. They are single axle, single stem, with the trademark extendable Dyneema sling. The cam lobes make use of the 13.75° camming angle, have an Active strength rating of 14 kN (and a Passive rating of 10 kN) and are Made in Wales.</p>

<p>As you might know, cams are active protection. While the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts.html">nuts and hexes</a> have no moving parts, cams do have moving parts - this allows them to suit a wider range of cracks - where you might need to carry one or more different nuts to place them in a crack, a cam’s lobes can be moved by pulling on the trigger which makes them narrower &amp; thus you can enter it in a crack. Release the trigger and the lobes will wedge themselves into the rock, being, if placed correctly, a solid piece of protection. They are also versatile in the sense that you can use them passively - that is that you just place the cam as it is into a crack, much like a Nut, without pulling the trigger. Unlike the DMM Dragon Cams the Demon Cam has a lower passive strength rating than active rating. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16743368334" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8774/16743368334_eff30e3137_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>The Demons come without a carabiner, so I got the colour-coded <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-alpha-trad-non-locking-carabiner/">DMM Alpha Trad ‘biners</a> and two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-phantom-non-locking-carabiner/">Phantom carabiners</a> with the cams. The Trad biners are very nice and easy to clip, quite large and at 34 g they’re still light. The Phantom is only 26 g but you can easily feel and note the difference in size, its gate is also a bit heavier to clip. If you get pumped or nervous and want to be sure you can easily and quickly clip the rope, take the Alpha trad carabiners, they have a far better handling. Cam Lobes, slings and Alpha Trad carabiners can (and should!) be colour-matched for easily finding the right cam when you’re on the wall.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365876125" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8824/17365876125_aaf623fb92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>Back to the Demon Cams, and lets look at their weights. Here’s the weight of the Demon Cam alone and with a Alpha Trad carabiner.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Size 4,0: 223 g (259 g)</li>
  <li>Size 3,5: 182 g (218 g)</li>
  <li>Size 2,5: 129 g (165 g)</li>
  <li>Size 1,5: 102 g (138 g)</li>
  <li>Size 1,0: 98 g (134 g)</li>
  <li>Size 0,5: 90 g (126 g)</li>
  <li>Size 0: 84 g (120 g)</li>
</ul>

<p>The whole rack of seven Demon cams with Alpha Trad biners is 1.160 g. That is a tad heavier than the Dragons (the six of them including carabiners is 819 g) but the size range of the Demons here speaks for them. For comparison:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Size 4 Demon Cam (223 g) has a lobe size range of 64 to 100 mm</li>
  <li>Size 4 Dragon Cam (149 g) has a lobe size range of 38 to 64 mm</li>
</ul>

<p>This difference can be seen throughout the two Cam lines. If you want to have a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/camming-devices/">Cam</a> with a large operating range, then the Demon is the way to go my opinion.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365533331" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8899/17365533331_95f25e7afa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>The 8 mm Dyneema sling is extendable to 23 cm which allows you to carry less slings and quick-draws to the hills. I love this feature of the DMM Cams and wouldn’t want to miss it. DMM also thinks along and offers a service to re-sling the cams when the Dyneema slings become worn out, which is a sustainable and environmentally friendly service and makes the cams long-lasting.</p>

<p>Which brings me to Quality. Which is fantastic. I guess you have expected this already, but I really value these cams - as all my other gear from DMM - very highly. The flexible stem, durable materials that are anodized makes them long-lasting, also at <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">sea stacks</a>. They have seen quite a bit of use but still look pretty good, and I expect them to last many more years.</p>

<p>If there’s something which I don’t like about them, well they are expensive - but then so are most cams. I also am wondering why DMM does repeat colours on the cams and ‘biners - Gold, Blue and Silver are used twice in the same series, and with there being hundreds of colours this is a bit odd. I would wish DMM would add more colours in the future, this makes it easier to choose the right cam and eliminates mix-ups. Imagine you want to grab the large blue 3.5 cam but grab the tiny blue 0 cam? Also the stem could be a tiny bit longer, which would make it easier to place them in deep cracks. I also think they could be offered as a complete set with a carabiner (preferably for a better price than buying them separately). And finally, if they’d be a <em>tiny</em> bit lighter, well, I wouldn’t mind that either!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17158410927" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8854/17158410927_28d89d8448_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I really like <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/brands/dmm/">DMM</a> gear. It’s well-designed and Made in Europe, which I value a lot. With the climbing trips this year I reckon the Dragons and Demons will both see plenty of use, especially in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html">Dolomites</a> and here in Finland. If you’re new to Trad climbing and in the market for some active protection then you might want to have a chat with your climbing partners and see what they recommend for your home crag, but eventually, and especially when you will travel to go climbing, you will likely end up with a complete rack or more. With the Demons you get a superb single stem, single axle cam. You’ll value the extendable sling pretty quickly as it allows you to leave some Quick-draws at the bottom of the crag. They are easy to place and equally easy to remove if you second. These durable cams will not make you a better climber, but they are so long-lasting that they will see you become better over time. </p>

<p>You can get the complete DMM Demon Cam package at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a> in Europe and <a href="http://bit.ly/1JLrstV">Backcountry.com</a> in North America. And <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157652287977376">more photos are on Flickr</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365531111" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7734/17365531111_16a28f5bf1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
