<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: climbing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/climbing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-01T15:01:21+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DMM Demon Cams]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/dmm-demon-cams.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T23:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/dmm-demon-cams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dragons and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">Demons</a> are not just part of any good fantasy novel, but also hang on the harness of many Trad Climbers. And because for longer routes you need more than just a set of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/dmm-dragon-cams.html">Dragon Cams</a>, a pair of Demon Cams has found their way into my climbing pack. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16743368694" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7688/16743368694_34f21b81ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">DMM Demon Cams</a> arrived last spring and have been along to Olhava, the local crag close to Vaasa, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">rock climbing in Poland</a> and Alpine climbing in Chamonix. But why would I need a 2nd pair of cams besides the Dragons? Well, longer routes need more protection, the Demon Cams have different size ranges than the Dragon, are a single axle design and are lighter. That was enough reason for me to get a pair from <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, and since they have free shipping on orders over 50€ in Europe it has gotten pretty easy to order from them.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/49821137?color=cc0033&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="600" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The Demon is a combination of two DMM Cams: It takes the single stem of the Dragon and the Cams of the 4CU. They are single axle, single stem, with the trademark extendable Dyneema sling. The cam lobes make use of the 13.75° camming angle, have an Active strength rating of 14 kN (and a Passive rating of 10 kN) and are Made in Wales.</p>

<p>As you might know, cams are active protection. While the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts.html">nuts and hexes</a> have no moving parts, cams do have moving parts - this allows them to suit a wider range of cracks - where you might need to carry one or more different nuts to place them in a crack, a cam’s lobes can be moved by pulling on the trigger which makes them narrower &amp; thus you can enter it in a crack. Release the trigger and the lobes will wedge themselves into the rock, being, if placed correctly, a solid piece of protection. They are also versatile in the sense that you can use them passively - that is that you just place the cam as it is into a crack, much like a Nut, without pulling the trigger. Unlike the DMM Dragon Cams the Demon Cam has a lower passive strength rating than active rating. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16743368334" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8774/16743368334_eff30e3137_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>The Demons come without a carabiner, so I got the colour-coded <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-alpha-trad-non-locking-carabiner/">DMM Alpha Trad ‘biners</a> and two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-phantom-non-locking-carabiner/">Phantom carabiners</a> with the cams. The Trad biners are very nice and easy to clip, quite large and at 34 g they’re still light. The Phantom is only 26 g but you can easily feel and note the difference in size, its gate is also a bit heavier to clip. If you get pumped or nervous and want to be sure you can easily and quickly clip the rope, take the Alpha trad carabiners, they have a far better handling. Cam Lobes, slings and Alpha Trad carabiners can (and should!) be colour-matched for easily finding the right cam when you’re on the wall.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365876125" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8824/17365876125_aaf623fb92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>Back to the Demon Cams, and lets look at their weights. Here’s the weight of the Demon Cam alone and with a Alpha Trad carabiner.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Size 4,0: 223 g (259 g)</li>
  <li>Size 3,5: 182 g (218 g)</li>
  <li>Size 2,5: 129 g (165 g)</li>
  <li>Size 1,5: 102 g (138 g)</li>
  <li>Size 1,0: 98 g (134 g)</li>
  <li>Size 0,5: 90 g (126 g)</li>
  <li>Size 0: 84 g (120 g)</li>
</ul>

<p>The whole rack of seven Demon cams with Alpha Trad biners is 1.160 g. That is a tad heavier than the Dragons (the six of them including carabiners is 819 g) but the size range of the Demons here speaks for them. For comparison:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Size 4 Demon Cam (223 g) has a lobe size range of 64 to 100 mm</li>
  <li>Size 4 Dragon Cam (149 g) has a lobe size range of 38 to 64 mm</li>
</ul>

<p>This difference can be seen throughout the two Cam lines. If you want to have a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/camming-devices/">Cam</a> with a large operating range, then the Demon is the way to go my opinion.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365533331" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8899/17365533331_95f25e7afa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>The 8 mm Dyneema sling is extendable to 23 cm which allows you to carry less slings and quick-draws to the hills. I love this feature of the DMM Cams and wouldn’t want to miss it. DMM also thinks along and offers a service to re-sling the cams when the Dyneema slings become worn out, which is a sustainable and environmentally friendly service and makes the cams long-lasting.</p>

<p>Which brings me to Quality. Which is fantastic. I guess you have expected this already, but I really value these cams - as all my other gear from DMM - very highly. The flexible stem, durable materials that are anodized makes them long-lasting, also at <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">sea stacks</a>. They have seen quite a bit of use but still look pretty good, and I expect them to last many more years.</p>

<p>If there’s something which I don’t like about them, well they are expensive - but then so are most cams. I also am wondering why DMM does repeat colours on the cams and ‘biners - Gold, Blue and Silver are used twice in the same series, and with there being hundreds of colours this is a bit odd. I would wish DMM would add more colours in the future, this makes it easier to choose the right cam and eliminates mix-ups. Imagine you want to grab the large blue 3.5 cam but grab the tiny blue 0 cam? Also the stem could be a tiny bit longer, which would make it easier to place them in deep cracks. I also think they could be offered as a complete set with a carabiner (preferably for a better price than buying them separately). And finally, if they’d be a <em>tiny</em> bit lighter, well, I wouldn’t mind that either!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17158410927" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8854/17158410927_28d89d8448_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I really like <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/brands/dmm/">DMM</a> gear. It’s well-designed and Made in Europe, which I value a lot. With the climbing trips this year I reckon the Dragons and Demons will both see plenty of use, especially in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html">Dolomites</a> and here in Finland. If you’re new to Trad climbing and in the market for some active protection then you might want to have a chat with your climbing partners and see what they recommend for your home crag, but eventually, and especially when you will travel to go climbing, you will likely end up with a complete rack or more. With the Demons you get a superb single stem, single axle cam. You’ll value the extendable sling pretty quickly as it allows you to leave some Quick-draws at the bottom of the crag. They are easy to place and equally easy to remove if you second. These durable cams will not make you a better climber, but they are so long-lasting that they will see you become better over time. </p>

<p>You can get the complete DMM Demon Cam package at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/dmm-demon-cam-cam/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a> in Europe and <a href="http://bit.ly/1JLrstV">Backcountry.com</a> in North America. And <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157652287977376">more photos are on Flickr</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17365531111" title="DMM Demon Cams by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7734/17365531111_16a28f5bf1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DMM Demon Cams" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[David Flanagan | Rock Climbing in Ireland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/david-flanagan-rock-climbing-in-ireland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-01T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/david-flanagan-rock-climbing-in-ireland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ireland has more to offer than <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">Sea Stacks</a> - there’s superb crags across the country. David Flanagan’s “<a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a>” helps you plan your trip to the Emerald Isle - which has climbing on half a dozen types of rock to offer, at sea cliffs, in the mountains and beautiful crags!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17307673186" title="Rock Climbing in Ireland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7759/17307673186_e118d35b78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Climbing in Ireland" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Fellow climbers will easily be able to relate - get a new guide book into your hands and immediately you start thinking about a trip to the area the book presents. While I just returned from Ireland a couple of weeks ago browsing <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a> has me thinking about when I could again visit the island for some climbing - and plenty of awesome climbing there is in Ireland.</p>

<p>The book starts of with the basics you need to know about climbing in Ireland - Access and Conservation, Equipment, When to Visit, Accommodation and how to get around the island. A Crag Table lists all 22 crags and what sorts of routes you will find there, and then right away dives in with describing the different crags. These include a introduction, tips on accommodation in the area, what you could do on rainy or rest days, conditions and directions to the crag. A large overview photo often shows the crag and the different sectors, and a small, basic overview map helps with navigating. The Topos and Route descriptions are coming with good details and some great photos of the climbs will get you in the mood for a route. And finally, a Route Index at the end of the book lets you find a route quickly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17331763072" title="Rock Climbing in Ireland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8735/17331763072_7285ee4f9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock Climbing in Ireland" /></a></p>

<p>I loved the clean, minimalistic and well-structured layout of the Guidebook. It was aesthetically very pleasing to read, with a nice &amp; clear typography and great topo photos - these are something that make a climbing guide book not merely good, but great. What I missed was that some crags didn’t have information on accommodation and rainy &amp; rest days tips, I think for many people visiting from abroad it would help to have a recommendation for where to stay and what to do when the weather is shite. This is my only complaint (<em>and something you can find out yourself with the help of an online search</em>), and overall I would highly recommend this book to anyone who is planning to go rock climbing in Ireland. The beautiful guide book will make you look forward to visiting this beautiful island with the fair weather and gives you with over 400 routes in it more than enough inspiration of where to go &amp; what to climb!</p>

<p>Buy Rock Climbing in Ireland at your local book store or climbing gym, order it directly from the author at <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Three Rock Books</a>, or your local taste of <a href="http://amzn.to/1GCHy2y">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1zkr3e1">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1bKkvdP">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sea Stack Climbing in Ireland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-20T23:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ashfall Quartz. Ebb. Tide. Swell. Mix it together, throw in a rubber dinghy and you have the stuff for a Sea Stack climbing adventure.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002240157" title="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/17002240157_6342150a0a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>From the distance Berg Stack looks like a wee little rock in the North Atlantic Ocean, just off the cost of An Port in County Donegal, Ireland. We - Iain, our guide, a photographer and an US American journalist - slept the last night in the Port Cottage and now a blue sky &amp; sunshine have us frolicking in the superb weather. <em>“Lets go and check out the swell and tide”</em> Iain announces. We pack up our climbing gear and the 40€ rubber dinghy, bought at a Toy Shop - three at a time, they’re not that durable and walk the <a href="http://www.walkni.com/iat/">IAT</a> path up to the sea stack.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589476163" title="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8697/16589476163_e1526639df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left" /></a></p>

<p>What looked like a wee sea stack from the lawn of the cottage turns out to be a 25 m high sea stack with a large ledge at the bottom, beautiful cracks and pin scars lining it from bottom to top and a Great black-backed gull with its nest on top. Oh, and an angry Atlantic Ocean with a two to four metre swell, making for not a good time to cross. We still inflate the unnamed dinghy, Iain gives me the instructions of how to assist him when he will board the sea worthy vessel to establish a tyrollean traverse on Berg Stack so I can get over, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17023512169" title="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8693/17023512169_4922bee743_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The we sit &amp; wait. Observe the swell. Finally Iain decides we’ll come back at high tide later in the afternoon, when the sea should be calmer. Adrenaline that was build up in anticipation disappears, shoes go back on and we go for a nice hill walk, checking out Cnoc na Mara - the Sea Stack we had originally planned to go up, but with this sea that would have been too much risk. The views are spectacular, the valley deserted and I can make out a dozen of superb spots for a wild camp.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021928808" title="A look up Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5322/17021928808_206ed924b5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look up Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>Sea stack climbing is less about climbing, really. Sure, it helps if you can climb well and know how to place gear - it’s all trad - but it is just as much about the skill set an Alpinist has: Patience, Risk Assessment, Speed &amp; Efficiency. Maritime skills &amp; knowledge are also essential, knowing when the tide is coming in, how high the swell is, if it is safe, being patient. Finally, a bit of daring for an adventure is also needed. After all, if you think paddling in a toyshop rubber dinghy on the Atlantic is insane, then sea stack climbing is nothing for you.</p>

<p>We’re back on the main land and observe the sea. It is high tide, the swell is still high but every now &amp; then there’s a calm moment - and one of these Iain uses to paddle over to Berg Stack. An euphoric cry echoes over the sea and you can see how a load is off his shoulders. He sets up an anchor for the tyrollean traverse, and during the next calm moment he’s back on the main land. We discuss the strategy and then it all goes quick: the dinghy is back in the water and Iain is in it, surfing the swell, a 240 cm sling connecting him to the tyrollean. A calm moment comes, he paddles in and I jump in - and just as quick out again off on Berg Stack. We both howl a cry of victory, a victory over the tide and swell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021935758" title="Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5343/17021935758_1ab7fb492e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>From here on it’s all basic rock climbing: Harness and rock shoes come on, Iain racks up and we tie into the rope. I stand barefoot on the ledge, the swell crashing on the rocks around. Iain leads up a variation the <em>Cormorant</em> which he probably has climbed a dozen times and before long an “Off belay” call echoes down to me. It is a nice route with great hand and foot holds up till the middle to the arête, then it goes around the arête and up a wet corner, which is also the toilet of the Great black-backed gull and its offspring which were kind enough to let us top out there. A moment later I stand on the top of Berg Stack next to Iain, high-fiving him, and again we both let out a howl of victory. But this is not a sports climb where you just clip into the chain and then rappel off. No, this is a sea stack. And the sea is angry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002250497" title="Roping up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7651/17002250497_95a7de41ea_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Roping up" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002062747" title="Me on Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8706/17002062747_44b293c870_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Me on Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17209684205" title="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5448/17209684205_822563f419_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The easiest way off the top back to the ledge is to down-climb a corner to about two meters above the rushing sea, and then traverse the sea stack on superb ledges &amp; holds back to where we started. We short-rope and five minutes later stand next to our dinghy. The sea is lower, more rocks can be seen as the ebb comes in, but the swell is still high. <em>“Lets wait till the tide is out and then walk off”</em> Iain says, and so we deflate the dinghy which has served us so well on the way here, pack up and wait. Wait for the water to retreat, for the swell to let us escape from this rock.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589483823" title="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5342/16589483823_e771dc38d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183741396" title="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8700/17183741396_a98415b910_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell" /></a></p>

<p>The sea does not see a reason for letting us off, it wants to keep us. The swell is high and white foam rushes over the barnacle-covered rocks, which would otherwise allow us to easily walk off. The sun throws its last rays on the main land, we can see the hut from our ledge and the comfort of the warm fire in the cozy cottage and slowly we’re getting cold &amp; hungry. Low tide arrives, but the swell still throws up large, foamy waves over the rocks we should have just walked off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183747146" title="Cold feet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17183747146_b904d8e834_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Cold feet" /></a></p>

<p>Iain goes first, jumps the large gap and makes it just to the top of a big rock when a wave comes in. He brings me my approach shoes and throws them over, as I do not fancy jumping barefoot on wet, slimy rocks and risking a broken ankle. Waiting for the right moment I too make the jump, and a final victory cry echoes from the rocks - the land has me again. We pack up and in the falling dusk walk to the cottage, where a warm fire and cool beer are waiting for us. My appetite for sea stack climbing is awakened, but first I’ll need to hike further on the International Appalachian Trail to Northern Ireland, to return another day for more sea stack climbing adventures.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17022143920" title="Patience by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17022143920_703730e92f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patience" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>
<p>There’s a <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/sea_stack_guide">free Sea Stack Guide book</a> if you want to go sea stack climbing - it has almost all sea stacks in it. A selection of sea stacks you also find in the <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a> book. I would suggest you do your first sea stack with Iain from <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/">Unique Ascents</a> and learn the ins &amp; outs from him about the sea and getting safely on and off the sea stack. He’s also a great guy and you’ll have a lot of fun on a day out with him. You’ll need a sea-worthy vessel - maybe <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Rentals:::34.html">loan a packraft</a>, but be sure you also know how to use it and have an idea about the tide, swell and weather forecast. If a sea stack is too much adventure, check out the <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/undiscovered_donegal">Donegal rock climbers guide</a> and visit one of the local crags, though there are also <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=CfM3DTcHcS8">calm days on Berg Stack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17208905321" title="Port Donegal Cottage by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8763/17208905321_de9c296ae9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage" /></a></p>

<p>If you plan to climb in the area around An Port stay in the <a href="http://port-donegal.com/">Port Donegal Cottage</a> - either book via their website or on <a href="http://www.ownersdirect.co.uk/accommodation/p8069109">Owners Direct</a>. It has a wonderful cozy feel and relaxing in the bathtub after a day out on the sea will be so good that you don’t wanna go out. It sleeps eight and with some luck Roland, the owner, will be around and delight you with his stories from far away places.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021740458" title="Port Donegal Cottage Inside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7725/17021740458_6b9517e048_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage Inside" /></a></p>

<p>The nearest village via a road is Ardara where you find several accommodation options like the <a href="http://www.bayviewcountryhouse.com/">Bayview Country House</a> and also shops and the <a href="http://www.nancysardara.com/">Nancy’s of Ardara Pub</a> for a after-climb pint, though it adds at least 45 minutes driving to your approach. For rest days go to Glencolmcille in the neighbouring valley and visit the <a href="http://glenfolkvillage.com/">Folk Museum</a> where you can see how people lived in the last centuries in the area, grab a good cup of coffee and a bite.</p>

<p>Gear wise you will need Trad gear as there are no bolts. Bring cord and slings if you want to abseil and need to build an anchor. Most of all, be patient with the sea and be open for the adventure!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-13T21:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>How do you go about planning a trip to the Dolomites with a mate who is currently in Australia?</em> Easy: You both get the same guide book, book the flights together and then start going via Skype through the book to pick the climbs you wanna do. And that’s exactly how we are planning our trip to the Dolomites this summer, with our guide book of choice being <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16614176108" title="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7607/16614176108_d918a4f9ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’ve been dreaming/ planning/ pondering/ almost-booking-flights-to-the-Dolomites since around four years. Vivid are the memories of driving through them as a child with mom and dad on the way to Southern Italy and back to Germany, then a <a href="http://www.rockandice.com">Rock &amp; Ice article</a> a few years ago re-kindled that love to go and visit one of the most beautiful areas in Italy. Sure, there would be some sweet hiking and cycling there, but it will still be there at another time. Now, this trip, it will be about climbing Multi-Pitch Routes and do Via Ferratas, visit a <a href="http://www.messner-mountain-museum.it">Messner Mountain Museum</a> and enjoy the good life with a great mate.</p>

<p>And with the <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata</a> Guide Book the good life already starts at home with the planning. I have been since a few weeks each evening going through the Guide Book and found it a superb resource to plan our trip. It’s so easy to send a short message á la <em>“Check out that sweet Multi-Pitch climb on page 384! Wanna do that?”</em> and literally be on the same page. It makes deciding on climbs a lot faster and easier, too, because opening a page in a book is faster &amp; more convenient than surfing to a webpage.</p>

<p>So how is this book lay out? Well, it starts with a bit of (climbing) history of the region and its geology, gives tips on other books and maps, and then tells you all you need to know about the Logistics of getting there, getting around, where to eat, sleep and what to bring. Then there’s a chapter each on Via Ferratas and Climbing, with explanations of grades, gear and how to plan a trip on the routes. Very useful and open pretty much all the time is the overview map of the Region (page 26/ 27 ;) before the book goes into the details.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16800637951" title="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7620/16800637951_e9fa1116c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata" /></a></p>

<p>And details means in this case detailed maps of the Region/ sector, photos with drawn-in topos and in-depth descriptions of the Via Ferratas and climbs. I found these descriptions very good, they give a bit of extra information on how hard the climb could be and how long it could take. What I like best about the <a href="http://www.rockfax.com">Rockfax.com</a> Guide Book is that you can download either the sectors/ climbs or the whole book onto your smartphone, allowing you to leave the 926 g Guide Book at home and don’t need to carry it up a climb - smart stuff. At the end there’s a Route Index and another map of the region with a General Index. </p>

<p>So, for me this has been a wonderful Guide Book thus far. The photos are top-notch and have me very much looking forward to this trip. What could be improved would be probably a larger fold-out/ take-out map as I feel I’m checking it all the time - we’re not staying in one Region/ Sector but plan to see a lot, though if you have more time and/ or stay in one Region you’ll probably be happy as it is. Overall I’d say you should get this Guide Book if you plan to visit the Dolomites for climbing and Via Ferrata hiking - or you should get it if you want to have a very good reason to visit them =) It’s a beautiful book with inspiring photos, all the information we needed to plan the trip logistics and it has in-depth information on the climbs and Via Ferratas of the region. It has been a source of joy for me in the last weeks and has me very much looking forward to visit this Region again - lets hope the weather will be kind for climbing!</p>

<p>Buy the book directly from <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">Rockfax.com</a>, at your local climbing or book shop or order it from your favourite taste of <a href="http://amzn.to/1x0WARt">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1GMfr5H">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1GMfYVk">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/gaston-rebuffat-starlight-and-strom.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-06T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/gaston-rebuffat-starlight-and-strom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A book review of Gaston Rébuffat’s classic “Starlight &amp; Storm” - a <em>Must Read</em> for anyone just remotely interested in going outdoors.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16730495671" title="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8629/16730495671_870bcfb3e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I ordered Starlight &amp; Storm and a bunch of <em>“Classic Mountain Literature”</em> last autumn, probably after getting just another recommendation that it’s a superb book. Getting a book recommended several times sometimes makes me hesistant, but well, I love to read and as the mountains are far away at the moment reading about them is pretty much the next best thing (after browsing <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html">photography books</a> of the mountains). Rébuffat’s most well-known book is likely this one or <a href="http://amzn.to/1MbylRU">The Mont Blanc Massif: The Hundred Finest Routes</a>, and I think both books will be found on the bookshelf of a well-read mountaineer, alpinist or hill walker.</p>

<p>The book starts of with a short biography blurb on Rébuffat’s life which is followed by an introduction from Jon Krakauer, which is followed by yet another introduction, a Foreword and then finally you get to read Rébuffat’s words. Puh. Well, the good thing is that the good stuff starts right there with Rébuffat’ story of his ascent of the Grand Jorasses. This and the following chapters, where he descibes his adventures with friends of the great North Faces of the Alps is what really makes this book worth reading. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everything about the climbing of it was a joy, and as we climbed I seemed to understand the meaning of our exploit. It was not the increasing nearness of the summit,
or the climb in itself, that filled us with a quiet joy, but the feeling that mind and muscles were fulfilling their intended function. Somehow we were “in the right place.”
- Gaston Rébuffat, Starlight &amp; Storm, The North-east Face of Piz Badile</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16111754843" title="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8595/16111754843_88fc5b01dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gaston Rébuffat: Starlight &amp; Storm" /></a></p>

<p>I loved the accounts of how he tied up with clients and friends, how they spend nights on these big faces and enjoyed the starlight and peace of the night but welcomed the first rays of sunlight in the morning after a cold bivy, or how they turned around to come back another time because of bad weather. The Brotherhood of the Rope is strong in this book, and you feel that the people Rébuffat was climbing with were more than just climbing partners - they were brothers, sharing a single objective, living together on the rock, between the sky, ice, snow, wind and rain. </p>

<p>The chapters are short enough so that it’s easy to read them before going to bed or commuting to work in a week, and every Mountain chapter is accompanied by a Black-White photo of the mountain in question. What bothered me slightly was that the height and distance measurements where given in illogic feet, but apart from that I loved every part of the book. It’s a fascinating read, not just for alpinists and mountaineers, but also for people who wonder why one would climb a steep, inhospitable rock face. If you can not get to the mountains any time soon, I recommend you pick up this book and dream of having a bivy on one of these Northfaces! Buy the book at your local book shop or order it online from <a href="http://amzn.to/1NoHTMW">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1DRShVx">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/18WyyMF">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
