<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: climbing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/climbing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-02T12:08:14+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alan Hinkes: 8000 Meters]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T12:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ve probably seen a trend in my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">book reviews</a> in the last years: They’ve been more and more about mountaineering and climbing. Why that is so I’ll explain at another time, but now I want to take you along and tell you about the latest book I have read, <em>8000 Meters - Climbing the World’s Highest Mountains by Alan Hinkes</em>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15985413000" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Meters - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8658/15985413000_e521caa7ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Meters - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There’s 14 8.000 m peaks on this planet and Alan Hinkes is the first British Mountaineer to have successfully summited all fourteen of them. In his splendid coffee table book “<a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/tab/detail/iid/1/show/description#.VKZk6cbvR_0">8000 Meters - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</a>” he tells the stories and shares his fantastic photos with the reader. Its a chronological layout and after a Foreword, Preface and Introduction we start at Alan’s first 8.000 m summit, Shisha Pangma, which he climbed in 1987. </p>

<p>From that year one Alan has been almost every season in the Himalayas and Karakoram on a quest to climb 8.000 m peaks, even if climbing all 14 of them wasn’t something that he set out to from the start. His writing style is very enjoyable: Honest, down-to-earth and lacking hyperboles which easily could sneak itself in when writing about climbing the highest peaks on the planet. The thoughtful texts describe the experiences of climbing the high mountains, what kind of mental and physical difficulties one can face, from the waiting game in base camp while sitting out bad weather and passing frozen corpses high on the mountains to climbing difficulties and getting up and down these peaks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15986690559" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Meters - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7463/15986690559_90c9064a27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Meters - Climbing the World &#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<p>Alan’s climbing Motto is <em>“No mountain is worth a life, coming back is a success and the summit is only a bonus”</em> and throughout the book he also highlights the importance to have enough power reserves for the descent. What happens if you don’t have these Alan has seen in his friends on some expeditions, which burned themselves out on the ascent and then had no energy left for the descent, which often is even more dangerous than going up. </p>

<p>In between chapers there are small anecdotes from Alan’s encounters with fellow mountaineers like Reinhold Messner and Jerzy Kukuczka or the Trek-Ins to base camps and local cuisine. These loosen up the already enjoyable peak stories. A real highlight for me are the fantastic photos Alan has shot during his ascents and from his travels to these two mountain ranges. The photos were shot before the rise of automatic digital cameras and so one needed to know how to adjust ISO, Aperture and Shutter Speed to get great results, and the photos in this book are proof that Alan knows his trade. I have spent a lot of time just browsing the photos, tracing the lines described in the texts to the summit, and enjoy the vast views which you can have when standing on the top of the world. </p>

<p><em>8000 Meters - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</em> is a highly enjoyable book that shouldn’t be missing on your bookshelf if you like mountaineering, alpinism and are dreaming of the highest peaks of the planet. The honest &amp; evocative writing is on par with the superb images in the book, and if you ever hope to stand on top of a 8.000 m peak you will do well to read Alan’s book and follow his Motto!</p>

<p>Get the book at your local bookshop, directly form <a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/title/8000-metres#.VKZejsbvR_0">Cicerone</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/1wIIMnr">Amazon.de</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1xzM7fy">Amazon.com</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1yehuvP">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard Interview]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T11:11:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An interview with Barry Blanchard, one of Canada’s most famous Alpinists, in which we chat about music, fear and his book “<a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">The Calling</a>”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15606594195" title="Barry Blanchard by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5608/15606594195_52bea0a1b6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Barry Blanchard" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Barry, thanks for taking the time to answer a few questions from an aspiring Alpinist in Finland. First things first: What song are you right now listening too?</strong></p>

<p><em>Snake Farm by Ray Wylie Hubbard. I’ve listen his music since I was teenager and had the pleasure of meeting the man, and his wife, Judy, yesterday at a concert in the park. Very, very cool.</em></p>

<p><strong>What’s your favourite medium: MP3, Vinyl or Cassettes?</strong></p>

<p><em>I listen to most music on my computer these days so I guess its MP3, although I still listen to CDs in my truck.</em></p>

<p><strong>If you would make a mixtape for a road trip, which songs would definitely be on there?</strong></p>

<p><em>On my road tripping mix there would definitely be: King of the Road by Roger Miller, Six Days on the Road by Dave Dudley and a cover by Steve Earle, Hurtin Albertan by Corb Lund and by Tim Hus, Running on Empty by Jackson Browne, Continental Trailways Blues by Steve Earle, Brand New Cadillac by the Clash, Cadillac Ranch by Bruce Springsteen, Born to Run by Bruce Springsteen … and the list goes on.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15421002960" title="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/15421002960_d3178af41a_b.jpg" width="678" height="1024" alt="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p><strong>I really enjoyed reading your book, by the way. It was raw, to the point and I had a few good laughs. It also had a Quentin Tarantino-esque feel to it at times: Good music, story lines that interweave and come together at the end. Did you plan it like that?</strong></p>

<p><em>My friend, Mark Twight, told me that my book would not end up being what I thought it would be, and that it would be more work than I thought it would be. He was right on both counts. I wanted to write a full 360 degree view of my life and climbing as I believe that much of the value in my writing is that which is common to all people: love, loss, desire, fear, hurt, joy. I believe I share the most that way and that is what writing is for me, a hope to share a little something about life with people.</em></p>

<p><strong>The weather this summer in Chamonix seems to have been much the same as you first visited the crucible of European Alpinism. Any idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer?</strong></p>

<p><em>I have no idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer. Mark Twight and I were pleased to see that our route, The Richard Cranium Memorial, had several repeats in the last couple years and that the ascensionists seemed to enjoy it.</em></p>

<p><strong>Reinhold Messner, another of your idols judging from your book, just got 70 in September. Did you send him a card or where even invited?</strong></p>

<p><em>Reinhold didn’t invite me to his birthday, but he might have invited my guiding mentor, Rudi Kranibitter, who took Reinhold out climbing in Reinhold’s early days and taught him some stuff. Rudi once told me “Ya, that guy was a fast learner!”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14985858864" title="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/14985858864_8c1c2399df_b.jpg" width="710" height="1024" alt="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You are well-read and have devoured a lot of books - from Heinrich Harrer’s “The White Spider” to Lionel Terray’s “Conquistadors of the Useless”. If you could recommend just three books to aspiring alpinists, which ones would that be?</strong></p>

<p><em>I would recommend: <a href="http://amzn.to/1xc7z5m">The Great Days</a> by Walter Bonatti, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vRe3bB">The Seventh Grade</a> by Reinhold Messner and <a href="http://amzn.to/12gRwtY">Feeding the Rat</a> by Al Alvarez.</em></p>

<p><strong>One of your colleagues, Andy Kirkpatrick from the UK, made in his essay “How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche” his first point to not have kids. You’re a father of two - do you feel you climbed harder pre-fatherhood or that you stayed on the same level?</strong></p>

<p><em>I definitely climbed harder before the birth of my daughters but I became a father at 45 and I was, by then, far past my physical prime that was, for me, between 25 and 35. I just can’t climb as hard now, especially at 55! as I could when I was younger. But! the inner journey up the easier mountain is still as challenging and rewarding, maybe more so on both counts.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15582918726" title="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3951/15582918726_29591133dd_b.jpg" width="672" height="1024" alt="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee" /></a></p>

<p><strong>As someone who likes to climb mountains myself it feels like the majority of climbers nowadays are rather enjoying themselves in gyms or bouldering. How would you try to get these people outside?</strong></p>

<p><em>I think that once gym climbers and boulders experience the added challenges of traditional climbing, especially dealing with risk, some of them will be called to the richness of alpinism, but it is a dangerous game so it is not for everyone.</em></p>

<p><strong>Is there a chapter of your climbing life that you wished would have made it in the book still?</strong></p>

<p><em>When I sat down to write The Calling I thought that it would cover my whole climbing life, but I’ve been cursed with a long memory and seemed to have a lot to write. I’d like to write a second book to cover the rest of my climbing life beyond 1988.</em></p>

<p><strong>Well Barry, many thanks again and have fun on the book tour!</strong></p>

<p><em>You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">read my Review of Barry’s book “The Calling” here</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard - The Calling]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T06:23:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What do Joy Division, The Rolling Stones, Les Droites, Nanga Parbet and the Cassin Ridge have in common?</em> They play a part in Barry Blanchard’s life, which is aptly re-told in his memoirs, “The Calling”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15451426995" title="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15451426995_53b9507d6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="675" alt="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge.of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Tune in to the soundtrack of Barry’s life with this Playlist, dutifully reconstructed from Chapter 2:</p>

<iframe src="https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify:user:skullmonkey:playlist:7qy8hUL8yIyABU8JFRfj3z" width="300" height="380" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true"></iframe>

<p>Alpinism and mountaineering books tend to often be of interest only to pursuers of these activities. But Barry manages to write his memoirs in such a compelling edge-of-your-seat style that also non-climbers will be eagerly turning each page to read how the stories unfold. And unfold they do. And if you haven’t heard of Barry before, that’s easily fixed: He is <em>one of North America’s top alpinists, noted for pushing the standards of highly technical, high-risk alpine climbing in the Canadian Rockies and the Himalayas.</em> But nobody is born an alpinist, even if it is their calling.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264859557" title="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15264859557_249539e96d_b.jpg" width="660" height="1024" alt="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the.exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never.been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p>In 20 chapters <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">The Calling</a> stops at important stations in Barry’s life, but does not take a linear approach. It’s more a Tarantino style, weaving stories together, jumping between different stations, different countries, different mountains, different climbing partners. It starts off with an Avalanche and only later on you learn more about how the four rope partners ended up in that situation on a high Himalaya peak. It’s followed two chapters on how Barry grew up and how he got into climbing (via the Canadian equivalent of the Boy Scouts), and that especially will be of interest to aspiring alpinists and climbers around the globe. From how he loaned books at the library on how to climb to saving up to buy his first climbing shoes, it shows that Barry is from a pre-Internet era where you couldn’t just order the latest gear and books online - but often head to search in shops across town to find what you wear looking for.</p>

<p>Really interesting are the personal stories and how Barry manages to illustrate his climbing partners: Kevin and Ward, Gregg and David, Mark and Phil and many more. If you climb, especially in the mountains, you know how important it is to be able to totally trust the person at the other end of the rope, and Barry is able to communicate that trust between climbing partners wonderfully. The story accompanies Barry and his partners as they learn to climb - from Trad at the Wasootch Slabs with Phil to alpine climbing the Calgary Route on Mt Yamnuska with Gray, all told in such a fun way that I couldn’t help but chuckle a few times. After a stop in Chamonix and taking Rebuffat’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1pECtyN">The Hundred Finest Routes</a> as a tick-list Barry travels a bit through Europe (and manages to lose his wallet and passport) before heading back to Canada and onwards to Yosemite. We see how Barry makes the decision to quit his salesman job to go more climbing and becoming a guide, all while repeating hard routes in Canada and the USA.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15448265551" title="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3929/15448265551_a50450ccbc_b.jpg" width="676" height="1024" alt="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p>And as the walls and routes keep getting bigger &amp; more committing we accompany Barry to the Karakoram &amp; Himalaya, to Peru and the Cassin Ridge and read captivating accounts of daring alpine ascents. Always interweaved are anecdotes from his time - be it books (I got away with a whole list of books to read) to music (see above) to relationships and how climbing gear has evolved. The writing is lively &amp; outspoken and I often was laughing out loud, and it was able to keep me on reading until I finished the book in a week, often reading in my lunch breaks and late till night. It were the personal connections with his rope partners that I found very fascinating and that kept me on reading past bedtime, how they pushed themselves on to become better climbers, train together, climb together, party together and go on expeditions together, all while trying to figure out how to be able to get out more to the mountains. If you have a longing for the mountains but can’t be in them as much as you like (and don’t want to quit your job just yet for them), I can warmly recommend you this fine book for your mountain fix. It’s captivating style with adventures from near &amp; far will keep you entertained for many days, and after you’re done you’ll go through the book again - to search out some of the books Barry mentioned, look up a song and re-read about the daring ascents.</p>

<p>Get your paper or digital copy today from <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">Patagonia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1rTGvIH">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vDx8O1">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1nTA8oO">Amazon.de</a> or your local book store.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264720600" title="The Calling Cover by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15264720600_920b3f8714_b.jpg" width="674" height="1024" alt="The Calling Cover" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Petzl RocTrip 2014 - Eastern Europe]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/petzl-roctrip-2014-eastern-europe.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-28T18:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/petzl-roctrip-2014-eastern-europe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Romania, Bulgaria, Macedonia, Greece and Turkey are host to the 2014 Petzl RocTrip which this year takes the form of a road trip. Come and join this great event and hang out with the likes of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">Ueli Steck</a>, Saïd Belhaj, Dave Graham, Mélissa Le Nevé, Nina Caprez and many more while exploring the crazy good climbing that can be had in Eastern Europe!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14843495327" title="Petzl RocTrip 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14843495327_53dc68084a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl RocTrip 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The first time I became aware of the <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en">Petzl RocTrip</a> was in 2011, when I saw some photos from the event in China. Then in 2012 the video of the event was published and it was mind-blowing. I still love to watch it, and if you have a moment watch it here.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/EcU255XBlcI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In 2013 the Petzl RocTrip traveled to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QllWNEGBKic">Argentina</a> and it was equally inspiring. In 2013 it returned closer to home to the Gorges du Tarn, and now in 2014 the event is back and takes a new, unique format: A road trip across five countries in Eastern Europe. This is a great idea on so many levels, as it promotes what climbing is about in many ways: Travel to new crags, explore new countries, meet new people, climb new types of rock, experience different cultures. In a way it is promoting the dirtbag lifestyle, in a slightly more comfortable way! The teaser sets the mood well:</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/92311979?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>What is special about the RocTrip are the low costs for taking part in the event: It’s just 15€! Comparing that to the costs of some other events this is <em>very affordable</em>. It’s well organized (<a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/practical-information">check the practical information</a>) and you get the opportunity to climb in some unique locations with members of the <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/news/spend-time-your-favorite-athletes-during-2014-petzl-roctrip">Petzl Pro Team</a>. </p>

<p>Interested? Then <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/join-us">pre-register until August 31th, 2014</a> to one (or all!) of the camps you would like to join. <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/practical-information#Transport">Organize your transportation</a>, for example join the carpool or get a ride in the Petzl bus. Book your flights (I’m flying to Antalya which is a smooth connection if flying from Helsinki, Stockholm or Oslo). Then start your <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html">climbing training</a> so you’re fit for the hundreds of routes which will be waiting for you! The Petzl Roctrip website has a lot more information available, so check it out, pick the locations you want to join and pre-register! </p>

<p>I will be joining the Roctrip on the last two stops in <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/base-camp/geyikbayiri-turkish-style-columns">Geyikbayiri</a> and <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/base-camp/olympos-climb-sky-fall-water">Olympos</a> and you’ll be able to read about it here and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>. But I really hope to meet some of you in Turkey =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en" title="Petzl RocTrip 2014 website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5593/14867744620_2815c6ed8c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="640" alt="Petzl RocTrip 2014 website" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Climbing Gear for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/climbing-gear-for-kids.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-09T13:39:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/climbing-gear-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Climbing is fun, and it’s even more fun to have your children along. In this article I share some thoughts on climbing with litte kids &amp; highlight some kids climbing gear that has worked well for us.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14863252951" title="Kids Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3865/14863252951_76a691f99f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kids Climbing" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Our son always has climbed: First on chairs and the sofa, up stairs and even on top of the table when no-one was looking. Taking him along to the climbing gym and outside bouldering and rock climbing, he quickly also wanted to climb like dad. As normal shoes are fairly inadequate for climbing and I want to encourage him to climb &amp; have fun, I did quite a bit on research on kids climbing gear: Interviewing friends who go climbing with their little ones, comparing at online shops and reading the handful of reviews on blogs. So that you have an easier time picking good gear for your little one to come along and climb safely &amp; have fun, here’s our gear recommendations.</p>

<h2 id="shoes">Shoes</h2>

<p>As children grow fast almost all <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kletterschuhe/fuer--kinder/">kids climbing shoes</a> are available in adjustable sizes. It hurts in the wallet if you need to buy a new pair each four to six months and at a regular price of around 50€ <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/kletterschuhe-kinder/">climbing shoes for kids</a> ain’t cheap. We bought the <a href="http://bit.ly/1A2essj">Climb X Monkey</a> in EU Size 29 (16 cm inside length). The Monkey print on them is a nice touch for kids, and parents will appreciate the large Velcro closure which makes it super easy to put on. In the heel there is a 2nd Velcro strap which lets you adjust the size. It has a flat, grippy rubber sole, a rubber toe bumper and the rubber goes up in the heel, too - ideal for heel hooks. The toe box is wide if I compare them to my shoes so you won’t damage your kids feet. The rubber sole is thick but still lets the little ones climb very precise - I’m often surprised by how well he can stand on narrow ledges with the shoes. </p>

<p>I usually buy his shoes a number larger and adjust the size then via the Velcro strap, that way we get more usage out of them. As it’s now summer sale in most shops it’s a good decision to check out what they have on offer - at least at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kletterschuhe/fuer--kinder/">Bergfreunde</a> all kids climbing shoes are almost 15 or more % reduced in price right now, so a good opportunity to pick up a pair. If you only go bouldering then a pair of shoes is pretty much all you’ll need for the start, but if you also do a lot of rock climbing you also might want to pick up a kids harness.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14864052894" title="Climb X Monkey Kids climbing shoe by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5568/14864052894_5cfb04c66a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Climb X Monkey Kids climbing shoe" /></a></p>

<h2 id="harness">Harness</h2>

<p>Our son started climbing before he was two years old and since then has been climbing indoors &amp; outdoors and often comes along bouldering with me. As I really like rock climbing I decided to buy him a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/klettergurte/fuer--kinder/">Kids harness</a> so he can come along to the gym and crag once and a while. After some research I quickly settled on the <a href="http://bit.ly/1h4WCge">Edelrid Fraggle</a> - it’s a full-body harness, affordable and easy to use. We use the XXS Size since January 2014 and I expect we’ll get another year or one and half out of this harness. The XXS size goes from a Torso length of 50 to 70 cm and the leg loops go till 37 cm in diameter and can carry a child up to 40 kg. </p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/1olaR65">Edelrid Fraggle</a> is easy to put on: Two leg loops and two arm loops with two buckles to adjust the size - one in the front, one on the backside. A Buckle closes the harness below the tie-in loop. It’s padded &amp; comfy and my son wears it often the whole time we’re at the crag until we go home. What’s special about it is that in the back it has a 2nd loop, which is ideal for kids that already can climb on their own but are too light and tend to get stuck when you lower them. In this back loop you can tie in a 2nd rope, wicht which you can gently pull the child down when it is stuck again. If your child is already a bit older and can already sit upright in a harness by itself then a normal harness like the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/edelrid-finn-kinderklettergurt/">Edelrid Finn</a> would be a good solution. For more safety you can add the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/edelrid-kermit-brustgurt/">Edelrid Kermit Chest Harness</a> which is compatible with any (normal) harness. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14679865078" title="Edelrid Fraggle - Back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5571/14679865078_e58cf79c49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Edelrid Fraggle - Back" /></a></p>

<h2 id="helmet">Helmet</h2>

<p>There are dedicated kids climbing helmets, like the <a href="http://bit.ly/1A2eFM4">Petzl Picchu</a>. While safety is of the utmost importance for us if we go climbing with our son we thus far have used my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Petzl Sirocco</a> for my son as with a thin beanie underneath it can be cinched down to a good fit for him. When he will be older &amp; we’ll be more regularly rock climbing he will get his own helmet (maybe the new <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-1.html">Edelrid Kids helmet</a>) but for now we use the Sirocco. If you’re child already has a bicycle helmet, that’d be an option that could work in a pinch, too.</p>

<h2 id="clothes">Clothes</h2>

<p>Clothes for climbing should be durable and give freedom of movement. It’s astounding how fast kids learn just by seeing what mom and dad do: We once were bouldering and I heel hooked, and the next time it was my sons turn to climb he started to also heel hook - without me having told him so! It’s a case of monkey see, monkey do =) So pants and shirts should not inhibite movement and should be robust: The little ones will often lean against the rock to take a break or slide down on it, so unless you want to buy new clothes after each climbing trip it’s well worth it to buy durable garments that have reinforcements in the seat and knees.</p>

<p>We like <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/">Isbjörn of Sweden</a> and so does our son, too. The <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.13.841/trapper-pant-cordura">Trapper Pant Cordura</a> has the afore-mentined reinfocements in the knee and seat area, made of Cordura these pants take any abuse my son throws at them. To keep mosquitos and UV rays at bay he wears the very cool <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.13.1339/mountain-longsleeve">MOUNTAIN Longsleeve</a> which has a topographic print of the Kebnekaise on it. Made from Tencel it’s soft on the skin and his favourite piece to wear when we go outdoors. If there’s a chance of rain then the <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.16.776/light-weight-jacket">Light Weight Jacket</a> comes into the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/fjaellraeven-kanken-mini-daypack/">backpack</a>. Made from a wind- and waterproof fabric with a high collar and removable hood, it’s a nice jacket that keeps him dry &amp; warm in bad weather. Finally, to keep the ears warm and make the helmet fit better we have the soft merino wool <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.18.878/beanie-extended">Isbjörn Beanie</a> along. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14680213960" title="Isbjörn of Sweden Kids clothing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5562/14680213960_fab69a0d94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="760" alt="Isbjörn of Sweden Kids clothing" /></a></p>

<h2 id="good-mood-snacks-and-toys">Good mood, snacks and toys</h2>

<p>Probably most important when we go to the crag is that there’s a good atmosphere and setting no objectives &amp; high expectations. When my son doesn’t want to climb but rather play with his toys or eat some fruit - that’s a decision I happily accept. Forcing kids likely will result in the opposite so he only climbs when he likes to do it. So one, two toys and snacks (We carry apples, water melon, sandwiches and nuts along &amp; go pick raspberries &amp; blueberries where available) are important to have along so he can be entertained. Often he likes to sit and watch what mom &amp; dad are doing and cheers us on. A couple more things are important to have along:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A full <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/klean-kanteen/">water bottle</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/mawaii/">Sunscreen</a></li>
  <li>A sun hat</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/julbo-looping-ii-spectron-4-baby-sonnenbrille/">Sunglasses</a></li>
  <li>The rain jacket in case the weather turns</li>
  <li>Something comfy to sit on (I use some segments of a <a href="http://bit.ly/1yguVGx">ZLite</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p>The last time we were at the crag I walked up to the top of the cliff with my son and we wanted to try to rappel down, so he can see how to “<em>walk down</em>”. We were almost over the lip as I realized that he didn’t seem to like it, so we made the two steps back up to the cliff and saved the rappel experience for another time. I think as a parent it is important in these situations to be <strong>a)</strong> Aware if the little one is doing fine and <strong>b)</strong> If one’s owns plans are feasible &amp; safe. If either of these questions is answered with “No” it’s a smart solution to just walk back down.</p>

<p><strong>That’s it. A pair of shoes, a harness and helmet along with comfy clothes, snacks and some toys and you’re ready to take you daughter or son along for a safe, fun climbing trip =)</strong></p>

<p><em>Here’s the small print: Climbing is dangerous and as a responsible adult you should know what you’re doing. Don’t do dangerous stuff when the health of your child is at risk, don’t force them to do things, and most of all, have fun. You’re a hero for them already, no matter if you manage to top out or not. Be wise &amp; be a good example.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14121989044" title="Kids Bouldering &amp; Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5221/14121989044_4ed8072ff0_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Kids Bouldering &amp; Climbing" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
