<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: approach shoes | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/approach-shoes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-26T18:16:04+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/arcteryx-acrux2-fl-gtx.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-07T20:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/arcteryx-acrux2-fl-gtx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Acrux² FL GTX from <a href="http://arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a> is the Canadian brand’s entry into the approach footwear business. Made of an hydrophobic outside and a Gore-Tex slipper with a Vibram MegaGrip sole, it is a unique shoe. How it performed in the outdoors, you can read here.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17203304149" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Side and Sole by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7794/17203304149_daccb18e5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Side and Sole" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The Acrux² FL GTX arrived in late March and has been along on the International Appalachian Trail in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ireland/">Ireland</a>, where I wore it for seven days straight in rain and sunshine. I usually review gear only after a long period of time - often a year or longer - but as there’s a lot of interest in this shoe I wrote this initial review. I will update it after more use in the future. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16767071834" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX at the coast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8700/16767071834_2caf372641_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX at the coast" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX is two shoes in one: A Gore-Tex liner (blue) and a Hydrophobic shell shoe (black). For simplicity’s sake I will refer to them as the liner and shell. As an approach shoe it’s function is to allow you to get easily to the crag and back and for that it has a grippy sole with a climbing zone in the toe area which allows you to do easy scrambles in them. The shell does not absorb water and the liner has a Gore-Tex lining, which makes it highly water-resistant.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Technical alpine approach footwear for multiple days spent in variable weather &amp; terrain.</em> - Arc’teryx</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17389527535" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Liner bootie and its insole by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5329/17389527535_206647f76f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Liner bootie and its insole" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>As from Arc’teryx’s website:</p>

<p>Sole: 
<br />- 3D moulded Ortholite™ footbed
<br />- Vibram® MegaGrip™ sole
<br />- 14 mm Heel Drop
<br />- Sharp heel brake and mountaineering heel tread</p>

<p>Shell:
<br />- Seamless one piece upper with thermolaminated construction
<br />- EVA foam midsole
<br />- Hydrophobic material</p>

<p>Liner:
<br />- Tongue free liner
<br />- Low height, light weight
<br />- Arc’teryx Adaptive fit is an independent liner that conforms to the foot for a custom fit with no pressure points
<br />- Stetchable GORE-TEX® liner
<br />- Completely removable, interchangeable liner
<br />- Rubberized sole</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EcIPgSWo_cA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Arc’teryx separated the shell and lining of a traditional shoe and made two separate ones out of it, while re-designing both. So the upper is made from a single-piece of fabric, with a TPU-coating on the non-perforated parts which make them abrasion-resistant and let them shed water easily. The shell is also not sewn, but all parts are laminated together for a seam-free feel, which minimizes the risk of blisters and chaffing.</p>

<p>While there might have been shoes like these before, Arc’teryx is the first brand in recent time that brings a shoe with a removable liner to market. What’s very special is that the liners of the Acrux² and the Bora² are interchangable - which means you can use the high, insulated liner of the Bora in your Acrux, or if you need more water-protection in the Acrux use the high Gore-Tex bootie liner - They all work together. The liner is also thought to increase the airflow inside the shoe, which should maximize ventilation. It’s made from stretchable materials which hug your feet for a comfortable feeling, all day long.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17363563336" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX 0.1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7789/17363563336_c26f9bc77a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX 0.1" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The quality of these shoes - both liner and shell - is superb as you expect from Arc’teryx. The whole construction is very tidy and clean, with no little threads hanging around. The laminated upper is super smooth and stylish, while the liner bootie has minimal seams and is very comfortable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17203302069" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Shell, insole and liner bootie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7762/17203302069_35755460e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Shell, insole and liner bootie" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX is a medium-weight shoe, in EU Size 42 they weigh:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Liner: 126 g</li>
  <li>Shoe: 371 g</li>
  <li>Total: 499 g</li>
  <li><strong>PAIR 998 g</strong></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17389527005" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 0.5 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8710/17389527005_3de2af25d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 0.5" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The Acrux² FL GTX is a stylish shoe. If you travel a lot to go climbing &amp; hiking and also will spend some time in civilization, airplanes, hotels and B&amp;Bs the Acrux FL² GTX are great beacause while they are functional approach shoes they also could pass as a stylish city sneaker. I used them as a scramble and approach shoe as I was <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">sea stack climbing</a> and there they worked fantastic. The Vibram MegaGrip sole had superb traction on the wet slabs at the coast, and the small climbing zones at the toes allowed for good foot placements on small ledges. </p>

<p>Also for hiking the shoes were very comfortable, even in hot weather (more on that underneath). I was a bit worried before flying to Ireland if the shoe would be too hot and might give me blisters, but the truth was that even on long, high kilometer days the shoes were comfortable and I finished the trip without blisters, even on those close to 20°C sunshine &amp; blue-bird days. The laces were very good and did not come undone, something which has been a problem with some other shoes. The shoe is comfortable all day long, the liner hugs my foot nicely and you can lace up the shell as loose or tight as you like. At 499 g per shoe they’re medium weight but I didn’t get tired feet in the shoes. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17203380689" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7681/17203380689_b77edb80bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX" /></a></p>

<p>Now one of the design ideas of this shoes was that you can take the Gore-Tex liner out if it gets wet and can dry it overnight in your sleeping bag or tent. In practice I am not sure if it works, to get the liners dry again I needed to place them close to a radiator so that they would be dry the next morning; if there was no heat source then they were still moist the next morning. It could be that if you take the moist liners into your sleeping bag at a bivy that they will dry out well, but in my limited tests I am not sure if it works. An alternative could be to carry a 2nd pair of liner booties - at 126 g they’re not too heavy - and so ensure always dry feet. What I missed in this respect was that the shell did not have some drainage/ ventilation holes at the sole-level, this would help to get water out faster when you wade through a stream (or bog!).</p>

<p>What the liners are really great for is being used as a camp shoe. I used them to stroll around and the grippy rubber sole and light weight made them excellent for that. I also can imagine them to work very well for <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/packrafting/">packrafting</a>, where you can use them as your bootie in the packraft and the complete shoe for hiking. I jumped from rock to rock over the Atlantic with them on my sea stack adventure and they gave good grip on the wet &amp; salty rocks at the Irish coast, which means for me that they should be good as a paddling booty. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17182072687" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 1.0 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7786/17182072687_852f3232fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 1.0" /></a></p>

<p>Fit-wise I found the liner and shell to be both spacious. The EU Size 42 shoe gave me plenty of space inside the liner bootie to move my toes around, and when laced tighly they gave me good control and feel on small ledges. The heel did feel a bit wider and could for me be more narrow, but with a sock that’s well-cushioned in the heel you will have a good feel and should be fine. Overall a good &amp; spacious fit for my normal feet with plenty of space for movement.</p>

<p>I have a couple of gripes thus far with the shoe: The black shell makes the shoe very hot. Even on the mild (+11°C) spring days we have currently here in Vaasa the shoe is getting very hot, very quickly. I wore <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/bridgedale-coolmax-liner-socke-doppelpack-black-black-36-39/?pid=81">Coolmax socks</a> which usually are good in warm weather, but in this shoe I got hot feet very quickly. I am not sure if another colour would mitigate this, or if the shell would just need more &amp; larger ventilation openings in the shell shoe so the ventilation is improved. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17203302519" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 2.0 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8702/17203302519_31521ebe12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - 2.0" /></a></p>

<p>The second thing I do not recommend: Walk through a bog with them. Along the IAT in Ireland I crossed several swamps, and the combination of bog flora &amp; fauna + my own sweat created an unbearable smell in the shoes. It was absolutely terrible and I felt slightly afraid to go sit with them in a plane for several hours. At home I first tried the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grangers-universal-spray-cleaner-275ml/">Granger’s Universal Spray Cleaner</a> but that showed no success in terms of getting rid of the smell (probably should have used the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grangers-odour-eliminator-60ml/?pid=81">Granger’s Odour Eliminator</a>), so they went into the washing machine with <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/nikwax-tech-wash-pflegemittel-002/?pid=81">Nikwax Tech Wash</a> which got rid of the smell for the most part. So I would not recommend them for walking in swamps right now, unless there’s a good way to get rid of the smell. If you’re in alpine environments where there’s no bogs this will not be of concern, but in Ireland, Scotland, Wales, England and Scandinavia you’re likely to encounter swamps in the hills, so keep this in mind (It might be of course that your sweat germs in combination with a bog’s flora &amp; fauna creates an irresistible odour and it’s just my sweat that’s wrong!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17182071337" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7728/17182071337_162901961c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, I hope Arc’teryx will release at the coming <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor</a> an membrane-free bootie liner. It really is missing for me in their bootie line-up, and I think it would make the shoe even more attractive for those of us who don’t need a Gore-Tex or Insulated bootie. Make it highly breathable with good drainage, with a material that’s odour-neutral, and it could be a winner.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17387539812" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Shell Inside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7721/17387539812_572df856b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Shell Inside" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>I am not aware right now if there’s similar shoes that are made of a liner + shell, but I have no doubts that there could be. For ultralight backpackers and weight-conscious alpinists a combination of a unlined approach shoe + a <a href="http://bit.ly/1F5m1op">Gore-Tex sock</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1F5lXVO">Neoprene Sock</a> could also create this combination of a quick-drying shoe and a waterproof liner that you can dry easily over night. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17387540382" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Made for approaches by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7786/17387540382_19e7fb9a24_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Made for approaches" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Acrux² FL GTX is a shoe that brings fresh wind into the approach shoe market. A comfortable, removable liner paired with a hydrophobic, stylish shell and a grippy Vibram MegaGrip sole make this a great shoe for approaches, Via Ferratas and scrambles. The price of 250€ puts it at the high-end, but then you get essentially two shoes for the price of one. Add in the versatilty the Acrux² offers with the interchangable, removable liners and you have a great shoe for your mountain adventures, and you can get rid of a stinky liner bootie if you have hiked through a bog! Finally, as this is the first Generation of Arc’teryx footwear we can be curious to see what they will come up with the next Generations!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157651938930537">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-acrux-fl-gtx">Where to buy the Acrux² FL GTX</h2>

<p>You can get them directly from <a href="">Arc’teryx</a> or at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-acrux-2-fl-approachschuhe/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-alpha2-fl-gtx-schuhe-black-big-surf-uk6-5/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1F5uZCc">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1GOzXhD">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1GYO9XR">REI</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17182073947" title="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Side by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7713/17182073947_cbcd710c7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Acrux² FL GTX - Side" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Salewa Wildfire Approach Shoes]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/salewa-wildfire-approach-shoes.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-07T12:35:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/salewa-wildfire-approach-shoes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Approach shoes are what climbers wear when approaching a crag, but this sort of shoe is becoming more popular as a footwear choice amongst backpackers and hikers, too. After having used the <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/">Salewa</a> Wildfire in both it’s GTX and unlined version for hundreds of kilometres the verdict is out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983871004/" title="Salewa Wildfire GTX &amp; Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7418/12983871004_5fa773a2c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire GTX &amp; Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/product/tech+approach/wildfire+gore-tex+man">Salewa Wildfire GTX</a> arrived with me in the end of the winter of 2013, while I picked up the unlined <a href="http://www.salewa.com/product/footwear/wildfire+man">Wildfire</a> version at the OutDoor. Both have been on several trips in the Alps, Germany, Sweden and Finland. Overall I estimate the GTX version have seen around 500 km of use, while the unlined Wildfires have seen a bit more than half of that.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12984685694/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7332/12984685694_97b3ddbd21_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>An approach shoe’s function is to bring you safely up to the start of your climb, where you change into your climbing shoes and start climbing. They’re made for scrambling, and can be tied pretty tight, so that you have a tight fit on more demanding scrambles. Finally, they also help to make a statement in public that you’re a climber =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12984401983/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3518/12984401983_31d36aef08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Salewa packed a whole lotta featuers into this shoe, which is in their <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/footwear/tech%20approach">Tech Approach Line</a>, where you also find the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/salewa-firetail-approachschuhe/">Firetail</a>. </p>

<ul>
  <li>3F SYSTEM EVO, which offers freedom of movement and support</li>
  <li>CLIMBING LACING gives accurate lacing in the toe area </li>
  <li>MFF+ MULTI-FIT FOOTBED gives you the ability to adjust the footbed of your shoe</li>
  <li>SILVERIZED for non-smelly shoes</li>
</ul>

<p>Salewa recommends these shoes for <em>Via Ferrata, Hiking, Mountain inspired urban lifestyle and Approach</em>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983865344/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2033/12983865344_54398d6579_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>

<p>Out of the box they fitted me well, and something interesting that was included in the box were two more insoles (for a total of four yellow ones and two black ones). The black part connects via Velcros to the yellow insole. That way you can add more cushioning  &amp; volume in the heel and front, to suit your needs. Me, I didn’t see a need for it and have used them with low volume insole they came with. The toe box is reasonably wide, so for people who like that there’s enough space for their toes without them being jammed together, this shoe will be a good choice. Also the heel cup has a good fit, and tightens when you lace up the shoe.</p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The above mentioned MFF+ Footbed system is a pretty interesting solution which lets the user adapt the shoe’s insole to his need, and you’re thus able to make them fit better. It’s a smart way as in this way Salewa can make one shoe and with the insole you can adopt it to your needs. </p>

<p>The Salewa EXA shell technology is basically a plastic grid on top of the mesh, which helps to protect it while still being flexible. It adds protection to the shoe and makes it more durable.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12986019963/" title="Salewa Wildfire MFF+ Footbed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7419/12986019963_3748452f1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salewa Wildfire MFF+ Footbed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The quality is very good. Salewa are an old Italian company with a long tradition in making gear for use in the mountains, and their athletes help develop their gear. I have put these shoes through a lot of walking on asphalt and the Vibram sole still looks almost like new. Also the uppers have been through rock fields, on scrambles and hikes, and have not much to show for it except those splatters of mud which I didn’t want to clean (gives them a more authentic look, ya see!). </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983444905/" title="Salewa Wildfire GTX on top, Salewa Wildfire on the bottom by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7371/12983444905_db48769d7b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire GTX on top, Salewa Wildfire on the bottom" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>They’re heavier than <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shoes/">shoes I usually wear</a>, but I was curious to see if approach shoes work for me. They do feel heavier, but not too bad.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Wildfire GTX 888 g for the pair in EU Size 42,5 or 444 g per shoe</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Wildfire 878 g for the pair in EU Size 42,5 or 439 g per shoe</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Salewa has a <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/csr">CSR</a> page and their 2013 CSR Report can be read <a href="http://csr.oberalp.com/">online</a>. The company is member of the <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/csr/fairwear%20foundation%20(fwf)">Fairwear Foundation</a> and is working on becoming greener, like much of our industry. As for the shoes, the easiest way for you to recycle them is to drop them in a shoe/ garment recycling bin in your town. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983433815/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3380/12983433815_29f580ddf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>Alrighty then, the most important part. I started wearing the Wildfire GTX in the end of the winter of 2013, and they quickly became a shoe I wore when walking with my son, cycling to work, doing day hikes and walking to the grocery store. The GTX version, as well as the unlined version, are - at least in black - pretty warm shoes, so after a day walking in hot weather expect to have very sweaty feet. I find them in warm weather unbearable hot and will not wear them in temps above 20°C as they’re just too hot for me. For winter they’re very good, as you can wear them with mid-weight socks and still have toasty feet.</p>

<p>I wore them on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/sul-in-the-swiss-alps.html">Swiss SUL trip</a> and while they were fine, I more than once wished I would be wearing a shoe with more grip. While the Vibram Tech Approach EVO sole is durable, I don’t find it has as much grip as other soles and as it’s stiff it also does not let you feel the underground very well. The lugs on the sole are narrow and tight together, which became especially evident when crossing frozen snow fields high up. Where e.g. the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/salomon-speedcross-3.html">Salomon Speedcross 3</a>’s lugs dig into the snow and give you a save grip, the Wildfires were a bit sketchy. Also on gravel and wet surfaces they don’t offer as much grip as competing shoes. On the plus side, the sole is very durable and shows little signs of wear, and because it is so stiff it’s a good shoe to cycle in, too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12984258655/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7375/12984258655_36f77a4412_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<p>Speaking of cycling, while the shoes weren’t made for biking, the sole stuck pretty well to the pedals on my bike and the stiff sole was good for power transmission when riding. For walking I would wish that the sole would be more flexible - it barely flexes - which makes a natural stride more difficult (but not impossible). Both versions, but especially the GTX version, are also great on windy days or when you ride fast as you won’t get cold feet. </p>

<p>The weight of the shoes is higher than what I’d normally wear, but it’s not too bad. For the increase in weight you get a more durable shoe, though I think Salewa should remove some of the lining to <strong>a)</strong> make the shoe less warm and <strong>b)</strong> make it lighter. Especially the GTX version would benefit immensely from that, and I think if the shoes could be pushed down to sub 400 g per shoe they’d very popular amongst hikers that look for a durable shoe.</p>

<p>The 3F System Evo technology which is employed in the shoe, which is supposed to support and offer freedom of movement, well it’s in a shoe like this a given. I can see why the technology would be useful in boots, but in low shoes it feels a bit like they’re just slapping another label on top. It helps with a good heel-fit, though, if that’s something you’re looking for in a shoe.</p>

<p>Climbing in the shoes is OK. I personally rather slip into my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/ultralight-climbing.html">climbing shoes</a>, but for scrambles on hikes, approaching the crag, and easy climbs they’re good. Keep in mind that you won’t have as much control and feeling in them as in a pair of climbing shoes. Finally, the shoes look pretty good and I often wear them to the city with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/outlier-woolback-og.html">Outlier pants</a>, which makes for a smart, casual look but you still can go for a scramble if the need arises.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a whole host of approach shoes, for example the <a href="http://bit.ly/1f5nL2u">Patagonia Rover</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/garmont-dragontail-lt-approachschuhe/">Garmont Dragontail LT</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/scarpa-zen-pro-approachschuhe/">Scarpa Zen Pro</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/O0GSzT">La Sportiva Xplorer</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1g50Yno">The North Face Verto</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/five-ten-camp-four-schuhe-dark-shadow-uk-5/">Five Ten Camp Four</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-womens-needle-approachschuhe/">Mammut Needle</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/hagloefs-roc-legend-q-gt-approachschuhe/">Haglöfs Roc Legend GT</a>, amongst <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/approachschuhe/?_artperpage=96">plenty more</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983603993/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3102/12983603993_2dd522ac7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/the-3-shoe-review-salewa-wildfires/">Keith</a> thinks they could be 1.000 km hiking shoes, <a href="http://www.examiner.com/review/salewa-wildfire-approach-shoe-a-new-generation-alpine-footwear-review">Erica</a> gives them 5 Stars and <a href="http://www.climberism.com/gear-review-salewa-wildfire-approach-shoe/">Jeremy</a> finds they blend into his life’s rhythms seamlessly.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983873444/" title="Salewa Wildfire GTX by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3654/12983873444_07b2c5b008_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I have used the Salewa Wildfires pretty much daily since they arrived, and have walked on two outdoor fairs with them. The main reason for that is that walking on my trailrunning shoes in the city eats up their sole at an alarming rate, and to save my wallet the Salewa Wildfire with their very durable Vibram sole are an excellent alternative, and I’m still ready for the trail or a scramble. They work well for hiking and I think for people that are transitioning from boots to lightweight footwear these are prime candidates to try. They combine the benefits of boots - durability and a stiff-ish sole - with the benefits of trailrunners: light weight, strengthening the foot muscles and allowing for a more natural movement.</p>

<p>If you’re an ultralight backpacker these might not be the shoes for you, unless you spend a lot of time hiking on rock which naturally eats up rubber pretty fast. Also if you’re on a budget and don’t want to buy more than a pair of shoes a year, these are a good choice for you. On the other hand, if you’re a climber who looks for a new pair of approach shoes, or are a backpacker transitioning to lightweight footwear, then these should be on the top of your list. The are durable, light, look pretty fetching (especially in green!) and work also well in the city. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157641987117703/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-salewa-wildfire-approach-shoes">Where to buy the Salewa Wildfire Approach Shoes</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/salewa-wildfire-gtx-w-s-schuhe-black-sulphur/">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/salewa-wildfire-approachschuhe/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/1gd4SXt">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/1g3t427">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/1gVsTDX">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Long-term observation and photos</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983462515/" title="Salewa Wildfire GTX &amp; Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7323/12983462515_bbc5ac4129_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire GTX &amp; Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
