<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: The Outdoor Guide to | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-outdoor-guide-to/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-30T23:29:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Outdoor Guide Directory]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/outdoor-guide-directory.html"/>
    <updated>2015-09-30T23:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/outdoor-guide-directory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>London, New York, Tokyo - Find the Outdoor Guide for your next city trip!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/carlosarriero/20463433660/in/photolist-xbhrTJ-kwZG3K-cNidQy-q5hXkg-nDkMqM-7G7USR-pak144-8hy7jE-dXXDpy-eyG44G-dLAxA-ctTxTS-e7rNC-8EZoT9-5WEyXh-bcgETF-9QWrZZ-aQmpgk-4C75U8-drLTGP-7VNGvD-4fGta-gn56DA-FjSaP-nvrmhm-fPHuWu-c6hGsf-cGfvR-4NA4gR-o5Gs9K-ac9FVr-wTHLEh-ew7bRw-abQij9-4LTKmk-81wxSw-JEFWL-f1CgZN-9A5m2U-acVEek-ade6WU-fERMoS-8KfhNK-3cSBTk-5TZMdA-cP7K5h-hmBVx8-7e5vNd-HoCFr-vLoECx" title="Sunset in Central Park from &quot;Top of the Rock&quot;, Rockefeller Center (New York)."><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5800/20463433660_03431835e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Sunset in Central Park from &quot;Top of the Rock&quot;, Rockefeller Center (New York)." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The idea of the Outdoor Guide Series is based on my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html">The Outdoor Guide to Helsinki</a> article. I have received my fair share of inquiries from people who read Hiking in Finland and visit Helsinki on a business trip and were wondering what they could do in Helsinki over a long weekend in the outdoors. Instead of writing the same email time &amp; again I wrote the Guide article to answer the questions and being able to refer people to it. And I knew there would be a lot of my outdoor friends in towns &amp; cities around the globe who get the same kind of Emails, so the idea to expand it was born. Right now you can find nearly a dozen Outdoor Guides to many different cities around the globe - from Tokyo, Japan to Boulder, Colorado, USA. </p>

<p><strong>But it shouldn’t stop there!</strong> If you write an outdoor blog, please feel invited to write an Outdoor Guide to your town! <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Get in touch and I send you the template</a>, let me know when the article is online and I will add it to this directory! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mariano-mantel/14532181033/in/photolist-o9ae8p-sy8dxE-jdRX2T-a5q6ec-5qm2tp-8bjYEn-2MG3eG-oW6cWS-9wUnWb-7ah5JL-8GnGC7-qs43f1-qHGzAz-4eqLQf-f3VuZa-rebBwe-7oQvr4-yRAF9-e1QXcz-9aAC2X-4pDZYU-843ibe-8FHZ5q-7aDsJU-egsQz6-fiEZ52-vr4kJY-7a6Ewy-7bajuP-fFtiua-7aKAMf-9hay4T-vmLDZA-awEMqZ-uwmsow-bkwkZB-cGedyw-7b2toh-dZZLyg-sTvohd-vveaGA-8qKVF-6vZPX6-xegMBg-fMYfxi-abLjnD-vecbnQ-uNRAiy-eQVtDk-3pmAAF" title="Helsinki Harbour"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2911/14532181033_5cf4413772_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Helsinki Harbour" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="helsinki-finland">Helsinki, Finland</h2>

<p>Heading to Helsinki, the capital of Finland? Then check out the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html">Outdoor Guide to Helsinki</a>!</p>

<h2 id="turku-finland">Turku, Finland</h2>

<p>Peter takes you through Turku, the gateway to the Archipelago and Finland’s former capital: <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2015/09/the-outdoor-guide-to-turku.html">The Outdoor Guide to Turku</a>.</p>

<h2 id="rovaniemi-finland">Rovaniemi, Finland</h2>

<p>Mark takes you on a round through Rovaniemi, the home of Santa and <em>the town</em> in Finland on the Arctic Circle: <a href="http://www.backpackingnorth.com/blog/outdoor-guide-to-rovaniemi">The Outdoor Guide to Rovaniemi</a>.</p>

<h2 id="vaasa-finland">Vaasa, Finland</h2>

<p>Vaasa, the sunniest city of Finland and the starting point to the Kvarken Archipelago, Finland’s only UNESCO World Heritage Site, is always worth a visit: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/the-outdoor-guide-to-vaasa.html">The Outdoor Guide to Vaasa</a>.</p>

<h2 id="stockholm-sweden">Stockholm, Sweden</h2>

<p>Jeremie shows you the European Green Capital of 2010 and what it has to offer to outdoor folks: <a href="http://injuringeternity.net/2015/09/28/an-outdoor-guide-to-stockholm-sweden/">The Outdoor Guide to Stockholm</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tommiehansen/9000198669/in/photolist-eHjnv8-oY6JN7-eT3hDJ-6HPopu-3tVsgB-kyRcj5-nAj6M2-aiYeRG-8q6fNm-9WZc9o-6Atk6H-eqtrea-rvWkiq-4gqxNF-ejhpBZ-eivqoK-eHqDxC-5wgAME-2hUzeb-eriqjQ-4kqNCi-cYcgDN-oaWDh1-eHjG4k-f3pbGp-tjE4tY-5XvqVD-ekD322-eHjx9D-6MGWSr-ob1fU5-kvjCip-ej4zLn-o4SG9T-9ramLP-81v4SH-aQd23Z-9rdjCU-aedxqa-5EUu5Q-hgjpj-63frN-aDMFxv-5vYSjF-6wzbac-oaWA35-4HF2QM-tQkJaZ-9jezYq-np6pXw" title="Djurgårdsbron, tram and a pink sunset (Stockholm)"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7328/9000198669_57003f7505_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Djurgårdsbron, tram and a pink sunset (Stockholm)" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="copenhagen-denmark">Copenhagen, Denmark</h2>

<p><a href="http://urbanpackrafter.com/Urban-Guide-Copenhagen">The Outdoor Guide to Copenhagen</a> helps you explore Denmark’s capital on foot, bike and packraft!</p>

<h2 id="luxembourg-luxembourg">Luxembourg, Luxembourg</h2>

<p><em>Coming soon!</em></p>

<h2 id="hamburg-germany">Hamburg, Germany</h2>

<p><em>Coming soon!</em></p>

<h2 id="berlin-germany">Berlin, Germany</h2>

<p><em>Coming soon!</em></p>

<h2 id="stuttgart-germany">Stuttgart, Germany</h2>

<p><em>Coming soon!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/guwashi999/7440253018/in/photolist-cktf1s-jk1vBS-n42ETD-5PnzDw-dgHyRY-hBvyGb-iUAFsB-iSAr8r-soAPNc-3bzz8p-8krryy-9JbWep-dfHpSe-e5xarz-okyGop-oCcSob-nV2jTx-nWPYxj-cUvoR5-ow9jDb-qTjsn6-wQydah-mYJ4vc-oQkHWP-mYH8Cx-dEbqC2-e9iW3N-dfHeTS-r5gNTk-dggkcU-hirFY1-8X4AD1-dtNkP5-qDE2B6-qab9Dp-uCyyyV-6u5qcN-pc5fd5-cyXDw-r9JgQr-mxshP6-8P8yhW-qSjkDm-dwGjKv-65xrzu-5JyGjr-of8BeX-hBvCWy-dWb3j3-qUrADu" title="Tokyo Night"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5036/7440253018_52853bdcf6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Tokyo Night" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="tokyo-japan">Tokyo, Japan</h2>

<p>David brings you <a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/musings/outdoors-in-tokyo/">The Outdoor Guide to Tokyo</a> which is the best starting point for your visit to Japan’s capital. </p>

<h2 id="hong-kong">Hong Kong</h2>

<p><em>Coming soon!</em></p>

<h2 id="vancouver-canada">Vancouver, Canada</h2>

<p>Karl takes you on a tour around Vancouver on Canada’s Westcoast with heaps of outdoor activities, from hiking to skiing and paddling: <a href="http://www.outdoorvancouver.ca/the-outdoor-guide-to-vancouver/">The Outdoor Guide to Vancouver</a>.</p>

<h2 id="boulder-colorado-usa">Boulder, Colorado, USA</h2>

<p>Paul shows you the awesome things you can do in his <a href="http://www.pmags.com/an-outdoor-guide-to-boulder-colorado">Outdoor Guide to Boulder, Colorado</a>.</p>

<h2 id="san-fransisco-california-usa">San Fransisco, California, USA</h2>

<p>Jacob takes you on a stroll in his <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2015/outdoor-guide-to-the-greater-san-francisco-area/">Outdoor Guide to the Greater San Francisco Area</a>.</p>

<h2 id="melbourne-australia">Melbourne, Australia</h2>

<p><em>Coming soon!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outdoor Guide to Vaasa]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/the-outdoor-guide-to-vaasa.html"/>
    <updated>2015-09-29T22:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/the-outdoor-guide-to-vaasa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Outdoor Guide to Vaasa - Finland’s sunniest city!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21593581188/in/dateposted/" title="Öjberget, Vaasa"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5769/21593581188_bc0746168b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjberget, Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-destinations">Outdoor destinations</h2>

<p>There’s plenty of nice nature trails around Vaasa which all can be found <a href="http://www.merenkurkku.fi/koe-merenkurkku/vaellusreitit/">here</a>. You can find coordinates and pdf maps on that website, though in general the trails are well marked and there’s an info board + map at the start. If you have a car or bike, I can recommend the <a href="http://www.merenkurkku.fi/koe-merenkurkku/vaellusreitit/ojenin-luontopolku/">Öjenin luontopolku</a> which is a nice 4 km loop with a fire place at the middle, which makes it ideal for adventures with kids. On the island of Vaskiluoto there’s a large forest trail which also is also groomed in winter for cross country skiing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21594552609/in/dateposted/" title="Öjenin luontopolku"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5704/21594552609_dc9de34f58_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjenin luontopolku" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.kvarkenworldheritage.fi/visit-kvarken/">Kvarken Archipelago</a> is Finland’s only UNESCO World Heritage site and an ideal destination to go birdwatching, a family or weekend hike or a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/pack-sail-rafting-in-the-kvarken-archipelago.html">packrafting adventure</a>. You will need a car or bike to get there (walking along the road is no fun), but it is worth it - the raising land is a sight to behold. </p>

<p>You prefer water sports? Good that Vaasa has at least half a dozen of fine <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/haku/Pages/tulos.aspx?paikka=436&amp;pakti=2&amp;a1akti=288">beaches</a>, with the one at Hietasaari probably being the easiest to reach and the most popular, too. The <a href="http://www.supstation.fi/vaasa/">Vaasa SUP Station</a> is also located there and a great opportunity to rent a SUP board and try our Stand Up Paddling. The photos from their sunset paddles look awesome, so check out their Instagram feed. In winter Hietasaari is also a good starting point to go Nordic Skating on the Baltic, or take your kite-surfing gear and hit the ice on the Eteläinen Kaupunginselkä.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21593424660/in/dateposted/" title="Vaasa SUP Station"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5680/21593424660_c0216dcf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaasa SUP Station" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Bouldering outdoors in Vaasa is so easy, you almost stumble over the blocs! <a href="http://27crags.com/areas/vaasa/">27 Crags</a> has you covered and is your guide to the best bouldering and climbing in town. If you actually prefer climbing with a rope then <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/falkiin-kallio">Falkiin Kallio</a> is the nearest crag of note, or you take the ferry to Umeå where there’s bigger and longer routes! In winter the crag at Höstvesi is good for whacking some ice, too.</p>

<p>Skiing in Vaasa is also possible at the nearby <a href="http://www.vaasa.fi/palvelut/talviurheilukeskus-ojberget">Öjberget Ski Centre</a>. You can check if its open from <a href="http://www.ski.fi/en/author/ojberget/">ski.fi</a>, though at 45 m elevation and the longest slope being 325 m long don’t expect long runs! However, in town there are <a href="http://www.latukartta.fi/vaasa/">14 cross country skiing loipes</a>, so if you come here in winter and enjoy some kick’n’glide take your skis along! </p>

<p>You can go packrafting and kayaking in town right from any of the many beaches and shores, but be careful around the harbour. At <a href="http://varppi.fi/en/">Varppi</a> you can rent a kayak or rowing boat if you don’t bring your own. A much nicer area to go paddling is the Kvarken Archipelago or one of the rivers. And if you prefer a <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/haku/Pages/tulos.aspx?paikka=436&amp;pakti=2&amp;a1akti=66">short cruise</a>, also that is possible in summer, with the old post boat being the most beautiful cruise as it has been sailing since 1679. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21160399993/in/dateposted/" title="Öjberget, Vaasa"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/734/21160399993_8dfd5f1d97_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjberget, Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you want to do long bicycle rides you’re in luck, though. There’s plenty of great cycling here, and Vaasa being in Pohjanmaa - the “flat country” - you won’t need to bother with long climbs. However, because we’re next to the Baltic expect wind, and as it goes - if there’s wind there’s going to be headwind. If you prefer to cycle around town, then the ride along the shore is a nice way to explore some of the best views of Vaasa and also grab an ice cream or a Toast Skagen at <a href="http://www.strampen.com/english">Strampen</a>. And if you look for some singletrack to shred check out the trail on the <a href="http://vsmtb.net/wp/reitit/">Vaasanseudun MTB</a> website.</p>

<p>Nice parks for a pick nick include the Satamapuisto next to <a href="http://kuntsi.vaasa.fi">Kuntsi</a> and the adjoining Hovioikeudenpuisto as well as Hietasaari, the tiny island just in front of Vaasa.</p>

<h2 id="in-case-of-rain-outdoors-indoors">In case of Rain: Outdoors, Indoors</h2>

<p>There’s plenty of gyms and sports halls in Vaasa, though you likely will need a membership to train in them. A better choice if the weather is not cooperating is the nice <a href="http://www.vaasa.fi/palvelut/uimahalli">swimming hall</a> of Vaasa, which has a 50 m pool for good work outs as well as a jump pool and a couple of kids’ pools. And this being Finland it obviously has a fine Sauna, too! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21755324106/in/dateposted/" title="Vaasa Vesitorni"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5759/21755324106_58df849764_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaasa Vesitorni" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Watertower of Vaasa houses the city’s <a href="http://www.highsport.fi/node/262">climbing gym</a>, which has public hours each Wednesday and Sunday from 18 to 20 o’clock. There’ currently two walls, one 17 m long with some overhang and one 20 m high wall, with a third wall being under construction. </p>

<p>The modern art museum <a href="http://kuntsi.vaasa.fi">Kuntsi</a> is well worth a visit if you like art, and there’s also the rather nice <a href="http://www.tikanojantaidekoti.fi">Tikanojan taidekoti</a> which is a good place to spent time. The <a href="http://www.pohjanmaanmuseo.fi/?page=Home&amp;setlang=l3">Pohjanmaa Museum</a> is actually four museums in one, of which the Terranova natural science exhibition is interesting to learn more about the Kvarken Archipelago. </p>

<p>There are only limited outdoor-sy happenings in Vaasa, but the yearly <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Luontoliikuntapäivä-Naturmotionsdag-Outdoor-Recreation-Day-338517656254113/timeline/">Outdoor Recreation Day</a> which usually happens every February is a good event to attend. You can learn about ice climbing, try nordic touring skating and ice fishing, eat a Pulla or Makkara and learn about other winter activities offered in the area.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12723806373/in/photostream/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid &amp; IcePack"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7408/12723806373_c1bf2dc325_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid &amp; IcePack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-shopping">Outdoor shopping</h2>

<p>Vaasa’s offerings in terms of outdoor equipment are OK. Don’t expect to find gear from Arc’teryx, Patagonia, Norrøna, Primus or Helsport in town, though if you like Fjällräven, Haglöfs, Salomon et al. you will find them at the Intersport shop just off the main square. Also the Hypermarkets just a wee bit outside of the centre carry some outdoor equipment, from fishing tackle to sleeping pads and backpacks.</p>

<p>On the other hand there are at least half a dozen Bike Shops in Vaasa, with <a href="http://www.pyoraviertola.fi/">Pyöräliike Viertola</a> in Rauhankatu 20 being my favourite. They carry <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Pelago Bicycles</a> and are friendly &amp; professional, and also sell used bikes. </p>

<p>As fas as I know there’s no possibility to rent gear in town, but you can always check <a href="http://www.kuinoma.fi">kuin oma</a> for renting gear in Finland.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21575445089/in/dateposted/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5734/21575445089_526faf99d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sleeping-outdoors--indoors">Sleeping outdoors &amp; indoors</h2>

<p>Stealth camping in Vaasa is no problem whatsoever. There are so many forests and parks close to the centre that camping out is not a problem. Some of the beaches are a great option, or if you want to be really on your own cycle or walk out to Pilvilampi and camp there. The Everymen’s Right is your friend in Finland, so just stay at least 100 m away from a house and you’re good to go. </p>

<p>If you prefer to sleep indoors, then check the <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel?s=8">AirBnB listings</a> in Vaasa, there’s currently 28 houses, flats and rooms on offer in town which range from cozy old wooden houses to modern flats with sea view. <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/alasivut/Pages/nuku.aspx">Hotels, Cottages and B&amp;Bs</a> can be found on the Vaasa website, and if you want to go camping then the <a href="http://www.topcamping.fi/fi/vaasa_fi/">Top Camping Vaasa</a> place is your only option. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18572119925/in/dateposted/" title="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/266/18572119925_8e67987dba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="food--cafs">Food &amp; Cafés</h2>

<p>What are the best Cafés in Vaasa? Well, all those that are closed on Sundays. Seriously though, don’t expect a Café to be open on Sunday in this town. I haven’t figured out <em>why</em> they are closed, but on the rare occasion that they are open on a Sunday they are full. But any other day of the week they welcome your business, and it’s a hard toss-up which of these four Cafés is my favourite.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.loftet.fi/ravintola-konsulinnan-kahvihuone/">Konsulinnan kahvihuone</a> serves a great lunch with a delicious salad table, their coffee is arguably the best in town and you get a free 2nd cup. Also their cakes are superb, and the atmosphere in the old building is wonderful. <a href="http://www.sweetvaasa.fi">Sweet Vaasa</a> makes tasty cakes and salads, the <a href="http://www.othello-products.fi">Othello Bakeries</a> also have great traditional pastries and the <a href="http://www.wasakonditori.fi">Wasa Konditoria</a> in the old market hall has a great atmosphere and sells goods from Finland’s best bakery, <a href="http://www.aroma.fi">Aroma</a>. Aroma itself is located a bit outside of town in Kvevlax and a great stop for a coffeeneuring trip with your bike. <a href="http://www.caferaawka.fi">Café Raawka</a> should be on your list if you like raw food - it’s on my list for this weekends Café trip to town!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21184299813/in/dateposted/" title="Brita Cake at Konsulinnan kahvihuone"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5625/21184299813_03900082dd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Brita Cake at Konsulinnan kahvihuone" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://magokoro.fi">Magokoro</a> is Vaasa’s Sushi Restaurant and my favourite option for a tasty lunch in the centre. Their sushi are fresh, tasty and will always make you wish you’d have taken one more. For Dinner the <a href="http://www.pizzabistromarcopolo.fi">Pizzabistro Marco Polo</a> is the best choice for Pizzas in town. Delicious, freshly made pizzas and a cozy atmosphere with friendly staff will make for a good start into the evening. <a href="http://www.tomyumthai.fi">Tom Yum Thai</a> is a great Thai Restaurant which makes tasty food and has very friendly staff, and my choice for Asian food when eating out. I haven’t yet been to <a href="https://villdravintola.wordpress.com/2015/08/31/villd-poytavarauksia-otetaan-vastaan-nu-tar-vi-emot-reservationer/">Villd</a>, the Pop-Up Restaurant from Ossi Palonevan, but plan to go there while it is here in Vaasa till the end of October. Locally sourced foods from the Baltic and forests for a uniquely Finnish dining experience - what’s not to look forward to?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21183941504/in/photostream/" title="©Veera Kujala"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/645/21183941504_42ea79e25a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="©Veera Kujala" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="microadventures">Microadventures!</h2>

<p>More than a couple of days in Vaasa? Take a bike and ride to Isokyrö and visit the <a href="http://www.kyrodistillery.com">Kyrö Distillery Company</a> and taste the worlds best Gin for Gin &amp; Tonic! You also might be able to grab a bite and witness some live music at this small distillery, but check their website and reserve a table if you plan to visit.</p>

<p>If you’re more than a couple of days in town you owe it to yourself to head out to the <a href="http://www.kvarkenworldheritage.fi/visit-kvarken/">Kvarken Archipelago</a>, Finland’s only UNESCO World Heritage Site and see how the land rises from the sea, spot a white-tailed eagle and traditional boat sheds. It’s a great place to visit summers as winters, and will surely will make you feel like you’re in a far-away, wild place. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8609916055/in/album-72157633438534075/" title="Svedjehamn harbour"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8121/8609916055_a79bbce51e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Svedjehamn harbour" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://www.meteoria.fi/en">Meteoria Söderfjärden</a> is probably the biggest meteorite crater in Finland, and right in the middle there’s a birdwatching tower to observe the cranes and other birds passing through in spring an autumn. Meteoria is the most important resting and feeding place for cranes in Finland and a great place to observe these birds. There’s also a small museum next to the tower, and it’s easy to reach by bike or car.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.stundars.fi/?lang=en">Stundars</a> is an open air museum with over sixty traditional buildings from the region, from a windmill to a fishermen’s hut. It’s a great place to visit in summer when it is open, or during one of the special events like the handcrafts fair. There’s also trail that leads to it from the Meteoria and it’s close to <a href="http://www.sundom.fi/en">Sundom</a>, the small village just a few kilometres away from Vaasa.</p>

<h2 id="getting-around-town-and-to-vaasa">Getting around town and to Vaasa</h2>

<p>The centre of Vaasa is compact enough that you can walk from the Railway Station to Hietasaari in 15 minutes, or from the Swimming Hall to Palosaari in about 25 minutes. There’s no easy way to loan a bike in Vaasa, and the public transportation is also not good - a couple of busses with drivers who seem to think they’re in a rally car, you’re better off walking. </p>

<p>Getting to Vaasa is fastest and most affordable by airplane. The airport is small and efficient and it’s just a 35 minute flight to Helsinki. If you like to see more of the country then travelling by bus is an option, either by <a href="https://www.matkahuolto.fi/fi/">Matkahuolto</a> or with the cheap <a href="http://www.onnibus.com/en/index.htm">Onnibus</a>. If you prefer unreliable transportation which is expensive then the <a href="https://www.vr.fi/cs/vr/fi/etusivu">Finnish Railways</a> should be your choice. If you’re in Sweden you also can fly from Stockholm to Vaasa, or take the <a href="http://www.wasaline.com/en/">Wasaline Ferry</a> from Umeå for a more relaxed way to arrive in town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21182653664/in/dateposted/" title="Flying with Finnair to Vaasa"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/764/21182653664_e6a003f2eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Flying with Finnair to Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-folks-in-vaasa">Outdoor folks in Vaasa</h2>

<p>There are outdoorsy people in Vaasa, though they are mostly organized in Clubs for their specific sports as you saw above, so you might want to check out their happenings if you want to socialize. However, to find like-minded outdoorsy people you can browse the <a href="https://instagram.com/explore/tags/vaasa/">Instagram Tag for Vaasa</a> and also search on Twitter for <a href="https://twitter.com/search?f=users&amp;vertical=default&amp;q=vaasa&amp;src=typd">tweeps from Vaasa</a>. And then there’s obviously me on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/14600027980/in/photolist-oypywx-of9XEm-owBYKE-ofadcg-ownNer-of9XAU-ofacnk-owBZTb-ofacpz-ofajmk-ouC46E-ofaeGu-6XnhwZ-89wNEi-89A8yA-89zZDu-89wWe2-89wRLR-89wJ7T-89wTpg" title="Crossing of one of the ridges ended up as a muddy wade through a bed of reeds and what not, while being chased by a flight of hungry horse flies - part of the game :)"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3881/14600027980_0567d7110c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Crossing of one of the ridges ended up as a muddy wade through a bed of reeds and what not, while being chased by a flight of hungry horse flies - part of the game :)" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="london-tokyo-stockholm-and-onwards">London, Tokyo, Stockholm and onwards!</h2>

<p>Liked this Outdoor Guide to Vaasa, but you’re more likely to visit Stockholm, Tokyo and San Francisco next? Well, you’re in luck! Direct your browser to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/outdoor-guide-directory.html">Outdoor Guide Directory</a> and check out the other Guides from across the globe!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outdoor Guide to Helsinki]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html"/>
    <updated>2013-11-28T10:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Helsinki is not just the capital of Finland, it also has a lot to offer for outdoor lovers who visit the city. You can meet outdoor types, go wild camping and packrafting in the middle of the city, visit nearby National Parks and pick up a Kuksa &amp; Puukko from one of the outdoor shops.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/rikukettunen/10122173714/" title="Helsinki by Riku Kettunen, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2868/10122173714_079090833d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="678" alt="Helsinki" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-folks-in-helsinki">Outdoor folks in Helsinki</h2>

<p>Going outdoors with like-minded people is a lot of fun. Helsinki boasts a large &amp; social population of outdoor types, many of whom are very likely to help you out with picking a destination and probably even meet you for a beer. Contact them via Twitter and visit their blogs for inspiration.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/korkealle">Aleksi</a> is the guy to contact for climbing</li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/valppaus">Joni</a> will join you for fatbiking, packrafting and ice climbing</li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/mtakanen">Marko</a> is a jack-of-all-outdoor-trades, and lately especially enjoys packrafting</li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/rollofunk">Mikael</a> snowshoes, hikes and speaks Japanese</li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/TAnttalainen">Timo</a> is a Finn who works at an outdoor store and likes sea kayaking</li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twitter.com/TobyinHelsinki">Toby</a> is an English expat who you should contact for climbing &amp; cycling</p>
  </li>
  <li><a href="http://sub24helsinki.blogspot.fi/">Sub 24 Helsinki</a> is a loose collective of outdoor folks who meet up once a month to go sleep outdoors together. Adventures take place all around the capital area, and often are conducted by bike.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>If you’re a social Helsinki outdoor person and want to be listed above, please comment underneath!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/papalars/2902429577/" title="Helsinki Train Station by papalars, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3027/2902429577_802b855435_b.jpg" width="1024" height="644" alt="Helsinki Train Station" /></a></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-destinations">Outdoor destinations</h2>

<p>So, you’ve landed in Helsinki and have some free time on your hands, which you’d like to spend outdoors. Good! There’s plenty of options available for you of where to go and what to do.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hugovk/7501133582/" title="Cycling with a bouldering mat by hugovk, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8281/7501133582_da6a8dc5d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Cycling with a bouldering mat" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re into climbing and bouldering, then pick up the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/southern-finland-bouldering-guide.html">Southern Finland Bouldering Guide</a>
and visit <a href="http://27crags.com/">27 Crags</a> to view the locations in the Helsinki area. If you want to boulder, you won’t even need to leave the centre as there’s plenty of great problems within walking distance of the centre.</p>

<p>If you’re more the hiking/ backpacking/ trailrunning kind of type, then you might want to go and visit <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/nuuksio/Pages/Default.aspx">Nuuksio</a> or <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/sipoonkorpi/Pages/Default.aspx">Sipoonkorpi</a> National Park, which are within an hour driving distance and easily reached via public transportation. Then there’s the Trail 2000, a 110-km-long hiking trail, which begins in Laakso in Helsinki, and goes through the Nuuksio National Park. Just follow the blue bands on the trees =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11097111065/" title="Nuuksio by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5545/11097111065_c2ce1a242a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nuuksio" /></a></p>

<p>Seakayaking &amp; packrafting is also possible as Helsinki is on a Peninsula and surrounded by the Baltic on three sides. If you prefer rivers, the Vantaajoki is the place to go, or ask one of the paddling &amp; packrafting guys from further up about good rivers! <a href="http://www.naturaviva.fi/en/">Natura Viva</a> rents kayaks and also has daily guided tours in the summer.</p>

<p>Cycling in Helsinki is fun. The cycling network is OK-ish (at least they try!) and <a href="http://www.bikemap.net/en/regional/Finland/Finland/Helsinki/">Bikemap</a> helps you to find different routes throughout the city. You also can use the <a href="http://pk.reittiopas.fi/en/">Journey Planner</a>, and check <a href="http://www.greenbike.fi/vuokrauskohteet_en.html">Greenbike’s Tips</a>, too. </p>

<h2 id="outdoors-indoors">Outdoors, Indoors</h2>

<p>Sometimes the weather is so bad that even the most hardened outdoor-types will gladly accept some shelter indoors. If you’re looking for outdoor related activities indoors, then <a href="http://www.haltia.com/">Haltia</a> is a good place to start. The new Finnish Nature Centre is next to Nuuksio National Park in a beautiful building, and enables you to experience nature from all over Finland in one building. </p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.luomus.fi/english/">Botanical Garden in Kaisaniemi</a> is not just in the summer a great place to go with its beautiful parks, also in winter it’s a fine destination. Right next to the railway station it has a few greenhouses with plants and trees from different climate zones which are well temperated and a real alternative to -20°C outside. If you prefer animals to plants visit the <a href="http://www.luomus.fi/english/nhm/">Natural History Museum</a> which is also smack-in-the-middle of the centre, or take a ferry to the <a href="http://www.korkeasaari.fi/en/services/visitorinformation">Korkeasaari Zoo</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11097167264/" title="Kiipeilyareena Helsinki by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/11097167264_5c7ffd3ef1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kiipeilyareena Helsinki" /></a></p>

<p>Climbers will visit the <a href="http://www.kiipeilyareena.com/">Kiipeily Areena</a> which has Scandinavia’s highest climbing wall and a sweet new boulder area. The <a href="http://www.boulderkeskus.com/fi/">Boulderkeskus</a> has two locations in the capital area and will present you with lots of fine problems.</p>

<p>In autumn there’s also a host of different events in the capital: The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/banff-mountain-film-festival-world-tour-helsinki.html">Banff Mountain Film Festival</a>, the <a href="http://www.relaa.com/han">Helsinki Adventure Night</a> + Reel Rock Tour and the <a href="http://www.bicyclefilmfestival.com/city/helsinki/">Bicycle Film Festival</a> all have stops in the city and will wow you with sweet outdoor movies. The <a href="http://www.messukeskus.com/Sites1/Skiexpo/Sivut/default.aspx">Skiexpo</a> is a trade fair about, yes, skiing and winter sports, while the <a href="http://www.messukeskus.com/Sites3/GoExpo2014/Sivut/default.aspx">GoExpo</a> is a consumer fair for hikers, cyclists, fishermen, and other outdoor activities.</p>

<h2 id="outdoor-shops">Outdoor Shops</h2>

<p><a href="http://pelagobicycles.com/">Pelago Bicycles</a> is not just Finland’s best bike shop, they also make sweet bicycles - right in the middle of the city. If you’re just remotely interested in cycling, go visit their beautiful store. And yes, if you purchase a bike, they will pack it ready for air travel for you! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11098457723/" title="Pelago Bicycles by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5484/11098457723_f217251879_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Pelago Bicycles" /></a></p>

<p>In a city the size of Helsinki you find plenty of outdoor/ climbing/ trailrunning shops, which enable you to pick up the stuff you couldn’t bring or forgot. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.4runners.fi/">4 Runners</a> is in the <a href="http://www.kamppi.fi/">Kamppi</a> shopping mall and in my opinion the best running shop in Helsinki. They have a super collection of minimalist and barefoot running shoes (yes, also Inov-8s!) and accessories from GU Energy Gels to tights and toe socks. </p>

<p>Partio Varuste / <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorstore.com/">Scandinavian Outdoor Store</a> are in the centre next to Kamppi and will satisfy gear needs of backpackers &amp; hikers. Pick up gas cartridges and alcohol fuel, try on Merrell shoes and get Woolpower underwear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.camu.fi/">Camu</a> and <a href="http://www.mountainshop.fi/">Mountain Shop Finland</a> will be two shops which budding climbers &amp; mountaineers will put on their “Must visit” list. Here you can get the good fitting outdoor garments from Arc’teryx, Black Diamond, Rab as well as ice screws, quick-draws and whatever else a climber’s heart desires.</p>

<p>Finally, <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/">Partioaitta</a> is also in the centre (opposite of the Scandinavian Outdoor Store) and has also a few more shops in the capital area.</p>

<h2 id="sleeping-outdoors">Sleeping Outdoors</h2>

<p>Yes, you can sleep outdoors in Helsinki. There’s plenty of parks in the centre which are silent in the nights, and if you have a stealth shelter and rise early there shouldn’t be a problem with sleeping right in the middle of the capital. If you want to sleep outdoors but not in downtown, for 4.50€ a train and bus ride take you to Nuuksio, from where you can walk in 30 minutes to several different camping places. You also could take a bus or train to one of the more silent suburbs and camp there in a wood.</p>

<p>There’s some sweet <a href="https://www.airbnb.com/tell-a-friend?airef=w3kpza02eczz5">Airbnb</a> places available in downtown Helsinki if you do not want to camp out. There’s also a few reasonably priced hotels, though if you like it fancy, stay at the <a href="http://www.klauskhotel.com/">Klaus K</a> as they also have a good sustainable programme.</p>

<h2 id="food--cafs">Food &amp; Cafés</h2>

<p>The afore-mentioned Kamppi shopping mall has a couple of Cafés, and the <a href="http://www.johtocafe.com/in-english/">Johto Café</a> at the top has free Wifi. However, I prefer the <a href="http://mbar.fi/">mBar</a> in front of it - good coffees and friendly service, and a great terrace in the summer. If you find yourself hungry during lunch time, I find <a href="http://www.ravintolahalikarnas.fi/">Halikarnas</a> the best place to eat - delicious Turkish food with a wide vegetarian selection, this is a great place. <a href="http://www.grandelicato.fi/">Gran Delicato</a> is a Greek run Café which makes superb coffees and sandwiches, while there’s a host of Asian Buffet &amp; Restaurant places in the centre - just take your pick. If you like beer, stop by at <a href="http://www.teerenpeli.com/ravintolat/ravintolat/helsinki">Teerenpeli</a>, which, you guessed it, is also next to Kamppi.</p>

<p>If you rather cook yourself, the <a href="http://www.hok-elanto.fi/ostoksille/s-market/toimipaikat/s-market-sokos-helsinki/">S-Market</a> in front of the railway station probably has the lowest prices in the centre, but there’s plenty of <a href="http://www.alepa.fi/helsinki.html">Alepa</a> and <a href="http://www.siwa.fi/fi/kaupat-ja-aukioloajat/?nearestStore=&amp;nearestStore_id=&amp;city=Helsinki">Siwa</a> Supermarkets spread throughout the city, as well as the large (and expensive) <a href="http://www.k-market.com/Myymalat/K-market-Kamppi/">K-Market</a> in Kamppi. If you prefer organic, Fair Trade food, head over to <a href="http://www.ruohonjuuri.fi/myymalat/">Ruohonjuuri</a> which is also on the side of Kamppi.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/visitfinland/6992587550/" title="Mbar Terrace in  Helsinki by Visit Finland, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7236/6992587550_9f830d3ee1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="714" alt="Mbar Terrace in  Helsinki" /></a></p>

<h2 id="getting-around">Getting around</h2>

<p>Helsinki is a small city, and you easily can walk pretty much anywhere. It’s surrounded by the sea on three sides, and there’s several islands around this peninsula. If you want to speed up a bit, take the Tram, Metro, Bus or Commuter Train from <a href="http://www.hsl.fi/en">HSL</a>. For the Tram &amp; Metro you can send a Text Message to 16355 with “A1” as a message and you receive a digital ticket to your phone. In the bus and commuter train you can get a ticket from the driver/ conductor. If you prefer to pedal, loan a cycle from <a href="http://www.greenbike.fi/index_en.html">Greenbike</a> which has a stall in front of Kamppi. </p>

<p><em>That’s the Outdoor Guide to Helsinki. I hope it helps you to make your stay in the capital more outdoors-y and pleasant. If you have suggestions on how to improve it, please leave a comment!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
