<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cicerone | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/cicerone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-25T19:52:39+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T12:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ve probably seen a trend in my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">book reviews</a> in the last years: They’ve been more and more about mountaineering and climbing. Why that is so I’ll explain at another time, but now I want to take you along and tell you about the latest book I have read, <em>8000 Metres - Climbing the World’s Highest Mountains by Alan Hinkes</em>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15985413000" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8658/15985413000_e521caa7ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There’s 14 8.000 m peaks on this planet and Alan Hinkes is the first British Mountaineer to have successfully summited all fourteen of them. In his splendid coffee table book “<a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/tab/detail/iid/1/show/description#.VKZk6cbvR_0">8000 Meters - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</a>” he tells the stories and shares his fantastic photos with the reader. Its a chronological layout and after a Foreword, Preface and Introduction we start at Alan’s first 8.000 m summit, Shisha Pangma, which he climbed in 1987. </p>

<p>From that year one Alan has been almost every season in the Himalayas and Karakoram on a quest to climb 8.000 m peaks, even if climbing all 14 of them wasn’t something that he set out to from the start. His writing style is very enjoyable: Honest, down-to-earth and lacking hyperboles which easily could sneak itself in when writing about climbing the highest peaks on the planet. The thoughtful texts describe the experiences of climbing the high mountains, what kind of mental and physical difficulties one can face, from the waiting game in base camp while sitting out bad weather and passing frozen corpses high on the mountains to climbing difficulties and getting up and down these peaks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15986690559" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7463/15986690559_90c9064a27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World &#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<p>Alan’s climbing Motto is <em>“No mountain is worth a life, coming back is a success and the summit is only a bonus”</em> and throughout the book he also highlights the importance to have enough power reserves for the descent. What happens if you don’t have these Alan has seen in his friends on some expeditions, which burned themselves out on the ascent and then had no energy left for the descent, which often is even more dangerous than going up. </p>

<p>In between chapers there are small anecdotes from Alan’s encounters with fellow mountaineers like Reinhold Messner and Jerzy Kukuczka or the Trek-Ins to base camps and local cuisine. These loosen up the already enjoyable peak stories. A real highlight for me are the fantastic photos Alan has shot during his ascents and from his travels to these two mountain ranges. The photos were shot before the rise of automatic digital cameras and so one needed to know how to adjust ISO, Aperture and Shutter Speed to get great results, and the photos in this book are proof that Alan knows his trade. I have spent a lot of time just browsing the photos, tracing the lines described in the texts to the summit, and enjoy the vast views which you can have when standing on the top of the world. </p>

<p><em>8000 Metres - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</em> is a highly enjoyable book that shouldn’t be missing on your bookshelf if you like mountaineering, alpinism and are dreaming of the highest peaks of the planet. The honest &amp; evocative writing is on par with the superb images in the book, and if you ever hope to stand on top of a 8.000 m peak you will do well to read Alan’s book and follow his Motto!</p>

<p>Get the book at your local bookshop, directly from <a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/title/8000-metres#.VKZejsbvR_0">Cicerone</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/1wIIMnr">Amazon.de</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1xzM7fy">Amazon.com</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1yehuvP">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The John Muir Trail]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/the-john-muir-trail.html"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T15:04:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/the-john-muir-trail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“In every walk with nature one receives far more than he seeks.”</em> - John Muir </p>

<p>The JMT is high on my list of places I’d like to hike. So high that it was time to get the <a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/396/title/the-john-muir-trail">Cicerone John Muir Trail</a> Guide book and a set of maps to plan &amp; dream over.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10589681926/" title="John Muir Trail by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2805/10589681926_9df593d4c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="John Muir Trail" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>John Muir is a <em>“Scottish-born American naturalist, author, and early advocate of preservation of wilderness in the United States.”</em> to quote <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Muir">Wikipedia</a>. He was very involved in preserving the Yosemite Valley, Sequoia National Park and other wilderness areas in the US, and the 340 km John Muir Trail was named after him. But why is the JMT so high on my list? I think these couple of photos explain that rather well:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ifl/4897076796/" title="John Muir Trail-20 by peretzp, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm5.staticflickr.com/4094/4897076796_eef1b5ed93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="765" alt="John Muir Trail-20" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/curtisnewton/9743235014/" title="IMG_2756 by flying white, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/9743235014_6ab5884544_b.jpg" width="1024" height="221" alt="IMG_2756" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/designministry/214810338/" title="River and flora by Kristin Myers Harvey, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm1.staticflickr.com/89/214810338_34129b6cb7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="River and flora" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jeffhester/4969130480/" title="Helen Lake by Jeff Hester, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm5.staticflickr.com/4127/4969130480_22cf801649_b.jpg" width="1024" height="385" alt="Helen Lake" /></a></p>

<p>You understand now. That’s why I got the <a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/396/title/the-john-muir-trail">John Muir Trail</a> guide book from <a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/">Cicerone</a> and the <a href="http://amzn.to/SPZ12I">John Muir Trail Map-Pack</a> to dream and plan the trip. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10589685786/" title="John Muir Trail by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5539/10589685786_b5779487dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="John Muir Trail" /></a></p>

<p>The guide book is great like all Cicerone guide books: After a short introduction and some background on the JMT it helps with planning the trip there. It highlights how to get the permits to hike the trail and climb Mt. Whitney, helps to plan &amp; organize transportation to and from the trail, and highlights some of the things you need to consider when hiking the trail: Dealing with bears, how to cross rivers, LNT principles and more. All in all I found the basics very well covered, and the author gives for important topics (like getting the permits to hike the trail) several alternatives (you can call, write a letter or reserve a permit online, for example). Even experienced hikers will find useful information from this section, especially if you’re not from the USA - things are done quite a bit different over the pond than in Europe, which in this guide book are very well high-lighted.</p>

<p>The Trail Guide section of the book then breaks the 340 km into 21 sections and gives you a great overview of what lies ahead for the day in terms of sights as well as stats (distance &amp; ascent, of the latter there’s quite a bit, too =). Every day finishes at a nice camping place, and while I find 21 days long to walk just 340 km, I do think the scenery is so majestic that it’s worth to take the time to see it all. After all, there’s no need to hurry in the outdoors.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>The book is 299 g and available at <a href="http://amzn.to/1bsaOgf">Amazon.com</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://amzn.to/1eIxoVi">Amazon.co.uk</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://amzn.to/1bmQ0mS">Amazon.de</a> and your local, well-sorted book store.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10589922143/" title="John Muir Trail by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5492/10589922143_53319a3495_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="John Muir Trail" /></a></p>

<p>While the book has maps, they’re not detailed. And the JMT and the Sierras are an area where you want detailed maps. Probably the best map is the <a href="http://amzn.to/SPZ12I">John Muir Trail Map-Pack: Shaded Relief Topo Map</a> from Tom Harrison. The map sheets, there’s 13 of them, show you in all glorious detail the trail from Yosemite to Mount Whitney. The 13 map sheets weigh 61 g and as they’re sheets, made of waterproof and tear resistant plastic (tyvek?) also, you can easily take half for the first part and pick up the other half when you resupply in the middle. They’re also most certainly something for map lovers!</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>The maps are available at <a href="http://amzn.to/SPZ12I">Amazon.com</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://amzn.to/1cRO2Sj">Amazon.co.uk</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://amzn.to/HL8m9A">Amazon.de</a> and your local, well-sorted book store.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>As for <strong>when</strong> I will be hiking the JMT, I think 2015 might be a good year =)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
