<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gas stoves | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gas-stoves/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-29T16:23:59+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Primus OmniLite Ti]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/primus-omnilite-ti.html"/>
    <updated>2012-02-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/primus-omnilite-ti</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a new lightweight multifuel stove on the block, and it’s name is <a href="http://www.primus.eu/omnilite">Primus OmniFuel Ti</a>. Ti obviously stands for Titanium, the coveted UL material which is so dear to us ultralight backpackers. With two winter tours on the programme for me, one which will be solo and over a week, I thought it might be high-time to look into those stoves which are common among Polar Explorers.</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/36014308?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff0179" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>It arrived in the last week of January 2012. So far I had it out and tested it with gas (Video coming) and try to get out this week to test it with Primus PowerFuel in -24°C or more. I might try other fuels, though as I don’t have a car I rarely visit gasstations.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/WEQDnf3uqGf0hfYNmyRp-BC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-d6hUWBbjX5Q/TypSm018PgI/AAAAAAAAGG8/ehdix8qGKAI/s640/DSC02061.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>It is a Multifuel Stove, which makes it a tool to produce boiling water for food &amp; drinks. However, Multifuel stoves have the advantage that they usually are excellent for very cold temperatures where other fuel sources are not working well, and that they can be used when travelling in different countries and it is unknown what fuel sources will be available - with a multifuel stove chances are that you will find one that works. The OmniLite Ti works with</p>

<ul>
  <li>Propane/ butane/ isobutane gas</li>
  <li>White Gas</li>
  <li>Vehicle fuel</li>
  <li>Kerosene</li>
  <li>Diesel</li>
</ul>

<p>So if you plan to do an around-the-world-trip, this stove certainly would have you covered (you also can rely on biomaterials for cooking). I got it less for an around-the-world-trip but more for its cold weather capabilities. Wood or gas are not very reliable at the low temperatures I am expecting on my trips, so a stove which can melt snow and boil water without much fuss is certainly not just a very comfortable solution, but at -25°C or more almost critical.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/sBEW9UY5TBYo3wFuLq-9MxC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-qH4Xui7K6lw/TypQDbouslI/AAAAAAAAGA4/51nD7gR9SSk/s640/DSC02072.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>A stand/ pot support made of Titanium, which makes it lighter than the OmniFuel or other multifuel stoves. Optimized to work with Eta pots (so pots with them fins down on the bottom). It is equipped with a system called “Primus Wind Proof Burner” that adjusts the flame to wind condtitions, minimizing the chance that it goes out. The fuel line and pump have a self bleeding system to eliminate flares and spills. Absent from this list is a pre-heater (A tube which pre-heats the fuel which comes from the bottle/ cartridge over/ near the flame). This is interesting, and I will probably soon find out if this is a bad thing, or if this stove works just wine without one.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/POyWy3pm-QW8ZrHJNV7PHxC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-QF85dKaKL5o/TypQuYYmqgI/AAAAAAAAGCg/T4qeRm0JcZ8/s640/DSC02116.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>It is made of Titanium. Not an innovation per se, though there’s not many Ti multifuel burners on the market, so this certainly makes it stand out. <br /><br />It is made to work with Eta Pots; that are those pots from Primus which allow for better fuel efficiency. I got their 2,1 litre pot with the stove, and will see if this is really the case (going to test it with a pot without the fins underneath).</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/UtIgIMzhoCiAke_XD7FmZRC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LgwvuMoZNe0/TypQaBJYkuI/AAAAAAAAGBo/dAEA8gFcPJk/s640/DSC02093.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>It is very well made, lemme tell ya. It is Made in Estland, and the quality is superb. It radiates trustworthiness and durability.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>An important part! Lets see:</p>

<ul>
  <li>219 gram - Stove</li>
  <li>194 gram - Fuel bottle with pump</li>
  <li>090 gram - Titanium windscreen</li>
  <li>134 gram - Bag</li>
  <li>042 gram - Multitool</li>
  <li>413 gram for stove and (empty) bottle with pump installed</li>
</ul>

<p>You can leave the fuel bottle at home is you plan to use it only with cartridges. The benefit of such a stove versus e.g. the Jetboil Sol Ti is that you can invert the cartridge, as in low temperatures the gas solidifies and in a normal stove will sink to the bottom - if you can invert the cartridge that means it goes right to the hose and the burner. Of course you could build a small cozy for the cartridge to insulate it from the cold, though I am not certain how well this works in very cold temperatures.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/2ayI8H6Rg9JkcwtLHkRBsBC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-cJXrN4x4PQ8/TypQOwgoi-I/AAAAAAAAGBQ/eBljAjstB1A/s640/DSC02078.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability">Sustainability</h2>

<p>It is the same question as with other gas/ multifuel stoves: The stoves themselves are fairly sustainable - I expect this stove will work for years to come - but it is the fuel it runs on which is not sustainable. The Primus PowerFuel comes in a plastic bottle (and it is made in the Netherlands) while the Primus Power Gas is Made in South Korea and comes in an Aluminium cartridge. Once empty, you need to buy a new one, and the fuels themselves also are not the most environmental friendly. The other fuels it can run on - diesel, gasoline and kerosene are in the same category, not very sustainable or environmentally friendly.</p>

<p>You’re in a hard place if you go winter backpacking and need a reliable fuel - you pretty much need to use one of the above or rely on wood, which might be very hard to get in some places and at -30°C or more can be difficult to work with. This is something to consider; though it is pretty much either one of the unsustainable fuels or melting snow with body heat and eating cold food (or make a wood fire if possible). <br /><br />It is made in Estland, which means at least for me it only had a short trip to arrive here.</p>

<h2 id="recyclability">Recyclability</h2>

<p>Looking at the stove unit, it consists of titanium, brass and steel, the hose is probably rubber and there’s a plastic knob. All of these materials can be recycled, digging them up takes quite a toll on the environment, though.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/h5Rs_mibzv6x9dDTs8Q3bRC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-IwqxAXoZ85U/TypQpktOd-I/AAAAAAAAGCQ/5UGicJSFmtg/s640/DSC02113.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>Stoves compete with other stoves, as well as a good old fire. So besides the BushBuddy, Ti-Tri Caldera Cone, Backcountry Boiler, <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti.html" target="_blank">Jetboil Sol Ti</a>, Gnat and others, the main competition will be from other Multifuel Stoves. The lightest is the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/mehrstoffkocher-soto-muka-benzinkocher.html">Soto Muka</a> (claimed weight of 160 gram, 200€, works with gasoline and white gas). A classic is the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/mehrstoffkocher-msr-whisperlite-intern-combo-kocher.html">MSR Whisperlite</a> (claimed weight of 305 gram, 120€, works with different liquid fuels). The <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/mehrstoffkocher-optimus-nova-kocher.html">Optimus Nova</a> (claimed weight of 435 gram, 140€, burns liquid fuels) is another familiar name when looking for multifuel stoves.</p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p>Only <a href="http://www.tgomagazine.co.uk/news/gearnews/the-primus-omnilite-ti-stove-exclusive-first-review">Chris Townsend has reviewed it</a>, and he says <em>If you want a stove that can run on a variety of fuels this is one of the best around.</em> He seems not to have tested it in the cold, though.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/36700656?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff0179" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Coming after further testing. <a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/Habichtshorst/PrimusOmniLiteTi?authuser=0&amp;authkey=Gv1sRgCP2wm9-N8cXOngE&amp;feat=directlink">More Photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-get-it">Where to get it</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-omnilite-ti-mehrstoffkocher-bf/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/primus-omnilite-ti-kocher/">Bergzeit</a> have the stoves in Europe, while <a href="http://bit.ly/1xYBYUi">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1otDTPe">Amazon</a> are the places to go in the USA.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ABgsDtjwjdgFNwfDMSnUDRC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-dKUoX6CGeM0/TypQ211Gy6I/AAAAAAAAGC4/TXhqSXsMO7g/s640/DSC02120.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a>
<a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/CQUmQmH1j-RFTkk0-BV-LxC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-AyaDCKZEon8/TypQ8jjcnYI/AAAAAAAAGDI/Oo-h-ARA7dE/s640/DSC02123.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a>
<a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/RzzRmPx6MNizuL-erR_pCRC7BOQfG_RQvqLIuOYHy8w?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-EVCTitrpWg8/TypQ_jLJX5I/AAAAAAAAGDQ/0mMjuq5j4mg/s640/DSC02126.JPG" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jetboil Sol Ti]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-23T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Titanium. The chemical element with the symbol Ti and atomic number 22. A standard atomic weight of 47.867(1) and a hexagonal crystal structure, it is one of the finest elements the ultralight backpacker lusts after. <a href="http://bit.ly/1Ahwlnp">Jetboil</a> makes use of that fine material in order to produce the lightest, fastest and most efficient gas stove currently on the market. <a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/">Webtogs</a> asked me if I’d like to give the <a href="http://bit.ly/17csUUu">Jetboil Sol Ti</a> some proper usage in nordic &amp; arctic conditions. Looking for a good reason to try gas stoves yet again, and I having read a lot of positive stuff about Jetboil products in general I was delighted about the possibility to try this newest and lightest creation. Lets dive in this living review.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/qt_Xk9k3j5UpGcwFLncDWQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-tximGAI1C5I/Tns6Xl4Jm_I/AAAAAAAAFXU/Fcg-3MWciS8/s640/_DSC2481.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/29561311?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I got the Sol Ti in mid August, and have so far only used it on day trips - this thus can be considered a rather detailed “first look”. I will update and annex the different sections over time.</p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The Sol Ti is made to boil water. You can cook in it, but need to do so at the smallest flame possible and keep on stirring to minimize the risk of burning your food in the pot - personally I go for boiling water exclusively and pour it into a freezer bag for “cooking”. With that in mind, I can already say that the Sol Ti fulfills its function exquisitely, as it does boil water.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/4Df5QyldgxS1uvv698PHfA?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-DYre4nP0mhI/Tns6YEOLDmI/AAAAAAAAFXY/isxcBLjAn-4/s640/_DSC2483.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Light, compact, efficient, fast is what I’d say are the main features. Of those four fast is of the least concern to me, though I won’t dismiss the merit of a fast stove in inclement conditions. But generally speaking, two or four or six minutes makes in a normal situation not much of a difference to me. Compactness on the other hand is something I value immensely. Going light has for me also a lot to do  with decreasing the size of the gear, and this is where the Sol Ti really scores well. Being efficient means I don’t need to carry more canisters with me, and I should be able to get around 12 liters of boiling water out of one 100 gram canister - if I calculate with one liter a day (500 ml morning, 500 ml evening), this would mean twelve days before I run out of fuel. Not bad at all. And being light, obviously, is great.</p>

<p>Jetboil says the features are the pour spout and strainer, the secure &amp; easy pot connection, the fluxring, and the advanced igniter. Lets look at these in detail. A pour spout and strainer definitely are nice. They are both integrated into the lid, though - less of a deal with the strainer, but I feel a spout would have been nice as part of the pot itself - especially if once leaves the lid at home. I didn’t find any info online or in the instructions if the lid, made of a plastic of sorts, is BPA free, but <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jetboil/status/117264726966280193">Jetboil replied on Twitter</a> that all their plastic is BPA free.</p>

<p>The secure &amp; easy pot connection is secure, but I wouldn’t say easy. It ain’t difficult, but easy is something like the MSR Reactor where I just put the pot on the burner and <em>Voilá</em>. With the Sol Ti putting the pot on the burner means you need to align the cut-out on the pot with the small bump on the burner and push them together until it feels secure. After that it is safe and sound, and shouldn’t fall off even if the complete unit tips over. Getting the pot off the burner after you have boiled water in it is a bit fiddly, but not a major obstacle.</p>

<p>The Fluxring is a nice feature. It makes the Sol Ti very efficient - I used on average 4 grams of gas to boil 500 ml of water in under two minutes on my daytrips. I might try to compare it to a pot without a Fluxring to see how much efficiency it adds. The igniter also is a useful feature, as it means you don’t need to use your firesteel &amp; puukko, a lighter or matches to get it on fire.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/vrDNlnUrvIRe4hIvu31_9Q?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-IwmX8IcEVuQ/Tns6bDytHXI/AAAAAAAAFXs/8hby3RHBzRg/s640/_DSC2488.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a>
<a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/4PknXinLxleBabXOa_UMPw?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-ky3t_Rp9Ki8/Tns6aakrjPI/AAAAAAAAFXo/XPANqZkU1jc/s640/_DSC2487.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>No real innovations on the Sol Ti, if we don’t see minimizing weight to an absolute minimum as an innovation. Jetboil claims an “<i>Increased Cold Weather Performance</i>” - it not yet being anywhere close to 0°C I can not confirm that and it will need to wait till winter. The “Fluxring” is Jetboil’s version of a heat exchanger with a fancier (or more confusing) name. It is nothing new, though, and also <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/04/first-look-monatauk-gnat-video.html">stoves made of titanium</a> are hardly an innovation.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ungMBfz33YK5qdEy9AgxAQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-GQF2mlrcv-c/Tns6bsyL6-I/AAAAAAAAFXw/JQuhinzzdIY/s640/_DSC2489.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>Overall quality is solid. The pot sleeve is not cut and sewn very clean, but it is more a cosmetic than a functional matter. The pot is nicely made, though some users have experienced the development of a white powder between the fluxring and the pot bottom (The fluxring is made of Aluminium, while the rest of the pot is made of titanium - this can create problems with corrosion, see “What Others Say”). The Burner unit has the orange plastic ring-support-thingy around it, which holds the Piezo ignition. The black ignition button has about a millimeter of movement in its hold, and also the cable, while firmly in place, could somehow get damaged. I imagine if the complete unit would have been made of Titanium of Aluminum and would be enclosed (much like the Reactor unit) it would probably be similarly light (now the stove seems to be made from steel, not titanium). However, this is serious nitpicking - it really is very well made, and I have no doubt that it will have a long life.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>Easily the most important bit on an ultralight blog!</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pot: 102 gram</li>
  <li>Pot lid: 18 gram</li>
  <li>Pot sleeve: 15 gram</li>
  <li>Pot support: 37 gram</li>
  <li>Pot bottom cup: 34 gram</li>
  <li>Burner unit: 104 gram</li>
  <li>Canister Tripod: 28 gram</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>TOTAL</strong>: 338 gram for everything.</p>

<p>A UL backpacker would leave the pot bottom cup (minus 34 g), the pot support if he doesn’t use some other pot (minus 37 gram) and the canister tripod (minus 28 gram) at home, and would ponder if he really needs the pot lid (which would save another 18 gram). That would mean he’d carry only the burner unit, the pot &amp; sleeve and the lid for a total of 239 gram. For a complete unit, if you want to be able to boil water fast &amp; convenient, surely a great setup. <br /><br /></p>

<h2 id="sustainability">Sustainability</h2>

<p>A look at the <a href="http://www.jetboil.com/">Jetboil website</a> shows there’s zero information on any sustainability efforts of the company. The Sol Ti itself is Made in China so will have quite a trip via ships, trucks, trains and plains behind it before it is in front of you. The packaging it comes in is compact and small, made of a clear PET plastic which can be (in Finland, don’t know how it is in your country) easily recycled. The papers and the packaging lack any information on if they’re printed on recycled/ FSC approved paper with soy inks et al. so it is save to think they’re most likely not. However, paper is easy to recycle in most countries.</p>

<h2 id="recyclability">Recyclability</h2>

<p>Aluminium and titanium can be recycled. However, Jetboil has no info on this, or a recycle system in place. You might be able to recycle your Sol Ti either via a scrapyard or, if it is still in good condition, sell it onwards or trade it at a service like Swap.com. Paper and packaging which come with it can be easily recycled (in Finland).</p>

<p>The big drawback of any gas stove is less the stove itself, but the gas canisters which are used. Now while Jetboil has a “Butane Canister Recycling Tool” I find this is just a mediocre solution. I still much more would prefer a refillable canister solution, which would save massive resources in terms of production, transportation and waste. However, I think JetBoil, Primus, SnowPeak and all other gas canister manufacturers are not interested in innovating and are happy with the rather poor status quo. Anyhow. The <a href="http://bit.ly/1CYBpR5">Crunch It tool</a> allows you to puncture butane canisters in a safe way and make them ready for recycling. It is a step in the right direction, though there are better solutions, as I outlined.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>Besides <a href="http://bit.ly/1zGKyaB">Jetboil’s own stoves</a> there’s a bunch of competeling products (practically every stove can be seen a competitor, but lets think systems here): The <a href="http://bit.ly/1xlQF7l">MSR Reactor</a> and <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/03/video-optimus-crux-lite-in-winter.html">Optimus Crux Lite</a> come to my mind, as they’re complete sets. If you open your mind a bit, then also the <a href="http://vimeo.com/22221272">Backcountry Boiler</a> and the <a href="http://www.traildesigns.com/stoves/caldera-sidewinder">Trail Designs Sidewinders</a> can be considered competing problems. </p>

<p>Of these I would consider the MSR Reactor the closest competitor. While being heavier it is has a higher volume (0,6 l for the Sol Ti versus 1,5 l for the Reactor) and is similarly efficient in its usage of gas and speed. I will do a video of them in the future to discuss them side-by-side; for now it is useful to point out similar systems.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/isLCQzX5VQRvq-xCY2npkg?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-81kVF7t9TBw/Tns6dGg1EFI/AAAAAAAAFX8/BbSXMKtiQlY/s640/_DSC2493.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/MN_tnKNehwQUWXizLrKFBQ?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-4PPNUCpgq1I/Tns6daUYQLI/AAAAAAAAFYA/EPsHYtN-0wc/s640/_DSC2494.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nielsenbrownoutdoors.com/2011/08/gear-reflections-lapland-2011.html">Roger found the Sol Ti a star</a> on his Nordkalottleden trip. <a href="https://twitter.com/tramplite/status/115512562900148224">Colin</a> reports some corrosion on his Sol Ti after using it on the Colorado Trail. </p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>On my daytrips, many of them in inclement weather, I was very happy about the convenience and fast speed of the stove. All in all you can have a hot beverage in about four minutes from taking it out of your pack to a steaming hot cup of tea in your hand. I was equally impressed about the efficiency - four grams of gas for 500 ml is very good, more use will see if this a constant variable. I like the compact size, as I use an Osprey Raptor 18 for biking, and it has little space - but also on backpacking trips I’m certain that I will enjoy the compactness of this stove - it is 15 cm high and 11 cm in diameter. Besides some nitpicking I can’t find any serious negative with the burner itself - the price of ~150€ is high, but then you get a great piece of kit.</p>

<p>Looking further than the Sol Ti, I would wish to see efforts from Jetboil in the sustainability department - Jetboil can start easy by becoming a <a href="http://onepercentfortheplanet.org/en/">1% For The Planet</a> member, get a Environmental Management System in place and if they wanna go the extra mile consider Cradle-to-Cradle aspects in the design of its products.</p>

<p><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/105306052609390995141/JetboilSolTi#">More photos</a> if you want to see some different angles as the one shown here.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Get yours at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/jetboil-sol-kochsystem/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/jetboil-sol-ti-premium-kocher/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1eEFmMh">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/17csUUu">CampSaver.com</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/16qVMT5">REI.com</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
