<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OutDoor Fair 2013 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T15:17:25+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News Conclusions]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/outdoor-news-conclusions.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-21T23:04:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/outdoor-news-conclusions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After all that <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">gear news</a>, it’s worth to ponder if it was worth going down south.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9508132549/" title="Hallways of Always by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7422/9508132549_966ab576f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hallways of Always" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I have been sceptical of the OutDoor in the past. Well, I was wrong. The OutDoor - and ISPO, for that matter - certainly have their place and it’s good that bloggers like <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">Benjamin</a>, <a href="http://ultraknilch.blogspot.fi/2013/07/outdoor-friedrichshafen-2013.html">Markus</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/">Corinna</a>, <a href="http://www.martin-huelle.de/blog/">Martin</a>, <a href="http://blog.fastpacking.de/">Carsten</a>, <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/">Sven</a> and <a href="http://www.trekking.lu/">Aender</a>, amongst others, are there. Not only can they cover news in real time on their blogs (Benjamin, for example, was updating his site every evening!) and <a href="http://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>/ <a href="http://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, they also present more unique view points. Magazines know the news often ahead of time, but I find their articles are often nothing more than re-phrased PR blurbs and photos. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9510923290/" title="Past by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2826/9510923290_0231a8493e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Past" /></a></p>

<p>So what about innovation at the fair? Well, there was some. That Montbell Plasma 1000 down jacket was certainly interesting, as were the La Sportiva Trango Cube boots. Also some of the ropes - from Petzl, Beal and Edelrid - and the hardware from Black Diamond and DMM was very interesting. The OutDry technology will be something to watch, and the increased use of 7 and 10 denier fabrics by major manufacturers is bringing lightweight garments to a wider audience. It was also nice to see companies using Silnylon for backpacks, and tyvek for sleeping bags. Cuben also is now used by some companies - sometimes well, and sometimes not so well. One of the companies which used cuben in a smart way, and was aware of its strengths and weaknesses, was CRUX. Using cuben for porches and vents on tents saves just minimal weight, but lets more light go through to the inner. Good stuff.</p>

<p>But while it was nice to see major companies adopt more and more lightweight materials, and making more simple designs, I missed that one thing which wowed me. Sure, there were heaps of nice gear, new fabrics and I personally am also very happy to see that hiking garments get a lot of nice colours (I’m a bit tired of black), but there wasn’t anything that stood out, like it was more often the case in the past (check <a href="http://lighthiker.wordpress.com/2010/07/06/outdoor-show-the-lightweight-preview/">Roman’s past posts</a>, for example). But then, does there need to be? </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9508179011/" title="Adam Ondra giving tips by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7442/9508179011_76b3ae527c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Adam Ondra giving tips" /></a></p>

<p>For me it was a lot of fun. I met friends again, got to know people I only knew digitally and via EMail, and even was able to go for a nice <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/sul-in-the-swiss-alps.html">Overnighter in the Swiss Alps</a> afterwards. The weather was superb in Friedrichshafen, sunshine all the time, super warm and there were good after-fair parties where you could chat with friends and company representatives in a relaxed atmosphere while drinking a good beer. Oh, and interviewing <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">Ueli Steck</a> certainly was a highlight which made the whole trip worth my while!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9510930730/" title="Boulder Competition by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7351/9510930730_dcbb16f3fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Boulder Competition" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9508138455/" title="Boulder Competition by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2808/9508138455_f415ca9cd8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Boulder Competition" /></a></p>

<p>There were also other excellent entertainment possibilities. You could try the Trail Running Parcour, slacklining, go bouldering - or watch Germany’s best climbers compete on some tasty boulder problems. There was no shortage of outdoor athletes, either: Adam Ondra was at the La Sportiva party, Ines Papert was around, and several other alpinists, climbers, mountaineers, runners and outdoor athletes were representing their sponsors at the Fair. It was a very relaxed atmosphere, and a superb opportunity to chat with some people whom you only know from magazines and Vimeo videos.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9467439976/" title="Need a USB Stick? by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2885/9467439976_6af4d8e1f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Need a USB Stick?" /></a></p>

<p>There’s room for improvement, though. My recommendation for companies is to ditch USB sticks and have info available digitally - Haglöfs, MSR, Therm-A-Rest and a couple others were smart like that, while others were handing out USB sticks (often just with a few MB of data on a 4 GB stick) like they were candy. Going digitally will save the environment and be just easier. That catalogues shouldn’t be handed out should be clear, too (this is from a Journalist &amp; blogger’s perspective, I’m aware that buyers have different requirements =)</p>

<p>For us Press folks there were two super-friendly staffed Press Centres, the staff there really was superb and it was a pleasure to go there in the morning and between meetings to catch a breath, have a coffee and pretzel before heading to the next meeting. And it was a good place to get some work done, too!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9510925078/" title="The Show Must Go On by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3708/9510925078_2e51ce4d60_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Show Must Go On" /></a></p>

<p>Will I go again next year? Maybe. I certainly won’t mind meeting all my friends again, and make new ones. It’s also a great opportunity to make industry contacts, or just meet really talented people and have a coffee with them - like I did with <a href="http://www.alexandrebuisse.org/">Alexandre</a>. And if I can combine it with some time in the mountains, well, then it certainly looks like a good idea to go =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9510964196/" title="Great to see you. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7291/9510964196_854461038c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Great to see you." /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News IV]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/outdoor-news-iv.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-14T23:04:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/outdoor-news-iv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And the final batch of new gear!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9448998107/" title="Jetboil booth by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3771/9448998107_0167bc05f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Jetboil booth" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="montbell">MontBell</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.montbell.jp/">MontBell</a> is a well known company when it comes to fast and light garments. The Japanese company didn’t disappoint at the OutDoor this year, and presented several garments and small accessories which should be high on the list of ultralight alpinists and backpackers alike. Hard to not notice was the Plasma 1000 down jacket, which uses 1000 cuin down, a 7 Denier Ballistic Airlight Nylon and a unique sewing pattern to create a truly warm garment which tips the scales at 145 g. I’m sure this will be a very popular garment in the fast &amp; light crowd - and it won a OutDoor Industry Award, too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9395784656/" title="montbell Plasma 1000 Down Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7309/9395784656_ea46828a68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell Plasma 1000 Down Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Montbell Crushable Lamp Shade uses cuben to make a lightweight cover for you headlamp - giving you the option for ultralight ambient light for reading and chilling in your shelter on dark evening.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9395912020/" title="montbell Crushable Lamp Shade by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3750/9395912020_702f2f3d18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell Crushable Lamp Shade" /></a></p>

<p>Montbell coffee filter and chopsticks combine for the perfect drip coffee tool. The filter comes in two sizes, and the chopsticks can be screwed apart for a smaller pack size.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9395922210/" title="montbell coffee filter &amp; chopsticks by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3715/9395922210_161b43c5e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell coffee filter &amp; chopsticks" /></a></p>

<p>The Thermawrap Skirt could be rather popular in Scotland. And other countries where men and women wear skirts. Looked superb and a useful item for colder evenings, where down/ synthetic pants would be too much.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9395858216/" title="montbell Thermawrap Skirt by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2814/9395858216_09846e2984_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell Thermawrap Skirt" /></a></p>

<p>My first encounter with Montbell sleeping bags. Wow - truly superb sleeping bags, so much room to move, pack small, are light - there’s a lot to like about these, and if I wouldn’t be such a proponent of quilts I’d be highly tempted to try one (OK, ok, I’m also so very highly tempted to try one =).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396387572/" title="montbell sleeping bags by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5506/9396387572_d69ff27564_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell sleeping bags" /></a></p>

<p>The Tachyon and Tachyon Anorak. There were a lot of runner-ups for lightest windshirt at the fair, but the Tachyon won. 45 g for the hoody version, 65 g for the one with a full zipper. Awesomeness in a tiny, packed package.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393649659/" title="montbell Tachyon Anorak by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2883/9393649659_899859bcb8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell Tachyon Anorak" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393636039/" title="montbell Tachyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5495/9393636039_55371bf7a1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell Tachyon" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393646103/" title="montbell Tachyon packed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2807/9393646103_649e2e65d7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell Tachyon packed" /></a></p>

<p>A UL Down T-Shirt. That’d go well with the Klättermusen Down shorts, for those days where you need a bit more warmth but want to go sleeveless.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393662675/" title="montbell U.L. Down T by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/9393662675_3b8421786a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell U.L. Down T" /></a></p>

<p>The Montbell Torrent Flier jacket, together with the other hardshells from the company, were really nice garments. The Torrent Flier uses 2.5 layer Paclite and weighs under 250 g, and it did feel really good on the skin. It comes with pit zips, one pocket and simple cuff and hem adjustability. There were a few other hardshells which used Montbell’s own Drytec fabric, which cost under 100€ and thus should be great for occasional hikers and backpackers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393036263/" title="montbell Torrent Flier jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5493/9393036263_7e00ae8a85_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="montbell Torrent Flier jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396398670/" title="montbell hardshells by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5340/9396398670_6ae68621fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="montbell hardshells" /></a></p>

<h2 id="montane">Montane</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.montane.co.uk/">Montane</a>, the fast and light company from the UK, came out with some great gear which will have mountaineers, trailrunners and backpackers alike be frolicking through the outdoors. Part of the Spring/ Summer 2014 collection is the Minimus Sleeping Bag, which uses PERTEX Shield+ and is filled with 345 g of 800 cuin down and weighs 828 g completely. Oh, it won a OutDoor Industry Award, too!</p>

<p>And then there’s a bunch of sweet new garments from Montane. The Spektr Smock got a re-design, there’s new materials being used in many garments - like POLARTEC Alpha, which is used in the Alpha Guide Jacket. It encases the POLARTEC Alpha in layers of PERTEX Microlight Stretch fabric for wind resistance and stretch for climbing. Thumbloops, an under-the-helmet hood and a two way zipper make it a great belay jacket on the mountain - and it got the POLARTEC Apex Award, too! (I’ll update the article on the other garments once I find my notes =).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396272722/" title="Montane Alpha Guide Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7452/9396272722_1e779cefa8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Montane Alpha Guide Jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396259154/" title="2. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5333/9396259154_2f0a7ba8d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="2." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396253918/" title="3. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3668/9396253918_2407593dd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="3." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393480883/" title="4. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7444/9393480883_8b7e0a2f5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="4." /></a></p>

<h2 id="klymit">Klymit</h2>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1ct7JOR">Klymit</a>, maker of the Inertia X Frame launched the Motion pack series, which Matthew from <a href="http://www.elementalhorizons.com/">Elemental Horizons</a> helped them design. The Motion comes in a 35 and 60 l version, and will weigh 695 g or 1233 g respectively. It uses the Air Beam Frame Sheet technology for suspension, and the Air Beam Frame Sheet also helps to compress the load in your pack, making for a tight package. The system (thus the Air Beam Frame Sheet) lets you adjust the pressure, so if you want it soft - air goes out - if you want it hard, - air goes in. It also should be compliant during motion and conforms 
with the body, and yes, it should also be a pretty light suspension system. </p>

<p>Then there will be a new pad, the Inertia O Zone pad which will be 346 g. It will be combining the comfort of the Static V with the weight savings from the Inertia series, and comes with an integrated 4-inch tall pillow.</p>

<p>Finally, packrafters will like the Lite Water Dingy. 992 g and a 11.4 x 23 cm packed size, this can help you to get a 1,5 kg packraft kit for lakes and slow rivers, be it for crossings, fishing or just going with the flow. Here’s a <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/61712293@N03/9260672257/">photo</a> of the LWD.</p>

<h2 id="dmm">DMM</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.dmmclimbing.com/">DMM</a> is likely my favourite climbing hardwear company, and I was quite excited to meet them in Friedrichshafen. They come out with some swell new gear, like the Rhino Belay carabiner, the horn on it prevents locking assisted devices rotating off the top bar and on to the spine reducing the risk of cross loading.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9395981412/" title="DMM Rhino by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5449/9395981412_9b3397de7b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Rhino" /></a></p>

<p>The Thor is a winter &amp; trad biner and boasts an 11kN gate open rating, the biner itself is 36 g and should give you extra security and robustness if that’s what you are looking for. The QD will be 73 to 77 g depending on the length you choose.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393198707/" title="DMM Thor quickdraw by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2833/9393198707_280a99e00c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Thor quickdraw" /></a></p>

<p>The Alpha Light is a 32 g trad biner which clips beautifully easy. A clean nose - like on almost all DMM ‘biners - reduces snagging and a wide gate opening makes clipping and unclipping easier. QDs weigh between 73 and 77 g depending on length, and they come in five different colours.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393189577/" title="DMM Alpha Light QD by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3709/9393189577_4000ebca7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Alpha Light QD" /></a></p>

<p>The DMM Zenith backpack is an 500 g, 18 l daypack for climbers. It’s harness compatible, holds food, water, a jacket and descent shoes while valuables go in the zip pocket. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396038196/" title="DMM Zenith backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5538/9396038196_fc8f2213c1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DMM Zenith backpack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393236821/" title="DMM Zenith backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7390/9393236821_1cf833aa41_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DMM Zenith backpack" /></a></p>

<p>A fine pack is the DMM Flight. 45 l volume, zips completely open and can be laid out, this sports climbing pack will hold an 80 m rope in its detachable tarp and all the other gear you might need for a long day at the crag. You even could use it as a carry-on if you want, as it complies with airline carry-on allowances measurements! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396354808/" title="DMM Flight backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7437/9396354808_99e7c149b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Flight backpack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393350189/" title="DMM Flight backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7346/9393350189_4ca078f9bb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Flight backpack" /></a></p>

<p>And a great pack which I’m tempted by is the DMM Vector trad pack. 45 l, 990 g, this light and durable pack ticks all the boxes for me, even if I just recently bought the <a href="http://camu.fi/shop/kiipeily/kalliokiipeily/kaysipussit/classicropebaggreen.html">DMM Classic</a>. The Vector holds a pitcher rope bag in the bottom, a Rack-Sack which will hold all your climbing gear - Cams, Nuts, QDs, et al. -  and keeps it dirt free whilst racking up. And then there’s still space for food, clothing, camera and water. It stands upright, you can haul it up a route and it carries nicely. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396096014/" title="DMM Vector trad pack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3737/9396096014_67a656bc5f_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DMM Vector trad pack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393475567/" title="DMM Vector trad pack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2809/9393475567_ce5c4389e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Vector trad pack" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, the DMM Void Duffle will get all that gear and more to the crag in Patagonia, Spain or Greece. Available in 45 l, 75 l and 100 l models in sweet colours, the duffles can be worn as a backpack.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396358050/" title="DMM Void Duffle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2893/9396358050_331b75060f_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DMM Void Duffle" /></a></p>

<h2 id="mountain-hardwear">Mountain Hardwear</h2>

<p>I’ve been a <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com/">Mountain Hardwear</a> fan for quite some time - besides the superb gear &amp; garments from the Ueli Steck Project they also have an innovative mix of kit which is of interest for lightweight backpackers. There’s the Ghost Whisperer Hooded Down Jacket, for example. A 212 g down jacket what uses 850 cuin water-repellant down and a 7D fabric, two zippered pockets and it can be packed into its own pocket when not needed. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9502403739/" title="Ghost Whisperer Hooded Down Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5549/9502403739_8348482351_b.jpg" width="775" height="785" alt="Ghost Whisperer Hooded Down Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>Made from the same 7 denier by 10 denier fabric is the Ghost Whisperer Hooded Jacket, a windjacket which also will keep you dry in a summer rain shower. It has a full zipper and a hood, reflective details to make you visible on those dark November evenings when you hike out along a road, and will pack tiny.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9502402199/" title="Ghost Whisperer Hooded Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7429/9502402199_6c31455499_b.jpg" width="828" height="798" alt="Ghost Whisperer Hooded Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Quasar Hybrid Pullover is part of the Ueli Steck Project and is a lightweight, waterproof-breathable and air permeable ice- and rock-climbing pullover shell. It boosts great articulation and stretch insets allow you to reach that good hold. And if <a href="http://uelisteck.ch/">Ueli</a> wears it it should be just fine for us average alpinists!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9502399419/" title="Quasar Hybrid Pullover by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3790/9502399419_b92a8a1446_b.jpg" width="764" height="807" alt="Quasar Hybrid Pullover" /></a></p>

<p>And then there’s the South Col 70 OutDry, the first really waterproof backpack. OutDry technology bonds a durable waterproof membrane directly to the shell fabric for a completely sealed interface so the pack stays light and dry without compromising weight or function. While made for mountaineering I can imagine that this pack could work rather well for packrafting and hiking in wet areas pretty well, too (Read more about OutDry in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-ii.html">Update II</a>).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9502396497/" title="South Col 70 OutDry by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3712/9502396497_769a08676f_b.jpg" width="705" height="809" alt="South Col 70 OutDry" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bergans-of-norway">Bergans of Norway</h2>

<p><a href="http://bergans.eu/">Bergans of Norway</a> isn’t really well known for lightweight kit, but that’s about to change. Their Air jacket tips the scales at 80 g in Size L - that’s less than two Snickers! PERTEX Quantum is used to make this windjacket, which has a full zip, hood and a chest pocket. The DWR finish is PFOA-free, and yes - it will store in its own pocket while reflective details make others aware of you between dusk and dawn.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9502657223/" title="Bergans Air Jacket Lady by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2816/9502657223_8a31862dd0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Bergans Air Jacket Lady" /></a></p>

<p>Then there’s the Rondane backpack series, where the 6 l and 12 l models are new for 2014. They use the Bergans Rock Steady Stability System (RS3TM) that should reduce the up-and-down motion when walking, and it felt very comfortable as I tried it on. It weighs 410 g for the small one, and 440 g for the 12 l one and comes in a host of nice colours. They should be of interest to trailrunners and mountain bikers, as they also can be equipped with a hydration system.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9505502320/" title="Bergans Rondane 6 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7301/9505502320_94f2689ec9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Bergans Rondane 6" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9502714959/" title="Bergans Rondane 38 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5455/9502714959_1fdc63cb9e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Bergans Rondane 38" /></a></p>

<h2 id="jetboil">Jetboil</h2>

<p>A new large stove from <a href="http://www.jetboil.com/">Jetboil</a>! The Jetboil Joule tips the scales at 715 gram with the 2,5 l pot and has a claimed boil time of 2:40 min for 1 l of water. It’s an inverted gas canister design and should give consistent heat output till down to -12°C. The pot has a flux ring for added efficiency, there’s a handle which folds away and a see through lid with a built in strainer. If this really works as claimed it could be a very great gas stove for winter and high alpine tours. Speaking of alpine, the Jetboil Joule Alpinist add-on allows you to hang it up and has an additional windshield. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9451784024/" title="Jetboil Joule by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3740/9451784024_b95d31e587_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Jetboil Joule" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9449000593/" title="Jetboil Joule Alpinist add-on by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2876/9449000593_007c2e01ed_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Jetboil Joule Alpinist add-on" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9449001723/" title="Jetboil Joule by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2840/9449001723_1100863365_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Jetboil Joule" /></a></p>

<h2 id="little-life">Little Life</h2>

<p>The Ranger Child Carrier from <a href="http://www.littlelife.com/">Little Life</a> looks like a strong contender for future outdoor families. 1,7 kg and a price tag of only 85€, this is not only the lightest child carrier on the market, but surely also the cheapest. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9396351514/" title="Little Life Ranger Child Carrier by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7413/9396351514_f1cc2d91f6_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Little Life Ranger Child Carrier" /></a></p>

<h2 id="snow-peak">Snow Peak</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.snowpeak.com/">Snow Peak</a> had a few really nice items, some I can show you, others not yet. Those I can’t show include a headlamp in which the beam moves separately from the lamp, which allows for a light beam moving more in line with your head (up and down). An axe is also coming, which looked extremely well made. What I can show you are the colourful Ti spoons - which makes identifying your spoon on the next UL meet-up a bit easier. If you have your Ti pan with you then you will like the spatula - which can be snapped to your spoon, for an extra long handle so you can’t burn your fingers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9393513199/" title="SnowPeak Spork &amp; Spatula by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5545/9393513199_7d48132734_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="SnowPeak Spork &amp; Spatula" /></a></p>

<h2 id="norrna">Norrøna</h2>

<p>The Norwegians from <a href="http://www.norrona.com/">Norrøna</a> had a fine line at their booth, and the most interesting pieces for the active mountaineer and backpacker will be from the falketind line, like the PrimaLoft60 jacket, which weighs 280 g, has a full zip, packs small and uses PrimaLoft 60 to keep you warm. The falketind flex1 pants are a 200 g (!) softshell pants, which are very breathable and offer superb freedom of movement. Zippered pockets, mountaineering fit and a DWR finish will surely make this a good pants to wear in the mountains. And then there’s the falketind warm1 Hoodie, which is made from a recycled Polartec fleece fabric. A kangaroo pocket lets you store stuff, wrist gaiters help keep your hands warm and the hood looks rather good, too. </p>

<p><strong>Stay tuned for my OutDoor 2013 conclusions article.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News III]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-iii.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-29T03:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-iii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With over 900 exhibitors, there’s plenty more new gear to come!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361759867/" title="Grüezi bag booth by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3816/9361759867_78598055ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Grüezi bag booth" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="swiss-advance">Swiss Advance</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.swiss-advance.com/">Swiss Advance</a> Pocket Knife weighs 38 g and you can take it inside an airplane cabin, as I tested on the flight home. It surprised me a bit - the knife is hellishly sharp and the Bradawl looks also like something that could hurt, but the security personal in Zürich was more concerned that the bottle opener might not be adequate. It’s a versatile tool with 15 functions, something that can easily come along on a hiking or cycling weekend trip.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305319017/" title="Wenger Multitool by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3781/9305319017_a590ace1ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wenger Multitool" /></a></p>

<h2 id="silva">Silva</h2>

<p>The Swedes had many different items on their booth, but the flask looked very interesting to me (soon it’s winter again). Double stainless steel design, the cup has a rubber outer for easy holding and sizes from 0,35 to 0,75 l. No idea on weights, but they felt light-ish.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305323559/" title="Silva Flasks by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3691/9305323559_febaa7aafd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Silva Flasks" /></a></p>

<h2 id="optimus">Optimus</h2>

<p>Visiting <a href="http://www.optimusstoves.com/">Optimus</a> is always nice. After all they made the Svea stove and the Optimus Crux, which looks like the USS Enterprise when folded (consider it entertainment on starry nights). The Crux Lite Piezo is their newest stove, which, as the name suggests, a Piezo ignition. For people who like to forget their lighter and matches at home, a god-send. The Elektra FE system now comes with a wind shield and a canister foot, including the Crux Lite Piezo, and makes the whole system more fuel efficient and faster to start. It’s a good, compact system which surely will find a lot of friends.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364629400/" title="Optimus Elektra FE Cook System by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2838/9364629400_f93ca939ce_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Optimus Elektra FE Cook System" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361854355/" title="Optimus Elektra FE Cook System by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7443/9361854355_ec066c3488_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Optimus Elektra FE Cook System" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364630844/" title="Optimus Elektra FE Cook System by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/9364630844_3abe9349fd_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Optimus Elektra FE Cook System" /></a></p>

<h2 id="adidas">Adidas</h2>

<p>Adidas, after buying 5.10 last year, has now access to that companies Stealth Rubber. It has been used in a number of new approach shoes from Adidas, and the terrex swift r and terrex swift r gtx looked like decent shoes with a good profile. A big player bringing out good shoes is always good, as it allows a wide audience to try &amp; buy the shoes in physical stores, slowly transitioning the boot wearing public to lightweight footwear!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297480516/" title="Adidas terrex swift r by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/9297480516_cfc8ffab62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Adidas terrex swift r" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297479726/" title="Adidas terrex swift r gtx by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5476/9297479726_ec37fba6b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Adidas terrex swift r gtx" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294702627/" title="Adidas terrex swift r by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3717/9294702627_40ac4fe52e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Adidas terrex swift r" /></a></p>

<h2 id="power-traveller">power traveller</h2>

<p>Staying charged on the trail is something that most everyone who carries his smartphone into the wilderness is thinking about. <a href="https://www.powertraveller.com/">power traveller</a> is the first company whose products I have used who actually are able to charge an iPhone on the trail. The PowerMonkey Explorer is 171 g and the PowerMonkey Extreme is 456 g - both will keep your smartphone (and the latter also will keep your iPad and DSLR, as well as a host of other gadgets) charged when you’re far away from the next power outlet. Expect a review on the PowerMonkey Extreme in the near future.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9308112358/" title="power traveller PowerMonkey Explorer by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7309/9308112358_047277381c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="power traveller PowerMonkey Explorer" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305327775/" title="power traveller PowerMonkey Extreme by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7387/9305327775_e4073bd21a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="power traveller PowerMonkey Extreme" /></a></p>

<h2 id="pajak">Pajak</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.pro.pajaksport.com/">Pajak</a> is a Polish company which already since 30 years produces high quality down products and backpacks. The XC3 is their UL backpack (weighing in at 780 g), which uses siliconized Cordura to make it waterproof and durable. A waterproof zipper on the side lets you access gear quickly. 42 l volume and a good looking carrying system, you’ll read more about this pack here in the future.</p>

<p>Their down garments are very well made, using Polish down from ethical sources, and their Tyvek sleeping bag allows you to leave your bivy at home. And yes, it can be printed upon, so you even could have your map printed on it =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361719679/" title="Pajak XC3 backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3729/9361719679_ababf5b89b_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Pajak XC3 backpack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361738841/" title="Pajak down garments by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2857/9361738841_606280793b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Pajak down garments" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361732117/" title="Pajak Tyvek sleeping bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/9361732117_7081fa97d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Pajak Tyvek sleeping bag" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-omm">The OMM</h2>

<p>I was very excited to meet the guys at <a href="http://www.theomm.co.uk/">The OMM</a>. Not only do they have a great event, they also make superb garments for fell &amp; trailrunners (and backpackers). The Aether Smock and Jacket use the latest eVent 3L fabric, and weigh in at just 200 g and 245 g respectively. Great cuts and colours, with thumbloops and an internal pocket on the Smock and two welded pockets on the jacket, these should proof to be very popular when they hit the stores.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364527972/" title="The OMM Aether Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3813/9364527972_d24ddd8067_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The OMM Aether Jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364522828/" title="The OMM Aether Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3693/9364522828_a0a8727fa5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The OMM Aether Jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361755937/" title="The OMM Aether Smock by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7441/9361755937_4d0e234ef1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="The OMM Aether Smock" /></a></p>

<p>Also very popular will be the Sonic Smock, their windshirt which comes in at 52 g. It uses a fabric called Point Zero, comes with thumbloops, reflective details and packs into its collar pocket. Yes, yes, it will be popular.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361752909/" title="071313_9424 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3722/9361752909_ce1a235a75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071313_9424" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361753949/" title="The OMM Sonic Smock by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3791/9361753949_98a6922937_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The OMM Sonic Smock" /></a></p>

<h2 id="grezi-bags">Grüezi bags</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.gz-bag.de/en/">Grüezi bags</a> hails from Bavaria and make sleeping bags with a twist. Not lightweight, but if you go camping with the family it may be a bit heavier and more comfortable =) Their kids model grows with your little one, and should suit them from 100 to 155 cm tall. Add in that it comes in various nice colours and you’ll see that sleeping outside will soon be your offspring’s new favourite past time!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361758053/" title="Grüezi bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7285/9361758053_f38bdeae5c_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Grüezi bag" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364537164/" title="Grüezi bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/9364537164_7c5b5632db_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Grüezi bag" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab">Rab</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.rab.uk.com/">Rab</a> has a fantastic new line for 2014, and there is plenty of gear which will have you start saving your €s. Backpacks are the big news at Rab. Yes, backpacks. Those things we carry on our backs, where you put gear in. Rab’s mother company also owns <a href="http://www.podsacs.com/">PodSacs</a> and <a href="http://www.lowealpine.com/">Lowe Alpine</a> so has access to a lot of knowledge when it comes to rucksacks, and hence their new packs should be rather good. The Alpine 55 pack is something for climbers and mountaineers, a nice streamlined pack which carries your climbing gear, is durable and has an extendable lid. At 1600 g it’s a bit heavy, but can be stripped don to 900 g. </p>

<p>The Dynamo 35 is a 940 g, 35 l volume top loader, which carries your ice axe or trekking poles, has hipbelt pockets and stretch side pockets. It compresses nicely, and will be very durable thanks to the used Robic™ fabric.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361812081/" title="Rab Super Alpine 53 backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5463/9361812081_d0cc97f99b_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Super Alpine 53 backpack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364589042/" title="Rab Dynamo 35 backpack"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3736/9364589042_befb951a0d_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Dynamo 35 backpack" /></a></p>

<p>Sleeping bags is what Rab started out with over 30 years ago, so they have quite a bit of knowledge in that area. The down sleeping bags will be using hydrophobic down from next year on, which uses Nikwax technology (which is Fluocarbon free!). Down bags have become lighter and smaller in pack size without losing any warmth, so if you’re a down sleeping bag user this will have you very excited! The synthetic bags from the Ignition series use a material called Pyrotec which has a good warmth to weight ratio. The lightest synthetic bag is 1050 g and keeps you warm till 5°C. Good stuff!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361792361/" title="071313_9453 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2842/9361792361_1d3f817247_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071313_9453" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364577308/" title="Rab Ignition sleeping bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5495/9364577308_7ccc39aea2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab Ignition sleeping bag" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364573720/" title="Rab Ignition sleeping bag packed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3701/9364573720_cc34abe172_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab Ignition sleeping bag packed" /></a></p>

<p>Garments is what we all love from Rab. The 375 g Newton jacket (build for Mr. <a href="http://thunderinthenight.blogspot.com/">Newton</a>) is a 3 Layer eVent jacket with a helmet compatible hood, two zip pockets and Velcro cuffs. Kiwi green is a rather sweet colour, too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361767419/" title="Rab Newton jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5329/9361767419_03686d744c_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Newton jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Myriad jacket is Rab’s newest NeoShell jacket and already available in stores. This 410 g jacket comes with a climbing/ mountaineering feature set - high pockets, helmet compatible hood with wired peak, and an internal pocket. The Atmos jacket comes out in 2014 again, and uses Pertex Shield+ in a 3L version. At 300 g with a minimal helmet compatible hood and high pockets this is a nice lightweight jacket which you can carry with you in case of bad weather.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364546204/" title="Rab Myriad jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7289/9364546204_edb10cb7ac_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Myriad jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364547360/" title="Rab Atmos jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3827/9364547360_f7cf6a3f1f_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Atmos jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Ventus Pull-On uses Matrix SWS fabric with a Polygiene treatment to keep away the smell, has a deep chest zipper and a pocket. Thumbloops and a slim fit for 250 g could make this a popular midlayer.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364552472/" title="Rab Ventus Pull-On by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3728/9364552472_92a9014dcf_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Ventus Pull-On" /></a></p>

<p>The Rab Vector are a softshell pants which use the Matrix DWS fabric. Articulated knees allow for freedom of movement, zippered pockets keep your stuff from falling out, and at 450 g its also a good weight. The webbing belt is a good design, you actually can adjust the tightness in this design and store the excess length away. The Award for the most comfy looking trousers goes to the Capstone pants, though. It’s a poly-cotton pant designed for bouldering and climbing and does look stylish enough to wear to the office, allowing you to hit the crag right afterwards. Rock climbers will also find the Torque pants  with its articulated and reinforced knees of interest, which is made of the Matrix DWS fabric. Zippered pockets keep your phone, wallet and keys from falling out high up, while the wicking waistband will feel comfortable also on warm days.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361777507/" title="Rab Vector pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7357/9361777507_ddbec1a939_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Vector pants" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364561732/" title="Rab Capstone pant by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3743/9364561732_cbf126847e_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Capstone pant" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361779179/" title="Rab Torque pant by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7412/9361779179_c6036b25b1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Rab Torque pant" /></a></p>

<h2 id="msr">MSR</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/msr">MSR</a> is well known for driving innovation forward, and making great designs. Their Hubba Hubba NX is no exception to this, and at 1,72 kg trail weight is a truly lightweight shelter for two. Two doors and two vestibules allow each inhabitant to come and go as they like, and large vents which stay take care of the ventilation. It’s free-standing, though two pegs for the door are recommended. The new colour is rather stealth, too - you shouldn’t have problems pitching it on the JMT!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364590166/" title="MSR Hubba Hubba NX by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5498/9364590166_7c7ee0b1d2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="MSR Hubba Hubba NX" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364601706/" title="MSR Hubba Hubba NX by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7351/9364601706_3d36c9f401_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="MSR Hubba Hubba NX" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364602666/" title="MSR Hubba Hubba NX by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7322/9364602666_b951e5b214_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="MSR Hubba Hubba NX" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361827571/" title="MSR Hubba Hubba NX by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7411/9361827571_dd78328e04_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="MSR Hubba Hubba NX" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364600838/" title="MSR Hubba Hubba NX packed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7343/9364600838_846e6c8a99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="MSR Hubba Hubba NX packed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="la-sportiva">La Sportiva</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.lasportiva.it/val-di-fiemme-trentino.html">La Sportiva</a> had a whole host of very nice news available on their booth. What I liked most was certainly the fresh amount of colours - their shoes, be it trailrunning, approach, casual or climbing - come in great colours, and the materials used are top notch. Their apparel line too was super nice, and I’m sure there will be many companies which will take inspiration from them in the next years.</p>

<p>The Trango Cube won an Gold Outdoor Industry Award, and this lightweight, 675 g boot indeed did look pretty fantastic. It uses Thermo Tech injection technology on the outer, which makes it highly waterproof and also keeps the lacing hooks in place, and a Gore Tex Performance Comfort membrane on the inside makes sure sweat goes out. At 675 g a boot it is at the moment the lightest technical boot for mountaineering and climbing. Sweet.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364607458/" title="Trango Cube Gore Tex by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5346/9364607458_15bd25a9bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Trango Cube Gore Tex" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364609962/" title="Nepal Cube GTX by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3783/9364609962_c916ccb260_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Nepal Cube GTX" /></a></p>

<p>That’s the mountaineering boots out of the way, onwards to trailrunning thus. The La Sportiva Bushido is a trailrunning shoe for 2014 and comes with a pretty sweet profile, 6 mm heel-to-toe drop, and should weigh just 278 g per shoe. The Mix is an approach shoe, </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364620670/" title="La Sportiva Bushido by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2851/9364620670_64cdabb487_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="La Sportiva Bushido" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361845719/" title="La Sportiva Bushido by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3736/9361845719_d8b72a84ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="La Sportiva Bushido" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364616842/" title="La Sportiva Mix by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7285/9364616842_0d5d0fc22e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="La Sportiva Mix" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364617838/" title="La Sportiva Mix by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7422/9364617838_a8bc0d17ae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="La Sportiva Mix" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361846565/" title="071313_9479 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5478/9361846565_0565c41606_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071313_9479" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361847563/" title="071313_9480 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2839/9361847563_1388c8ca60_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071313_9480" /></a></p>

<p>The Solution climbing shoe is machine washable and should be of very high interest for climbing gyms and people who hate smelly climbing shoes. They XsGrip2 soles and a Velcro closure and could mean that in the future you no longer need to slip into sweaty, smelly rental shoes at the climbing wall when you forgot your own shoes!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361834729/" title="La Sportiva Women's Solution by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7376/9361834729_3528d668c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="La Sportiva Women's Solution" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9364613364/" title="La Sportiva Women's Solution by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3774/9364613364_b00dd2a3b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="La Sportiva Women's Solution" /></a></p>

<p>I don’t remember the name of these flip-flops, but they’re super cool with a Frixion sole which should offer good grip on the trail and in the city. They make me feel like going on a holiday in the south, too - which with the rain we currently have here certainly would be welcome!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361842871/" title="071313_9475 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7451/9361842871_96e81e0190_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071313_9475" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9361843861/" title="071313_9476 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3704/9361843861_172fed296f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071313_9476" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-24T02:04:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More news from the world’s biggest outdoor fair, the OutDoor in Friedrichshafen.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9308085754/" title="Haglöfs"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7379/9308085754_cc8d9881db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Haglöfs" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="berghaus">Berghaus</h2>

<p>The highlights at <a href="http://store.berghaus.com/">Berghaus</a> were the Vapour Light Hyper Smock and the Vapour Light Hyper Therm, two very lightweight garments which will make Ultralight Backpackers very happy. The Hyper Smock is a 110 g (Size L) waterproof (!) jacket. It packs tiny, has a deep zipper for venting, an adjustable hood, elastic cuffs and a sleeve pocket. With current waterproof jackets weighing in at 200+ gram and more, this is in the UL realm quite a substantial weight saving. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9304754629/" title="Vapour Light Hyper Smock"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7375/9304754629_1a413d1bc1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Vapour Light Hyper Smock" /></a></p>

<p>The Vapour Light Hyper Therm could be considered an updated, lighter and better Infinity Smock, the very popular Berghaus insulation garment. The Hyper Therm is a reversible jacket - one side is for warmer weather, and one for cooler temperatures. Full zip, elastic cuffs, no hood, a very minimalistic insulation garment that adapts to the conditions. A highly air permeable fabric allows air to circulate through the insulation for cooling on the one side, while a wind-resistant outer shell keeps wind out and heat in but allows perspiration to escape. Should weigh about 167 g.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307539194/" title="Vapour Light Hyper Therm"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7361/9307539194_8a1ddea6e3_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Vapour Light Hyper Therm" /></a></p>

<p>The Hyper 22 Rucksack is a minimalist backpack with large mesh pockets on the side and front, a zip opening, and a carrying system similar to the Octans backpack. It looked like a good, simple design which could become a popular entry UL backpack. There’s going to be a 37 l version with a lid, as well as a bunch of other really good looking gear for trail running, alpine endeavours and hiking.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9304760473/" title="Hyper 22 Rucksack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7401/9304760473_b9c9a65735_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Hyper 22 Rucksack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="outdry">OutDry</h2>

<p>I visited OutDry, who make in my opinion one of the best membranes on the market. My <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html">Scarpa Phantom Ultra</a> have OutDry, and it’s a superb material. OutDry is directly laminated to the upper and is not just another layer of material which means the water can not penetrate and stay in the glove/ shoe as it can with other membranes. More and more companies start to use OutDry, which is great for us consumers. One of the latest innovations is a Mountain Hardwear backpack which uses OutDry - this makes it virtually completely waterproof and thus will be of interest for those who are a lot outdoors in the rain or go packrafting. Also the Montrail Bajada trail running shoe uses OutDry, so I think we’ll soon hear more about this technology in UL circles.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307562076/" title="071213_7207 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7300/9307562076_12e2172c1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_7207" /></a></p>

<h2 id="scarpa">Scarpa</h2>

<p><a href="http://en.scarpa.net/">Scarpa</a> is finally again available in Finland! You already can get their superb climbing shoes and mountaineering boots in various shops (Prisma Tampere!) so if you have waited for your chance to try on a pair of Phantom Ultra boots or Feroce climbing shoes, now you have the chance!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9358401807/" title="IGNITE by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5346/9358401807_4d228debb4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="787" alt="IGNITE" /></a></p>

<p>New from Scarpa this year is the Ignite, a trailrunning shoe which weighs 610 g for the pair in Size 42,5. An 8 mm drop adds some cushioning, and an EVA midsole protects your foot from roots and rocks on the trail. Ueli Steck uses these shoes (he just finished the Eiger Ultra!) so expect them to be good.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9358357925/" title="INSTINCT VS BLACK by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7410/9358357925_150d99b239_b.jpg" width="1024" height="904" alt="INSTINCT VS BLACK" /></a></p>

<p>The Instinct VS Black weighs 400 g for the pair in Size 40,5. A XS grip2 3.5 mm sole adds grip on difficult routes, and they’re recommended for bouldering, indoors and sport climbing. </p>

<p>Also mountaineers and traditional backpackers will be like the new shoes from Scarpa, be it the MONT BLANC GTX PRO for technical mountain adventures or the MONT BLANC GTX PRO PRO GTX which is a classical trekking boot, or the ZEN PRO and ZEN PRO GTX which are approach shoes which have a COCONA® lining.</p>

<h2 id="sherpa-adventure-gear">Sherpa Adventure Gear</h2>

<p>I have been reading during the last 12 months more and more about Sherpa Adventure Gear and so was excited to meet them in Friedrichshafen. The company was founded by Tashi Sherpa in 2003, produces 95% of the garments in Nepal, reinvests much of the profits in the region into schools, hospitals et al. and hence is a model company if it comes to Corporate Social Responsibility. But not only the history and social record of the company is fascinating, also their garments are top notch. Great waterproofs and insulation jackets, wonderful colours, good cuts and attention to details and also a superb looking female line, this is a company you definitely should check out if high quality and a great CSR record is important for you.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305170667/" title="071213_9560 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5473/9305170667_a9ba0e6d6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9560" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305164205/" title="071213_9556 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2891/9305164205_98c862ffa4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9556" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307950420/" title="071213_9558 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7323/9307950420_562ea16d8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9558" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307960818/" title="071213_9562 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7350/9307960818_ea49733031_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="071213_9562" /></a></p>

<h2 id="haglfs">Haglöfs</h2>

<p>Haglöfs has re-vamped the LIM - Less Is More - line and there’s a host of interesting garments coming from them, all in fresh colours and many bluesign certified. The Essens Jacket for example is a 185 down jacket. They also bring out trailrunning shoes, which use ASICS’ knowledge in making shoes (Haglöfs is owned by ASICS) and did look very nice. The lightest shoe was 195 gram and had a aggressive profile, thus should have good grip on trails. Also other lines employed a LIM approach, and designs were minimized but kept their function and good designs.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305177433/" title="071213_9563 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5331/9305177433_e446e54443_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9563" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307962926/" title="071213_9564 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3669/9307962926_e605f3f48b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9564" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305179731/" title="071213_9565 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7454/9305179731_de200d4110_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="071213_9565" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305187857/" title="071213_9567 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7444/9305187857_7e80a2c51b_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="071213_9567" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307973846/" title="071213_9568 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7352/9307973846_d459700980_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9568" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307997472/" title="071213_9582 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2883/9307997472_29abfde5da_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="071213_9582" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305316413/" title="071213_9578 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2822/9305316413_198ee070f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9578" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305307231/" title="071213_9577 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7329/9305307231_2909902a8d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9577" /></a></p>

<p>The sleeping bag line was completely overhauled, too. The top of the line bag employs a zipper similar to the GoLite Adrenaline now, but looks better made and warmer. The Indus syntethic blanket is 200 x 130 cm and uses Pertex Quantum as a shell, and is interesting for those who want a syntetic quilt. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305199769/" title="071213_9573 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3696/9305199769_c20d5b8f4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9573" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305299657/" title="071213_9572 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3730/9305299657_25eea1213e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9572" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305206419/" title="071213_9580 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3694/9305206419_297af2012c_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="071213_9580" /></a></p>

<h2 id="inov-8">Inov-8</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.inov-8.com/new/">Inov-8</a> comes out with some very cool products for fell and trail runners. The backpack comes with a 2 l, insulated reservoir and two 500 ml bottles, and if you take everything out will lay completely flat on your body - no annoying straps, pockets or anything else to hinder you while running. This happens because of elastic mesh pockets (they will also hold other bottles than the provided ones). It’s a One-Size-Fits-All design that can be adjusted in multiple ways to fit you, and a few additional mesh pockets will hold power gels, shots, and small items. The UltraRace Hand pouch holds an flexible 250 ml bottle for on the run, and in the mesh pocket you also can fit a energy gel or your keys. Quick hydration on the go, this could also be of interest for hikers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307998658/" title="071213_9584 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2848/9307998658_60b91f5da6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9584" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305219315/" title="071213_9585 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3762/9305219315_4479fb5b78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9585" /></a></p>

<p>The shoes coming from Inov-8 are obviously of the most interest. Classics like the much-loved <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/07/inov-8-x-talon-190.html">X-Talon 190</a> is re-vamped and comes now in orange with a much more durable mesh upper, while still being so wonderfully light. It also comes with more of a toe box, so should be quite a bit more durable. The TrailRoc 165 is the Barefoot trailrunning shoe which had me really excited. It sports the triple design sole which uses different materials in different areas for improved grip and durability. The TrailRoc 245 has a bit more cushioning, and the TrailRoc 255 will have you walk on clouds. All in all a really great line-up in fantastic colours. Oh, and the ROCLITE™ 286 GTX returns. Rejoice for the lightest boot available!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305226153/" title="071213_9587 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3830/9305226153_8fca61bb51_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9587" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9308012682/" title="071213_9588 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2863/9308012682_f22be4019f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9588" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9308036394/" title="071213_9591 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5456/9308036394_8d27aaefc8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9591" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305271651/" title="071213_9594 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5520/9305271651_8649b00421_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9594" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9308061412/" title="071213_9595 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7456/9308061412_27987724d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9595" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305259989/" title="071213_9593 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3739/9305259989_ce7bd3e0ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_9593" /></a></p>

<h2 id="drytech-real-turmat">Drytech | Real Turmat</h2>

<p>The Norwegians from <a href="http://drytech.no/index.php/en/">Drytech</a> have a new taste in their line up - Kebab casserole - and also added soups (Meat Soup) a while ago to their offerings. I haven’t tried it yet but am sure they will be as tasty as the other meals from them. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9358468649/" title="Real Turmat by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3833/9358468649_52093206b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Real Turmat" /></a></p>

<h2 id="crux">Crux</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.crux.uk.com/en/index.php">Crux</a> won an OutDoor Award for their X1 Strike shelter. This is a highly breathable mountain tent for two and gear, and I can imagine this shelter become very popular among ultralight backpackers who venture out in winter and high altitudes. The design is stormproof - Carol, the owner of Crux and Lightwave, regularly tests his designs in the New Zealand Alps and Himalayas - and can be attached to a belay via the hoop at the roof, so if you’re looking for something to pitch on an exposed ledge, this could be it. It also should be a super breathable shelter, employing a carbon coated fabric which drives moisture through to the outside. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9304783551/" title="071213_7210 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7346/9304783551_216896734d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_7210" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9307567550/" title="071213_7211 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7428/9307567550_64513d4428_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071213_7211" /></a></p>

<h2 id="powertrekk">PowerTrekk</h2>

<p><a href="http://powertrekk.com/">PowerTrekk</a> finally has made it to market! I have followed this company from Sweden for the last two years, and am happy to see that their charger is now available to buy. The system has three parts: The green “top” which also has a battery which you can charge at home, the black “bottom” where is a water tank and opening for the hydrogen “puck”. The pucks are replaceable and work a bit like coffee machines which use those pods - you put the pod into the bottom, connect it to the top and then close it. Then you attach your gadget which will be charged. It didn’t feel too light, but if you go outdoors and need to keep your smartphone, etc. charged this might be a very good solution. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9305326495/" title="071113_7280 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3702/9305326495_cf794be771_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="071113_7280" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-i.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-16T02:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-i</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I surprised myself and a bunch of friends by going to the OutDoor Fair in Friedrichshafen this year. Here’s some news from my first day at the fair.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297083380/" title="Brands &amp; Booths by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3796/9297083380_dba402267f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Brands &amp; Booths" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>As always, hover with your cursor over the photo to see the description.</em></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx">Arc’teryx</h2>

<p>The Canadian brand is at the top of their game, making arguably some of the best garments for outdoor enthusiasts. If you’re into alpine stuff, be it fast &amp; light ascents, ice climbing or mountaineering, then the Alpha FL Jacket will be of interest. A 310 g Gore-Tex Pro jacket (Size M) which is cut in a such a way that it only has 7 m of seams (usually a jacket has 14+ m of seams, which means more seam tape, which means more weight) is quite something. One chest pocket, Storm Hood, hip-length cut in a trim fit = cut down to the minimum for fast &amp; light activities where durability is important.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294350087/" title="Arc'teryx Alpha FL Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3792/9294350087_3b0860167d_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Arc'teryx Alpha FL Jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294351153/" title="Arc'teryx Alpha FL Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5483/9294351153_b7222c5b18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arc'teryx Alpha FL Jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294352155/" title="Arc'teryx Alpha FL Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2885/9294352155_c4216c8f40_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arc'teryx Alpha FL Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>Like-wise for climbing fast &amp; light are the Alpha FL packs. 610 g for the 30 l version, 680 g for the 45 l version - and superb prices: 150€ the small one, 170€ the bigger one. It uses a N400r-AC2 Nylon 6 ripstop fabric, which can be taped making for a waterproof construction - and while it sports a drawcord closure, underneath that is the extendable RollTop closure which works like a waterproof packsack. A very simple and minimalistic pack which also will work great for backpacking in wet environments as well as packrafting.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297132130/" title="Arc'teryx Alpha FL backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2829/9297132130_f4712118c5_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Arc'teryx Alpha FL backpack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294357733/" title="Arc'teryx Alpha FL backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7310/9294357733_1242009baf_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Arc'teryx Alpha FL backpack" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297137700/" title="Arc'teryx Alpha FL backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3706/9297137700_e62a17c414_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Arc'teryx Alpha FL backpack" /></a></p>

<p>Lots of companies make Duffles, but Arc’teryx makes them really waterproof - and light: The 100 l version weighs 680 g - half what comparable sizes duffles weigh. It can be worn as a backpack or over the shoulder for easy carrying, and straps can be packed away when they go into a plane, while four grab handles make these easy to strap on a camel for your next desert trek. I want one.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297127802/" title="Duffles from Arc'teryx"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7292/9297127802_b090e4f894_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Duffles from Arc'teryx" /></a></p>

<p>The Endorphine Line is the trailrunning/ jogging Line, and includes the fantastic Sarix Short Sleeve Shirt &amp; Soleus Shorts which I have been wearing on my trail runs and backpacking trips in the last weeks. These have superb cuts and details, and are surely going to be very popular among those who like to go a bit faster and longer on their “hikes”. The 24 Line on the other hand is for those of us who appreciate technical and smart cuts in their everyday garments. Interesting for cyclists will be the A2B Commuter Pant and Jacket which come with cycling specific cuts and details. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294356657/" title="Arc'teryx Endorphin Line by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7368/9294356657_9b02dc4d3c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arc'teryx Endorphin Line" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294355629/" title="Arc'teryx 24 Line by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5485/9294355629_7b822e2d68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arc'teryx 24 Line" /></a></p>

<h2 id="salewa">Salewa</h2>

<p>The Salewa Capsico can be transformed from a comfy shoe into a sandal in seconds. It’s very meshy and should dry quickly, which could make it a good shoe for packrafting or those who like to have camp shoes. It’s intended purpose is a ápres-climbing shoe, so it will work good for belaying, too. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297463424/" title="Salewa Capsico shoes by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7443/9297463424_95e4d51f65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Salewa Capsico shoes" /></a></p>

<p>The Via Ferrata Vario harness is light (under 300 g) and packs very small, so could be of interest to those who have a few via ferrata sections on their hikes in the Alps and like to save weight.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294693309/" title="Salewa Via Ferrata Vario harness by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5344/9294693309_5f24b2dcd3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Salewa Via Ferrata Vario harness" /></a></p>

<h2 id="petzl">Petzl</h2>

<p>The big news at Petzl are ropes. Made in cooperation with Edelrid. Single ropes and Twin/ Half-Ropes. Competitively priced. This will be very interesting, and weighs et al. will follow when I have them. The handling is great from what I tried at the fair, and they come with various different treatments.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297320484/" title="Petzl Ropes by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7420/9297320484_3fc800b79a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Ropes" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294543337/" title="Petzl Ropes by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5341/9294543337_b9fd8276ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Ropes" /></a></p>

<p>The Meteor Helmet got a new, simple to use closure system and a few new colours. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294545633/" title="Petzl Meteor Helmets by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7450/9294545633_c7f96d0b7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Meteor Helmets" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297322522/" title="Petzl Meteor Helmet closure by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3708/9297322522_0f4387763d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Meteor Helmet closure" /></a></p>

<p>The Petzl Spirit is back! Lighter with better breaking load values, this surely will be a very popular ‘biner.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297324868/" title="Petzl Spirit by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7330/9297324868_809013c81d_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Petzl Spirit" /></a></p>

<p>Headlamps are now divided into three segments and have experienced a few re-designs. The Tikka RXP makes use of the Nao’s Sensor Technology which automatically adjusts the light output depending on where you watch and so increases battery life. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297326032/" title="Petzl Tikka by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7427/9297326032_af7fc778f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Tikka" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294551035/" title="Petzl Tikka R+ by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3667/9294551035_d5f9b1fa4f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Tikka R+" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294550005/" title="Petzl Tikka RXP by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5335/9294550005_316c99fd38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Tikka RXP" /></a></p>

<h2 id="evernew">Evernew</h2>

<p>Evernew’s collapsible bottles are now available in Europe, as will be much of their Ti Pots. The newest UL pots come with red lettering and red handles, so that are the ones you want.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297472748/" title="Evernew collapsible bottle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7409/9297472748_630cf150fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Evernew collapsible bottle" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297473600/" title="Evernew Ti Pots by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2892/9297473600_b796b92ce4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Evernew Ti Pots" /></a></p>

<h2 id="pronto-caf">Pronto Café</h2>

<p>A wonderful find is <a href="http://prontocafe.eu/de/">Pronto Café</a> who make real brew coffee which weighs a fantastic 8 g for everything! The filter includes very tasty Arabica coffee, which is roasted in Italy and then 24 hours later packed in Switzerland. A shelf life of at least 12 months and a really good taste will surely make this very popular amongst coffee lovers. Immediately available from <a href="http://prontocafe.eu/de/">Pronto Café</a> and <a href="http://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/">Outdoor Food Shop</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294569935/" title="Pronto Café by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5518/9294569935_1f2e3214fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pronto Café" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294570851/" title="Pronto Café by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3734/9294570851_60ebfdb3f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pronto Café" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294571713/" title="Pronto Café by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7283/9294571713_3bae389c04_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pronto Café" /></a></p>

<h2 id="mammut">Mammut</h2>

<p>Mammut Ultimate Alpine Hoody and the Mammut Ultimate Hoody are softshell jackets. They have been re-designed, and the Alpine version is specifically made for climbing as it has harness compatible pockets et al. No info on weights, but looked to be in the medium weight category.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294707983/" title="Mammut Ultimate Alpine Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2892/9294707983_17fe6dc366_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Mammut Ultimate Alpine Hoody" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294707189/" title="Mammut Ultimate Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7337/9294707189_12f06dc6ff_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Mammut Ultimate Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>The Rainspeed jacket is a 175 g light waterproof jacket, with a hydrostatic head of 10.000 mm. It’s from the Mammut Performance Line, which is aimed at Trailrunning and similar high-output activities.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294704689/" title="Mammut Rainspeed Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3669/9294704689_ff3f7173a7_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Mammut Rainspeed Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Realization pants is the long version of the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-realization-shorts-short-klettergurt/">Realization Shorts</a>. It’s a pants with an integrated harness, two gear loops and a loop for your chalk bag. They should be very comfortable and if you consider that you safe an extra harness there’s also some good weight savings. Oh, and they feel and look great, too!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9301318074/" title="Mammut Realization Pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/9301318074_de5462b92f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mammut Realization Pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research">Outdoor Research</h2>

<p>Plenty of very cool, thought-through garments coming from OR this &amp; next season. The Helium Hybrid is a very light Pertex jacket with reinforced shoulders, so you can wear it with a backpack on.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294710757/" title="Outdoor Research Helium Hybrid by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3722/9294710757_27af949723_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Helium Hybrid" /></a></p>

<p>Very cool are the Hot Pursuit Wrist Warmers, which are a pair of wrist warmers which transform into mitts when the temperatures drop. 36 g (I think that’s for the pair, will need to check), breathable, reflective details - this could be very popular with runners.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297496900/" title="Outdoor Research Hot Pursuit Wrist Warmers by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2871/9297496900_090715002f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Outdoor Research Hot Pursuit Wrist Warmers" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297497794/" title="Outdoor Research Hot Pursuit Wrist Warmers by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5504/9297497794_2cb62c2b0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Outdoor Research Hot Pursuit Wrist Warmers" /></a></p>

<p>The Hot Pursuit gloves are 50 g (again, I think that’s for the pair, will confirm), and these are for a bit cooler temps. The gloves can operate your smartphone, have a nose wipe, reflective details and transform in seconds into a lobster mitt if it gets too cold. I can see these as very useful for hiking in shoulder season.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297494640/" title="Outdoor Research Hot Pursuit gloves"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2850/9297494640_5877eac0f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Outdoor Research Hot Pursuit gloves" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9294716839/" title="Outdoor Research Hot Pursuit gloves"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3831/9294716839_386d04f28c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Outdoor Research Hot Pursuit gloves" /></a></p>

<p>The Sparkplug Gaiter is very minimalistic and shouldn’t be very heavy either. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297493698/" title="Outdoor Research Sparkplug Gaiters by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3688/9297493698_170d54de34_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Sparkplug Gaiters" /></a></p>

<p>It’s hot, or windy, and you don’t want to get your hoody out? Put on a pair of sun sleeves. These are coming with an insect repellant and UPV 50+ so keep the bugs and the nasty UV rays at bay. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297498750/" title="Outdoor Research Sentinel &amp; Spectrum Sun Sleeves by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3708/9297498750_3753596eed_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Sentinel &amp; Spectrum Sun Sleeves" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, also OR is coming out with an urban line. A very simple, but beautiful line coming with various garments, backpacks and duffles will have you look like the outdoorsy guy you are in the office!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9297487692/" title="Outdoor Research by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7328/9297487692_b0cfd8ae6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sea-to-summit">Sea To Summit</h2>

<p>The Australian company makes a lot of interesting gear for ultralight backpackers. There’s going to be </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9301621096/" title="Sea To Summit UL Down Bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3767/9301621096_70625f2f73_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Sea To Summit UL Down Bag" /></a>
very warm and light down sleeping bags</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9298865397/" title="Sea To Summit Tarps by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5548/9298865397_e2c1d28c61_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Sea To Summit Tarps" /></a>
different tarps with inners</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9298886265/" title="Sea To Summit Ultra-Sil Compression DrySacks by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5474/9298886265_8a7ae1875c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sea To Summit Ultra-Sil Compression DrySacks" /></a>
even lighter compression sacks with eVent</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9301686638/" title="Sea To Summit Ultra-Sil Nano Poncho Tarp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3687/9301686638_db2ea66ff1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sea To Summit Ultra-Sil Nano Poncho Tarp" /></a>
a new, lighter poncho-tarp (230 g)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9298941683/" title="Sea To Summit Nano Mosquito Pyramid Net Permethrin by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2869/9298941683_6b687fe942_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sea To Summit Nano Mosquito Pyramid Net Permethrin" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9301704658/" title="Sea To Summit Nano Mosquito Pyramid Net by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7294/9301704658_8931071228_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sea To Summit Nano Mosquito Pyramid Net" /></a>
a swell Permethrin (and untreated) Pyramid Mesh inner which weighs 82 gram</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9298954931/" title="Sea To Summit Nano Headnet by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3811/9298954931_f572200a2f_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Sea To Summit Nano Headnet" /></a>
an even lighter head net</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9301745482/" title="Sea To Summit Field Repair Buckle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3688/9301745482_6249b2524a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sea To Summit Field Repair Buckle" /></a>
Field repair buckles in different sizes. What a superb invention!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9298982645/" title="Sea To Summit UltraSil Dry Daypack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5492/9298982645_88c0c5e6fb_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Sea To Summit UltraSil Dry Daypack" /></a>
The new-ish Ultra-Sil Dry Pack</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9299017251/" title="Sea To Summit Pocket Umbrella by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3690/9299017251_f59bb4e3a4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sea To Summit Pocket Umbrella" /></a>
and a Pocket Umbrella, which is 155 g. All in all a very cool selection.</p>

<h2 id="laufbursche-gear">Laufbursche Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://laufbursche-gear.de/">Laufbursche</a> now offers Evernew pots and the great collapsible bottles as well as Trail Designs stoves. Now you can almost get a complete UL setup at the cottage, as there’s also very good CCF pads and other gear besides the huckePACK and huckePÄCKchen. There’s more coming, too - but it’s still secret =)</p>

<p><a href="http://laufbursche-gear.de/" title="Laufbursche News"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7457/9297450516_3e2915b682_b.jpg" width="960" height="822" alt="Laufbursche News" /></a></p>

<h2 id="more">More</h2>

<p>More coming this and next week. Have a look at <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">Benjamin</a>, <a href="http://ultraknilch.blogspot.fi/2013/07/outdoor-friedrichshafen-2013.html">Markus</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/">Corinna</a>, <a href="http://blog.fastpacking.de/">Carsten</a>, <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/">Sven</a>, <a href="http://www.gipfelblick.org/">Gipfelblick</a>, <a href="http://www.trekking.lu/">Trekking Blog</a> and <a href="http://www.oe-mag.co.uk/">outdoor enthusiast</a> to see their view on the OutDoor 2013. And there’s <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157634659437008/">more photos on Flickr</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
