<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Advent Calendar 2015 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2015/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-01T23:37:35+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/advent-calendar-door-2.html"/>
    <updated>2015-12-02T11:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/advent-calendar-door-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/advent-calendar-door-2.html" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Logo"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/621/22811712953_db8e6346c1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Logo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>watching the sun rise in the mountains - is there anything better? Not really. With the new <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=13582&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.hyperlitemountaingear.com%2Ffeatured-ultralight-packs%2Fdaybreak-pack.html">Daybreak Pack</a> from <a href="http://bit.ly/1QQRFL2">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> I always have all I need along for a day in the hills. It has side pockets for my water bottles, the possibility to attach an ice axe and a back pocket with additional bungees to easily access rain gear or a puffy jacket. Made from Dyneema® Cuben Fiber it takes the abuse of scrambling in the mountains and bushwhacking through the forests, and at 539 g it is so light you can carry it all day long. And if you consider that it’s made in Maine, USA, you know it is a quality piece of gear that is gonna last many, many years!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=13582&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.hyperlitemountaingear.com%2Ffeatured-ultralight-packs%2Fdaybreak-pack.html" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Daybreak"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5664/23412707586_da0385d7a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Daybreak" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="enter">Enter!</h2>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd89558/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd89558" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_rfdbdhur">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="http://hikinginfinland.com//widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/advent-calendar-2015-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The winner can choose the size and the backpack is sent directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1QQRFL2">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a>.</em></p>

<p>Read more about <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/ultralight-summit-daytrippin.html">Day hiking</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/advent-calendar-door-1.html"/>
    <updated>2015-12-01T11:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/advent-calendar-door-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/12/advent-calendar-door-1.html" title="OAC-Logo"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15764883519_e37a8939a1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OAC-Logo" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>with snow on the ground there is no reason to hike or cycle - snow means it is time to ski. And the <a href="http://skinbased.com/5/">WAP 127</a> from <a href="http://www.oacsport.fi">OAC</a> is the perfect tool to ski - from home to the cabin, up the hills and down the slopes. Best thing: I don’t even need to get expensive ski boots, as I can use my normal winter boots thanks to the <a href="http://skinbased.com/10/">OAC EA Binding</a> where I can step in with my winter boots or trailrunners alike and go to the fjells. The patented Unicoat base structure of the WAP 127 allows me to climb steep hills and have great grip on any snow. And at just 1.050 g they’re lighter than many snowshoes - and a lot faster and more fun, too! With these winter will be a lot of fun, so please bring me a pair! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://skinbased.com/5/" title="OAC WAP 127"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/619/23345928911_d49f8d737f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OAC WAP 127" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="enter">Enter</h2>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd89557/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd89557" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_nv648cwg">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="http://hikinginfinland.com//widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/advent-calendar-2015-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The skis and bindings are sent directly from OAC to the winner.</em></p>

<p>Read more about <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">Backcountry skiing</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off.html"/>
    <updated>2015-11-23T23:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <em>“Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off 2015”</em> is open.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22542560793/in/dateposted/" title="Advent Calendar 2015"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5734/22542560793_19e29f4f9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar 2015" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>While I’m Opting to be Outside, sometimes litte things are needed to make them more comfortable. Be that a stove to brew a hot cup of tea or a warm beanie, small things make being outside more fun and pleasurable. The focus, however, is always on being outside, and not the gear. Sure you need it, but it’s not the reason to go out. That is to relax, be inspired, spend times with family &amp; good friends and enjoying the beautiful nature. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16888796258/in/album-72157651506091295/" title="Fatbiking over the mires"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7668/16888796258_73067eb837_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fatbiking over the mires" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With that said, some warm down gear does help to make cold winter hikes more fun. Damn, even sitting in a wooden hut is made better with some down around your feet. The <a href="https://goosefeetgear.com/products/1-down-socks">Down Socks</a> from Goose Feet Gear not only ensure that toes are toasty, they make it possible to dry my trailrunners by the fire so they’re ready for next days hike. And if you have cold feet in your quilt - these Down Socks ensure you wake up with warm feet!</p>

<p>Also <a href="https://www.blackrockgear.com/product/test/">The Original Black Rock Gear Down Beanie</a> is filled with 950 cuin Hungarian Down and ensures a warm head when the wind is blowing in sub-zero temperatures. Hiking with cold ears is so last year, thus a Black Rock Hat is not only keeping the ears warm but also is <em>trés chic</em>! Did I mention it is ultralight? Of course it is!</p>

<p>Feet and head being cared for, that leaves the hands as the third extremities which tend to not like to much snow, wind and cold. And it just so happens that the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=37&amp;products_id=51">Mountain Laurel Designs eVent Mitts</a> are not just excellent to keep the rain of my hands, they also work great in winter! Cold wind and snow won’t trouble you anymore with these ultralight gloves on your hands.</p>

<p>When you do take the gloves off, it often is to boil water for a hot cup of tea. The <a href="https://www.traildesigns.com/stoves/caldera-sidewinder-solo">Caldera Sidewinder Solo</a> is not just a very great stove system, with the 1,1 litre pot you can even boil water for your mates so that everyone has a warm cup of tea! It all packs compactly into the pot and is fuel-efficient, thus a great choice for ultralight outdoor enthusiasts.</p>

<p>That leaves a warm coat for those cold temperatures. Or a toasty pair of trousers. Long underwear. Warm winter shoes. Well, sometimes you’re missing one piece of gear, and that’s where the 50€ Gift Card from <a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/?pid=81/">Bergzeit.co.uk</a> comes in very useful. With it you can save a nice amount of cash on your next big purchase - be that a Merino Baselayer or your new AT skis, Bergzeit.co.uk has it all. </p>

<h2 id="enter">Enter!</h2>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd89556/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd89556" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_7h2g4q0c">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="http://hikinginfinland.com//widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: <a href="">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. All prizes are sent directly from the Sponsor to the winner. The winner can choose the Size &amp; Colour of his Goose Feet Gear Down Socks, pick from a Original Black Rock Hat in either Black, Blue, Red or Green and the Size of her MLD eVent Mitts.</em> </p>

<p>Read more about <a href="">Winter Backpacking</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar 2015 - The Rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/advent-calendar-2015-the-rules.html"/>
    <updated>2015-11-23T10:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/advent-calendar-2015-the-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8230998731/" title="HiF Advent Calendar"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8350/8230998731_e265161b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HiF Advent Calendar Logo" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Welcome again to a new Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar! Like in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2013/">years</a> <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2014/">before</a>, a good set of rules makes running this a lot easier for everyone involved. Read them carefully and everything will be clear, and check out the <strong>tips</strong> at the end!. </p>

<p>This years calendar will run 25 days (= 25 Doors), and behind each door you will find a fine piece of brand-new gear which should make your next outdoor adventure fun and ultralight. Some information on the prizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>All prizes are sent directly from the company providing them. </li>
  <li>Sometimes it is possible that you can choose size, colour and other variables. Where this is the case, it will be mentioned in the text of the Door.</li>
  <li>This means garments can be either female or male, backpacks can be different torso sizes and meals can be vegetarian or with meat. </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-rules">The Rules</h2>

<p>To win something you should check in each day here and enter the raffle. There are a couple of things to keep in mind, though:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You only can win once. If you don’t win one day, you should try your luck the next day - you got 25 chances!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I am using a paid-for version of <a href="https://www.rafflecopter.com/">Rafflecopter</a> for the Give-Aways. With Rafflecopter you can get multiple entries by following someone on Instagram, Twitter, visit a page on Facebook, follow a Pinterest page or susbscribe to a Mailing List. This increases your chances to win, but is not mandatory. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Rafflecopter Widget is integrated with <a href="http://www.random.org/">Random.org</a> and it choses the winner. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Once you won, I contact you via the provided Email address and you have 24 hours to reply. If I don’t hear from you, I imagine you don’t want the item and will let Random.org chose a new winner.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Posts go online in the morning around nine-ish, and the raffles close at midnight - Finnish time. Rafflecopter then will show the name of the winner after I pushed that button, this keeps posts to a minimum.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It is open to everyone. As in from Australia to Zimbabwe, prices are send everywhere (unless noted otherwise).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Possible Import Duty taxes and fees are paid by the winner. If you’re not willing to pay these, don’t compete. </p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>8.. You can’t bribe me or anyone involved to win. You use the item(s) on your own responsibility. Use common sense.</p>

<h2 id="tips">Tips</h2>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You can participate via the Rafflecopter widget by registering with your Email or your Facebook accoount. Please make sure for either option that it’s an Email address you regularly check, so when I contact you you get the email. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There is usually one mandatory option to answer to participate. This can be something fun or a question about the price in question. You should be easily able to answer the question by reading the text or visiting the manufacturer website. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can get additional entries which improve your chances of winning. This could be visiting a Facebook page or following someone on Twitter, Instagram and the like. It’s a good thing to do, and also allows you stay up-to-date with news about the HiF Advent Calendar and the company sponsoring the prize.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you think your friends and fans would like to participate - spread the word! Use the #HifAdventCalendar hashtag on Instagram, Twitter &amp; Facebook when you spread the word =)</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That’s it. The Advent Calendar starts today, the 23rd of November. Subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/105082905705272949032">Google+</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to get an update every time a new door opens.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: All gear is sponsored. I try to not spend all time in front of a screen so relax if a post goes up a tad late or I don’t reply an email asap.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
