<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hiking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/hiking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-01T13:06:14+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking &amp; Scrambling in the Polish Tatras - Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-03T10:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">climbing &amp; mountaineering in the Polish Tatras</a> to hiking and backpacking. In the rain &amp; sunshine, up high in the mountains and low in the valleys.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397717831" title="Focus on the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397717831_9014d3f632_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Focus on the rain" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rain--misery">Rain &amp; Misery</h2>

<p>As we wake up at the <a href="http://www.piecstawow.pl/en/">Przedni Staw Polski Refuge</a> and I look out from my window the mist hides the mountains and the rain drops leave little circles on the lake. Everything is wet. Marcin and I silently get out of bed and move to the big common room, give in our orders for breakfast and enjoy the tasty food that comes through the small window from the kitchen. Slowly it gets busy, people packing, but with the rain keeping up a constant drum on the roof none leave the hut. At ten we’re the first ones to venture outside, curious looks on us in our rain gear, and as Marcin tells where we headed people just look even more confused.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214238360" title="A look back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214238360_3bfa19dbfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin gave me a few options: Walk the easy trail through the valley to the Schronisko Murowaniec refuge, or the shorter but high route across a pass at the end Orla Perć. We had light packs, good gear and so it was easy to make the decision to go via the pass. I either way was a bit disappointed that we didn’t take my original route, but plans are plans: Drawn on paper, dreamed up looking over maps in the warm comfort of home. When the weather turns it’s best to adapt them and stay safe - something I can now say in hindsight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400893955" title="Crossing snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15400893955_db1585c08f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crossing snow" /></a></p>

<p>We walk by the mist-enshrouded lakes, cross the stream via the little bridge and hear the waterfall thunder down towards the valley while we slowly ascend. I carry my camera underneath my jacket so I can keep on making photos, but in the drizzle and thick mist there isn’t much to see. We cross small streams, old snow, and steadily keep on walking uphill. Once in a while the mist has a gap and we can see a bit further - the other side of the valley, further up, down the valley.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397714501" title="Slippery by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/15397714501_32e8d0e031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slippery" /></a></p>

<p>To be able to continue to take photos I left <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hestra/">my gloves</a> in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">my pack</a> - a decision I regret the higher and windier it gets. I also ponder why I decided to put on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1BD2sfW">Alpha Comp Jacket</a> instead of my <a href="http://bit.ly/1rRRHpb">Patagonia Alpine Houdini</a> rain jacket as I start the get wet inside - or then it’s the sweat from hiking and scrambling up? At least I’m warm and the jacket and pants keep the wind outside. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214147809" title="Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/15214147809_699c6e2391_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up" /></a></p>

<p>We scramble up steep passages, rain and small streams making things slippery - it’s a good thing I’m wearing my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a> boots, that way I have good grip on the wet rocks and half-way dry &amp; warm feet. Soaked we arrive at the pass and the wind howls past us. I shelter behind a big rock, but Marcin lets me know we should push on. So on we push.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14363720837" title="Wind. Rain. Honesty. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14363720837_7ac4627792_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wind. Rain. Honesty." /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400901985" title="At the top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/15400901985_9d8d44d8b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the top" /></a></p>

<p>On the way up I thought about how nice it will be to go down in the downwind side. But I must have misunderstood Marcin, as we hike down on wet talus fields on the upwind side. At a narrow stretch of path between the talus I finally decide to go search for my gloves in my pack, as my hands started to be just too damn cold in the strong wind. When I finally have managed to get my soaking wet &amp; cold hands in the gloves they need a moment to warm up, but then it’s infinitely more comfortable. The same time I pack away my camera, so I can concentrate on the path. We down climbing a few sections and then slowly are getting lower. </p>

<p>We hike over snowfields and I can believe it as down, out of the treacherous wind, we see a solitary figuring coming our way, wearing a Poncho. Marcin chats with him, and as we continue to walk I hear a similar story like the ones I have heard the days before: First time in the mountains, wants to continue to the hut we started out from. A bit later we meet a couple who also have the same plan and think that now they’re at least three if they catch up with the guy, which makes it a bit safer. We pass a high-alpine lake and low pines are starting to appear. <em>“Not long anymore”</em> Marcin tells me - he must see that I’m not feeling too great: By now I’m drenched. Soon we are walking through a pretty pine forest in the mist. After a final small uphill we stand in front of the massive <a href="http://www.murowaniec.e-tatry.pl">Schronisko Murowaniec refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214246510" title="Schronisko Murowaniec by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15214246510_1e268ebe57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schronisko Murowaniec" /></a></p>

<p>We head inside and it is full of people - some dressed in dry clothes, others looking just as wet &amp; miserable as we. Marcin shows me the drying wall, where I hang my wet gear after I slipped into my dry layers. Then it’s feasting time - I’m starving and munch away a soup and pancakes, a hot tea and coffee give more warmth. We sit for a while at the hut, with people coming and going. My clothes still moist but a bit drier I put them back on after almost two hours inside. Outside it’s still as misty as before, but the rain has become just the faintest drizzle. </p>

<p>Steadily we go down, soon the rain stops while the mist lingers on. We descend on paths that get broader and broader to a wide meadow. The mist mixes with the clouds and hangs above us while we walk towards Kuznice, a suburb of Zakopane and the start of a gondola up to Kasprowy Wierch.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214316898" title="Down by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15214316898_c764198aa9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Down" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214153899" title="Green under grey by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214153899_189ef3dfff_b.jpg" width="863" height="1024" alt="Green under grey" /></a></p>

<p>Here Marcin and I separate for a while - he needs to run an errand in town and hopes to catch a bus from here - we’ll meet up at the refuge later. After checking out the the small settlement with the gondola station and resisting buying some more food I hike up the broad cobblestone trail and take the first possibility into the forest.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400906185" title="Cobblestone by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15400906185_c9f9fbcb40_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cobblestone" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214397527" title="Fast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214397527_125435355d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fast" /></a></p>

<p>There’s several possibilities to visit shrines and monasteries along the trail, but I just want to reach the refuge to finally strip out of all the moist clothes, take a hot shower, dress in dry clothes and eat some good food. But the scenery is lovely on the way, and so I stop here and there to take photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400582682" title="Tranquility by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3915/15400582682_cba7c400f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tranquility" /></a></p>

<p>As the forest disappears another wide meadow comes into view, with the pretty <a href="http://schroniska.pttk.pl/kondratowa/pl">Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali refuge</a> sitting at its side. I go in and am welcomed by smiling faces in the common room. While I don’t speak a word of Polish I still am able to communicate with the wonderful owners of the refuge and she shows me the room I am staying in. I put down my pack, get rid of the wet clothes and then just am for a moment. Then the rest of the evening is just as I imagined it would be: Hot shower, dry, warm clothes, good food, early to bed. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214400107" title="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/15214400107_6ca4d4a074_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ridges-and-summits">Ridges and Summits</h2>

<p>I slept great after the day before, and as we get up at 6 in the morning the sky is blue and the sun is already shining across the summits opposite my window. Marcin and I head silently down, where the two ladies of the refuge have a breakfast waiting for us! We eat, pack, and are out of the hut by 7 and make our way to the pass.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214320388" title="Up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214320388_576117b4da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>The sky is blue with the occasional white cloud running across it and we quickly are hot from the sun and hiking. At the final spring we refill the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/platypus/?pid=81">Platypus</a> bottles with cold, clear water and then walk on. Soon we are at the pass where we drop our packs into the shrubbery and almost run up to Giewont, so light we are!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397733501" title="Further up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3866/15397733501_cb1086ff52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Further up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377897226" title="Final bit up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15377897226_c0ec8a1c1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Final bit up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214268900" title="Summit of Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3848/15214268900_d99bdd983e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit of Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400602172" title="Down from Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3853/15400602172_b9e263692a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Down from Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>It doesn’t take us long and we’re standing on the summit, underneath the massive iron cross which can be seen from Zakopane. The views are hazy but good nevertheless: Zakopane towards the north with the small villages surrounding the city towards east &amp; west, and you even can glimpse into Slovakia from here. On the way down we encounter a lonely, old chamois and then soon are back at our packs. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214337218" title="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/15214337218_b8187c6356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377902416" title="A look down at the valley by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/15377902416_901ef59a4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look down at the valley" /></a></p>

<p>The trail to Kondracka Kopa is a long, steady climb over a wide ridge. Clouds float over the ridge and surroundings summits, while alpine flowers are adding bright colours to the grey &amp; white of the sky. On my left I can see the lower hills of the Tatras and the meadow and refuge we slept in last night, and on the left zig-zags the trail down to the meadow from my original route. It does not take long and we’re on the summit of Kondracka Kopa, and now we will walk on the border of Poland and Slovakia while ticking off the next few summits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214340958" title="Along the border by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15214340958_71b3d109f2_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Along the border" /></a></p>

<p>We stay now almost all the time above 2000 m elevation while we hike in the clouds from Kondracka Kopa to Malolaczniak, Krzesanica, Ciemniak and then Twarda Kopa. Once in a while the clouds rip open and we can see the lower Tatras in Slovakia, narrow valleys, high walls, streams running towards the far off sea. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214423037" title="Towards Twarda Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3844/15214423037_2c456098d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Towards Twarda Kopa" /></a></p>

<p>From Twarda Kopa we can see Giemont in the distance, now in the clouds - but more worrisome is the helicopter which flies up to it from the valley. We don’t know what happened, but hope no one died.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400937025" title="A look back to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2943/15400937025_742b942b3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin waits for me at a large summit cairn and suggests we take the green trail down to the next refuge. It’s just around 11 and we have the whole day really in front of us still, so I agree and we take a turn from the big main path and walk on a very narrow path in a hanging meadow towards the Western Tatras.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214191449" title="Down 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3852/15214191449_334c07144a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="964" alt="Down 2" /></a></p>

<p>The views and the trail are spectacular. A narrow singletrack trail that’s demanding and exposed, but with gorgeous views on the lower-lying mountains, valleys, meadows - and in front of us, the Western Tatras. A pair of chamois give us a show as they are fighting in a couloir, but my view often just drifts to the horizon, where large mountains try to reach the sky with their summits. At a turn in the path we sit down and have a snack &amp; drink, while Marcin names the peaks and valleys and tells me anecdotes about geographical features. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377924676" title="A look back up the green trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2941/15377924676_45d34c6126_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="A look back up the green trail" /></a></p>

<p>Too soon we reach the tree line, but the path continues to be lovely. It gradually widens and Marcin tells me that it has been an old road for an iron ore mine, and I again wonder about how much work it must have been to clear the forests to create it. While we talk we reach the meadow and a group of fully loaded foreign backpackers pass us, just as amazed about the beautiful scenery around them as we are. The trail now runs next to a stream, and it does not take long until we reach the <a href="http://www.schronisko-ornak.pl">Schronisko Ornak refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397759651" title="Schronisko Ornak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397759651_65b41d3012_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Schronisko Ornak" /></a></p>

<p>It is busy outside and not even 13 o’clock. I check in with the help of Marcin and then accompany him down the valley - our hike ends here today, and I will be venturing on for the next two days on my own. The trail is now a wide dirt road and full of people, with plenty of trails going off on the right and left - trails which I will explore on my way back up to the refuge, I decide. And as Marcin tells me about the long caves up on the mountains which one can explore my afternoon suddenly looks like it will be filled with plenty of adventure!</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Climbing & Mountaineering in the Polish Tatras]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-26T10:32:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In June I visited a country which has since a long time fascinated me: <a href="http://www.poland.travel/en/">Poland</a>. Friendly people. Forests. The Baltic. Great food. And the Tatra Mountain Range. Plenty of reasons to pay a visit to this lovely country, but it was the latter one which brought me here, and which I set off to explore for a week of climbing, mountaineering and hiking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14810289940" title="Early morning at Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5565/14810289940_6369caa369_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Early morning at Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-approach">The Approach</h2>

<p>I arrived after a short flight in Krakow, got my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">backpack</a> and then started the ride to <a href="http://www.zakopane.pl/en">Zakopane</a>. It was almost 23 o’clock as I arrived at the <a href="http://www.skalny.com.pl/">Hotel Skalny</a> and then just took a quick shower before I fell tired into my bed.</p>

<p>After a delicious breakfast and the best scrambled eggs I have ever eaten I pack my hiking gear, deposit some stuff at the reception and then walk to the centre. Zakopane has a nice pedestrian shopping street and it felt like every third store was a outdoor shop, so if I’d had forgotten something there’d been plenty of chances to stock up on gear. I only needed a map which I found from one of the various stalls along the street. Then I took out some Polish Zloty from an ATM, bought a few more snacks and walked to the bus station - Zakopane is small city and I found I could walk everywhere.</p>

<p>The bus to Polana Palencia/ Morskie Oko was quickly found and at noon the bus left punctually. We drove through the centre of Zakopane, suburbs and then slowly in a wide curve to where I would start my walk in the Polish Tatras. Along the way always in view on my right: The Tatras. A compact mountain range these mountains are a natural border between Poland and Slovakia, and for many of their citizens a prime destination to visit. The infrastructure in place is very good, with plenty of huts and signs along the often very well maintained trails. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856089468" title="Road to Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3889/14856089468_4a9f8815b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Road to Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>As I arrive at the parking lot at Polana Palencia I pay the 25 Zloty for my 7 Day ticket to the National Park and then started the 9 km walk to the Morskie Oko Refuge. Around half way I switched from my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX boots</a> into my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a>, and am very happy I took them along on this trip. Nuns in white dresses pass me, a sight one not often sees on other trails.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042318042" title="Nuns by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3862/15042318042_58997ddf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="632" alt="Nuns" /></a></p>

<p>There are plenty of people on the road and regularly horse-drawn carriages go up and down. For a small fee these take you up &amp; down and shave some 6 km off the approach to the Morskie Oko Refuge. Between the spruces, far away, distant peaks come into view. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042321752" title="White Tatras by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3926/15042321752_f73f0894fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="773" alt="White Tatras" /></a></p>

<p>I come to a large oval where the horse carriages disembark their cargo and their passengers head for refreshments at the near restaurant. People with ice creams and cool drinks pass me, some looking happy, some exhausted, and I can understand why: It’s hot and humid. The last few hundred meters to the refuge I only have my eyes on the grand scenery which unfolds in front of me and I see the peaks I will be climbing the next couple of days, and many more which would make any alpinist, climber and mountaineer happy. As I round a corner my day dreams of summits are interrupted: Dozens of people mingle in front of the beautiful old wooden building, taking in the mountains and the clear lake which lays at the bottom of them. Morskie Oko. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042286112" title="Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/15042286112_f2b6ce6b1a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>I check in, drop my pack in my room and then head out for a stroll around the lake. Finally I am walking on beautiful, narrow paths along the shore. Waterfalls come rushing down to the lake. People sit at the water, take in the view. I am one of them. Bliss.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856084348" title="Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5556/14856084348_ac58545096_b.jpg" width="1024" height="401" alt="Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>Back at the refuge I spend small money on delicious local food: Soups, sausages, pancakes, a beer. I sit on the terrace, waiting for Marcin, the Mountain Guide with whom I will be spending the next few days climbing &amp; mountaineering in this cradle of Polish Alpinism. He arrives as the sun is setting in the west and quickly identifies me, even if we have never seen before =) We eat dinner together, quickly understanding each other well and making plans for the following days.</p>

<h2 id="mountaineering">Mountaineering</h2>

<p>It’s Tuesday, 6 o’clock in the morning. Our Alarms ring, we get up and take a look out of the window. The weather looks mixed, Marcin says - lets sleep another hour and then see how it looks. At 7 the weather looks similar in my opinion, but we start to pack either way. We have a light breakfast as the kitchen is still closed, so I pack a couple of extra bars and then we’re off. To Rysy. Poland’s highest summit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14994487991" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/14994487991_897226ec65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>We hike around the lake, ascent to the 2nd lake above it and see that we are not the only ones. A couple of German girls are before us. A few lone hikers further ahead. We walk around the higher lake and cross the first snow fields. A wrong step and you’d slide into the ice cold lake, and there’s evidence of some of these wrong steps in the snow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14810877719" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5571/14810877719_c1b80e274b_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Around us steep walls and high peaks. Marcin tells me about alpine and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ice-climbing/">ice climbing</a> routes and adventures, but right now my mind is set on our summer mountaineering route ahead of us. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14974591296" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3850/14974591296_103d187940_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Soon the path gets steeper. We traverse a few more snow fields, kicking steps, still crampons aren’t needed. Marcin leads the way, he has hiked this trail so often that he can not even remember the amount of times that he has summited Rysy.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14997563215" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3837/14997563215_33337048d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>He is also working for the local Mountain Rescue group, and gets at times a bit agitated when we pass solo hikers. As he chats shortly with them I can not make out anything of their conversation and when I enquire what they talked about it’s often the same answer: The person is the first time ever in their life in the mountains. Has no crampons nor ice axe along. No experience of how to traverse steep snow fields. But they want to stand on the summit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14997199162" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/14997199162_242889170f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Some turn around and listen to his advice, to wait a few more weeks till the snow is gone. Some ignore it and push on. At least until the large snow field which then is in front of us and needs to be traversed to get to the summit. Which is where I put on my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-air-tech-light-new-classic-wide-steigeisen/">Grivel Air Tech Light crampons</a> and take my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-air-tech-racing-eispickel/">Grivel Air Tech Racing ice  axe</a>. I put my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Sirocco helmet</a> on, we rope up and then front point the snow field up. We ignore the path others have made and take a direct route till the rocks. It takes us not long, maybe 15 to 20 minutes, and we are where the chains start. But without crampons and an ice axe you do one wrong step and then slide down the 50° slope for a long time. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14811061178" title="Rysy Summit Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5557/14811061178_47a7e85fd0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rysy Summit Selfie" /></a></p>

<p>Snow and ice are along the route up, it’s some serious scrambling at times, and exposed. After a while in the clouds I can make out other shapes in front of us. And then we’re at the summit. Clouds hang around us, it’s windy. I put my <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/product_info.php?cat=110&amp;products_id=373">PHD Ultra Down Jacket</a> on to stay warm, scramble to the summit marker and take a Selfie. Have a snack. Wait for the clouds to part. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14994583221" title="Rysy Summit View by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3854/14994583221_a0835797ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rysy Summit View" /></a></p>

<p>They cooperate only a bit, but what they reveal is beautiful. Views into Slovakia and the easy path up to Rysy. Deep valleys. Steep walls. Many possibilities. After a while we pack up again and start the descent. It goes fast, we make good speed and are at 15 o’clock back at the refuge. And I reward myself with them delicious pancakes!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856826070" title="Pancakes by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5567/14856826070_d14f461315_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pancakes" /></a></p>

<h2 id="climbing">Climbing</h2>

<p>It’s 4 am as our alarms ring in unison the next morning. We eat the breakfast we bought the evening before and then silently leave the hut. The lake lies silently on our left as we ascent the beautiful path which runs up on the right of the lake. We cross clear streams, the water running noisily down to the lake. And always in front of us: Mnich. The beautiful spire we’re about to climb.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856082608" title="Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3873/14856082608_23c6383a49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>We left most of our gear at the refuge, and I’m only carrying my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts.html">DMM Nuts</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/dmm-dragon-cams.html">DMM Dragons</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-demon-cam-klemmgeraet/">DMM Demons</a>, some quick draws and screw lock carabiners, harness and climbing shoes. After a mere 45 minutes we stand at the crossroad, and Marcin is a bit surprised about the speed we were able to come up here.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14855955819" title="Approach to Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5585/14855955819_2b5e7f275c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Approach to Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>We walk another 20 minutes and then are at the start. We put on harnesses, I rack up and slip into my climbing shoes. We walk a bit further till the beginning of the route and then I tie in. Marcin gives me some general advice in which direction the route goes, and off I go. Placing gear wherever I can, but it ain’t much. I’m using an old, massive bolt and wonder how many climbers have used it before me. Then I reach a good ledge and build a belay to bringing Marcin up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14855951469" title="Climbing on Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3908/14855951469_a4a7103933_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Climbing on Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>Another pitch and we are on the top of Mnich. On the way lots of scratches tell the story of alpinists climbing this route in winter with crampons. But right now the sun bathes us in its golden light and warms us up while a light breeze goes through the air. We’re sitting on the dining table big top of this 2.068 m high spire, happy about the fast ascent and the good weather. But from the south-east already some clouds are coming over the ridge line we see. I snap a few more photos, then thread the ropes through my <a href="http://bit.ly/1qp0MV4">Reverso 4</a> and start the rappel.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042304012" title="Selfie on top of Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5560/15042304012_db42d936f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Selfie on top of Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>I go first again, clip in at the large bolt, let Marcin know that he can come down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042862322" title="Rappel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15042862322_10e8af3874_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rappel" /></a></p>

<p>Twenty minutes later we are down where we racked up earlier. I slip out of the climbing shoes, put the OSOs back on, pack and then we’re off. Back to Morskie Oko.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856070018" title="Back to Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3923/14856070018_a4d994b7cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Back to Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>We arrive well in time before Check-out and I’m having a coffee and pancakes. Then it’s packing up and leaving for the Przedni Staw Polski Refuge in the neighbouring valley. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856065398" title="Easy path by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3921/14856065398_24143e8845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Easy path" /></a></p>

<p>The path goes from easy to steep in no time, and I start to wonder what classifies as <em>easy</em> for Marcin. But then he has walked these paths for years. As we start to overtake other hikers I get a sense of what he might mean.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15039600801" title="Path by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3894/15039600801_ce0db4cb87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="612" alt="Path" /></a></p>

<p>I take a last look back on Morskie Oko and the surrounding mountains, this cradle of Polish Alpinism, and know I will be back when they will be wearing their white dress. So many possibilities. So beautiful. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042865632" title="Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3870/15042865632_bb65f7e793_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Storm" /></a></p>

<p>The weather turns fast and as we reach a pass also the rain reaches us. We put on our <a href="http://bit.ly/1qeJIQv">rain jackets</a> and pants, I have another quick bite from a Müsli bar and then go on. Light showers come down on us, but my view is set on our right.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856100147" title="Hiking in the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5586/14856100147_5784882629_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hiking in the rain" /></a></p>

<p>There is Orla Perć, the most difficult <em>“trail”</em> in all of the Tatras, and we plan to hike it the next day. A magnificent ridge walk, all of it above 2.000 m, much of it on steep, exposed terrain.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856097037" title="Valley of Five Polish Lakes by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3850/14856097037_d825f77c5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Valley of Five Polish Lakes" /></a></p>

<p>After a shortcut we top out on a small summit which gives a superb view over the Valley of Five Polish Lakes, and down at the shore I already can make out the refuge. We don’t need long till we arrive at it, and are happy to be inside as the rain sets in. The large, wooden common room is full of other hikers, it’s noisy and humid, but people are happy. Good food leaves the kitchen, tasty smells wafting pass me. I can’t resist long.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15043223405" title="Przedni Staw Polski Refuge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3845/15043223405_de16d20beb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Przedni Staw Polski Refuge" /></a></p>

<p>I feast yet again on pancakes, have another cup of coffee, and then set out with Marcin for a quick stroll while the rain has stopped. We go and check out some high water falls, the lakes, walk on narrow trails, and then the rain comes. Lots of rain. We walk back to the refuge, I accelerate, feel the joy of running in my Luna Sandals in the mountains. And it feels like the rain wants to make sure it puts as much water drops down on us before we reach the warm, dry refuge. We arrive dry at the hut, but the weather forecast is not very positive. There’s rain and thunderstorms coming our way, which turn to snow and hail above 1800 m, and I wonder if we’d be able to continue the route I have planned if the weather is like this.</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Back from the Polish Tatras]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/07/back-from-the-polish-tatras.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-01T11:27:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/07/back-from-the-polish-tatras</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Radio silence interrupted.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14550172205" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/14550172205_4436dd8d70_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>If you don’t <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">follow along</a> you’re bound to think I fell off a mountain as I missed two <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/archives/">TWIRs</a>. But the truth was that I was in Poland. In Europes smallest, biggest mountains: The Tatras. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14548243432" title="Bystrá summit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2909/14548243432_5cbb3e1e26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bystrá summit" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14569427913" title="Cloudy Ridge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/14569427913_af09317aff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="553" alt="Cloudy Ridge" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14548333782" title="Grzes by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2924/14548333782_ba4a5c55c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grzes" /></a></p>

<p>More to come. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outdoor Guide to Helsinki]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html"/>
    <updated>2013-11-28T10:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Helsinki is not just the capital of Finland, it also has a lot to offer for outdoor lovers who visit the city. You can meet outdoor types, go wild camping and packrafting in the middle of the city, visit nearby National Parks and pick up a Kuksa &amp; Puukko from one of the outdoor shops.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/rikukettunen/10122173714/" title="Helsinki by Riku Kettunen, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2868/10122173714_079090833d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="678" alt="Helsinki" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-folks-in-helsinki">Outdoor folks in Helsinki</h2>

<p>Going outdoors with like-minded people is a lot of fun. Helsinki boasts a large &amp; social population of outdoor types, many of whom are very likely to help you out with picking a destination and probably even meet you for a beer. Contact them via Twitter and visit their blogs for inspiration.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/korkealle">Aleksi</a> is the guy to contact for climbing</li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/valppaus">Joni</a> will join you for fatbiking, packrafting and ice climbing</li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/mtakanen">Marko</a> is a jack-of-all-outdoor-trades, and lately especially enjoys packrafting</li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/rollofunk">Mikael</a> snowshoes, hikes and speaks Japanese</li>
  <li><a href="https://twitter.com/TAnttalainen">Timo</a> is a Finn who works at an outdoor store and likes sea kayaking</li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twitter.com/TobyinHelsinki">Toby</a> is an English expat who you should contact for climbing &amp; cycling</p>
  </li>
  <li><a href="http://sub24helsinki.blogspot.fi/">Sub 24 Helsinki</a> is a loose collective of outdoor folks who meet up once a month to go sleep outdoors together. Adventures take place all around the capital area, and often are conducted by bike.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>If you’re a social Helsinki outdoor person and want to be listed above, please comment underneath!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/papalars/2902429577/" title="Helsinki Train Station by papalars, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3027/2902429577_802b855435_b.jpg" width="1024" height="644" alt="Helsinki Train Station" /></a></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-destinations">Outdoor destinations</h2>

<p>So, you’ve landed in Helsinki and have some free time on your hands, which you’d like to spend outdoors. Good! There’s plenty of options available for you of where to go and what to do.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hugovk/7501133582/" title="Cycling with a bouldering mat by hugovk, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8281/7501133582_da6a8dc5d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Cycling with a bouldering mat" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re into climbing and bouldering, then pick up the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/southern-finland-bouldering-guide.html">Southern Finland Bouldering Guide</a>
and visit <a href="http://27crags.com/">27 Crags</a> to view the locations in the Helsinki area. If you want to boulder, you won’t even need to leave the centre as there’s plenty of great problems within walking distance of the centre.</p>

<p>If you’re more the hiking/ backpacking/ trailrunning kind of type, then you might want to go and visit <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/nuuksio/Pages/Default.aspx">Nuuksio</a> or <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/sipoonkorpi/Pages/Default.aspx">Sipoonkorpi</a> National Park, which are within an hour driving distance and easily reached via public transportation. Then there’s the Trail 2000, a 110-km-long hiking trail, which begins in Laakso in Helsinki, and goes through the Nuuksio National Park. Just follow the blue bands on the trees =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11097111065/" title="Nuuksio by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5545/11097111065_c2ce1a242a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nuuksio" /></a></p>

<p>Seakayaking &amp; packrafting is also possible as Helsinki is on a Peninsula and surrounded by the Baltic on three sides. If you prefer rivers, the Vantaajoki is the place to go, or ask one of the paddling &amp; packrafting guys from further up about good rivers! <a href="http://www.naturaviva.fi/en/">Natura Viva</a> rents kayaks and also has daily guided tours in the summer.</p>

<p>Cycling in Helsinki is fun. The cycling network is OK-ish (at least they try!) and <a href="http://www.bikemap.net/en/regional/Finland/Finland/Helsinki/">Bikemap</a> helps you to find different routes throughout the city. You also can use the <a href="http://pk.reittiopas.fi/en/">Journey Planner</a>, and check <a href="http://www.greenbike.fi/vuokrauskohteet_en.html">Greenbike’s Tips</a>, too. </p>

<h2 id="outdoors-indoors">Outdoors, Indoors</h2>

<p>Sometimes the weather is so bad that even the most hardened outdoor-types will gladly accept some shelter indoors. If you’re looking for outdoor related activities indoors, then <a href="http://www.haltia.com/">Haltia</a> is a good place to start. The new Finnish Nature Centre is next to Nuuksio National Park in a beautiful building, and enables you to experience nature from all over Finland in one building. </p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.luomus.fi/english/">Botanical Garden in Kaisaniemi</a> is not just in the summer a great place to go with its beautiful parks, also in winter it’s a fine destination. Right next to the railway station it has a few greenhouses with plants and trees from different climate zones which are well temperated and a real alternative to -20°C outside. If you prefer animals to plants visit the <a href="http://www.luomus.fi/english/nhm/">Natural History Museum</a> which is also smack-in-the-middle of the centre, or take a ferry to the <a href="http://www.korkeasaari.fi/en/services/visitorinformation">Korkeasaari Zoo</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11097167264/" title="Kiipeilyareena Helsinki by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/11097167264_5c7ffd3ef1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kiipeilyareena Helsinki" /></a></p>

<p>Climbers will visit the <a href="http://www.kiipeilyareena.com/">Kiipeily Areena</a> which has Scandinavia’s highest climbing wall and a sweet new boulder area. The <a href="http://www.boulderkeskus.com/fi/">Boulderkeskus</a> has two locations in the capital area and will present you with lots of fine problems.</p>

<p>In autumn there’s also a host of different events in the capital: The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/banff-mountain-film-festival-world-tour-helsinki.html">Banff Mountain Film Festival</a>, the <a href="http://www.relaa.com/han">Helsinki Adventure Night</a> + Reel Rock Tour and the <a href="http://www.bicyclefilmfestival.com/city/helsinki/">Bicycle Film Festival</a> all have stops in the city and will wow you with sweet outdoor movies. The <a href="http://www.messukeskus.com/Sites1/Skiexpo/Sivut/default.aspx">Skiexpo</a> is a trade fair about, yes, skiing and winter sports, while the <a href="http://www.messukeskus.com/Sites3/GoExpo2014/Sivut/default.aspx">GoExpo</a> is a consumer fair for hikers, cyclists, fishermen, and other outdoor activities.</p>

<h2 id="outdoor-shops">Outdoor Shops</h2>

<p><a href="http://pelagobicycles.com/">Pelago Bicycles</a> is not just Finland’s best bike shop, they also make sweet bicycles - right in the middle of the city. If you’re just remotely interested in cycling, go visit their beautiful store. And yes, if you purchase a bike, they will pack it ready for air travel for you! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11098457723/" title="Pelago Bicycles by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5484/11098457723_f217251879_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Pelago Bicycles" /></a></p>

<p>In a city the size of Helsinki you find plenty of outdoor/ climbing/ trailrunning shops, which enable you to pick up the stuff you couldn’t bring or forgot. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.4runners.fi/">4 Runners</a> is in the <a href="http://www.kamppi.fi/">Kamppi</a> shopping mall and in my opinion the best running shop in Helsinki. They have a super collection of minimalist and barefoot running shoes (yes, also Inov-8s!) and accessories from GU Energy Gels to tights and toe socks. </p>

<p>Partio Varuste / <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorstore.com/">Scandinavian Outdoor Store</a> are in the centre next to Kamppi and will satisfy gear needs of backpackers &amp; hikers. Pick up gas cartridges and alcohol fuel, try on Merrell shoes and get Woolpower underwear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.camu.fi/">Camu</a> and <a href="http://www.mountainshop.fi/">Mountain Shop Finland</a> will be two shops which budding climbers &amp; mountaineers will put on their “Must visit” list. Here you can get the good fitting outdoor garments from Arc’teryx, Black Diamond, Rab as well as ice screws, quick-draws and whatever else a climber’s heart desires.</p>

<p>Finally, <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/">Partioaitta</a> is also in the centre (opposite of the Scandinavian Outdoor Store) and has also a few more shops in the capital area.</p>

<h2 id="sleeping-outdoors">Sleeping Outdoors</h2>

<p>Yes, you can sleep outdoors in Helsinki. There’s plenty of parks in the centre which are silent in the nights, and if you have a stealth shelter and rise early there shouldn’t be a problem with sleeping right in the middle of the capital. If you want to sleep outdoors but not in downtown, for 4.50€ a train and bus ride take you to Nuuksio, from where you can walk in 30 minutes to several different camping places. You also could take a bus or train to one of the more silent suburbs and camp there in a wood.</p>

<p>There’s some sweet <a href="https://www.airbnb.com/tell-a-friend?airef=w3kpza02eczz5">Airbnb</a> places available in downtown Helsinki if you do not want to camp out. There’s also a few reasonably priced hotels, though if you like it fancy, stay at the <a href="http://www.klauskhotel.com/">Klaus K</a> as they also have a good sustainable programme.</p>

<h2 id="food--cafs">Food &amp; Cafés</h2>

<p>The afore-mentioned Kamppi shopping mall has a couple of Cafés, and the <a href="http://www.johtocafe.com/in-english/">Johto Café</a> at the top has free Wifi. However, I prefer the <a href="http://mbar.fi/">mBar</a> in front of it - good coffees and friendly service, and a great terrace in the summer. If you find yourself hungry during lunch time, I find <a href="http://www.ravintolahalikarnas.fi/">Halikarnas</a> the best place to eat - delicious Turkish food with a wide vegetarian selection, this is a great place. <a href="http://www.grandelicato.fi/">Gran Delicato</a> is a Greek run Café which makes superb coffees and sandwiches, while there’s a host of Asian Buffet &amp; Restaurant places in the centre - just take your pick. If you like beer, stop by at <a href="http://www.teerenpeli.com/ravintolat/ravintolat/helsinki">Teerenpeli</a>, which, you guessed it, is also next to Kamppi.</p>

<p>If you rather cook yourself, the <a href="http://www.hok-elanto.fi/ostoksille/s-market/toimipaikat/s-market-sokos-helsinki/">S-Market</a> in front of the railway station probably has the lowest prices in the centre, but there’s plenty of <a href="http://www.alepa.fi/helsinki.html">Alepa</a> and <a href="http://www.siwa.fi/fi/kaupat-ja-aukioloajat/?nearestStore=&amp;nearestStore_id=&amp;city=Helsinki">Siwa</a> Supermarkets spread throughout the city, as well as the large (and expensive) <a href="http://www.k-market.com/Myymalat/K-market-Kamppi/">K-Market</a> in Kamppi. If you prefer organic, Fair Trade food, head over to <a href="http://www.ruohonjuuri.fi/myymalat/">Ruohonjuuri</a> which is also on the side of Kamppi.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/visitfinland/6992587550/" title="Mbar Terrace in  Helsinki by Visit Finland, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7236/6992587550_9f830d3ee1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="714" alt="Mbar Terrace in  Helsinki" /></a></p>

<h2 id="getting-around">Getting around</h2>

<p>Helsinki is a small city, and you easily can walk pretty much anywhere. It’s surrounded by the sea on three sides, and there’s several islands around this peninsula. If you want to speed up a bit, take the Tram, Metro, Bus or Commuter Train from <a href="http://www.hsl.fi/en">HSL</a>. For the Tram &amp; Metro you can send a Text Message to 16355 with “A1” as a message and you receive a digital ticket to your phone. In the bus and commuter train you can get a ticket from the driver/ conductor. If you prefer to pedal, loan a cycle from <a href="http://www.greenbike.fi/index_en.html">Greenbike</a> which has a stall in front of Kamppi. </p>

<p><em>That’s the Outdoor Guide to Helsinki. I hope it helps you to make your stay in the capital more outdoors-y and pleasant. If you have suggestions on how to improve it, please leave a comment!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outdoor Gift Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/11/the-outdoor-gift-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T14:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/11/the-outdoor-gift-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is that time of the year again, even if I see <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2012/">Advents Calendars</a>, Spekulatius and Stollen already already since September in the stores. Time to ponder what is the best gift for hikers, armchair adventurers, climbers, and trail runners.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mjanicki/5295571160/" title="Presents under the Tree by M. Janicki"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5210/5295571160_d78c515584_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Presents under the Tree" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>The Best Gifts are No Gifts or Services.</strong> <em>Despite what follows, I strongly believe the best gift you can give your loved ones are non-tangible gifts, as in services and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/guided-trips/">experiences</a>. Go for a hike or climb together (or let him/ her go for one!), maybe eat out or a give a nice Spa visit. Also arranging time off for your loved ones, so that they could pursue what they’d like to do, are great gifts. They’re better for the planet, too =)</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7751496934/" title="Up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7279/7751496934_f2be74de50_b.jpg" width="1024" height="487" alt="Up" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gifts-for-the-hiker">Gifts for The Hiker</h2>

<p>High on the list of any hiker are gifts from his favourite cottage. Here is whats definitely worth getting for your hiking friend:</p>

<ul>
  <li>You can’t go wrong with a <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/hiking-climbing-shelters/mids.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Mid</a>. Light, spacious and easy to pitch, you also can find shelter under it when you head outdoors with your hiking buddy!</li>
  <li>Outside it is getting cold, so a warm <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Schlafsaecke/Quilts:::2_78.html?refID=hif">down quilt</a> from <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/index.php?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a> will ensure warm nights during winter camps.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/">Laufbursche Gear</a> is coming out with four completely re-designed packs in 2014. There’s never such a thing as too many backpacks, so getting a brand new 2014 huckePACK is definitely something to wait for January 2014 and get!</li>
  <li>And as its cold and wet outside, a <a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/32-synthetic-insulation">synthetic insulation garment</a> would work well also in the summer. Warms even when moist, synthetic is the way to go in wet &amp; cold environments.</li>
  <li>Finally, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=9933&amp;pw=73183">REI Gift Cards or e-Gift Cards</a> are a one-size-fits-all gift for your favourite outdoor enthusiast. Don’t trouble yourself picking up the wrong gift - just give a gift card!</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8544632349/" title="Anders leading a route by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8508/8544632349_56e6a0a150_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Anders leading a route" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gifts-for-the-climber">Gifts for The Climber</h2>

<p>Ah, the climber. Divided into many sub-species - the Boulderer, the Sports Climber, the Trad Climber, the Mountaineer or the Alpinist - you hopefully know which kind of climbing the receiver of your gift is practicing. Because a boulder doesn’t do much with a pair of crampons!</p>

<ul>
  <li>The ice climber will be giving you extra hugs and thanks for a pair of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools.html">Petzl Nomic ice tools</a>. </li>
  <li>Boulderers fall. That the fall is more soft, put a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/ocun-paddy-dominator-crashpad.html">Ocún Paddy Dominator Crashpad</a> under the tree for them - large, light and functions as a mattress in a pinch, this is a superb crashpad to fall on when the holds are just too small to hold on to any longer.</li>
  <li>The Sport &amp; Trad Climber alike will welcome the gift of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/dmm-classic-rope-bag.html">DMM Classic Rope Bag</a> for their ropes, be they single, twin or halfs. </li>
  <li>Alpinsts and Mountaineers need helmets for their adventures. At the moment there’s no lighter and fully certified helmet on the market than the <a href="http://bit.ly/1apnPXN">Sirocco Climbing Helmet</a>, and I can say out of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/climbing-at-havukallio.html">experience</a> that it survives falls just great!</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/scarpa/">Scarpa climbing shoes</a> will be a welcome gift for any climber. <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/scarpa-instinct-vc-climbing-shoe-silver-orange/">Instinct VCs</a> for the boulderers &amp; sports climbers, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html">Scarpa Phantom Ultra Boots</a> for the alpinists, ice climbers and mountaineers, Scarpa makes great shoes for all!</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/garryknight/8560855544/" title="Mounted Police on a City Street by garryknight, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8392/8560855544_eb1a0bc3df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="678" alt="Mounted Police on a City Street" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gifts-for-the-urban-hiker">Gifts for The Urban Hiker</h2>

<p>The urban hiker, also called Armchair Adventurer, would like to spend more time in the wild but finding enough time between family, work and other commitments proves difficult. You could make sure he has a free weekend for some hiking/ climbing/ packrafting/ cycling, and maybe consider one of these items for the everyday outdoor adventure:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Is there a backpack which can do everything? Yes, it’s the <a href="http://www.goruck.com/en/gr1">GORUCK GR1</a>. Wear it to work, go climbing, travel for a week and then head out backpacking, cycling to work. The GR1 does it all, and will last you a lifetime. </li>
  <li><a href="http://us.shop.ecco.com/men-outdoor/men-outdoor,default,sc.html#sz=60">ECCO shoes</a> look the deal and will perform on the way to the office and for the after-work hike to the scenic lookout.</li>
  <li>Trousers. Some call them pants. Whatever you call them, with a pair from <a href="http://shop.outlier.cc/retail/pants/">Outlier</a> you will sport a functional pair that looks great in the city and takes you everywhere your bike and feet can take you, keeping you dry and warm in nasty weather.</li>
  <li>Again a late day at the office? A fine <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">outdoor book</a> is just what’s needed then. Sit down at home, take a dram and skim through one of these fine books to let at least the mind escape the urban environment. A good option is also a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription to trekking Magazin</a>.</li>
  <li>Also in an urban environment it is useful to know the time. And the barometric pressure. And where is north. That’s why a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">Garmin fēnix</a> might be an useful gift for those that easily get lost in the city, and need to find their way back.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/akunamatata/2821684589/" title="UTMB 2008 (160) by akunamatata, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3291/2821684589_0fbf842eeb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="UTMB 2008 (160)" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gifts-for-the-trailrunner">Gifts for The Trailrunner</h2>

<p>The trailrunner is the kind of person who will head out in pretty much any weather. Snow? Extra fun! Rain? Where’s that hardshell? Cold feet? Run faster! </p>

<ul>
  <li>You can not go wrong with a Vest from <a href="http://bit.ly/17Iug9J">Ultimate Direction</a>. Hands-down the best running vests, your trailrunning mate will run in happy circles around you!</li>
  <li>A second pair of his favourite <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/trailrunningschuhe/fuer--maenner/">trailrunning shoes</a>. Chances are his first pair are at the end of the life already, so why not get her/ him a new pair?!</li>
  <li>Chances are your trailrunning gift receiver also is just now outside running, despite the weather being close to 0°C and it’s rainy. Time to get some sweet <a href="http://www.theomm.com/products/clothing/">The OMM</a> garments which will keep him/ her warm in this fresh weather!</li>
  <li><a href="https://guenergy.com/">GU Energy</a> makes top notch gels, and getting a mix of these will be the best running nutrition stuff you can get to keep him running.</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1bAKKwa">Running glasses</a> create shade and keep wind, dirt and rain from the eyes, so that they can stay focussed on the trail ahead. Being able to change lenses is a big advantage - the light is different in the snow than in the desert!</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hades2k/6598576457/" title="Christmas presents by Hades2k, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7029/6598576457_8234fc4768_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Christmas presents" /></a></p>

<p><em>Pssst! All of the above not good enough? May I then recommend getting a <a href="https://www.alpackaraft.com/index.cfm/store.catalog/Packrafts">packraft</a> &amp; <a href="http://surlybikes.com/bikes/moonlander">Fatbike</a>? You sure may get me one ;) !</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
