<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hiking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/hiking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-17T23:22:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outdoor Guide to Vaasa]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/the-outdoor-guide-to-vaasa.html"/>
    <updated>2015-09-29T22:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/the-outdoor-guide-to-vaasa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Outdoor Guide to Vaasa - Finland’s sunniest city!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21593581188/in/dateposted/" title="Öjberget, Vaasa"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5769/21593581188_bc0746168b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjberget, Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-destinations">Outdoor destinations</h2>

<p>There’s plenty of nice nature trails around Vaasa which all can be found <a href="http://www.merenkurkku.fi/koe-merenkurkku/vaellusreitit/">here</a>. You can find coordinates and pdf maps on that website, though in general the trails are well marked and there’s an info board + map at the start. If you have a car or bike, I can recommend the <a href="http://www.merenkurkku.fi/koe-merenkurkku/vaellusreitit/ojenin-luontopolku/">Öjenin luontopolku</a> which is a nice 4 km loop with a fire place at the middle, which makes it ideal for adventures with kids. On the island of Vaskiluoto there’s a large forest trail which also is also groomed in winter for cross country skiing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21594552609/in/dateposted/" title="Öjenin luontopolku"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5704/21594552609_dc9de34f58_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjenin luontopolku" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.kvarkenworldheritage.fi/visit-kvarken/">Kvarken Archipelago</a> is Finland’s only UNESCO World Heritage site and an ideal destination to go birdwatching, a family or weekend hike or a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/pack-sail-rafting-in-the-kvarken-archipelago.html">packrafting adventure</a>. You will need a car or bike to get there (walking along the road is no fun), but it is worth it - the raising land is a sight to behold. </p>

<p>You prefer water sports? Good that Vaasa has at least half a dozen of fine <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/haku/Pages/tulos.aspx?paikka=436&amp;pakti=2&amp;a1akti=288">beaches</a>, with the one at Hietasaari probably being the easiest to reach and the most popular, too. The <a href="http://www.supstation.fi/vaasa/">Vaasa SUP Station</a> is also located there and a great opportunity to rent a SUP board and try our Stand Up Paddling. The photos from their sunset paddles look awesome, so check out their Instagram feed. In winter Hietasaari is also a good starting point to go Nordic Skating on the Baltic, or take your kite-surfing gear and hit the ice on the Eteläinen Kaupunginselkä.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21593424660/in/dateposted/" title="Vaasa SUP Station"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5680/21593424660_c0216dcf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaasa SUP Station" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Bouldering outdoors in Vaasa is so easy, you almost stumble over the blocs! <a href="http://27crags.com/areas/vaasa/">27 Crags</a> has you covered and is your guide to the best bouldering and climbing in town. If you actually prefer climbing with a rope then <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/falkiin-kallio">Falkiin Kallio</a> is the nearest crag of note, or you take the ferry to Umeå where there’s bigger and longer routes! In winter the crag at Höstvesi is good for whacking some ice, too.</p>

<p>Skiing in Vaasa is also possible at the nearby <a href="http://www.vaasa.fi/palvelut/talviurheilukeskus-ojberget">Öjberget Ski Centre</a>. You can check if its open from <a href="http://www.ski.fi/en/author/ojberget/">ski.fi</a>, though at 45 m elevation and the longest slope being 325 m long don’t expect long runs! However, in town there are <a href="http://www.latukartta.fi/vaasa/">14 cross country skiing loipes</a>, so if you come here in winter and enjoy some kick’n’glide take your skis along! </p>

<p>You can go packrafting and kayaking in town right from any of the many beaches and shores, but be careful around the harbour. At <a href="http://varppi.fi/en/">Varppi</a> you can rent a kayak or rowing boat if you don’t bring your own. A much nicer area to go paddling is the Kvarken Archipelago or one of the rivers. And if you prefer a <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/haku/Pages/tulos.aspx?paikka=436&amp;pakti=2&amp;a1akti=66">short cruise</a>, also that is possible in summer, with the old post boat being the most beautiful cruise as it has been sailing since 1679. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21160399993/in/dateposted/" title="Öjberget, Vaasa"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/734/21160399993_8dfd5f1d97_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjberget, Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you want to do long bicycle rides you’re in luck, though. There’s plenty of great cycling here, and Vaasa being in Pohjanmaa - the “flat country” - you won’t need to bother with long climbs. However, because we’re next to the Baltic expect wind, and as it goes - if there’s wind there’s going to be headwind. If you prefer to cycle around town, then the ride along the shore is a nice way to explore some of the best views of Vaasa and also grab an ice cream or a Toast Skagen at <a href="http://www.strampen.com/english">Strampen</a>. And if you look for some singletrack to shred check out the trail on the <a href="http://vsmtb.net/wp/reitit/">Vaasanseudun MTB</a> website.</p>

<p>Nice parks for a pick nick include the Satamapuisto next to <a href="http://kuntsi.vaasa.fi">Kuntsi</a> and the adjoining Hovioikeudenpuisto as well as Hietasaari, the tiny island just in front of Vaasa.</p>

<h2 id="in-case-of-rain-outdoors-indoors">In case of Rain: Outdoors, Indoors</h2>

<p>There’s plenty of gyms and sports halls in Vaasa, though you likely will need a membership to train in them. A better choice if the weather is not cooperating is the nice <a href="http://www.vaasa.fi/palvelut/uimahalli">swimming hall</a> of Vaasa, which has a 50 m pool for good work outs as well as a jump pool and a couple of kids’ pools. And this being Finland it obviously has a fine Sauna, too! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21755324106/in/dateposted/" title="Vaasa Vesitorni"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5759/21755324106_58df849764_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaasa Vesitorni" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Watertower of Vaasa houses the city’s <a href="http://www.highsport.fi/node/262">climbing gym</a>, which has public hours each Wednesday and Sunday from 18 to 20 o’clock. There’ currently two walls, one 17 m long with some overhang and one 20 m high wall, with a third wall being under construction. </p>

<p>The modern art museum <a href="http://kuntsi.vaasa.fi">Kuntsi</a> is well worth a visit if you like art, and there’s also the rather nice <a href="http://www.tikanojantaidekoti.fi">Tikanojan taidekoti</a> which is a good place to spent time. The <a href="http://www.pohjanmaanmuseo.fi/?page=Home&amp;setlang=l3">Pohjanmaa Museum</a> is actually four museums in one, of which the Terranova natural science exhibition is interesting to learn more about the Kvarken Archipelago. </p>

<p>There are only limited outdoor-sy happenings in Vaasa, but the yearly <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Luontoliikuntapäivä-Naturmotionsdag-Outdoor-Recreation-Day-338517656254113/timeline/">Outdoor Recreation Day</a> which usually happens every February is a good event to attend. You can learn about ice climbing, try nordic touring skating and ice fishing, eat a Pulla or Makkara and learn about other winter activities offered in the area.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12723806373/in/photostream/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid &amp; IcePack"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7408/12723806373_c1bf2dc325_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid &amp; IcePack" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-shopping">Outdoor shopping</h2>

<p>Vaasa’s offerings in terms of outdoor equipment are OK. Don’t expect to find gear from Arc’teryx, Patagonia, Norrøna, Primus or Helsport in town, though if you like Fjällräven, Haglöfs, Salomon et al. you will find them at the Intersport shop just off the main square. Also the Hypermarkets just a wee bit outside of the centre carry some outdoor equipment, from fishing tackle to sleeping pads and backpacks.</p>

<p>On the other hand there are at least half a dozen Bike Shops in Vaasa, with <a href="http://www.pyoraviertola.fi/">Pyöräliike Viertola</a> in Rauhankatu 20 being my favourite. They carry <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Pelago Bicycles</a> and are friendly &amp; professional, and also sell used bikes. </p>

<p>As fas as I know there’s no possibility to rent gear in town, but you can always check <a href="http://www.kuinoma.fi">kuin oma</a> for renting gear in Finland.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21575445089/in/dateposted/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5734/21575445089_526faf99d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sleeping-outdoors--indoors">Sleeping outdoors &amp; indoors</h2>

<p>Stealth camping in Vaasa is no problem whatsoever. There are so many forests and parks close to the centre that camping out is not a problem. Some of the beaches are a great option, or if you want to be really on your own cycle or walk out to Pilvilampi and camp there. The Everymen’s Right is your friend in Finland, so just stay at least 100 m away from a house and you’re good to go. </p>

<p>If you prefer to sleep indoors, then check the <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel?s=8">AirBnB listings</a> in Vaasa, there’s currently 28 houses, flats and rooms on offer in town which range from cozy old wooden houses to modern flats with sea view. <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/alasivut/Pages/nuku.aspx">Hotels, Cottages and B&amp;Bs</a> can be found on the Vaasa website, and if you want to go camping then the <a href="http://www.topcamping.fi/fi/vaasa_fi/">Top Camping Vaasa</a> place is your only option. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18572119925/in/dateposted/" title="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/266/18572119925_8e67987dba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="food--cafs">Food &amp; Cafés</h2>

<p>What are the best Cafés in Vaasa? Well, all those that are closed on Sundays. Seriously though, don’t expect a Café to be open on Sunday in this town. I haven’t figured out <em>why</em> they are closed, but on the rare occasion that they are open on a Sunday they are full. But any other day of the week they welcome your business, and it’s a hard toss-up which of these four Cafés is my favourite.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.loftet.fi/ravintola-konsulinnan-kahvihuone/">Konsulinnan kahvihuone</a> serves a great lunch with a delicious salad table, their coffee is arguably the best in town and you get a free 2nd cup. Also their cakes are superb, and the atmosphere in the old building is wonderful. <a href="http://www.sweetvaasa.fi">Sweet Vaasa</a> makes tasty cakes and salads, the <a href="http://www.othello-products.fi">Othello Bakeries</a> also have great traditional pastries and the <a href="http://www.wasakonditori.fi">Wasa Konditoria</a> in the old market hall has a great atmosphere and sells goods from Finland’s best bakery, <a href="http://www.aroma.fi">Aroma</a>. Aroma itself is located a bit outside of town in Kvevlax and a great stop for a coffeeneuring trip with your bike. <a href="http://www.caferaawka.fi">Café Raawka</a> should be on your list if you like raw food - it’s on my list for this weekends Café trip to town!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21184299813/in/dateposted/" title="Brita Cake at Konsulinnan kahvihuone"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5625/21184299813_03900082dd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Brita Cake at Konsulinnan kahvihuone" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://magokoro.fi">Magokoro</a> is Vaasa’s Sushi Restaurant and my favourite option for a tasty lunch in the centre. Their sushi are fresh, tasty and will always make you wish you’d have taken one more. For Dinner the <a href="http://www.pizzabistromarcopolo.fi">Pizzabistro Marco Polo</a> is the best choice for Pizzas in town. Delicious, freshly made pizzas and a cozy atmosphere with friendly staff will make for a good start into the evening. <a href="http://www.tomyumthai.fi">Tom Yum Thai</a> is a great Thai Restaurant which makes tasty food and has very friendly staff, and my choice for Asian food when eating out. I haven’t yet been to <a href="https://villdravintola.wordpress.com/2015/08/31/villd-poytavarauksia-otetaan-vastaan-nu-tar-vi-emot-reservationer/">Villd</a>, the Pop-Up Restaurant from Ossi Palonevan, but plan to go there while it is here in Vaasa till the end of October. Locally sourced foods from the Baltic and forests for a uniquely Finnish dining experience - what’s not to look forward to?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21183941504/in/photostream/" title="©Veera Kujala"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/645/21183941504_42ea79e25a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="©Veera Kujala" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="microadventures">Microadventures!</h2>

<p>More than a couple of days in Vaasa? Take a bike and ride to Isokyrö and visit the <a href="http://www.kyrodistillery.com">Kyrö Distillery Company</a> and taste the worlds best Gin for Gin &amp; Tonic! You also might be able to grab a bite and witness some live music at this small distillery, but check their website and reserve a table if you plan to visit.</p>

<p>If you’re more than a couple of days in town you owe it to yourself to head out to the <a href="http://www.kvarkenworldheritage.fi/visit-kvarken/">Kvarken Archipelago</a>, Finland’s only UNESCO World Heritage Site and see how the land rises from the sea, spot a white-tailed eagle and traditional boat sheds. It’s a great place to visit summers as winters, and will surely will make you feel like you’re in a far-away, wild place. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8609916055/in/album-72157633438534075/" title="Svedjehamn harbour"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8121/8609916055_a79bbce51e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Svedjehamn harbour" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://www.meteoria.fi/en">Meteoria Söderfjärden</a> is probably the biggest meteorite crater in Finland, and right in the middle there’s a birdwatching tower to observe the cranes and other birds passing through in spring an autumn. Meteoria is the most important resting and feeding place for cranes in Finland and a great place to observe these birds. There’s also a small museum next to the tower, and it’s easy to reach by bike or car.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.stundars.fi/?lang=en">Stundars</a> is an open air museum with over sixty traditional buildings from the region, from a windmill to a fishermen’s hut. It’s a great place to visit in summer when it is open, or during one of the special events like the handcrafts fair. There’s also trail that leads to it from the Meteoria and it’s close to <a href="http://www.sundom.fi/en">Sundom</a>, the small village just a few kilometres away from Vaasa.</p>

<h2 id="getting-around-town-and-to-vaasa">Getting around town and to Vaasa</h2>

<p>The centre of Vaasa is compact enough that you can walk from the Railway Station to Hietasaari in 15 minutes, or from the Swimming Hall to Palosaari in about 25 minutes. There’s no easy way to loan a bike in Vaasa, and the public transportation is also not good - a couple of busses with drivers who seem to think they’re in a rally car, you’re better off walking. </p>

<p>Getting to Vaasa is fastest and most affordable by airplane. The airport is small and efficient and it’s just a 35 minute flight to Helsinki. If you like to see more of the country then travelling by bus is an option, either by <a href="https://www.matkahuolto.fi/fi/">Matkahuolto</a> or with the cheap <a href="http://www.onnibus.com/en/index.htm">Onnibus</a>. If you prefer unreliable transportation which is expensive then the <a href="https://www.vr.fi/cs/vr/fi/etusivu">Finnish Railways</a> should be your choice. If you’re in Sweden you also can fly from Stockholm to Vaasa, or take the <a href="http://www.wasaline.com/en/">Wasaline Ferry</a> from Umeå for a more relaxed way to arrive in town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21182653664/in/dateposted/" title="Flying with Finnair to Vaasa"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/764/21182653664_e6a003f2eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Flying with Finnair to Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-folks-in-vaasa">Outdoor folks in Vaasa</h2>

<p>There are outdoorsy people in Vaasa, though they are mostly organized in Clubs for their specific sports as you saw above, so you might want to check out their happenings if you want to socialize. However, to find like-minded outdoorsy people you can browse the <a href="https://instagram.com/explore/tags/vaasa/">Instagram Tag for Vaasa</a> and also search on Twitter for <a href="https://twitter.com/search?f=users&amp;vertical=default&amp;q=vaasa&amp;src=typd">tweeps from Vaasa</a>. And then there’s obviously me on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/14600027980/in/photolist-oypywx-of9XEm-owBYKE-ofadcg-ownNer-of9XAU-ofacnk-owBZTb-ofacpz-ofajmk-ouC46E-ofaeGu-6XnhwZ-89wNEi-89A8yA-89zZDu-89wWe2-89wRLR-89wJ7T-89wTpg" title="Crossing of one of the ridges ended up as a muddy wade through a bed of reeds and what not, while being chased by a flight of hungry horse flies - part of the game :)"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3881/14600027980_0567d7110c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Crossing of one of the ridges ended up as a muddy wade through a bed of reeds and what not, while being chased by a flight of hungry horse flies - part of the game :)" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="london-tokyo-stockholm-and-onwards">London, Tokyo, Stockholm and onwards!</h2>

<p>Liked this Outdoor Guide to Vaasa, but you’re more likely to visit Stockholm, Tokyo and San Francisco next? Well, you’re in luck! Direct your browser to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/outdoor-guide-directory.html">Outdoor Guide Directory</a> and check out the other Guides from across the globe!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Gear from the Cottages 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T22:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What new gear can you expect to see from the ultralight cottages in 2015? We have talked with our sources and deliver you the lightest and finest new gear for 2015!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16240736587" title="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7455/16240736587_ee1a0957b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="685" alt="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Remember your roots,</strong> they say. Our roots are in ultralight backpacking. We have spread the gospel about ultralight backpacking since a long time, have <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/interviews/">interviewed cottage manufacturers</a> and used a lot of ultralight kit on our hikes and treks. And even when I nowadays am attending the big outdoor trade fairs like <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/ispo-news-2014.html">ISPO</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor</a>, it’s the new gear from the cottages that I am most excited about. And so <a href="http://hrxxlight.com">Benjamin</a> and me again set out to ask Cottage Manufacturers about the new gear they have been developing, prototyping and testing in the last months and are now ready to release to you. So here we are, and we wish you a lot of fun checking out the <strong>New Gear from the Cottages 2015</strong>!</p>

<p><em>You have a cottage and should be on this list with your new gear? <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Email me</a> and I’ll add you!</em> </p>

<h2 id="locus-gear">Locus Gear</h2>

<p>Jotaro and the team at <a href="http://locusgear.com">Locus Gear</a> have been dreaming big. Big in two ways: A ultralight, breathable dome tent for the winter mountains and a massive 8 Person shelter. The Djedi eVent Dome Shelter sleeps 2 persons, is 2,3 m long and 1,3 m wide with a height of 1 m and will tip the scales at 1,2 kg with the poles included. It looks like a spacious mountain shelter and being made from eVent you know it will be breathable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425702462" title="Locus Gear Djedi eVent Dome by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7321/16425702462_abcb9f94df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Locus Gear Djedi eVent Dome" /></a></p>

<p>I dubbed it the “Party Tent” as I saw the Prototype Photos on the Locus Gear Instagram stream and I still think that the Soris Sil Shelter could be that. Or a great group tent for scouts, a family with kids, or a a handful of hiking buddies. It can sleep six to eight persons and is pitched with two poles - and it is huge: 6 m long, 3 m wide and 1,8 m high. But it only weighs in at 1,7 kg (without poles, stakes and extra guylines) which, if broken down on the number of people it can sleep, is very light (283 g per person if there’s six in it!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239236370" title="Locus Gear Soris Sil Shelter 149 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7458/16239236370_73bae29845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Soris Sil Shelter 149" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hanchor">Hanchor</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.hanchor.com/">Hanchor</a> releases two new backpacks in 2015 which are currently in the prototyping stage. The Marble is a 65 l roll-top closure pack that will weigh around 918 g (or 1032 g with aluminum stays). Made from XPac vx07 it has a backpanel that allows for some ventilation. Horizontal seams of the Marble are folded to the upper side to make it more waterproof though they are not seam taped, while the seam between bottom panel and the body are seam taped with wide webbing from the outside to prevent water coming in. It can carry a lot of gear, too: It has one large Kangaroo pocket, 2 side pockets, 2 hip pockets and 2 daisy chains for attaching shock cord, accessories and gear. The two aluminum stays are removable, as is the padded hip belt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15804131964" title="Hanchor Marble by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8651/15804131964_ca206f9d87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hanchor Marble" /></a></p>

<p>The Chert on the other hand is a 51 l pack that will be made from XPac wx20 and has a removable frame pad and stays which will weigh in at 847 g or 961 g with the aluminum stays. It also comes with a lot of features: A roll top closure, 2 daisy chains for shock cord, accessories and gear, 2 removable aluminum stays, a removable, padded hip belt, 4 gear loops and straps and buckles for attaching ice axes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238994458" title="Hanchor Chert by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/16238994458_9a3d5dfa5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hanchor Chert" /></a></p>

<p>The guys at Hanchor are also working on a new version of their patents-pending, built-in chock sock chalk bag. The opening of the built in chalk sock is constructed with a circular plastic ring that makes it super easy to fill in the chalk and the amount of chalk coming out is enhanced. If you can’t wait for it to come out, have a look at their <a href="http://www.hanchor.com/products/SUL%20Series/Steam_drawstring_backpack?locale=en">STEAM Cuben drawstring pack</a> which came out last December.</p>

<h2 id="porcelain-rocket">Porcelain Rocket</h2>

<p>The big news from <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com">Porcelain Rocket</a> is that they just opened a Workshop in the USA which will be manufacturing their most popular items in the most popular colours, decreasing lead times and making shipping within the States easier. There’s still the option for the custom gear you can dream up, with the usual lead times =)</p>

<p>New this years is the MCA Handlebar System which replaces the PR Mission Control as their sole handlebar offering. It is easier to use, accepts any commercial drybag in the 5 - 15 l range, is lighter and works with drop bars. It consists of a simple series of nylon webbing straps mounted to a rubberized fabric plate which will keep everything organized and tidy. The drybag loads hassle-free from the front and comes with the accessory pouch which is easy to attach &amp; detach. The whole set sans drybag weighs in at 284 g and is made from 500D Cordura and now available.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/53243955@N05/16327109566" title="Porcelain Rocket &quot;MCA&quot; by Sim Works, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7287/16327109566_29bd105424_b.jpg" width="900" height="900" alt="Porcelain Rocket &quot;MCA&quot;" /></a>
© Sim Works, used with Permission</p>

<p>You might have seen the custom-made PR Panniers in the past, which where probably what has led to the development of the Micro Panniers. They’re intended as an auxiliary to the other gear systems for more volume on longer tours and allow you to get rid of your Ortlieb panniers and invest into a pair of these. They attach to most popular racks on the market including fatbike-specific racks, and are made from 500D &amp; 1000D Cordura with a weight of 340 g per pannier. You don’t need to wait to get these, either, as they’re available now and cost $250 CAD for a set of two.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/53243955@N05/16350764831" title="Porcelain Rocket &quot;Micro Panniers&quot; by Sim Works, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7349/16350764831_46d48677a9_b.jpg" width="900" height="900" alt="Porcelain Rocket &quot;Micro Panniers&quot;" /></a>
© Sim Works, used with Permission</p>

<h2 id="mountain-laurel-designs">Mountain Laurel Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> has updated the Burn, Prophet, Exodus and Ark. They now come with hybrid solid/ mesh outside pockets which was done after research on the areas where mesh pockets wear or snag in brush - those parts are now solid Dyneema X. Also the side pocket’s front edges are solid and the bottom of the large rear pocket is solid, while the large mesh holes allows faster drying times. The 2015 packs also come with improved hardware and webbing: The 10 mm and 15 mm buckles MLD now uses are twice as strong as the 25/ 30 mm buckles of the past and the narrower webbing is a lot lighter without being thin and fragile. </p>

<p>MLD continues to uses their tried &amp; tested Dyneema X fabric, which has the highest strength and is much better than the weaker Robic fabric and regular ripstop nylons that some other manufacturers use. The reason for cheaper fabrics like Robic is obvious: It’s just $3 a yard - versus $25 a yard for DXG! I imagine you’re a gear freak if your following this blog, so you’ll appreciate this little nugget Ron shared: </p>

<p><em>Interestingly, the white Dyneema ripstop threads that makes the Dyneema X so recognizable and known for the highest quality has lead to some pack makers now using regular nylon woven with a plain white nylon thread ripstop pattern (no Dyneema in the weave at all) to look like it is Dyneema X ripstop!</em></p>

<p>So the next time you’re shopping for a pack, make sure to read the material descriptions well! Right, onwards to the new gear.  MLD has replaced the Newt with a small and ultra clean and simple pack code named Core, and all backpacks will be available in the new Wasabi Green and the signature MLD Stealth Gray colours, with a shipping date of Mid-February.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426661665" title="MLD Corepack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7400/16426661665_d61f16733b_b.jpg" width="720" height="918" alt="MLD Corepack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806623933" title="MLD Wasabi Exodus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/15806623933_065e5e7684_b.jpg" width="720" height="907" alt="MLD Wasabi Exodus" /></a></p>

<p>Also coming from MLD in 2015 is an Apex Balaclavas in three sizes, <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?products_id=222">Cuben Packing Cubes</a> for the lightweight traveller and Size Small eVENT Rain Mitts, while all 2015 Mids now use the stronger 10 mm buckles &amp; the SuperLight bivys use the new Mountain 10d fabric and nicer nickel zip pulls. The Superlight Bivy Duo is already available and additional sizes of the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=47&amp;products_id=127">PyraMid InnerNets</a> are on the website.</p>

<h2 id="nature-base">Nature-Base</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.naturebase.de/">Nature-Base</a> from Germany has several products on offer which are interesting for the ultralight winter backpacker. Their <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/pulka">Folding Pulka</a> has been improved and now can be ordered with a few options like skids, a stiffening rail and a pack sack. It’s a great option for lightweight ski and snow-shoe hikes where you might want to pull your kit instead of carrying it most of the time.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16424876091" title="Nature-Base UL Pulka by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8627/16424876091_61b77fc790_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nature-Base UL Pulka" /></a></p>

<p>Great looking is the EtaProof 110g/m² <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/ul_weste">Vest</a> which tips the scales at 130 g in Size L! The material is windproof and water-resistant which makes it ideal for your skiing adventures on the fjells, while it has a hood that also protects your head. EtaProof is a material with great environmental credentials, and all Nature-Base garments can be fully customized.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238993008" title="Nature-Base UL Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16238993008_43813e7247_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Nature-Base UL Vest" /></a></p>

<h2 id="waldschneider">Waldschneider</h2>

<p><a href="">Waldschneider</a> is a new cottage in stealth mode that will launch in the summer 2015. Based in Germany they have been working since a couple of years on different shelter designs, from Tarps to Pyramids and Inners, as well as bivy bags and bathtub floors. You can check out some of their work here: <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/1643-solo-pyramide/page-2#entry28601">Trollhaus 1</a>, <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/2296-und-noch-ein-lavvu/">Laavu</a> and <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/983-nur-ein-tarp/page-2#entry30186">Sägewerk 2</a>. When they have launched their webshop you’ll hear it here first =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/16078382599" title="014 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8643/16078382599_0970a80c30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="014" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/16263679582" title="010 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7538/16263679582_169cfda566_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="010" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/14463223102" title="001 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2902/14463223102_c7eb32716c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="001" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hyperlite-mountain-gear">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> has a lot of news coming in 2015 - though keeps its card close to their chest. Coming soon is their 100% Woven Dyneema Canyoneering Pack which you might already have spotted on their Social Media outlets. There are also inserts for the Ultamid 2 and Ultamid 4 coming, Chalk Bags for climbing, Throw Bags for packrafting and several other items. Right now <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-of-hyperlite-mountain-gear-two-years-on.html">Mike</a> and his team are working on getting inventory to be built up, so expect some of these items to be available soon!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16400660386" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Canyoneering Pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8619/16400660386_9b7eaf759e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Canyoneering Pack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="packrafting-store">Packrafting Store</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de">Packrafting Store</a> helps in 2015 even more people to enjoy packrafting. They will start to offer some alternative Packrafts in the familiar shape, from a reasonable material (TPU), a good construction, slightly heavier, less varied (= less colors etc.) and <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Packrafts/Nortik-Trekraft-no-deck::598.html">more affordable</a>. There will be also superlight and high performance packrafts available later this spring, but the Classic Alpacka Rafts will remain their prime product. </p>

<p>You’ll also be able to shop for a new paddle from them this year or build your own. There’s four options:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Anfibio Ultimate, a full Carbon Packraft Paddle, 730 g, 5 pieces, fully adjustable (length/angle), stiff and tough at 335€</li>
  <li>Anfibio Smash is the Whitewater Packraft Paddle, 1025 g, 4 pieces, rigid carbon shaft, full size blades, a real “smasher” 209€</li>
  <li>Anfibio Vertex is their well-loved combi paddle (Vertex multi) in a classic version (double blade), fine shaft and very reasonable specs (920 g/ 129€)</li>
  <li>Or make your own webbed paddle with the Shearwater DIY kits. Webbs, rods &amp; clamp shell are provide. Find your shaft (in the garage or in the forest) and follow the instructions (300 g/ 69€)</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425701182" title="Packrafting Store Paddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16425701182_e436981b4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packrafting Store Paddle" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806595653" title="Anfibio Shearwater Paddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8612/15806595653_19b14b066b_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Shearwater Paddle" /></a></p>

<p>The Anfibio Multibag come snow in 60 l and in black, selling for 39€. Also the Anfibio Buoy Boy grows up in Size and now will be available in XL (in black), gets pockets and secured inflation tubes for 89€. The Anfibio Packsuit gets enhanced materials and will be lighter (~100 g per suit), more breathable (25.000 g/m2/24h), softer (better packing) but retains its robustness and price! The fabric also now is Bluesign certificated (environmentally friendly). And as usually each suit can be tailored - That’s cottage style! Also new neoprene gloves, a lightweight whitewater PFD and other accessories as well as courses on the river Soca in Slovenia are coming, and most of this sweet gear will be launched on their 3rd anniversary on February 15th. Check their website then or subscribe to the <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/newsletter.php?language=en">Newsletter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426633735" title="Anfibio Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/16426633735_23a6f0bd9c_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Vest" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16240402769" title="Anfibio Multibag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8668/16240402769_bbd00aea0b_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Multibag" /></a></p>

<h2 id="as-tucas">As Tucas</h2>

<p><a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a> introduces the new schoeller®-ftc fabric with ecorepel® finish this year to their offerings. It’s not just a lighter fabric at 28 g/m2, it is also stronger, more breathable and softer to the skin than any other fabric they have seen so far. Their quilts, insulated &amp; windproof garments are being upgraded to this new fabric, which I find rather exciting. </p>

<p>Their collection of quilts just was expanded with a wearable quilt: the Sestrals 2 Poncho. It features an insulated collar, which they think is more efficient and elegant than the simpler slit designs. Marco expects it will become the cornerstone of those who are looking for a truly versatile sleeping system that also doubles as a insulation garment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806594903" title="As Tucas Sestrals 2 Poncho by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7377/15806594903_e65805e35a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Sestrals 2 Poncho" /></a></p>

<p>As Tucas enters in 2015 the waterproofs market with two new ultralight pants: the Otal Pants made with a 2,5 layer WPB fabric and the Acher Pants made with WPB Cuben fiber. Starting at 120 &amp; 85 grams respectively they are really light but don’t skimp on essential features like an elasticated waist and adjustable cuffs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238993098" title="As Tucas Otal Acher Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/16238993098_f1c454c4e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Otal Acher Pants" /></a></p>

<p>Marco is very busy designing and testing new products, too: The Zilindro 2 collection of base layers made from a new grid fabric by Eschler is almost ready, a Sestrals 2 insulated bivy is under development, and their down quilts are coming soon, too! </p>

<h2 id="tarptent">Tarptent</h2>

<p>Henry has been busy at <a href="http://www.tarptent.com/">Tarptent</a>, redesigning the popular Contrail which is available from February onwards as the ProTrail. It includes all the feedback Tarptent has received over the years since they introduced the Contrail in 2006.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426661605" title="Tarprent Proshelter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8674/16426661605_09c54b282d_o.jpg" width="640" height="360" alt="Tarprent Proshelter" /></a></p>

<p>Here’s a short statement from Henry on Cuben Fibre: <em>We receive our share of requests for cuben fiber products from the die-hards but have opted not to go that route due to the extreme cost. I have always prided myself on producing lightweight shelters that are also affordable and unfortunately cuben just isn’t. I understand that there are people who are willing to pay but if we’re going to do a product it has to pass the “would Henry buy it?” test and at the price of cuben (and the labor involved in hand seam-taping all the seams) the answer is no. I would very much love to move to lighter fabrics but is has to make cost/ benefit sense.</em> So for a Cuben Tarptent to become a reality CubicTech would need to drop their prices, which they as a Monopolist probably aren’t likely to do just yet. </p>

<h2 id="yama-mountain-gear">YAMA Mountain Gear</h2>

<p>Do you like the opener pic at the far top of this article? Because I do. It says freedom and ultralight to me. I think <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/interview-gen-shimizu-from-alpinlite-gear.html">Gen</a> from <a href="http://www.yamamountaingear.com">YAMA Mountain Gear</a> hopefully thinks the same, and maybe it even where some of the ideas he had in mind when he designed the <a href="http://www.yamamountaingear.com/swiftline-2P/">Swiftline Tent</a>, a sub 1 kilo, 2-person, side-entry tent. The versatile new design lets users roll up the walls in nice weather to enjoy bug-free views, while two unobstructed entrances make entry &amp; exit a breeze with a large vestibule that keeps your gear protected and out of the way.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806594923" title="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/15806594923_3267baebdd_o.jpg" width="1200" height="803" alt="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P" /></a></p>

<p>What I also like about YAMA is that they help thru-hikers. In 2015 they welcome five aspiring Pacific Crest Trail thru-hikers to the second year of their <a href="http://mYAMAdventure.com">mYAMAdventure program</a>. The program’s team of mentors is currently helping the 2015 hikers prepare for their upcoming hikes, which will also benefit the Pacific Crest Trail Association. It’s definitely something worth checking out if you plan to hike the PCT!</p>

<h2 id="katabatic-gear">Katabatic Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://katabaticgear.com">Katabatic Gear</a> has released three <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/category/backpacks/">backpacks</a> in 2014 will appeal to both the lightweight and traditional crowds, because they do not sacrifice function, comfort or design while shedding weight from your shoulders. All packs are Made in Colorado, and here’s a quick look at the three packs: </p>

<p>The Artemis is a lightweight, durable pack with 55 l Volume. It’s made from durable 420D nylon fabrics throughout with a Dual Density, Ventilated Framesheet with a removable Aluminum Stay. The ribbed and perforated backpanel provides airflow while the stretch side pockets expand to accommodate loads while keeping pockets low profile when empty. The large zippered front pocket allows for easy access and the stretch woven hipbelt pockets with have an inner key clip. Finally, dual hydration ports ensure you can keep hydrated on the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16400660046" title="Katabatic Gear Artemis 55 Quarter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7336/16400660046_eb5f583b1e_o.jpg" width="475" height="606" alt="Katabatic Gear Artemis 55 Quarter" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/helios-40-backpack/">Helios</a> is similar in design to the Artemis, but focuses more on saving weight. It is made from a lightweight Cuben Fiber laminate which delivers exceptional strength for it’s weight. The woven polyester face fabric gives it additional abrasion resistance and seam strength. The Helios features all of the same design elements as the Artemis, above except that the front pocket is zipper free and uses durable stretch panels. It is currently available in 40 and 55 liter volumes, with the 40 l version tipping the scales at around 850 g in Size Medium.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16424876241" title="Katabatic Gear Helios 55 Quarter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8635/16424876241_4b8ef522a3_o.jpg" width="470" height="594" alt="Katabatic Gear Helios 55 Quarter" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, the Eos is their 30 l lightweight, durable alpine climbing pack. Made from the same durable and water resistant fabric as the Artemis it is designed with climbing and ski-mountaineering in mind. The compression straps allow for carrying skis while the front daisy chain and bungee securely carry ice tools and crampons. The webbing waist belt, compression straps, ice tool bungee, and aluminum stay can be removed when not needed - saving weight when you wanna go really fast &amp; light, but the padded bottom adds durability while carrying a climbing rack. The extension collar expands capacity to 39 l and the zippered inner security pocket with key hook stores your wallet and keys while you’re climbing your Dawn Wall. Finally, major seams are sewn with Dyneema thread for maximum seam strength. Expect this pack to last!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425700432" title="Katabatic Gear Eos 30 Tool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7403/16425700432_3234424f01_o.jpg" width="466" height="554" alt="Katabatic Gear Eos 30 Tool" /></a></p>

<h2 id="yamatomichi">YAMATOMICHI</h2>

<p><a href="http://yamatomichi.com">YAMATOMICHI</a> is also one of the fine Japanese cottages which add style to the ultralight + functionality equation. Right now in the prototyping stage are their YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap, the U.L.Backpack No.3 and their 5-Pockets Long pants. Here’s a couple of photos to get you curious, with the gear coming out in March.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239235120" title="YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7365/16239235120_a5f60764ca_o.jpg" width="640" height="640" alt="YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239235200" title="YAMATOMICHI U.L.Backpack No.3 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7300/16239235200_e90cae49b8_o.jpg" width="640" height="640" alt="YAMATOMICHI U.L.Backpack No.3" /></a></p>

<h2 id="terra-rosa-gear">Terra Rosa Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.terrarosagear.com">Terra Rosa Gear</a> is teaming up with Australian DIY supplier and hammock maker <a href="http://www.tiergear.com.au">Tier Gear</a> for a hammock tarp. It will be available as a package with the Tier Gear hammock shortly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15812036024" title="TRG Tarp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7404/15812036024_7300e9bf2e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="TRG Tarp" /></a></p>

<h2 id="underground-quilts">Underground Quilts</h2>

<p><a href="http://undergroundquilts.com/">Underground Quilts</a> has several new items coming in 2015. Just a month ago they released their <a href="http://undergroundquilts.com/renegade/default.html">RENEGADE TQ</a>. The cold weather quilt uses a combination of vertical and horizontal chambers and can be made with your choice of HyperDRY 800/ 850 fillpower down. The quilt is fully customizable so you can get the quilt of your dreams. Underground Quilts also now offers a 10d fabric option for the inner shell on their top and bottom quilts and 20d fabrics for their our tarps - going lighter!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16429141215" title="RENEGADE TQ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8659/16429141215_4733bfa2f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="RENEGADE TQ" /></a></p>

<h2 id="flat-cat-gear">Flat Cat Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flatcatgear.com">Flat Cat Gear</a> has a new website! Besides that they offer a trio of DIY titanium Stove kits which should be interesting for the MYOG girls and guys out there: </p>

<ul>
  <li>The Epicurean Titanium UL 15 is designed for use with Esbit and will burn up to 50-60 minutes</li>
  <li>The Focus Fire 14 in Titanium is designed to burn Esbit efficiently, one 14 gram tablet can bring 4 cups of 70F water up to 200F</li>
  <li>The new TiLight stove is a tea light replacement stove and weighs 2,84 g</li>
</ul>

<p>They are pre-assembled and you do the final sanding and folding, and cost $10 in the USA and $15 Internationally.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16243283067" title="Flat Cat Gear Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/16243283067_4a53feef8e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="617" alt="Flat Cat Gear Website" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15804132074" title="Flat Cat Gear  Flight by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8584/15804132074_ab3b89bcfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="Flat Cat Gear  Flight" /></a></p>

<h2 id="zpacks">ZPacks</h2>

<p><a href="http://zpacks.com">ZPacks</a> has a few things coming soon, like a synthetic insulated jacket. It will be similar to their <a href="http://zpacks.com/accessories/wind_shell.shtml">wind shell</a> but with Climashield insulation. ZPacks has the insulation in stock and have a prototype which right now is out on the trail, but it needs some work on the patterns. Joe and his team also just got Dyneema X Gridstop fabric in stock and a prototyp Arc Blast and Arc Zip backpacks are being tested right now - expect some photos later this week. Finally Joe is working in a Dyneema pack that can handle 35-40 lbs. There will be some changes to their frame system and more padding on the belt and straps . again, a prototyp is being tested as I write this, so expect some news on it later on. What’s available already since last November is their <a href="http://zpacks.com/shelter/altaplex.shtml">Altaplex shelter</a>. The whole system weighs in at 479 g and is very versatile in use.</p>

<h2 id="warbonnet-outdoors">Warbonnet Outdoors</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.warbonnetoutdoors.com">Warbonnet Outdoors</a> is working on a new Camo pattern specifically designed for larger items like tarps and hopes to have it available later this spring. This should be pretty interesting for the hunters and Bushcrafters out there, so keep your eyes on the Warbonnet website this spring.</p>

<h2 id="more">More</h2>

<p>Cottage Manufacturers are busy people - some are just now out hiking, other’s are finishing up your gear. That’s why not every cottage is on this list. It’s a living document, though, and likely will be updated a couple of times during the next few days while more companies are added. Either check back at the end of the week or follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> where I will announce updates.</p>

<p>And if you liked this article, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> =)</p>

<p><strong>Want more gear news?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> &amp; <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a> for gear reviews and previews!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking &amp; Scrambling in the Polish Tatras - Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-03T10:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">climbing &amp; mountaineering in the Polish Tatras</a> to hiking and backpacking. In the rain &amp; sunshine, up high in the mountains and low in the valleys.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397717831" title="Focus on the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397717831_9014d3f632_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Focus on the rain" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rain--misery">Rain &amp; Misery</h2>

<p>As we wake up at the <a href="http://www.piecstawow.pl/en/">Przedni Staw Polski Refuge</a> and I look out from my window the mist hides the mountains and the rain drops leave little circles on the lake. Everything is wet. Marcin and I silently get out of bed and move to the big common room, give in our orders for breakfast and enjoy the tasty food that comes through the small window from the kitchen. Slowly it gets busy, people packing, but with the rain keeping up a constant drum on the roof none leave the hut. At ten we’re the first ones to venture outside, curious looks on us in our rain gear, and as Marcin tells where we headed people just look even more confused.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214238360" title="A look back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214238360_3bfa19dbfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin gave me a few options: Walk the easy trail through the valley to the Schronisko Murowaniec refuge, or the shorter but high route across a pass at the end Orla Perć. We had light packs, good gear and so it was easy to make the decision to go via the pass. I either way was a bit disappointed that we didn’t take my original route, but plans are plans: Drawn on paper, dreamed up looking over maps in the warm comfort of home. When the weather turns it’s best to adapt them and stay safe - something I can now say in hindsight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400893955" title="Crossing snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15400893955_db1585c08f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crossing snow" /></a></p>

<p>We walk by the mist-enshrouded lakes, cross the stream via the little bridge and hear the waterfall thunder down towards the valley while we slowly ascend. I carry my camera underneath my jacket so I can keep on making photos, but in the drizzle and thick mist there isn’t much to see. We cross small streams, old snow, and steadily keep on walking uphill. Once in a while the mist has a gap and we can see a bit further - the other side of the valley, further up, down the valley.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397714501" title="Slippery by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/15397714501_32e8d0e031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slippery" /></a></p>

<p>To be able to continue to take photos I left <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hestra/">my gloves</a> in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">my pack</a> - a decision I regret the higher and windier it gets. I also ponder why I decided to put on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1BD2sfW">Alpha Comp Jacket</a> instead of my <a href="http://bit.ly/1rRRHpb">Patagonia Alpine Houdini</a> rain jacket as I start the get wet inside - or then it’s the sweat from hiking and scrambling up? At least I’m warm and the jacket and pants keep the wind outside. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214147809" title="Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/15214147809_699c6e2391_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up" /></a></p>

<p>We scramble up steep passages, rain and small streams making things slippery - it’s a good thing I’m wearing my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a> boots, that way I have good grip on the wet rocks and half-way dry &amp; warm feet. Soaked we arrive at the pass and the wind howls past us. I shelter behind a big rock, but Marcin lets me know we should push on. So on we push.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14363720837" title="Wind. Rain. Honesty. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14363720837_7ac4627792_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wind. Rain. Honesty." /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400901985" title="At the top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/15400901985_9d8d44d8b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the top" /></a></p>

<p>On the way up I thought about how nice it will be to go down in the downwind side. But I must have misunderstood Marcin, as we hike down on wet talus fields on the upwind side. At a narrow stretch of path between the talus I finally decide to go search for my gloves in my pack, as my hands started to be just too damn cold in the strong wind. When I finally have managed to get my soaking wet &amp; cold hands in the gloves they need a moment to warm up, but then it’s infinitely more comfortable. The same time I pack away my camera, so I can concentrate on the path. We down climbing a few sections and then slowly are getting lower. </p>

<p>We hike over snowfields and I can believe it as down, out of the treacherous wind, we see a solitary figuring coming our way, wearing a Poncho. Marcin chats with him, and as we continue to walk I hear a similar story like the ones I have heard the days before: First time in the mountains, wants to continue to the hut we started out from. A bit later we meet a couple who also have the same plan and think that now they’re at least three if they catch up with the guy, which makes it a bit safer. We pass a high-alpine lake and low pines are starting to appear. <em>“Not long anymore”</em> Marcin tells me - he must see that I’m not feeling too great: By now I’m drenched. Soon we are walking through a pretty pine forest in the mist. After a final small uphill we stand in front of the massive <a href="http://www.murowaniec.e-tatry.pl">Schronisko Murowaniec refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214246510" title="Schronisko Murowaniec by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15214246510_1e268ebe57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schronisko Murowaniec" /></a></p>

<p>We head inside and it is full of people - some dressed in dry clothes, others looking just as wet &amp; miserable as we. Marcin shows me the drying wall, where I hang my wet gear after I slipped into my dry layers. Then it’s feasting time - I’m starving and munch away a soup and pancakes, a hot tea and coffee give more warmth. We sit for a while at the hut, with people coming and going. My clothes still moist but a bit drier I put them back on after almost two hours inside. Outside it’s still as misty as before, but the rain has become just the faintest drizzle. </p>

<p>Steadily we go down, soon the rain stops while the mist lingers on. We descend on paths that get broader and broader to a wide meadow. The mist mixes with the clouds and hangs above us while we walk towards Kuznice, a suburb of Zakopane and the start of a gondola up to Kasprowy Wierch.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214316898" title="Down by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15214316898_c764198aa9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Down" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214153899" title="Green under grey by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214153899_189ef3dfff_b.jpg" width="863" height="1024" alt="Green under grey" /></a></p>

<p>Here Marcin and I separate for a while - he needs to run an errand in town and hopes to catch a bus from here - we’ll meet up at the refuge later. After checking out the the small settlement with the gondola station and resisting buying some more food I hike up the broad cobblestone trail and take the first possibility into the forest.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400906185" title="Cobblestone by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15400906185_c9f9fbcb40_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cobblestone" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214397527" title="Fast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214397527_125435355d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fast" /></a></p>

<p>There’s several possibilities to visit shrines and monasteries along the trail, but I just want to reach the refuge to finally strip out of all the moist clothes, take a hot shower, dress in dry clothes and eat some good food. But the scenery is lovely on the way, and so I stop here and there to take photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400582682" title="Tranquility by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3915/15400582682_cba7c400f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tranquility" /></a></p>

<p>As the forest disappears another wide meadow comes into view, with the pretty <a href="http://schroniska.pttk.pl/kondratowa/pl">Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali refuge</a> sitting at its side. I go in and am welcomed by smiling faces in the common room. While I don’t speak a word of Polish I still am able to communicate with the wonderful owners of the refuge and she shows me the room I am staying in. I put down my pack, get rid of the wet clothes and then just am for a moment. Then the rest of the evening is just as I imagined it would be: Hot shower, dry, warm clothes, good food, early to bed. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214400107" title="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/15214400107_6ca4d4a074_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ridges-and-summits">Ridges and Summits</h2>

<p>I slept great after the day before, and as we get up at 6 in the morning the sky is blue and the sun is already shining across the summits opposite my window. Marcin and I head silently down, where the two ladies of the refuge have a breakfast waiting for us! We eat, pack, and are out of the hut by 7 and make our way to the pass.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214320388" title="Up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214320388_576117b4da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>The sky is blue with the occasional white cloud running across it and we quickly are hot from the sun and hiking. At the final spring we refill the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/platypus/?pid=81">Platypus</a> bottles with cold, clear water and then walk on. Soon we are at the pass where we drop our packs into the shrubbery and almost run up to Giewont, so light we are!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397733501" title="Further up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3866/15397733501_cb1086ff52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Further up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377897226" title="Final bit up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15377897226_c0ec8a1c1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Final bit up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214268900" title="Summit of Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3848/15214268900_d99bdd983e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit of Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400602172" title="Down from Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3853/15400602172_b9e263692a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Down from Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>It doesn’t take us long and we’re standing on the summit, underneath the massive iron cross which can be seen from Zakopane. The views are hazy but good nevertheless: Zakopane towards the north with the small villages surrounding the city towards east &amp; west, and you even can glimpse into Slovakia from here. On the way down we encounter a lonely, old chamois and then soon are back at our packs. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214337218" title="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/15214337218_b8187c6356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377902416" title="A look down at the valley by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/15377902416_901ef59a4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look down at the valley" /></a></p>

<p>The trail to Kondracka Kopa is a long, steady climb over a wide ridge. Clouds float over the ridge and surroundings summits, while alpine flowers are adding bright colours to the grey &amp; white of the sky. On my left I can see the lower hills of the Tatras and the meadow and refuge we slept in last night, and on the left zig-zags the trail down to the meadow from my original route. It does not take long and we’re on the summit of Kondracka Kopa, and now we will walk on the border of Poland and Slovakia while ticking off the next few summits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214340958" title="Along the border by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15214340958_71b3d109f2_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Along the border" /></a></p>

<p>We stay now almost all the time above 2000 m elevation while we hike in the clouds from Kondracka Kopa to Malolaczniak, Krzesanica, Ciemniak and then Twarda Kopa. Once in a while the clouds rip open and we can see the lower Tatras in Slovakia, narrow valleys, high walls, streams running towards the far off sea. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214423037" title="Towards Twarda Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3844/15214423037_2c456098d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Towards Twarda Kopa" /></a></p>

<p>From Twarda Kopa we can see Giemont in the distance, now in the clouds - but more worrisome is the helicopter which flies up to it from the valley. We don’t know what happened, but hope no one died.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400937025" title="A look back to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2943/15400937025_742b942b3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin waits for me at a large summit cairn and suggests we take the green trail down to the next refuge. It’s just around 11 and we have the whole day really in front of us still, so I agree and we take a turn from the big main path and walk on a very narrow path in a hanging meadow towards the Western Tatras.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214191449" title="Down 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3852/15214191449_334c07144a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="964" alt="Down 2" /></a></p>

<p>The views and the trail are spectacular. A narrow singletrack trail that’s demanding and exposed, but with gorgeous views on the lower-lying mountains, valleys, meadows - and in front of us, the Western Tatras. A pair of chamois give us a show as they are fighting in a couloir, but my view often just drifts to the horizon, where large mountains try to reach the sky with their summits. At a turn in the path we sit down and have a snack &amp; drink, while Marcin names the peaks and valleys and tells me anecdotes about geographical features. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377924676" title="A look back up the green trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2941/15377924676_45d34c6126_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="A look back up the green trail" /></a></p>

<p>Too soon we reach the tree line, but the path continues to be lovely. It gradually widens and Marcin tells me that it has been an old road for an iron ore mine, and I again wonder about how much work it must have been to clear the forests to create it. While we talk we reach the meadow and a group of fully loaded foreign backpackers pass us, just as amazed about the beautiful scenery around them as we are. The trail now runs next to a stream, and it does not take long until we reach the <a href="http://www.schronisko-ornak.pl">Schronisko Ornak refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397759651" title="Schronisko Ornak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397759651_65b41d3012_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Schronisko Ornak" /></a></p>

<p>It is busy outside and not even 13 o’clock. I check in with the help of Marcin and then accompany him down the valley - our hike ends here today, and I will be venturing on for the next two days on my own. The trail is now a wide dirt road and full of people, with plenty of trails going off on the right and left - trails which I will explore on my way back up to the refuge, I decide. And as Marcin tells me about the long caves up on the mountains which one can explore my afternoon suddenly looks like it will be filled with plenty of adventure!</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Climbing & Mountaineering in the Polish Tatras]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-26T10:32:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In June I visited a country which has since a long time fascinated me: <a href="http://www.poland.travel/en/">Poland</a>. Friendly people. Forests. The Baltic. Great food. And the Tatra Mountain Range. Plenty of reasons to pay a visit to this lovely country, but it was the latter one which brought me here, and which I set off to explore for a week of climbing, mountaineering and hiking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14810289940" title="Early morning at Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5565/14810289940_6369caa369_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Early morning at Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-approach">The Approach</h2>

<p>I arrived after a short flight in Krakow, got my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">backpack</a> and then started the ride to <a href="http://www.zakopane.pl/en">Zakopane</a>. It was almost 23 o’clock as I arrived at the <a href="http://www.skalny.com.pl/">Hotel Skalny</a> and then just took a quick shower before I fell tired into my bed.</p>

<p>After a delicious breakfast and the best scrambled eggs I have ever eaten I pack my hiking gear, deposit some stuff at the reception and then walk to the centre. Zakopane has a nice pedestrian shopping street and it felt like every third store was a outdoor shop, so if I’d had forgotten something there’d been plenty of chances to stock up on gear. I only needed a map which I found from one of the various stalls along the street. Then I took out some Polish Zloty from an ATM, bought a few more snacks and walked to the bus station - Zakopane is small city and I found I could walk everywhere.</p>

<p>The bus to Polana Palencia/ Morskie Oko was quickly found and at noon the bus left punctually. We drove through the centre of Zakopane, suburbs and then slowly in a wide curve to where I would start my walk in the Polish Tatras. Along the way always in view on my right: The Tatras. A compact mountain range these mountains are a natural border between Poland and Slovakia, and for many of their citizens a prime destination to visit. The infrastructure in place is very good, with plenty of huts and signs along the often very well maintained trails. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856089468" title="Road to Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3889/14856089468_4a9f8815b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Road to Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>As I arrive at the parking lot at Polana Palencia I pay the 25 Zloty for my 7 Day ticket to the National Park and then started the 9 km walk to the Morskie Oko Refuge. Around half way I switched from my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX boots</a> into my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a>, and am very happy I took them along on this trip. Nuns in white dresses pass me, a sight one not often sees on other trails.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042318042" title="Nuns by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3862/15042318042_58997ddf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="632" alt="Nuns" /></a></p>

<p>There are plenty of people on the road and regularly horse-drawn carriages go up and down. For a small fee these take you up &amp; down and shave some 6 km off the approach to the Morskie Oko Refuge. Between the spruces, far away, distant peaks come into view. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042321752" title="White Tatras by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3926/15042321752_f73f0894fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="773" alt="White Tatras" /></a></p>

<p>I come to a large oval where the horse carriages disembark their cargo and their passengers head for refreshments at the near restaurant. People with ice creams and cool drinks pass me, some looking happy, some exhausted, and I can understand why: It’s hot and humid. The last few hundred meters to the refuge I only have my eyes on the grand scenery which unfolds in front of me and I see the peaks I will be climbing the next couple of days, and many more which would make any alpinist, climber and mountaineer happy. As I round a corner my day dreams of summits are interrupted: Dozens of people mingle in front of the beautiful old wooden building, taking in the mountains and the clear lake which lays at the bottom of them. Morskie Oko. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042286112" title="Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/15042286112_f2b6ce6b1a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>I check in, drop my pack in my room and then head out for a stroll around the lake. Finally I am walking on beautiful, narrow paths along the shore. Waterfalls come rushing down to the lake. People sit at the water, take in the view. I am one of them. Bliss.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856084348" title="Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5556/14856084348_ac58545096_b.jpg" width="1024" height="401" alt="Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>Back at the refuge I spend small money on delicious local food: Soups, sausages, pancakes, a beer. I sit on the terrace, waiting for Marcin, the Mountain Guide with whom I will be spending the next few days climbing &amp; mountaineering in this cradle of Polish Alpinism. He arrives as the sun is setting in the west and quickly identifies me, even if we have never seen before =) We eat dinner together, quickly understanding each other well and making plans for the following days.</p>

<h2 id="mountaineering">Mountaineering</h2>

<p>It’s Tuesday, 6 o’clock in the morning. Our Alarms ring, we get up and take a look out of the window. The weather looks mixed, Marcin says - lets sleep another hour and then see how it looks. At 7 the weather looks similar in my opinion, but we start to pack either way. We have a light breakfast as the kitchen is still closed, so I pack a couple of extra bars and then we’re off. To Rysy. Poland’s highest summit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14994487991" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/14994487991_897226ec65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>We hike around the lake, ascent to the 2nd lake above it and see that we are not the only ones. A couple of German girls are before us. A few lone hikers further ahead. We walk around the higher lake and cross the first snow fields. A wrong step and you’d slide into the ice cold lake, and there’s evidence of some of these wrong steps in the snow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14810877719" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5571/14810877719_c1b80e274b_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Around us steep walls and high peaks. Marcin tells me about alpine and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ice-climbing/">ice climbing</a> routes and adventures, but right now my mind is set on our summer mountaineering route ahead of us. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14974591296" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3850/14974591296_103d187940_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Soon the path gets steeper. We traverse a few more snow fields, kicking steps, still crampons aren’t needed. Marcin leads the way, he has hiked this trail so often that he can not even remember the amount of times that he has summited Rysy.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14997563215" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3837/14997563215_33337048d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>He is also working for the local Mountain Rescue group, and gets at times a bit agitated when we pass solo hikers. As he chats shortly with them I can not make out anything of their conversation and when I enquire what they talked about it’s often the same answer: The person is the first time ever in their life in the mountains. Has no crampons nor ice axe along. No experience of how to traverse steep snow fields. But they want to stand on the summit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14997199162" title="Hike up to Rysy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/14997199162_242889170f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hike up to Rysy" /></a></p>

<p>Some turn around and listen to his advice, to wait a few more weeks till the snow is gone. Some ignore it and push on. At least until the large snow field which then is in front of us and needs to be traversed to get to the summit. Which is where I put on my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-air-tech-light-new-classic-wide-steigeisen/">Grivel Air Tech Light crampons</a> and take my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-air-tech-racing-eispickel/">Grivel Air Tech Racing ice  axe</a>. I put my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Sirocco helmet</a> on, we rope up and then front point the snow field up. We ignore the path others have made and take a direct route till the rocks. It takes us not long, maybe 15 to 20 minutes, and we are where the chains start. But without crampons and an ice axe you do one wrong step and then slide down the 50° slope for a long time. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14811061178" title="Rysy Summit Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5557/14811061178_47a7e85fd0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rysy Summit Selfie" /></a></p>

<p>Snow and ice are along the route up, it’s some serious scrambling at times, and exposed. After a while in the clouds I can make out other shapes in front of us. And then we’re at the summit. Clouds hang around us, it’s windy. I put my <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/product_info.php?cat=110&amp;products_id=373">PHD Ultra Down Jacket</a> on to stay warm, scramble to the summit marker and take a Selfie. Have a snack. Wait for the clouds to part. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14994583221" title="Rysy Summit View by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3854/14994583221_a0835797ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rysy Summit View" /></a></p>

<p>They cooperate only a bit, but what they reveal is beautiful. Views into Slovakia and the easy path up to Rysy. Deep valleys. Steep walls. Many possibilities. After a while we pack up again and start the descent. It goes fast, we make good speed and are at 15 o’clock back at the refuge. And I reward myself with them delicious pancakes!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856826070" title="Pancakes by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5567/14856826070_d14f461315_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pancakes" /></a></p>

<h2 id="climbing">Climbing</h2>

<p>It’s 4 am as our alarms ring in unison the next morning. We eat the breakfast we bought the evening before and then silently leave the hut. The lake lies silently on our left as we ascent the beautiful path which runs up on the right of the lake. We cross clear streams, the water running noisily down to the lake. And always in front of us: Mnich. The beautiful spire we’re about to climb.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856082608" title="Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3873/14856082608_23c6383a49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>We left most of our gear at the refuge, and I’m only carrying my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts.html">DMM Nuts</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/dmm-dragon-cams.html">DMM Dragons</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-demon-cam-klemmgeraet/">DMM Demons</a>, some quick draws and screw lock carabiners, harness and climbing shoes. After a mere 45 minutes we stand at the crossroad, and Marcin is a bit surprised about the speed we were able to come up here.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14855955819" title="Approach to Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5585/14855955819_2b5e7f275c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Approach to Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>We walk another 20 minutes and then are at the start. We put on harnesses, I rack up and slip into my climbing shoes. We walk a bit further till the beginning of the route and then I tie in. Marcin gives me some general advice in which direction the route goes, and off I go. Placing gear wherever I can, but it ain’t much. I’m using an old, massive bolt and wonder how many climbers have used it before me. Then I reach a good ledge and build a belay to bringing Marcin up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14855951469" title="Climbing on Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3908/14855951469_a4a7103933_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Climbing on Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>Another pitch and we are on the top of Mnich. On the way lots of scratches tell the story of alpinists climbing this route in winter with crampons. But right now the sun bathes us in its golden light and warms us up while a light breeze goes through the air. We’re sitting on the dining table big top of this 2.068 m high spire, happy about the fast ascent and the good weather. But from the south-east already some clouds are coming over the ridge line we see. I snap a few more photos, then thread the ropes through my <a href="http://bit.ly/1qp0MV4">Reverso 4</a> and start the rappel.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042304012" title="Selfie on top of Mnich by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5560/15042304012_db42d936f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Selfie on top of Mnich" /></a></p>

<p>I go first again, clip in at the large bolt, let Marcin know that he can come down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042862322" title="Rappel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15042862322_10e8af3874_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rappel" /></a></p>

<p>Twenty minutes later we are down where we racked up earlier. I slip out of the climbing shoes, put the OSOs back on, pack and then we’re off. Back to Morskie Oko.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856070018" title="Back to Morskie Oko by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3923/14856070018_a4d994b7cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Back to Morskie Oko" /></a></p>

<p>We arrive well in time before Check-out and I’m having a coffee and pancakes. Then it’s packing up and leaving for the Przedni Staw Polski Refuge in the neighbouring valley. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856065398" title="Easy path by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3921/14856065398_24143e8845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Easy path" /></a></p>

<p>The path goes from easy to steep in no time, and I start to wonder what classifies as <em>easy</em> for Marcin. But then he has walked these paths for years. As we start to overtake other hikers I get a sense of what he might mean.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15039600801" title="Path by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3894/15039600801_ce0db4cb87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="612" alt="Path" /></a></p>

<p>I take a last look back on Morskie Oko and the surrounding mountains, this cradle of Polish Alpinism, and know I will be back when they will be wearing their white dress. So many possibilities. So beautiful. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15042865632" title="Storm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3870/15042865632_bb65f7e793_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Storm" /></a></p>

<p>The weather turns fast and as we reach a pass also the rain reaches us. We put on our <a href="http://bit.ly/1qeJIQv">rain jackets</a> and pants, I have another quick bite from a Müsli bar and then go on. Light showers come down on us, but my view is set on our right.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856100147" title="Hiking in the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5586/14856100147_5784882629_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hiking in the rain" /></a></p>

<p>There is Orla Perć, the most difficult <em>“trail”</em> in all of the Tatras, and we plan to hike it the next day. A magnificent ridge walk, all of it above 2.000 m, much of it on steep, exposed terrain.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856097037" title="Valley of Five Polish Lakes by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3850/14856097037_d825f77c5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Valley of Five Polish Lakes" /></a></p>

<p>After a shortcut we top out on a small summit which gives a superb view over the Valley of Five Polish Lakes, and down at the shore I already can make out the refuge. We don’t need long till we arrive at it, and are happy to be inside as the rain sets in. The large, wooden common room is full of other hikers, it’s noisy and humid, but people are happy. Good food leaves the kitchen, tasty smells wafting pass me. I can’t resist long.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15043223405" title="Przedni Staw Polski Refuge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3845/15043223405_de16d20beb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Przedni Staw Polski Refuge" /></a></p>

<p>I feast yet again on pancakes, have another cup of coffee, and then set out with Marcin for a quick stroll while the rain has stopped. We go and check out some high water falls, the lakes, walk on narrow trails, and then the rain comes. Lots of rain. We walk back to the refuge, I accelerate, feel the joy of running in my Luna Sandals in the mountains. And it feels like the rain wants to make sure it puts as much water drops down on us before we reach the warm, dry refuge. We arrive dry at the hut, but the weather forecast is not very positive. There’s rain and thunderstorms coming our way, which turn to snow and hail above 1800 m, and I wonder if we’d be able to continue the route I have planned if the weather is like this.</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Back from the Polish Tatras]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/back-from-the-polish-tatras.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-01T11:27:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/back-from-the-polish-tatras</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Radio silence interrupted.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14550172205" title="Luna Sandals OSO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/14550172205_4436dd8d70_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Luna Sandals OSO" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>If you don’t <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">follow along</a> you’re bound to think I fell off a mountain as I missed two <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/archives/">TWIRs</a>. But the truth was that I was in Poland. In Europes smallest, biggest mountains: The Tatras. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14548243432" title="Bystrá summit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2909/14548243432_5cbb3e1e26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bystrá summit" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14569427913" title="Cloudy Ridge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/14569427913_af09317aff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="553" alt="Cloudy Ridge" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14548333782" title="Grzes by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2924/14548333782_ba4a5c55c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grzes" /></a></p>

<p>More to come. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
