<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: quilts | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/quilts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-09T13:57:49+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/jacks-r-better-high-sierra-sniveller.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-06T21:03:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/jacks-r-better-high-sierra-sniveller</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller</a> is the Multi-Tool amongst the winter quilts, as it not just is a toasty quilt for your autumn to spring backpacking trips but also works as a Poncho/ Serape and can be used with your hammock. Toasty times!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17375828181" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Reading/ chilling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5464/17375828181_01ce55ee52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Reading/ chilling" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller</a> arrived in December 2013 at HiF HQ and has seen several outings since, amongst others to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html">Lake District</a> in England.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376802441" title="Bed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5515/14376802441_7b2115dea3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller is not just a quilt. It is</p>

<ul>
  <li>A quilt</li>
  <li>A serape/ poncho</li>
  <li>A top quilt for your hammock</li>
  <li>Almost a sleeping bag</li>
</ul>

<p>Made for cold temperatures the High Sierra Sniveller is a winter quilt which should keep you toasty to around -5°C to -10°C, maybe even colder temperatures if you’re a warm sleeper.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17350199956" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Inside open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7785/17350199956_125178e9ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Inside open" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The High Sierra Sniveller can be used as a flat blanket, a sleeping bag/ quilt and a serape. A serape is like a poncho, and for that it has a Velcro head hole in the middle which you can open and put your head through. You then can tie it closed around your waist to minimize drafts. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376162885" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Closed in the back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8698/17376162885_dbf25b1de9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Closed in the back" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The JRB Sierra Sniveller Quilt is very well constructed, with clean seams, durable and high-quality materials. It uses a 1.1 oz., 30 denier ripstop nylon and 800 cuin fill power goose down. The shell &amp; lining material is soft and comfortable on the skin and the high-quality down keeps you toasty warm.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17375828531" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Tags by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7795/17375828531_440530fdf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Tags" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>679 g High Sierra Sniveller Quilt, Regular length</p>

<p>38 g Compression stuff sack</p>

<p><strong>717 g Total</strong></p>

<p>That’s a very good weight for a winter quilt, especially when set in relation to the price. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376164525" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Down under by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5450/17376164525_c009b7de26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Down under" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/quilt-comparison-chart/">Quilt Comparison Chart</a> is ideal in my opinion for anyone considering a JRB quilt. These kind of tables should be standard for any company offering many similar products within the same category, as it makes choosing the right product for a customer much easier. </p>

<p>The High Sierra Sniveller is unassuming. A green, stealthy shell blends in in forest environments, and the black inside helps with drying the quilt in the sun in the morning. The construction is clean and sturdy, and while being lightweight I didn’t have the feeling that I need to treat it with silk gloves. The cord locks and cords as well as the Velcro closures radiate sturdiness, too. </p>

<p>I have used the High Sierra Sniveller mostly as a quilt/ sleeping bag and a flat blanket, in both configurations I was very happy with it. The footbox is long enough for me and it is easy to take one leg out of it to <em>“cool down”</em>. The Regular length has a small taper, it’s 132 cm wide at the top and goes down to 96 cm at the foot end. It was a good size for my thin self and drafts where no problem, also when sleeping on my side. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376164655" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Chilling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8715/17376164655_8c5f7da7c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Chilling" /></a></p>

<p>I have used the JRB High Sierra Sniveller on autumn and spring trips where temperatures went down to around -2°C and it was too warm for me in those conditions, so I think it’s easily good to -5°C to -10°C as claimed by JRB. If you like to strap the quilt to your mat then there’s three pairs of webbing loops to allow you to do that. </p>

<p>Using it as a serape is only something for morning and evening use in Camp, I wouldn’t want to wear it while moving throughout the day - it’s not very ergonomic. If you’re out on a winter trip and want to minimize the puffy, space-consuming down jacket for camp and breaks, the High Sierra Sniveller will be a good solution for you. The draw-back is that you need to be more careful around campfires when wearing your High Sierra Sniveller, as you don’t want any holes from sparks or such in it. If saving weight &amp; space is a high importance, then the multiple use aspect of this quilt will be high. If not needed the head hole closes tightly and almost can’t be seen, and also has not been a source of drafts or similar. This is a good feature for people who want it, and if you don’t need it it’s easy enough to ignore that it’s there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17168694907" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole closed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8782/17168694907_cb451e5ed1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole closed" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188369558" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7774/17188369558_f630c2f75a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole open" /></a></p>

<p>I didn’t like the compression bag a lot - it does tend to get into a strange shape, and the biggest problem I have with that is that packing it in a backpack creates some unusable, empty space. Also the pull strap you can hold on to feels, while being sturdily sewn, that it could break. I much prefer super basic roll-top closure stuff sacks that are light. The storage <em>“sack”</em> is a plastic square bag with a zipper, which I also felt isn’t the best place to store a down bag. Here I prefer large (organic) cotton bags or at least a fabric that’s breathable. Organic cotton bags also would be more environmentally friendly, and look nicer if stored in plain sight. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17189931059" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Size comparison by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8728/17189931059_3b7cb85afd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Size comparison" /></a></p>

<p>With the sleeping bag I have no serious complaints. I saw that the head end got a push button in 2014 which allows you to close the quilt around your neck so it stays in place, this is a nice feature especially on more breezy, cold nights as it keeps drafts out and the warm air in. JRB also is now using a hydrophobic down, which is good for a quilt which is likely used in wet &amp; cold environments. The cord locks and cords are very durable and big, I imagine JRB could easily use smaller &amp; lighter versions of these without making them more difficult to use but saving a bit of weight. I also would put the top loops for attaching the quilt to a mat further down, though in use the two pairs in the middle should be enough if you use that feature.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193694557" title="Camp II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2898/14193694557_4fe213486b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Camp II" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>The quilt maker market has seen some influx in the last years, and also some big brands have started to make quilts. Directly competing with the JRB High Sierra Sniveller are for me, given it’s unique feature set, only the <a href="http://astucas.com/en/products/sestrals-poncho">As Tucas Sestrals Poncho</a> and the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=42&amp;products_id=133">MLD Spirit Quilt</a>, though both are synthetic insulation quilts. These have the option to wear it as a poncho. A warm winter quilt is also the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/01/katabatic-gear-sawatch-quilt.html">Katabatic Gear Sawatch Quilt</a>, and then there’s several other quilts &amp; sleeping bags which are fit for winter use.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188583110" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Top View by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7664/17188583110_59c95bb036_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Top View" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Ultralight-Sleeping-Bag-Reviews/Jacks-R-Better-Sierra-Sniveller">Outdoor Gear Lab</a> gave it 4 Stars and <a href="http://treadoutdoors.blogspot.fi/2014/11/love-sniveller-jack-r-better-sierra.html">T.R.E.A.D. Outdoors</a> rates it high, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188369208" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - A look from beneath by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8732/17188369208_47fa87f620_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - A look from beneath" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I like the Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller. The Multiple-use aspect of it is great: You can use it as an open blanket, a quilt, a poncho and also as a top quilt in your hammock, which is superb value for your money - if you need these options. If you don’t plan to use the High Sierra Sniveller as a serape you might be able to save some weight by getting a quilt without the head hole, though it probably is useful to have in an emergency - and does not add a substantial amount of weight. As a quilt it performs just as it should: Unpack, let it loft and then have a comfortable, un-restricted night’s sleep underneath it. It’s easy to vent when you run warm, and if you plan to use it as a serape it will save you money that you’d spent on a dedicated down jacket. If you’re looking for a multiple-use, lightweight, warm and affordable autumn to spring quilt, take a good look at the High Sierra Sniveller from Jacks ‘R’ Better - you won’t be disappointed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157652366367951">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>You can buy the <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">High Sierra Sniveller</a> at <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/">Jacks ‘R’ Better</a>. Right now it is on Sale and starts at $310 (regular price starts at $410).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188368038" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Sleeping by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7708/17188368038_aac28bc259_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Sleeping" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[enLIGHTened equipment Revelation quilts]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/enlightened-equipment-revelation-quilts.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-14T15:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/enlightened-equipment-revelation-quilts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.enlightenedequipment.com/">enLIGHTened equipment</a> has been making quilts since 2008 and produces quilts which are warm, light, high-quality and affordable. For the past two summers, autumn and spring I have been sleeping under Revelation quilts - time enough for a <em>living review</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13133227485/" title="enLIGHTened equipment by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3713/13133227485_b870623fb8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="437" alt="enLIGHTened equipment" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>This really is a review about three <a href="http://www.enlightenedequipment.com/?product_cat=revelation">enLIGHTened equipment Revelation quilts</a>: The Revelation 40°F &amp; Revelation X 40°F from 2012 and Revelation 30°F from 2013. All quilts have spent a minimum of ten nights outside - on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/ultralight-summit-daytrippin.html">UL Summit in Slovenia</a>, packrafting and backpacking trips and overnighters.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7783259222/" title="Open Doors by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8307/7783259222_fbc46ab400_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Open Doors" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The idea of a quilt is to give you flexibility and to save weight in comparison with a sleeping bag. In a sleeping bag the down underneath you is largely compressed and so can not loft as much. This means the down on which you lay is material and weight which isn’t performing 100% - thus just take it out to save money and weight. After all, you have a good <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/sleeping-mats/">mattress</a> to keep your back warm. The Revelation quilts can be used as a quilt with a closed footbox or as a flat blanket, depending on your needs. Its open baffle construction means you can move the down where you need it (usually to the top), and there are elastic straps which let you connect it to your mattress to eliminate drafts.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7458/13140815315_8be5a98c5f_b.jpg#tl-500938784263634945;1043138249" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>What’s great about the Revelation quilts is that you can order the quilt which suits your needs best and choose from</p>

<ul>
  <li>Three down sorts</li>
  <li>Six temperature ratings</li>
  <li>Four lengths</li>
  <li>Four widths</li>
  <li>Five inside colours</li>
  <li>Five outside colours</li>
  <li>Additional head and foot weather protection</li>
</ul>

<p>That’s seven options to play with to create the quilt of your dreams, with prices going from $160 for a summer quilt to $565 for a serious winter quilt. Features in my three quilts are the zippered foot box, an adjustable neck closure, dual-use as a hammock under-quilt and removable straps. All are regular length and width.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3742/13133224325_e2185ae526_b.jpg#tl-500938784460767233;1043138249" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The open baffle construction of the Revelation Series probaly was a technical innovation (The Epiphany quilt was a major innovation in that it used cuben fibre as the shell and lining for the down!). enLIGHTened equipment is staying at the top of the innovation chain and is quickly adopting new technologies for their products, like the Downtek treated Goose down for their top-of-the-line quilts.</p>

<p>You also can see that enLIGHTened equipment is improving their designs every year. My two 2012 quilts e.g. have rubber bands to connect the quilt to the pad, while the 2013 version uses flat buckles through which you can pull flat webbing or elastic straps to connect quilt and pad. And now in 2014 enLIGHTened equipment is using an updated baffle system, new down, and added several more options and features to their quilts.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2558/13133531584_78aa5903c9_b.jpg#tl-500938785559674881;1043138249" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The quality of the enLIGHTened equipment quilts is great. No lose threads, clean strap ends, the used material is very down-proof, well-running zippers, and the quoted weight is spot on which is a sign of great craftsmanship. While the Revelation X uses Ripstop Nylon seconds and is cheaper than the Revelation and a bit heavier, I could not find any errors in the fabric. If you’re on a budget then the Revelation X (nowadays comparable to the Revelation 750 although the 750 uses high-quality materials - no seconds - and a better baffle system) is a superb choice to try out quilts and see if they’re something for you. All quilts are made in Winona, MN, USA. </p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2274/13133226885_3348f89b81_b.jpg#tl-500938784716619777;1043138249" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<ul>
  <li>489 g for the Revelation X 40°</li>
  <li>389 g for the Revelation 40°</li>
  <li>497 g for the Revelation 30°</li>
  <li>17 g for the Silnylon stuff sack</li>
</ul>

<p>The weight difference between the Revelation X 40° and Revelation 40° is 100 g and due to the heavier shell and lining of the Revelation X. The Revelation 30° on the other hand is a warmer quilt, suitable for spring and autumn use, and the increase in weight is almost exclusively due to to more down being used.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3751/13133360933_a40b7f9c5c_b.jpg#tl-500938784993443841;1043138249" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Down is a natural material that has a long life if you take well care of it - wash it regularly and a down quilt can last 20 years or longer. The shell and lining materials, while thin, have proven this far very durable and show no signs of use, even after dozens of nights spend outside and stuffed into compression sacks. There’s no a take-back scheme (yet) where you could return the quilt after many years of use, though you could just drop it in your local garment recycle bin and let them sort things out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13140821365/" title="Revelation X 40° by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3759/13140821365_177fbd61a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Revelation X 40°" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>All three quilts have seen a lot of nights outside since they arrived - the enLIGHTened equipment quilts are a lot lighter than my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2009/09/gear-talk-golite-ultra-20-initial-review.html">Golite Ultra 20°</a> and in my opinion just as warm (GoLite’s quilt is not a 20°F quilt, even if claimed to be!). I love the tiny pack size of the Revelation 40° - it packs very small and is excellent for fast and light trips where not just weight, but also volume matter.</p>

<p>With the open baffle structure it’s best if you just check already at home how to use it right. I moved the majority of down to the top in the torso area, and in that configuration the 40°F quilts where plenty warm for summer - often even to warm, but the beauty of a quilt is that you can easily get in and out of it. In the middle of summer where night temps will stay above 10°C I will use the quilt open, and just like a blanket as you’d at home. If it goes under 10°C I zip the footbox closed so my toes stay warm at night.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13141103004/" title="Revelation 40° by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7299/13141103004_d8d8444ab4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Revelation 40°" /></a></p>

<p>The tapered design helps in saving weight and works well with modern mats which are also tapered. I usually do not connect the quilt to the pad and prefer to just drape it loosely over me, , tucking the sides under me - also because I move a lot in my sleep. It are warm quilts and I had the 40° Revelations down to 0°C without problems (in a bivy on a warm mat), while the Revelation 30°F is fine to around -5°C with a good mattress, a baselayer and in a bivy. If you’re going SUL you can use the quilt as a blanket/ coat at camp and wrap it around you, just snap the head piece around your neck and tighten the strap. You then can fold the footbox up and use the strap from the footbox to wrap it around your waist, which keeps arms, buttocks and back warm with the option of wrapping the quilt further closed in the front for a very cozy “jacket”. </p>

<p>Nowadays enLIGHTened equipment quilts can get a head and foot weather protection, which is a DWR treated shell fabric which minimizes the possibility of the down getting wet from your breath at night or condensation that’s on the inside wall of your shelter, against which the footbox might rub. My quilts don’t have that extra, though I think it’s a smart addition, especially if you do not use a bivy to protect the quilt. I sometimes had a bit of moisture at the head end in the mornings but hanging the quilt in the sun to dry for a bit had it dry in no time (that’s why you always should choose one side black!).</p>

<p>My Revelation quilts both have a 10D fabric on the inside and outside - the lightest option. If you hold the quilts into the sun you can see the down through it, and while a very light material it has shown it can take weeks on end of sleeping under, stuffing into a compression bag and being hanged from trees and fences to dry without getting damaged. It’s a good, lightweight material for summer and autumn bags, and likely will be just as good for a winter bag. </p>

<p>The quilts pack very small and loft quickly at camp - shake it a few times, then move the down where you want it and <em>Voilá!</em> you can tuck in. Packing is just as fast - just stuff it in the bag and you’re done.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13141104834/" title="Footbox by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3678/13141104834_5a23686c46_b.jpg" width="940" height="1024" alt="Footbox" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>If we stay in the same weight class, the amount of competing products is limited: There’s the <a href="http://www.zpacks.com/quilts/sleepingbag.shtml">ZPacks quilt</a>, <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/chisos-sleeping-bag/">Katabatic Gear Chisos</a>, <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/sierra-stealth/">Jacks ‘R’ Better Sierra Stealth</a>, <a href="http://nunatakusa.com/site07/arc_products/arc_edge.htm">Nunatak Ark Edge</a> and <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Schlafsaecke/Cumulus-Quilt-250::500.html?refID=hif">Cumulus 250</a>. </p>

<p>If we also look at light sleeping bags, then there’s the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/yeti-passion-one-daunenschlafsack/">Yeti Passion One</a>, <a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/equipment-c3/sleeping-bags-c21/sleeping-bags-c88/lightwave-firelight-150-down-sleeping-bag-p2337">Lightwave Firelight 150</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1i7XDE9">Therm-A-Rest Navis</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1nmDvTX">Alpine 35 Down Blanket</a> and several more.</p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p><a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2012/revelation-quilt-enlightened-equipment/">Jacob</a> likes the Revelation, <a href="http://wildernessdave.com/review/revelation-x-from-enlightened-equipment/">David</a> finds the Rev X great and <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Ultralight-Sleeping-Bag-Reviews/Enlightened-Equipment-Revelation">Max</a> gives it four stars.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7807716658/" title="Bivy in the barrens by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8293/7807716658_859e883944_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bivy in the barrens" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I have been very satisfied with the Revelation quilts from enLIGHTened equipment. They’re very well made, light, functional and pack small for the trail. They loft quickly and I can adjust the down to my needs - evenly spread on warm nights or on top if it is a bit colder. They’re very affordable for such a high-quality product, and given that you can chose from seven options it’s possible for you to design the quilt which suits your needs perfectly. While there are a couple other quilt makers the enLIGHTened equipment Revelation quilts have probably the best quality-to-price ratio of all, and hence are ideal for those that want to give quilts a try or need a 2nd quilt as you’re unlikely to get such a good quilt for such a good price. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157642311751283/">More photos</a>. <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2009/12/interview-tim-marshall-from-enlightened-equipment.html">Interview with Tim Marshall</a>, owner of enLIGHTened equipment.</p>

<p><em>The reviewed quilts here have been <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2014/02/cottage-news-2014/">updated for 2014</a></em> with new fabrics and baffle systems!*</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-revelation-quilts">Where to buy the Revelation quilts</h2>

<p>You can buy the <a href="http://www.enlightenedequipment.com/?product_cat=revelation">Revelation quilts</a> in your own wish-configuration directly at enLIGHTened equipment. <a href="http://www.enlightenedequipment.com/?product=revelation-850dt">Revelation 850DT</a>, <a href="http://www.enlightenedequipment.com/?product=revelation-800">Revelation 800</a> <a href="http://www.enlightenedequipment.com/?product=revelation-750">Revelation 750</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13133228735/" title="Revelation 30°, Revelation X 40° and Revelation 40° by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7376/13133228735_8685d5272d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Revelation 30°, Revelation X 40° and Revelation 40°" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Long-term observations</li>
  <li>Video</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear Talk: GoLite Ultra 20° Initial Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2009/09/gear-talk-golite-ultra-20-initial-review.html"/>
    <updated>2009-09-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2009/09/gear-talk-golite-ultra-20-initial-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few readers have been asking me about the <a href="http://www.golite.com/Product/ProdDetail.aspx?p=SS7500&amp;mc=181&amp;t=&amp;lat=">GoLite Ultra 20° quilt</a> and how I like it, and I told them I would like to sleep a few more nights under it before I write an initial review. I slept a few more nights under it, and am now ready to let you know my first impressions.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/MPouWwXrfqbVxUW1cJbeAQ?authkey=Gv1sRgCP3AxonxzYCB3QE&amp;feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/SrzjOZ7lqcI/AAAAAAAAAio/Uv1RijkwRjA/s800/IMG_1921.JPG" /></a><br />Ready for sleeping!<br /><br />Lets start off with the important bits and pieces, which UL backpackers find interesting. My GoLite Ultra 20°, which is 175 cm long, weights 561 g including its packsack. Its filled with 270 g of 800-fill goose down, the turquoise outer is made of a very thin yet durable and down proof material, and in the grey foot and head area GoLite used Pertex Endurance, which is a waterproof material. The inside is very soft and feels comfortable on the skin - the outer as well.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ahs4KKse-8nq0nC2kfvx-A?authkey=Gv1sRgCP3AxonxzYCB3QE&amp;feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/SrzizXJNF3I/AAAAAAAAAic/aEWMqQnmc1g/s800/IMG_2006.JPG" /></a><br />The turquoise outer.<br /><br />There were two bands which are supposed to go under the mattress, but I found this not practical and just took them off, and stuff the sides under my back when I go to sleep, that arrangement lets no warmth escape. Totally at the top there’s a button, so you can close the collar around your neck and with the draw cord you can zip it tight - a smart system which functions very well for me. The quilt has a footbox, which means your feet are completely surrounded by down and will be toasty. Its a smart idea, because it adds a bit more insulation to the bottom, considering that the majority of UL backpackers sleep on a torso sized mattress. It also fixates the quilt. Finally, I got a bit extra space in the foot box, so I can dry stuff there or keep batteries and other equipment warm.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8avpx5pcXC2M98pW4n8y4A?authkey=Gv1sRgCP3AxonxzYCB3QE&amp;feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/SrzjA8SjWMI/AAAAAAAAAik/q7MSLP8xRC0/s800/IMG_2027.JPG" /></a><br />Button and draw cord = trapping all warmth inside. <br /><br />Speaking of a mattress, I have been sleeping on a small  <a href="http://cascadedesigns.com/therm-a-rest/mattresses/fast-and-light/neoair/product">NeoAir</a> with my Ultra 20° and found it a very fine combo. The NeoAir did reach it limits on colder nights, though, so I’ll combine it with a <a href="http://cascadedesigns.com/therm-a-rest/mattresses/fast-and-light/z-lite/product">Z Lite</a> for the next nights. The solution I used without the Z Lite  with me was to put my <a href="http://www.rab.uk.com/clothing/shell/new_momentum_jacket---131/">Rab Momentum Jacket</a> with the outside down under me. That worked excellently, and kept me also from underneath very warm. Multipurpose all the way!<br /><br />Lets talk about pack size. The Ultra 20° packs very small, as you can see from the photo. That’s for me a huge plus, because I do not like a big pack size (I’m looking at you, dear winter sleeping bag of colossal proportions). The packsack itself is waterproof to some extent, it leaks in at the seam so if you don’t use a packliner or similar I recommend using a waterproof packsack for it. Forgot to weigh the packsack and am currently not at home, so let me guesstimate its weight at ~10 g.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/7aBrybKFj-Sl5w1J-16piQ?authkey=Gv1sRgCP3AxonxzYCB3QE&amp;feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/Srzi68jKlkI/AAAAAAAAAig/ZXz_bldArmQ/s800/IMG_2007.JPG" /></a><br />Small, isn’t it?<br /><br />The Ultra 20° is supposed to keep one warm till about -7°C (or 20° Fahrenheit). I haven’t yet experienced that low temperatures, given that it is September and we have night temperatures of about 5°C. Until those temperatures I was toasty warm, and could have done without the merino base layer I was wearing. I’m going to sleep under it tonight, and temps might drop to around 0°C (I’m a bit further up north and at the coast for the next few days), so I’ll see how it goes and let you know tomorrow.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/W8WNXkHYSlw3eGyt_gDP2Q?authkey=Gv1sRgCP3AxonxzYCB3QE&amp;feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/SrzjoOqgFUI/AAAAAAAAAis/_sQVV0jW-_w/s800/IMG_1937.JPG" /></a><br />The bed is made for tonight!<br /><br />So, what do I think? I had a few nights with quite a bit of condensation in the Scarp 1, and in the morning the areas with Pertex Endurance where nice and dry, but the turquoise material was wet and the down under it sticked to the outer material. Nothing that a while in the sun can’t fix, though I think a complete shell outer of Pertex Endurance would be nice - this might make it more heavier, though. That’s the only thing I can think of which could be improved. I’m really satisfied with the quilt so far, it doesn’t lose down, it has plenty of space for movement, its warm and very practical in regards to weight and pack size. For people who are considering the switch from sleeping bag to quilt, the Ultra 20° is the perfect quilt as it is both high quality and affordable - 180€ including shipping from <a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/golite_ultra_20_-_unisex_backless_down_sleeping_bag.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a> is a very good price, much cheaper then other high quality UL quilts. I’m actually already thinking how I can make the Ultra 20° useable in deep Winter, because I like it so much!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
