<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tarp | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/tarp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-09T20:53:42+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HMG ECHO I Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/hmg-echo-i-review.html"/>
    <updated>2010-10-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/hmg-echo-i-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
Time to start the in-depth reviews of some of the gear used in &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/from-russia-with-love.html"target="_blank"&gt;Russia. I had the &lt;a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/products/echo-i-ultralight-system.html"target="_blank"&gt;Hyperlite Mountain Gear ECHO I Shelter System since a couple of months, doing a few overnighters in it and then of course putting it up and down for eight nights in a row in Russia. Enough nights spent under it to make a objective review, and to let you know if it is worth the money.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/fvnXRe9v6EPxc6FkPpLWiwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TLAcnnAfacI/AAAAAAAADYY/EN8eSX4m_tE/s800/IWG_Russia_0319.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br /><br />Lets start with the basic details, the weights as they were when I got my shelter system:<br /><br />Tarp: 228 g incl. guylines (HMG site: 226 g)<br />Beak: 112 g incl. guylines (HMG site: 116 g)<br />Inner: 305 g (HMG site: 325 g)<br />Stuff sack: 15 g (HMG site: 15 g)<br /><span style="font-weight:bold;">Total: 660 g</span> (HMG site: 682 g)<br /><br />Additional: <br />Nine Titanium pegs: 72 g<br />GG LT4 Trekking Poles: 198 g<br /><span style="font-weight:bold;">Total: 270 g</span><br /><br />The weights on the HMG site are without guylines attached, (I took the HMG weights with guylines as stated by Dan on the BPL forum in &lt;a href="http://www.backpackinglight.com/cgi-bin/backpackinglight/forums/thread_display.html?forum_thread_id=37100"target="_blank"&gt;this thread); also, I got a pre production sample so the to-be-expected weights are what's stated on the HMG site, which are not far off as you can see.<br /><br />In case you're still asking yourself, what is it made of, then the answer is cuben fibre. It is my first cuben shelter, and the weight saving in comparison to my &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/gossamer-gear-spinntwinn-review-video.html"Target="_blank"&gt;Gossamer Gear Spinntwinn is 52 g. The advantage with cuben versus spinnaker is that cuben is 100% waterproof and even more tear resistant, and well, super strong and lighter. As a UL backpacker, lighter (usually) equals better. <br /><br />Now that we got the important bits out of the way, lets get to the tasty chunks. As a starter, I serve today this HD video of how to set up the complete shelter.<br /><br /><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/14928877?title=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0"></iframe><br /> &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TQ75e8R68Ck"target="_blank"&gt;Click here to see the Youtube version.<br /><br />There were some questions about the speed of my pitch, and if it does take so long or if it is difficult to set up the ECHO I. The short answer is "No". The more detailed answer is, in the video I try to do it more slowly to be able to show and explain things, and not just hurry through it as I would in a downpour when on a mountain. I'm also a perfectionist when it comes to setting up my shelter, so I make an effort to get it pitched flawless. Hence the "slow" speed, for a normal, flawless pitch I need around three to five minutes, which probably seems like an eternity to people sleeping in a Tarptent Moment. Anyhow. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/b4BHklVuEkVGgvfUMHQNRwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUPekXRebI/AAAAAAAADbw/7NjoKpjm570/s800/IWG_Russia_0959.JPG" height="800" width="600" /></a><br />Bird's view. <br /><br />I have used the tarp mostly, as there aren't much bugs around anymore which would make me take the inner. I am thinking about if I might take the inner in winter, but am not sure yet. The beak was used on the days that I got extra gear (as a Daily Guide you get to carry a Satphone, GPS and two massive First Aid kits) so the extra space came in handy. Also if it is raining or very windy, the beak will come in handy. And of course one could use the beak as a Mini tarp just for the head when bivying. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/Bxv9Vph0jeclAOhbAr6NvAaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUPkqNTyAI/AAAAAAAADb0/V7rxx47tFbs/s800/IWG_Russia_0928.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />When good stake-out points are rare, attach it to a tree!<br /><br />The tarp is one person + plenty of gear size, though you could squeeze with two and gear under it if you really like each other. I found it perfect for my needs, the smaller size also means I need less space for pitching it, which is great - so often in Russia I pitched in places where there was no a lot of good spots, so having a small tarp definitely put me at an advantage - my SpinnTwinn would not have fit some of the spots where I pitched, as it is so much wider than the ECHO I. So if you tarp a lot in areas where space for a good, perfect pitch, is at a premium, you will, like me, value the good size of the ECHO I. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/ATn64QoKuDILq-BAmREZ3QaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TLAWz-cj3kI/AAAAAAAADT4/P2lJI_aDzwk/s800/IWG_Russia_0747.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/fEnGLe6m4Rh1wm0AOUYp7QaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TLAgB2o0oaI/AAAAAAAADZ4/4H4lhp4HDAc/s800/IWG_Russia_0745.JPG" height="800" width="600" /></a><br />Extra rain and wind protection with the beak.<br /><br />Speaking of size, the ECHO I tarp is 262 cm long, 213 cm wide in the front and 152 cm wide in the back. I can fit all my gear underneath the tarp, often at the foot end while only keeping the essentials - puukko, headlamp, water, camera - with me in the front, but I also can spread them out, for example while packing. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/UbvB3WUYKWoSEZ2vTwHjXwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TLAf_bLowNI/AAAAAAAADZw/xFxjzY9HQY4/s800/IWG_Russia_0744.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />Spread out gear.<br /><br />The quality is topnotch, as you would expect. The tarp has catenary curves everywhere - ridgeline, front, end and sides - and instead of sewing them, which would weaken the material, they're bonded. The tie out points are reinforced and it comes with custom made, that means in HMG's colours, guylines. My problem with the guylines is that they're a bit heavier than other lines, and also they're not reflective. I like reflective guylines, as they help other people not to trip over them - that's my usual problem &amp; worry. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/wBu0ZSgDzcL22z6bTWpRxgaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQYFQzgHI/AAAAAAAADcM/Vc889bKUdmU/s800/IWG_Russia_0332.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />In case you're not using trekking poles, you also can cut &amp; sharpen sticks and pitch with them.<br /><br />On to the beak. A very nice addition for when wind and rain are coming down horizontal from every direction. It is easy to attach with the help of buttons, as you can see in the video or on the photo underneath. It comes with a two way zipper which is waterproof, and it runs very smooth and doesn't get stuck in other material. Now attaching should be done under the front guyline, but I always do it over the front guyline as that's easier for me. You can attach both beak and front guyline to the same peg, but I like to use two different pegs. Also, when using the beak you should tie out the sides, something I usually don't do. While possible to do without, it is tauter and more stable when you do. <br /><br />Furthermore, and these questions have been raised elsewhere as well, some might wonder why there's no beak or wall for the back - after all, when you pitch into the wind and then it turns 180°, what then? The reason (or my reason, for that matter =) is that HMG assumes you'll use the complete system, so tarp, beak and inner. The inner, as you'll see, has a full wall in the back and thus would, if used with the beak, provide 360° coverage. Just looking at the weights, I personally would rather have a wall or beak for the back instead of the inner, as that separate beak/ wall for the back would be lighter than the inner. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/XDWChtAWb8pN4Ym3XN-o0gaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQ0CDX93I/AAAAAAAADcg/saa_hDQMRzA/s800/P1030794.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />Buttons to attach the beak in front.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/httSBqgcXv8WsKUWTjGRLQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQxw-OzeI/AAAAAAAADcc/qHBriiN-42A/s800/P1030792.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />D-Rings to attach the beak at the side tie-outs.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/dJ92fzzUEmoNX_0YRBFXzwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQryvevwI/AAAAAAAADcU/p-pkcl1vRJI/s800/P1030786.jpg" height="800" width="600" /></a><br />Back wall of the inner.<br /><br />Thus the inner. The heaviest piece of the shelter system, it gets attached with bungee cords to the tarp and you can get it nice taut with the line-locks. I haven't used this at all yet on a trip, but given that you can pitch it on its own - bug invested summer days - or with the tarp - bug invested summer days with rain - I can see it as a possible replacement for the LightHeart Gear Solo tent I used last summer. It has a tough black cuben floor and high sidewalls, as well as the aforementioned cuben back wall. The top and front have no-see-um mesh, and the door is fully openable with a two-way zipper. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/bqtlR2O54llyuoimqOpYYQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQwWsFiQI/AAAAAAAADcY/0giIcbAxOEM/s800/P1030790.jpg" height="800" width="600" /></a><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/AdRYPXR70eAXjRoEVeX6WQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQ6LxwLaI/AAAAAAAADcs/brH19S0R9ZI/s800/P1030797.jpg" height="800" width="600" /></a><br />Front door of the inner, with and without beak.<br /><br />The inner is 185 long and tapers from 81 cm wide in the front to 51 cm in the back. It is enough for you and your sleep system, but your gear will stay outside. That shouldn't be a big problem, though, as there's still plenty of tarp covered space to hide under for it. You can peg out the inner with the loops at all four corners, which makes life a bit easier and also keeps it in place. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/El3ltoZeTspIBUo9-EwfPQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQoQUgPWI/AAAAAAAADcQ/D9tfzGxHvyE/s800/P1030784.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />Full system - inner, tarp &amp; beaks.<br /><br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/cB8dZuPz4gqbxX0V1OkGbwaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQAecuVWI/AAAAAAAADcA/Vzsfk6ihYGA/s800/IWG_Russia_0606.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />While moving in, pitching the front slightly higher. <br /><br />As the regular reader knows, I really enjoy tarping, so it is with great pleasure that I now carry even less weight with me when out on a trip. The modularity and high craftsmanship of the Hyperlite Mountain Gear ECHO I is its strongest selling point. You buy one system to suit all your needs. For spring and autumn you take the tarp and maybe beak, in the summer its the inner and tarp and in winter you take all three to have a bomb-proof shelter. <br /><br />What I could imagine, taking HMG's modular approach on step further, is that they could introduce a full cuben inner with small mesh windows at the top for winter use. In winter I'd like to keep the wind at bay, and with a double-wall shelter I even might gain a degree or two in warmth. I also can imagine that it's lighter than the mesh version =) I'd also like to see a beak/ wall for the back on those days where I wouldn't take the inner but would like full 360° protection. <br /><br />To conclude, I really like the ECHO I and I believe it could become my dedicated solo trip shelter. Its small footprint, light weight and modularity all speak in favour of it. It is easy and fast to pitch, looks great, and it is a joy to wake up under! It packs very small and I carry it, like my other tarps, in the outside pocket of my pack so it is easy &amp; quickly accessible. Finally, I will use this shelter during the coming winter, so you can expect a long-time review sometime next spring.<br /><br />The price for the ECHO I is 490$ plus shipping, and you can order one directly at &lt;a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/echo-i-ultralight-system.html"target="_blank"&gt;Hyperlite Mountain Gear. If you want to learn more about HMG, check out the &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-from-hyperlite.html"target="_blank"&gt;interview with Mike St. Pierre, the Founder and CEO of the company, which I did a while back.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/8_tzsXiKBLBabpHzjEIIUQaHJjYRDRV4S5g4VqcfkwU?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TMUQS9RyfdI/AAAAAAAADcI/cOnKmL_OLGQ/s800/IWG_Russia_0298.JPG" height="600" width="800" /></a><br />Pitch on a ridge with a view.</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gossamer Gear SpinnTwinn Review + Video]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/gossamer-gear-spinntwinn-review-video.html"/>
    <updated>2010-06-29T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/gossamer-gear-spinntwinn-review-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
In my effort to lighten my load, I decided to try out tarps. It took me a while to decide, after all we are so used nowadays to be inside that it seems very common to stay inside if it comes to shelters when backpacking. By the time I made the decision the temperatures were already under zero and the earth was covered in snow. Not being shy or scared of a challenge, I decided to try them out just then in winter, because I might as well collect these experiences right then and there - after all, tarping in summer is relatively easy.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/lhdALE1HNVO580JmnAJklp2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmvQaBBi8I/AAAAAAAAC10/bdUoWf_i11s/s800/P1030665.jpg" /></a><br /><br />Besides the aim of going lighter it was also the idea of being closer to nature and enjoying the views. Being in a tent, even a tarptent, puts you in a confined space away from nature and your surroundings. That can be a nice thing when the air is buzzing with insects or if a snowstorm is going down, but only very few folks will find themselves in the latter conditions outside and for the former there are also solutions when tarping available. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/9amM1WVd8elOpuxnBqa1-Z2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmvc1cqIVI/AAAAAAAAC14/hef1aQMXjiI/s800/P1030670.jpg" /></a><br />A palace for one.<br /><br />So I got a <a href="http://www.gossamergear.com/cgi-bin/gossamergear/Spinn-Twinn.html">Gossamer Gear SpinnTwinn</a>, which is including guylines 282 g. Lets put that into perspective with this list of shelters I own (I reckon I will get rid of some of them soon, no need for that much):<br /><br /><a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/04/msr-hubba-hp-2010-review.html">MSR Hubba HP</a>: 1385 g (all included)<br /><a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2009/08/gear-talk-tarptent-scarp-1-initial.html">Tarptent Scarp 1 Mk I</a>: 1347 g (all included)<br /><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4ZsbeJsibRo">Lightheart Gear Solo tent</a>: 754 g (excluding pegs, poles &amp; stuff sack)<br /><br />It is thus fairly light, but to be honest one needs to add to the SpinnTwinn the pegs and the poles. Now, I am not a big user of trekking poles - I rather walk hands free - but for crossing streams and for pitching a tarp they are mighty useful. The poles I have for the SpinnTwinn are 80 g for front and rear pole, versus 200 g for a pair of Gossamer Gear LT4 trekking poles, the difference ain't too bad and the user of trekking poles will certainly use them. Add in your favourite set of pegs, which can be anywhere between 5 to 33 g for a peg, and you're looking at a trail weight of about 400 - 450 g for the SpinnTwinn, which is over two thirds less than the above two tents and half of the LightHeart Gear Solo tent.<br /><br />I had some time on my hands during my spring trip to the north and made this little video of how I set it up on snow, have a look. <br /><br /><object width="853" height="505"><param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/fPKXZfT78fg&amp;hl=en_US&amp;fs=1&amp;color1=0xe1600f&amp;color2=0xfebd01" /><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always" /><embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/fPKXZfT78fg&amp;hl=en_US&amp;fs=1&amp;color1=0xe1600f&amp;color2=0xfebd01" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="853" height="505" /></object><br /><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fPKXZfT78fg">Watch it in HD</a> - click the link and choose 720p from the drop down menu.<br /><br />Its fairly easy to set up with the two poles, with the trekking poles I find it less straight forward because you'd need to find the right height for them - I don't carry a tape measure with me outdoors, so it is by trial and error that I find the correct height. Other than that I can nowadays pitch it in about three to five minutes until it is nearly perfect.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/FnQRtafMYns5mAIJ7nqNn52eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmv8a3ZRRI/AAAAAAAAC18/jUT1RvKfMA4/s800/P1040210.jpg" /></a><br />Mucho espacio!<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/FIuGwkHAGOaLxcV4AEyhXZ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmwK0LAmgI/AAAAAAAAC2E/wCDWqEq3cDs/s800/P1040228.jpg" /></a><br />Side view, pitched high.<br /><br />So how do I like tarping? Short answer: I love it. It is absolutely fabulous, I sleep far better than in a tent, I enjoy that I can right away see and hear everything that is happening around me, the fresh air, minimal condensation, lots of space - there is plenty to like about tarping. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/rQw-C5yfjS4_FXXHsFU6X52eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmzrreYB9I/AAAAAAAAC2M/QOR_3iENp90/s800/P1040247.jpg" /></a><br />Sitting under the SpinnTwinn in my sleeping bag.<br /><br />The SpinnTwinn is a fantastic shelter. Fantastic, because at 175 dollars it is very affordable and allows the beginner as well as the pro to gain a great shelter made of Spinnaker. Spinnaker is lighter than Silnylon and does away with the sagging that is so common of silnylon shelters. I also find it very resistant against abuse, it is not easily pierced through, and there's also not any problems with water spraying through it. My subjective feeling is that it sits right between cuben and silnylon and combines the best of both: affordability of silnylon, lightness, zero sagging, no water spraying and the abrasion resistance of cuben.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/DssmTQbWf31wsDhB_S-RHJ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm-kIUNt2I/AAAAAAAAC3A/x6Ni2uPxgZc/s800/P1040748.jpg" /></a><br />SpinnTwinn next to a MLD Cuben DuoMid and a MLD Silnylon Trailstar.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/OV78g-iTnJc-NX8sGbOTUJ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm-yV4FqcI/AAAAAAAAC3E/8OoOiqNMmyI/s800/P1040737.jpg" /></a><br />Same shelters, different view. Phil checking out the SpinnTwinn.<br /><br />I know that some stay away from tarps because they life in areas with heaps of insects, especially the blood sucking kind. In those environments you're glad if you can stay in a shelter where you can keep your sanity and blood. Going lightweight doesn't mean that you can not stay away from the insects and need to go mad. The solution is a bivy or a bug net, the latter being a simple tent made of mesh, giving you that insect free zone. Another argument against tarps is that they can't stand adverse weather conditions.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/C2LLmqEXxu-PLOqpglhn3J2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmz6ZOHQYI/AAAAAAAAC2Q/AtYhjkycJsk/s800/P1040276.jpg" /></a><br />My tyvek bivy protects my sleeping bag from eventual snow or rain which might be blown under the tarp, or insects in the summer.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/77p9r8E_-BU9gxytSn41KJ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCmz-80VYzI/AAAAAAAAC2U/Ba8v1m6Di78/s800/P1040279.jpg" /></a><br />Inside loops allow for the hanging of a line, or as in my case, an attachment point for my bivy.<br /><br />I get that. In Finland, and much of the Nordic countries, we have plenty of forests which are great for keeping the wind at bay and thus allow one to often find a sheltered camping spot. The scenery is different in the north, though, where treeless fjells will allow the wind and elements to run free and you won't find any protection besides your shelter. That is where the majority of folks will take their "bombproof" shelters, because the wind and rain/ snow could make life hard. Not having camped under those conditions yet, I nevertheless believe that the SpinnTwinn would be just fine and offer sufficient protection from the elements - if pitched correctly. That would mean to pitch low and with one side into the wind, make sure your pegs are well dug in and don't come out, and you hopefully have a bivy to protect your down quilt from rain/ snow. <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/99p0EkV-gRW29BHn3A5cDp2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm0c7ikFpI/AAAAAAAAC2g/biY4OZKTh9Y/s800/P1040341.jpg" /></a><br />Morning view.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/LQm7HfMA1BPmlGXTjxfaCZ2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm-E3n1z-I/AAAAAAAAC24/_bAnEdljh_M/s800/P1040749.jpg" /></a><br />Evening view.<br /><br />There will be those who might disagree, and because of my lack of experience of tarping in the fjells I can only speak hypothetically. And I would trust the SpinnTwinn (or any other tarp) to protect me also in more adverse conditions when out on the fjell. I will keep this opinion until I have gathered sufficient experience to proof this right or wrong, but for me UL backpacking has as much to do with skills as it has to do with the gear. <br /><br />Back to the SpinnTwinn. As you can see from the photos, I have used the tarp during winter and spring, on snow and on earth, in rain &amp; snow and in sunshine, with strong winds going and without even a breeze. Once I learned to pitch it correctly - that took pitching it once or twice - it is easy and fast to set up. While it is a two person tarp I haven't yet tried it with someone else, but I am very confident that two could be very comfortable under it, even in the rain. As you can see above, it offers sufficient head room in the front (I'm 175 cm tall, no idea how tall I am when sitting) and changing clothes or packing your rucksack is no problem.<br /><br />I also like that it packs very small, and it fits perfectly in the front pocket of my <a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/05/packing-your-frameless-backpack.html">LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK</a> besides all the other stuff, where it can dry out when it is wet - that allows me to take it without stuff sack as well, saving a further 11 g! <br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/18UoROMrx4XIi1wFF4Am9Z2eZUFR80q8PS1hkIG7Zn4?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TCm0S4NcxgI/AAAAAAAAC2Y/snfewpoB3vY/s800/P1040325.jpg" /></a><br /><br />As you can see, I like this tarp a lot. For the price you're hard pressed to find something lighter which has so much features. And as far as I know Gossamer Gear is one of the two companies which makes tarps out of Spinnaker (the other one being MLD which have usually an eight week waiting queue), and the benefits of the material I already discussed above. My conclusion is: If you're looking for a light tarp which is affordable, doesn't sag and offers a lot of space, look no further than the Gossamer Gear SpinnTwinn. It is your cheapest start into lightweight tarping (MYOG aside) and lets you find out in the best way if tarping is something for you. I really love it =)<br /><br /><a href="http://flattr.com/thing/985/Hiking-in-Finland-Ultralight-Backpacking-Blog" target="_blank"><img src="http://api.flattr.com/button/button-compact-static-100x17.png" title="Flattr this" border="0" /></a></div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
