<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ItsGreatOutThere | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/itsgreatoutthere/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-20T18:18:39+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get Out into Nature because #ItsGreatOutThere]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/get-out-into-nature-because-itsgreatoutthere.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-08T23:44:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/get-out-into-nature-because-itsgreatoutthere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Its Great Out There</em> has been my thinking since I started to regularly go outdoors and climb, hike, packraft, cycle or camp. Why I thinks that way you find out in this post!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27700551721/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Sunrise on the Kanisfluh"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7180/27700551721_12abb83624_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise on the Kanisfluh" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>This article is part of an <a href="http://en.outdoor-blogger-network.com/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Network</a> campaign &amp; I got paid to write it. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site.</em></p>

<p>In last years #MyWeek #BeActive Challenge you got a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/take-part-in-the-myweek-beactive-challenge.html">permit to get outdoors</a>, and following up on that initiative this year the European Outdoor Group wants you to realize once more that <a href="http://www.itsgreatoutthere.com">#ItsGreatOutThere</a>. If you <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">follow me on Instagram</a> you probably have seen that hashtag quite a bit, because I honestly prefer being outside instead of standing in front of my desk. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26965430150/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Paddling at Matka Canyon 01"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7138/26965430150_1868afd7c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Paddling at Matka Canyon 01" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The #ItsGreatOutThere campaign’s believe - which I fully support - is that outdoor activites have an positive impact on individuals and society as a whole. Fitness, self-confidence, life skills, fun, health, unforgettable memories &amp; a sustainable connection with nature – that is the power of outdoor sports. Add in friends &amp; your family and you will create lasting memories &amp; bonds which you will fondly look back to in old age! I much prefer to spend my time in nature with the family &amp; friends instead of being in a busy city or working at the office. When the latter gets too much I jump on my bike and head out for a ride, coming back feeling much more satisfied and happy.</p>

<p>To help you realize that its better outside (just in case you have forgeotten ;) the European Outdoor Group has partnered with a lot of cool events &amp; companies to offer you some great prizes in their competitions this autumn. First off is the <a href="http://www.itsgreatoutthere.com/competition01-timeout/">timeout</a> competition where you can win two tickets for the The North Face Mountain Festival as well as some cool outdoor kit which makes autumn adventures warmer &amp; drier. Click that link if you feel like chilling with like-minded folks in Switzerland in the middle of September!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23380978901/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Hello Beach!"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/1/720/23380978901_4d30838bf6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hello Beach!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But even if you don’t have the desire to go to Switzerland for hiking, camping, climbing and good campfire vibes, you always can use the #ItsGreatOutThere and #beactive hashtags when you’re outside. Be it your cycle commute to the office, an after-work run in the forest, a packrafting Microadventure at the weekend or going for a dayhike with the kids. Need some ideas how you can #BeActive? Here you go:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Explore a Nature trail near where you life</li>
  <li>Go geocaching</li>
  <li>Build a den in the forest with your kids</li>
  <li>Go bouldering</li>
</ul>

<p>And after that, share your outdoor fun with your friends &amp; followers on Social Media. Don’t forget to add the #ItsGreatOutThere and #BeActive hashtags - That’s it =) You now have a great permission to get outdoors and a superb excuse, too - in case you need one! Have fun and feel free to share your adventures with us in the comments underneath!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27976948552/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Hiking towards the sunset"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7417/27976948552_cefcfdeaf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking towards the sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>This article is part of an <a href="http://en.outdoor-blogger-network.com/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Network</a> campaign &amp; I got paid to write it.This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Take Part in the #MyWeek #BeActive Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/take-part-in-the-myweek-beactive-challenge.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-24T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/take-part-in-the-myweek-beactive-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you belong to the people who need a reason to get outdoors? </p>

<p>Then you’re in luck: Coming from the top of the food chain is <strong>your Permit to go Outside</strong>. Skip work and get outdoors by joining the European Commission’s #MyWeek #BeActive Challenge - and win some sweet prizes, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9362400047/in/album-72157634791158392/" title="Up there?"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7321/9362400047_eaee21dd2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Up there?" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Getting outside often involves numerous steps: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Get off from work</li>
  <li>Ask for permission from family members if it’s alright if you go for a run/ climb/ cycle/ swim</li>
  <li>Then you need to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">dress up correctly</a></li>
  <li>You’ll need to bring the rubbish out on the way, too</li>
  <li>And on the way home, please bring milk and bananas, thank you</li>
</ul>

<p>Finally, you’re able to enjoy the fresh smell of the forest, taste the salt in the air while you swim in the Baltic Sea, get sweaty palms four meters up on a Highball and look forward to the downhill run. This week is different, however. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856082608/in/album-72157645045051650/" title="Mnich"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3873/14856082608_23c6383a49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Mnich" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This week is part of the European Commission’s #BeActive week which gives you basically <strong>a free pass to be active outdoors and do fun stuff</strong> in nature. The week is for everyone, regardless of age, background or fitness level - yes, also you sitting in front of that screen. Just grab your shoes and go for a stroll in the park, take your swim suit and take a dip in a lake, swing your leg over the bike and cycle to the top of the next hill, climb a rock or maybe even go camping! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9708360775/in/album-72157634403205347/" title="HMG UltaMid"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7324/9708360775_3eec0c98f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HMG UltaMid" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Even better, you can win some sweet outdoor kit by taking part in the #MyWeek #BeActive Challenge. It’s as easy as walking: </p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://ec.europa.eu/sport/week/take-part/register-photo-competition_en.htm#myweek_signup">Sign up</a>!</li>
  <li>Pick a single week between 15 June and 28 August in which to take the Challenge <strong>(So this is the last week - Get OUT there!)</strong></li>
  <li>Engage in sport or physical activity 3 days (minimum) in that week</li>
  <li>Take a picture or video of yourself engaged in each of your activities</li>
  <li>Post a minimum of 3 pictures or a video, adding the hashtags #BeActive &amp; #MyWeek, and post them on either <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a></li>
  <li><strong>Invite your friends</strong> to take part - the more, the merrier!</li>
</ol>

<p>I’m so good I’ll even make it dead easy for you and help you decide what you could do:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Today you go for a run. </li>
  <li>Tomorrow you go swimming.</li>
  <li>Wednesday you go cycle (even to work!).</li>
  <li><strong>Extra Day Outdoors:</strong> Thursday evening to Friday morning you go on a <a href="http://microadventures.strikingly.com">Microadventure</a> and sleep outside for a night <strong>OR</strong> go climbing!</li>
</ol>

<p>And <strong>I will do the same</strong>, too! So stay tuned on the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for photographic evidence and feel free to comment underneath if you join the campaign &amp; post your photos in the comments, too!</p>

<p>btw, you can win some sweet prizes, remember? The winner who posts three photos this week can win an Outdoor kit which consists of a Nordisk tent, an the North Face backpack and sleeping bag, a Therm-A-Rest air mattress, Merrell Capra hiking shoes and a Katadyn Outdoor Kitchen-Set - so pretty much everything you’ll need to go out backpacking and camping!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19316551233/in/album-72157653909966154/" title="A bit of Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/543/19316551233_bdc4a09d8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="A bit of Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also going  on is the <a href="http://www.itsgreatoutthere.com">Its Great Out There</a> campaign. It’s part of the EC’s European Week of Sports and aims to promote our beautiful, fascinating, and relaxing outdoor environments and their positive influence on our well-being by spending time in them. Check out their <a href="http://www.itsgreatoutthere.com/takesomeoneoutdoors/">#TakeSomeoneOutdoors</a> initiative to get you started and introduce a loved one to the outdoors!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16729443800/in/album-72157649527471007/" title="Salsa Mukluk in Bikepacking Mode"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8712/16729443800_883ef6836b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Salsa Mukluk in Bikepacking Mode" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>The #BeActive, #ItsGreatOutThere and #MyWeek Campaigns are part of the annual <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/sport/week/index_en.htm">European Week of Sport</a> which is this year from the 7th to 13th of September and aims at getting people being more active. The reason is simple: Participation in sports &amp; physical activity is stagnating, and in some EU Member States, even declining. As being outdoors means being active taking part in these campaigns, and maintaining the habit of doing sports, helps you to lead a healthier, less stressful life.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
