<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Arc'teryx | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/arc-teryx/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-07T23:20:42+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lightweight Hiking Pants]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-pants.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-28T18:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-pants</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Together with a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts.html">lightweight shirt</a> you’ll need something lightweight to cover your legs - unless you like sunburn, nettle and mosquito stings, and dust - lots of dust because you are so fast &amp; light!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6966862963/" title="Seven-legged hiking pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7176/6966862963_aa9a9fffb2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Seven-legged hiking pants" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Pants =/= Pants. I didn’t think so in the beginning, but have realized through much experience since that lighter pants are a lot more comfortable than <em>“heavy”</em> pants. I don’t have objective proof that they make you hike faster and better, but a well fitting, light pants just makes the hiking in my experience more comfortable. All pants underneath I have picked with durability, windproofness, comfort and quick-drying in mind and they’ve seen years of use, so if you’re looking for a new pair of pants - check these out! <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157629182054730/">More photos of all pants on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-palisade">Arc’teryx Palisade</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 307 g</td>
      <td> Material: 94% TerraTex—nylon, 6% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>My go-to pants since they arrived three years ago. Have they held up well in those years? Absolutely. The only damage to them is a tiny burn hole in the leg as I was sitting too close to the fire and a spark burned through it, but other than that they’re still in tip-top shape. And I haven’t been kind to them: Backpacking, bouldering, climbing, bikepacking, hiking, and because they’re so comfortable I’ve also worn them during “normal” activities whenever I could get away with it. All pockets are zipped which is superb, because that way your phone, wallet, keys and whatnot stays inside and doesn’t fall out of your pocket while you hike, run, climb or sit. They are absolutely windproof, dry very quickly, are a slim fit and very minimalistic in their appearance so fit well under a pair of rain pants. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Get a pair at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-palisade-pant-graphite.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/10Fk74J">Backcountry.com</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13XfHu6">CampSaver.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870574360/" title="Arc'teryx Palisade pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7291/8870574360_d19a99c37e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arc'teryx Palisade pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="backpacking-light-thorofare-pants">Backpacking Light Thorofare Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: M</td>
      <td> Weight: 113 g</td>
      <td> Material: 100% Nylon (I guess)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The Thorofare pants get’s a honourable mention - not because it’s the lightest pants I own, but because it ain’t available anymore (unless you happen to pick one up on Gear Swap). Windproof, light like a feather, quick drying, two pockets and two cargo pockets, and an elastic “belt” to keep the pants up (don’t overload those pockets thus). In hot environments where there’s no wind going they might be a tad hot, but other than that they’re excellent. If you can get your hands on one, get a pair for those SUL trips where the lightest pants is what you want.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870106505/" title="BPL Thorofare pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5453/8870106505_333a97a2a7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="BPL Thorofare pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-traverse-pants">Rab Traverse Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 295 g</td>
      <td> Material: 93% Polyamide, 7% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The second-most worn pants, the <a href="http://rab.uk.com/">Rab</a> Traverse pants also sports zipped pockets, which in my book is always good as it is just a bit safer. It has a push-button closure, which is very comfortable and is bomb-proof. UPF 35 gives plenty of UV protection for your legs, and if you only carry one pant and want to wash it on the trail - the Traverse pants will be dry again in no time. A very comfortable fit that’s also excellent for acrobatic climbing moves, this is a pants that is great in the backcountry as well as in town. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870099019/" title="Rab Traverse Pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2880/8870099019_9bc4a6648d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab Traverse Pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="patagonia-zip-off-pants">Patagonia Zip-Off Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 326 g</td>
      <td> Material: 96% Polyamide, 4% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>A Zip-off pants?</em> Yes! <em>Why?</em> Because in very hot &amp; humid environments I like shorts. So instead of trapping my athletic calves in polyamide, I let them taste the sun and wind. It’s getting too windy? Just zip them back on. Patagonia was extremely smart when making the zippers for this pants: They’re two different colours, so no more mixing up left &amp; right legs. Also this pant is durable, windproof and dries very fast, and if you walk a lot in environments where the weather lets you wear shorts during the day while in the evenings a long pair of pants is preferable, check these out.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-nomader-zip-off-hose-stone.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/18x7PAt">Backcountry.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870750934/" title="Patagonia Pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3783/8870750934_9dcbf1d205_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fjllrven-greenland-trousers">Fjällräven Greenland Trousers</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 44</td>
      <td> Weight: 537 g</td>
      <td> Material: G-1000 aka 65% polyester, 35% cotton</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>Fjällräven pants?</em> Yes, because I still own a pair. The defacto standard trouser for the outdoors man &amp; women population in Scandinavia, it feels like it’s the pants you gotta wear when you go to the Fjell. I thought so too when I was a young grasshopper, but not anymore. If you waxed them before you head out they’re OK waterproof-ish, though they will soak through in a deluge just as much as the other pants above. And then they need more time to dry. They got seven pockets, which would mean an SUL backpacker could just carry his gear in this pants. I also needed a belt with these pants, as the sizing of them is even in the smallest size too big for me.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/s/fj%C3%A4llr%C3%A4ven/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/fjaellraeven-trekkinghose/">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13Xglb4">Backcountry.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870061787/" title="Fjällräven Greenland trousers by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8546/8870061787_7a2846ab8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fjällräven Greenland trousers" /></a></p>

<p>There are a lot more pants - but I haven’t worn them and hence can’t judge them. The most worn ones for me are the Arc’teryx and Rab pants, as I like their zippered pockets, I know that they’re super-durable and allow enough movement for climbing and bouldering, they’re windproof and dry quickly if they get wet. Oh, and they look both also rather good! <strong>What are your favourite lightweight pants?</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lightweight Hiking Shirts]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T18:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Summer. What better time to be outdoors: The sun shines, a breeze goes through the grass, a light pack is on your back, butterflies fly by, and you wear a light shirt to keep you cool.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bmp_creep/8698798735/" title="2012-08-02 00.40.02 by b.m.p., on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8268/8698798735_4a8df70265_b.jpg" width="1024" height="679" alt="2012-08-02 00.40.02" /></a>
© <a href="http://hikesinatra.blogspot.com/">bmp</a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="patagonia-mens-capilene-1-silkweight-t-shirt">Patagonia Men’s Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: M</td>
      <td> Weight: 94 g</td>
      <td> Material: 100% Polyester</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>If you look for the lightest shirt with the best environmental credentials and great looks, then you won’t need to look further than the Patagonia Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirts. I love mine and its probably my most-worn shirt if I hit the trail. It dries in mere minutes in the sun, the funk (<em>that’s informal American English for smelly</em>) is minimal and 15-UPF sun protection keeps you from burning (although it could be more). It’s surprisingly durable for being so light, climbing and bushwacking didn’t pull a single thread from it, and it’s been in use since two years already. It feels very good on the skin and you’ll look good with this shirt on the trail as well as walking the dog in town.  My go-to shirt, if it’s not in the wash!</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-capilene-1-sw-graphic-t-shirt.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-capilene-1-silkweight-stretch-t-shirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.patagonia.com/us/product/mens-capilene-baselayer-1-silkweight-graphic-t-shirt?p=45321-1-791">Patagonia</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13nUCrw">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/18qa7T1">REI</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/13nUQ1Z">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717114654/" title="Patagonia Men's Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7425/8717114654_2ecd5b0f2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Men's Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt" /></a></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-ether-crew-ss">Arc’teryx Ether Crew SS</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 108 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 100% Polyester</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This shirt has been updated since I got it (it’s the problem of testing gear long-term, ya see!) and now sports mesh underarm panels, which does seem like a very nice improvement. However, my “old” shirt is still looking good as it is quite durable. It’s a good looking shirt, though after a few days wearing it on the trail it needs a wash as the guff (that’s informal Scottish for smelly) is tangible. It’s UPF Rating of 50+ keeps your skin aristocratic white, while the flatlocked seams add much comfort to the wearing experience. The fabric comes in a bunch of nice colours, and once you’ve hiked up a mountain in 35°C and the shirt is drenched in your sweat the fabric’s quick-drying capabilities will kick in and you’ll have a dry shirt in no time (well, maybe about 10 to 15 minutes).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/16OIeod">Backcountry</a> </td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-ether-comp-crew-ss-funktionsshirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717116334/" title="Arc'teryx Ether Crew SS by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7328/8717116334_8431851723_b.jpg" width="1024" height="546" alt="Arc'teryx Ether Crew SS" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-meco-120tee">Rab MeCo 120 Tee</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 111 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 65% Merino, 35% Cocona</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>A shirt made of <em>ethically sourced Australian Merino wool and recycled polyester with Cocona technology</em> which has gotten a lot of positive reviews. I have found them great shirts, the 120g/m² fabric is light and dries very fast, rivalling the synthetic shirts above. They do pill a bit, but it’s just a cosmetic thing and doesn’t affect it’s durability. Speaking off, I used mine for climbing, hiking, cycling and everyday use for over 12 months, and they still look great. The reflective details are a nice touch which cyclists and pedestrians will appreciate, and the flatlock seams make them comfortable to wear. They also do not easily smell, I can wear mine for five days and more and they still don’t reek. If you’re looking for the best of both worlds - that’s merino &amp; synthetic combined - then you’ve found it with Rab’s MeCo garments. Here’s more <a href="http://rab.uk.com/reference/technology/baselayer/meco.html">info on Cocona</a> if you’re of the curious kind.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/10lOht7">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/baselayer/meco-120-tee.html">Rab</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/rab_meco_120_tee.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8715999439/" title="Rab MeCo 120 Tee by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7339/8715999439_0eccb79614_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab MeCo 120 Tee" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-meco-120ls-tee">Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 148 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 65% Merino, 35% Cocona</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The same material and properties than the Rab MeCo 120 Tee above, I have used this longsleeve on colder days in spring and autumn, and as a layering piece in winter. Because it dries so fast it is in winter quite nice to wear, but not on its own - an Aclima Woolnet longsleeve underneath it is a great combination. Also for summer use, if you want to protect your arms a bit more from the sun or easily get cold in a stiff breeze, this longsleeve fits the bill. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/11eqJNm">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/baselayer/meco-120-long-sleeve-tee.html">Rab</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/rab_meco_120_long_sleeved_tee.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717116892/" title="Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/8717116892_7af29e03fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee" /></a></p>

<h2 id="icebreaker-tech-t-lite-short-sleeve-lancewood">icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 138 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 100% Merino</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>It’s a fancy name, but then it’s a fancy shirt as well! The only 100% Merino summer shirt in my closet at the moment, this is a great T-shirt in so many respects: Even after a week on the trail it doesn’t reek (maybe just a tiny bit), it dries reasonably fast (slower than the synthetic shirts, though), it’s very comfortable on the skin and it too looks superb. Where the synthetic shirts dry fast, the Merino one needs a bit longer to get dry, though that also can be a benefit if you’re hiking in sweltering heat - in that case the shirt provides a bit more cooling. If you’re hiking on a trail where you’ll be in the company of a lot of other people (staying in huts, for example) this one might be your best choice - you’ll smell less and look good =)</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/10lFBTB">icebreaker</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/icebreaker-sf150-tech-t-lite-lancewood-funktionsshirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Ficebreaker-tech-lite-stripe-mountain-t-shirt-short-sleeve-mens">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10008&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Ftech-t-lite-short-sleeve-men-s">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/icebreaker-tech-t-lite-ridge-stealth.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8715996421/" title="icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7322/8715996421_6cca361558_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood" /></a></p>

<p>Of course these aren’t all lightweight shirts that are available. You can get good shirts from <a href="http://www.chocolatefishmerino.co.uk/">Chocolate Fish</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/17JcA9E">The North Face</a>, <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.eu/mens-shirts-tees/mens-tops,default,sc.html?prefn1=productSubcategory&amp;prefv1=Short%20Sleeve&amp;prefn2=activity&amp;prefv2=024">Mountain Hardwear</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/or-gear/shirts.html">Outdoor Research</a> (which also make <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/or-gear/shirts/mens-echo-sentinel-l-s-crew.html">Insect Shield</a> shirts!), <a href="http://www.salomonrunning.com/ir/segment/trail-running-tees.html">Salomon</a>, <a href="http://marmot.com/catalog/mens/shirts/ultralight/216-132-185--4?ft=185">Marmot</a> and many more.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8716001087/" title="Lightweight hiking shirts by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7389/8716001087_df160b3591_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lightweight hiking shirts" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc'teryx Squamish Hoody First Look]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2010/07/arc-teryx-squamish-hoody-first-look.html"/>
    <updated>2010-07-20T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2010/07/arc-teryx-squamish-hoody-first-look</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally have a windshirt! After the discussion over on Martin’s blog I decided it is time to get one, and I settled on the &lt;a href=”http://www.arcteryx.com/Product.aspx?Mens/Jackets/Squamish-Hoody”target=”_blank”&gt;Arc’teryx Squamish Hoody&lt;/a&gt;. It is 141 g on my scale (I reckon I can get it a bit lower still after pimping it), for a size S. I was wearing it on my daytrips around town and to the beach, and also when cycling it is making a good figure thus far.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/09y31j8FdPx4ZHOu7UtAO8flLpbZ7OAcOldKk_ryVO0?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TEMfNAYbfRI/AAAAAAAAC68/os2NPuVMl7g/s800/P1020404.JPG" /></a><br />A nice hood.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/MM3_HEa3_iZAX67zEUN1psflLpbZ7OAcOldKk_ryVO0?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TEMfgLt9-RI/AAAAAAAAC7A/WhMo8aapXz4/s800/P1020408.JPG" /></a><br />Full zip and a front pocket.<br /><br />It has a good DWR as I was able to test during the occasional thunderstorm we had, and the hooded brim is good to keep rain and wind out of my face. Drawcords at the hem, elastic cuffs with velcro and the front pocket round it out. It will be my main jacket on the next couple of trips, accompanied by an umbrella for those really wet days =) Review in the autumn, but thus far I am very happy with it.<br /><br /><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/CFosDRLww8_LCVH0e1qP4sflLpbZ7OAcOldKk_ryVO0?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_TyRaf0hBoEE/TEMgHQ8cawI/AAAAAAAAC7E/_L8Qlvlo7bQ/s800/P1020426.JPG" /></a><br />And it is black!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
