<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ice climbing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/ice-climbing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-03T14:13:27+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ice Climbing in Korouoma]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T10:41:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Korouoma has been for a long time on my list of places to visit. A long canyon with up to 100 m high cliffs, Golden Eagles soaring above in the sky, and a good dozen of icefalls to climb make this the best ice climbing destination in Finland.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595259601/" title="Boulders by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8241/8595259601_a2a1080513_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Boulders" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>My fast &amp; light trip to Korouoma started Friday afternoon as Heini, Mikko and their dog Alli picked me up in Vaasa, before us an eight hour drive to the north. After a late dinner at one of the countless ABC Stations along the road I dozed off on the backseat, awakening once in a while as we drove on empty roads further towards <a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Home">Posio</a> and <a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Places-to-visit/Nature-destinations/Korouoma-Nature-Reserve#.UVK1k1tQhGQ">Korouoma</a>. It was past midnight as we arrived on the parking place, and in the light of our headlamps and the moon we gathered our gear to start the descent towards the canyon. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587936563/" title="All packed up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8365/8587936563_6ac57e172b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="All packed up" /></a></p>

<p>It’s very late as we arrive down at the Kota which the rest of the group is already sleeping in, and Heini and Mikko head inside while I sleep outside. It’s so late, the weather is clear, so I just roll out my pads and the new Tyvek quilt cover I have on test and slip in my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/01/katabatic-gear-sawatch-quilt.html">Katabatic Gear Sawatch</a> while the moon shines over the valley. My watch says it’s -15°C but inside my quilt and down hoody I am warm and soon fall asleep.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8589038686/" title="First night bivy by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8513/8589038686_3efd441cb9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="First night bivy" /></a></p>

<p>I wake up as at sun rises close to 6 o’clock, though as no one else is yet up I turn around and sleep a bit more. By seven o’clock the sun shines on my bivy spot and so I get up, a hot coffee - a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos bottle</a> is a must on these trips - and I’m off exploring the surroundings, waiting for my climbing friends to wake up. No Alpine Start, it seems. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587935987/" title="Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8229/8587935987_4e7d8db06c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Camp" /></a></p>

<p>To be productive I pitch my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review.html">Khufu</a> eVent II and sort all my climbing gear for the day ahead, and a bit past eight Mikko and Heini appear outside with Alli. We have breakfast together, and finally around ten o’clock Mikko and me set off to the icefalls. We pass Ruskeavirta, the longest and steepest icefall, but which we won’t climb yet. We walk onwards to the Mammutti icefall, a smaller and slightly easier climb for the start of the day. A group of people is already at the fall, and they have their first walking with crampons &amp; iceclimbing lessons while Mikko and me look for a route.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596493414/" title="Mikko by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8529/8596493414_81e25043d1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mikko" /></a></p>

<p>After we found a good line which suits us both, and offers a good belay &amp; rappel possibility, Mikko is leading while I belay him. The wind is cold but the sky is clear, and behind us the sun is throwing long shadows across the canyon. As the majority of the climbs are on north-facing walls, we get no sun, though - it’s in the shadows where we climb.</p>

<p>Six ice screws later Mikko topped out and established a belay spot, and I follow. I make my way up, cleaning up the ice screws and quick-draws he installed, and top out after a good climb. The view from up here, some 30 m higher now, is superb - we can see wide into the canyon to each side. The sun looks warm on the other side of the valley, while up here the wind &amp; shadow keep us cold. Mikko lets me down and then follows with a rappel. </p>

<p>Tea time. We snack and drink while discussing the next line. The other group climbed on a very wet fall and would like to climb our more dry line, so we let them and move more to the right. Steeper but a bit shorter, with a more exposed belay at the bottom, Mikko again sets off. While he climbs a Golden Eagle soars above us through the canyon, a majestic sight with its long, wide wings. Arriving at the ledge Mikko sets up a belay and I start my climb up. I arrive at the edge of the ledge with cold hands after having again collected all screws and quick-draws, slowly getting a hang of how to sort them on my harness so that they’re not in the way, as Mikko again lets me down. The plan was to build an Abalakov and abseil, though I was carrying the Abalakov tool and forgot to give it to Mikko. D’oh! Happily the other group is close enough with their toprope to Mikko, and so he is able to just clip into it and rappel down. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596482264/" title="Abseiling by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8226/8596482264_59b61e5f03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abseiling" /></a></p>

<p>We switch to the Revontuli icefall next, further down the canyon. The approach down in the valley is fast, as a well established trail leads through the snow, which at times is over a meter high. The walk up to the cliff is also easy, as two members of our group were just climbing there =) After two Lämmin Kuppi hot soups, chips and nuts I’m again warm and in good spirits, as is Mikko. Again we discuss the route, and decide that Mikko would climb to a ledge, then I follow and then we continue. </p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/62851129?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Mikko, who climbs his third season on ice this year, gets up to the ledge, though as I follow the cold hands, a sure sign of gripping my axes to hard, return, and just as I arrive at the ledge I get a cramp in my left leg. Demotivated, I get down after I handed Mikko the ice screws and belay him further. After an exciting climb - Mikko droped an axe (<a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-double-spring-2-0.html">leashes</a> on Multipitch routes are handy!) and I provided him with a new one - we pack up and head back to camp, passing some of out friends who are still climbing. I take it slow, and photograph along the way. I head up to the foot of Ruseka Virta, from where one has a fine view over the valley looking south-east, and arrive after a nice walk at the Kota and my Khufu. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595387013/" title="Khufu-&amp;-Kota by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8385/8595387013_f40fefb2c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Khufu-&amp;-Kota" /></a></p>

<p>Slowly all the members and friends of Vaasa’s climbing club <a href="http://www.highsport.fi/">High Sport</a> arrive at the Kota. With a few Trangias and gasstoves on, as well as the oven in the centre of the hut, the temperature inside soon rises to sauna levels, while outside the thermometer again drops towards -15°C. Good conversations take place, though after a long day of climbing we are all rather tired, and by ten o’clock I slip into the Khufu, zip the door closed and fall asleep.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595374377/" title="Khufu-eVent-II by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8525/8595374377_49e7f2d121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Khufu-eVent-II" /></a></p>

<p>A new morning and there’s again no Alpine Start, so I too sleep in till 8 o’clock. Coffee and breakfast in the kota, while I am thawing my shoes a bit by the oven. And of course more talk of where to climb today. Mikko and I settle on a small ice fall not far from camp, and a tad after ten o’clock walk over the snowshoe established trail direction north-west, until we reach the Enkeliputous ice fall. It’s a pretty fall, quite short but it’s still untouched and that also means we need to get through the snow till the base of the cliff. </p>

<p>Which is easier said than done. Somehow if one carries ice climbing gear and a rope my elven skills of walking over the snow disappear, and I’m hip deep at times making my way to the cliff. We pick an easy starter route for the morning up the right side, and we both have great fun (see the video) on the route, for me it was easily the best climbing. We set a toprope for two of our friends, and then I rappel down, getting ready for a much steeper climb.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596473480/" title="Liisa by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8237/8596473480_a6035fa5dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Liisa" /></a></p>

<p>And steep it was. While Mikko made his way up without problems, for me it was a real Suffer-Fest to get the steep ice up - crampons or axes blew out, I barn-doored a time or two, and felt like just going down a couple of times. But it’s mind over matter, and so I made it up, over the ledge and euphoric feelings of success were the reward. I made my way further up to Mikko and the belay spot, where we built an abalakov to abseil. <em>Will it hold?</em> went more than once through my head, though as I made my way down, and also Mikko abseiled after me, we both knew that we built a good abalakov. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595377849/" title="Enkelliputous by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8252/8595377849_c28d4b2303_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Enkelliputous" /></a></p>

<p>I toproped once more, and then packed up and headed back to the Kota to get my camping gear and head back to the car. A long walk up back to the parking lot later, which put the Gore Tex Active Shell membrane to a good, final test, I arrived in the sunshine on top. Storing gear, driving, eating at an ABC Station, and arriving before midnight in Vaasa - a superb trip. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587938931/" title="Trail by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8236/8587938931_023b7dfb47_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trail" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If you’re into ice climbing, life or visit Finland, then a visit to Korouoma is a must. With it’s superb infrastructure (short approaches, free lean-tos, fire places, toilets as well as rental cabins) and the beautiful surroundings ice climbing in Korouoma is an experience you won’t forget. You can climb up to 14 different ice falls of different heights and difficulties in the canyon, all within about an hour of walking distance from the free lean-to shelters which are a mere 200 m from Ruskeavirta. Some of the ice falls even offer paths for setting topropes if you’re not yet leading or want to first get a feeling for the fall. All in all I’m certainly returning next winter, and with the ice climbing season at Korouoma going from November till April (depending on the weather each year, obviously) maybe even more than once.</p>

<p>Even if you’re not an ice climber Korouoma is worth a trip. You can ski and snowshoe in winter, and enjoy the gorgeous scenery of the canyon with its unique flora and fauna. Golden Eagles, herbrich forests and great views are worth a trip at any time of the year, though I imagine in autumn when the leaves turn golden and red it is especially worthwhile.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633086621480/">More photos on Flickr</a></p>

<p>A very useful <a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2012/03/korouoma-derby-2012.html">map with all ice falls in the canyon</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.climbingextreme.com/2009/02/korouoma-best-spot-for-ice-climbing-in-finland/300">Info on routes and some beta</a>, and some <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/korouoma">more beta</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Activities/Winter-activities/Ice-climbing#.UVK1xVtQhGQ">General info on ice climbing at Korouoma</a>, and more <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/otherprotectedareas/korouoma/Pages/Default.aspx">information on Korouoma</a>.</p>

<h2 id="information">Information</h2>

<p><strong>Getting there</strong> is easiest by car. Alternatives are flying to Rovaniemi or Kuusamo and taking a bus to Posio, from where one can take a Taxi to the Korouoma Parking lot. Ot rent a car in Rovaniemi/ Kuusamo to get there.</p>

<p><strong>Accomodation</strong> is either own shelter/ tent, the free lean-tos which are all along the canyon, or some of the rental cabins of which the <a href="http://www.lomarengas.fi/varaamo/villipohjola/mokki/posio-piippukota-erakamppa-10694?villiPohjolaLevel=&amp;mapAreaIDs=&amp;maxPrice=&amp;startDateString=&amp;endDateString=&amp;persons=&amp;code=&amp;name=&amp;customSearch=&amp;noElectricity=&amp;shower=&amp;wc=&amp;heating=&amp;waterSupply=&amp;swimmingShoreShallowAndHard=&amp;allowPets=&amp;maintainedSkiingTracks=&amp;fishing=&amp;canoeing=&amp;hunting=&amp;snowmobiling=&amp;hikingTrail=&amp;suitableForDisabled=&amp;accessByCarDuringSummer=&amp;accessByCarDuringWinter=&amp;holidayCenter=&amp;newLocale=en_EN">Piippukota</a> is for climbers the best option as it is some 400 m from Ruskeavirta. There’s a gas stove at the Piippukota and some pans &amp; pots, too.</p>

<p><strong>Food</strong> you can buy in Posio, which is 30 km from Korouoma. If you stay at the Kota you can almost bring normal food and cook and don’t need to rely on trekking meals. I recommend Bacon &amp; Eggs on bread for breakfast - my MYOG Müsli was OK but bacon and eggs would have been much better =) </p>

<p><em>Happy trails &amp; climbing!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Climbing Ice]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/02/climbing-ice.html"/>
    <updated>2013-02-21T20:53:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/02/climbing-ice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Want to go ice climbing this weekend?</em></p>

<p><em>Anyday.</em></p>

<p><strong>And so they went.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8486288705/" title="Ice curtains by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8096/8486288705_e0a48a3430_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Ice curtains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’ve been itching to go ice climbing since winter 2011/ 2012. Last winter things didn’t work out (new born babys tend to demand a lot of attention and wives are less willing to let one go away for long trips) so the plan to go ice climbing was renewed this season. In anticipation of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/01/abisko-ice-climbing-festival.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> I was hoping to be able to visit a <a href="http://www.adventurepartners.fi/pirunkallio.aspx">course</a>, but things got in the way. And even as my local climbing club offered a <a href="http://www.highsport.fi/">course</a> I was too busy to attend. </p>

<p>So when <a href="http://www.valppaus.com/">Joni</a>, whom I met at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/banff-mountain-film-festival-world-tour-helsinki.html">Banff Mountain Film Festival World Tour</a> in Helsinki last autumn, asked if I’d be interested to go to the local quarry for some ice climbing I didn’t need to think long. Saturday evening I was packing gear, adjusting crampons, and packing a lot of food before it was off to bed early. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8496127564/" title="Going up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8112/8496127564_66c5626533_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Going up" /></a></p>

<p>We started early on Sunday, and after we drove to the quarry we walked in the short bit, though the deep, puffy snow made going forward quite a task - skis or snowshoes would have been easier. After checking out the spots we decided on one cliff and geared up. Equipped with ropes we walked to the top of the cliff and set up ropes, here Joni decided for me that we’re now going to rappel straight down - as I haven’t climbed in a bit, I was planning to walk back, but in the end all went well and it was a nice experience to rappel down past icicles. Then it was my turn to make a figure eight knot and start the journey upwards. After a few instructions on ice tool and crampon use I was off. </p>

<p>It was fun. It was difficult. It <em>is</em> addicing.</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/60198868?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="607" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The first time going up was the hardest. But with every climb I got better, remembered the ingrained way the body should behave - stay close the the ice, legs straight, heels down, one axe after the other, use the holes from the tools for the crampons. Joni didn’t mind if I needed a break or was hanging like a sack of potatoes in the rope because I forgot to use my legs or blew the crampons out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8486287141/" title="Tendon Rope by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8372/8486287141_7f341247e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Tendon Rope" /></a></p>

<p>It was a great session, and I learned a little bit about ice climbing. The road ahead will take me to Sweden next week where I should learn a bit more, and if fortune smiles on me, Korouoma in March. Before that hopefully a weekend in Helvetinjärvi, and as often as possible at the local quarry. <em>It is addicing.</em></p>

<p>A big <strong>Thank You</strong> to Joni for having the patience to teach me ice climbing. I’m looking forward to more adventures together in the future - be they on frozen or liquid water!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157632825137162/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="gear-geekery">Gear Geekery</h2>

<p>The ice climbing gear already arrived last December, and I have been playing with it at home, hoping to get to try it outdoors soon. A pair of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-g20-cramp-o-matic-steigeisen.html">Grivel G20 crampons</a>, (848 g for the pair or 424 g per crampon), <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/scarpa-phantom-ultra-bergstiefel/">Scarpa Phantom Ultra boots</a> (1845 gram for the pair or 918 g per shoe, Size 42,5)  make for a very light ice climbing setup. A pair of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-nomic-eisgeraet.html">Petzl Nomic Ice tools</a> (608 g per tool). Additionally I used my existing <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/ultralight-climbing.html">climbing gear</a>: A <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/tendon-master-97-mm-einfachseil/">Tendon Master 9,7 mm Single rope</a>, a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-speed-kletterhelm/">CAMP Speed Helmet</a> (NEVER climb ice without helmet!), a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-verso-sicherungsgeraet/">Petzl Verso</a> belay device as well as a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/mammut-smart-sicherungsgeraet-brg-3.html">Mammut Smart</a> belay device and my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-r-320-hueftgurt/">Arc’teryx R 320</a> harness. I was wearing <a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">POC Iris 3P Googles</a>, the superb <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-research-alibi-pants-softshellhose/">Outdoor Research Alibi Pants</a> and the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-felsturm-half-zip-jacket-hardshelljacke/">Mammut Felsturm jacket</a>, an <a href="http://aclima.no/">Aclima</a> Woolnet baselayer underneath and the gloves of the <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/gloves.html">Rab Modular Mitts</a>; my belay jacket was the <a href="http://paramo.co.uk/en-gb/garments/detail/index.php?pgc=NIKWAXINSULATORLTPACKAGETORRESUNISEX">Paramo Torres</a>. All gear was carried in a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/gregory-alpinisto-50-rucksack-alpine-gold.html">Gregory Alpinisto</a> backpack. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8495028095/" title="Boots n Crampons by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8093/8495028095_4273ee70a4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Boots n Crampons" /></a></p>

<p>The gear performed flawlessly on this outing, some of it has seen plenty of action before, for other it was the first time at the fresh air. I might tell more about it once I get more time on the ice with it under my belt, until then you should do your research at <a href="http://coldthistle.blogspot.com">Cold Thistle</a> and <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/">Nick’s blog</a>.  </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abisko Ice Climbing Festival]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/01/abisko-ice-climbing-festival.html"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T09:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/01/abisko-ice-climbing-festival</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the end of February the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> kicks off in Abisko, Sweden. Clinics, trying new gear and plenty of ice climbing are on the programme - a good reason to go and check it out!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/paddymurphy/8357101058/" title="Ice climbing by PaddyMurphy, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8493/8357101058_15f372dac9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Ice climbing" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Since last year I’m enamoured with ice climbing, and this year is going to be the year where I whack my ice tools and crampon-fitted boots into frozen waterfalls until I reach the summit. While <a href="http://amzn.to/TB6oXw">reading</a> about it is certainly a good way to get prepared, you actually should do a <a href="http://www.adventurepartners.fi/pirunkallio.aspx">course</a> or visit an <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Ice Climbing Festival</a> like this one in beautiful Abisko, Sweden - rather famous as being a) the Village where the superb Kungsleden Trail starts and b) one of the best places to see Northern Lights. </p>

<p>The Abisko Ice Climbing Festival (AICF), organized by the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/">Arctic Guides</a>, is an arctic festival for all ice climbing enthusiasts, so it is perfectly suited for everyone, from the beginner over to those who have a basic foundation in ice climbing and now want to strengthen their skills as well as seasoned ice climbers. At the festival you can join climbing clinics and get coaching by professional instructors &amp; international climbers, which is the best way to learn about this fascinating sport. You also can test new gear - <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl.html">Petzl</a> is one of the Partners, so expect there to be plenty of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-nomic-eisgeraet.html">Nomic tools</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-lynx-steigeisen.html">Lynx crampons</a> around! - and, if you’re competitively minded, join a competition! The climbing takes places on the ice falls around Abisko, from Kaisepakte till Spansdalen in Norway so besides great climbing you can expect superb scenery. And with <a href="http://www.xn--hjdmeter-n4a.se/">Höjdmeter.se</a> as another Partner I imagine there will also be some opportunities to try some great skiing gear!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/nilssonharhund/3643632092/" title="Nuolja looking southeast by NilssonHarHund, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3580/3643632092_2f32d77563_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Nuolja looking southeast" /></a></p>

<p>After the climbing you can listen to interesting lectures and watch the latest climbing films, or just chill with fellow climbers from around the world. The festival base camp is at the <a href="http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/en/Discover-Sweden/Facilities-and-activities/Lappland/Fjallstationer/STF-Mountain-station-Abisko/">STF Abisko mountain station</a> which offers accommodation, too - so you don’t need to travel far! Transportation to the climbing locations is included in the Festival Pass, so that’s also taken care of!</p>

<p>Want to go? <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/wp-system/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/aicf_esite_www.pdf">Check the flyer</a> for more information on schedules &amp; Guides, and <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">book your Festival Pass here</a>. I’m very excited to travel north to Abisko and visit this Festival, I think it will be the perfect place to ice climb, meet like-minded people and enjoy the stunning scenery of Northern Sweden. If you’re going - comment underneath, it’d be cool to meet &amp; climb together! <strong>Getting to Abisko</strong> is easy: Jump on the train in Stockholm and get out in Abisko! Get your ticket at <a href="http://www.sj.se/">SJ</a>. If you prefer to fly, take a plane to Kiruna and then travel onwards by train or taxi to Abisko. </p>

<p><em>You can follow <a href="http://www.facebook.com/arcticguides">Arctic Guides on Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/arcticguides">Twitter</a>, and check out their <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/">website</a> - they offer some truly unique trips and have experience guiding you in the Arctic &amp; Antarctic, Greenland, Baffin Island, Svalbard and Greenland!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/napdsp/6764561053/" title="Level 5 Aurora Borealis in Abisko by nate2b, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7030/6764561053_760eacd342_b.jpg" width="900" height="600" alt="Level 5 Aurora Borealis in Abisko" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
