<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ice climbing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ice-climbing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-03T15:45:21+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T15:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a long, boring ride from Vaasa to Abisko: 1.000 km of asphalt, past dozens of speed traps, trees, lakes and the Gulf of Botnia. Just the last hour, from Kiruna onwards, is interesting, and gets you in the mood for mountains, ice climbing, and making new friends at the northern-most ice climbing festival of the world.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083811733/" title="Road to Abisko by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7443/13083811733_5834be0283_b.jpg" width="1024" height="541" alt="Road to Abisko" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Vaasa, Wednesday afternoon, grey sky, +1°C</strong>. An academic quarter means being 15 minutes late. As Andreas is a student, it was thus just normal that he adhered to the academic quarter when he picked me up on Wednesday afternoon. Packs were loaded in the trunk, seats adjusted, and then we were the kings of the road. Before us lay roughly 600 km of riding till Rovaniemi. Even with good company, music and the roads in good conditions the ride to the gateway to Lapland takes so much time, that we were happy when we arrived past eleven in Rollo. A quick beer with our host Chris and it was off to bed.</p>

<p><strong>Rovaniemi, Thursday morning, grey sky, 0°C</strong>. As I silently get up at seven the next morning Chris, our host, is already up. <em>Coffee?</em>. Sure. We drink and talk at his kitchen table and lament the lack of good winter this year. <em>In the past everything was better</em>, that is how it must sound to people a generation younger than us. Andreas and me pack up our stuff and drive to Prisma, where we meet the third Musketeer for this journey: <a href="https://twitter.com/aleksimehtonen">Aleksi</a>. A few last groceries are purchased, another coffee is drunk, and we commence to the car. The ride out of Rovaniemi and into the north is as spectacular as leaving any other city, and the grey weather does not help to improve this feeling. It’s an hour drive to Pello where we cross into Sweden.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083701395/" title="Road by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7375/13083701395_b598697d56_b.jpg" width="1024" height="540" alt="Road" /></a></p>

<p>I gotta hand it to the Swedes, they at least know how to make the journey more interesting. The road from Pello onwards is going almost constantly along a wide river, which in the summer would be a superb packrafting adventure. Now, it at least makes for a slightly more interesting sight. In the middle of nowhere we stop and eat one of the best pea soups ever, and a set of pancakes to satisfy the sweet tooth. Another cup of dark coffee, and we’re on the road again. We pass Kiruna, the mining town that will be moved completely in the next twenty years, and steering the car north we can see the fjells of Sweden. The sun is breaking through in the distance, immersing the distant hills in a spectral light. The closer we come to our destination, the higher the fjells become, and from the road we already see many beautiful lines of ice going up.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083826363/" title="Abisko Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3729/13083826363_d93a660b6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Abisko Canyon" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Abisko Canyon, Thursday afternoon, grey sky, -2°C</strong>. Merja from the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/">Arctic Guides</a> welcomes us to the festival, hands out Festival Passes and lets us know where to find everything. We bring our gear to the Nuolja Ski Hut, where we will be staying that night, dress up in our ice climbing clothes and head down to the canyon. On the way down I meet <a href="http://www.said-belhaj.com/">Said Belhaj</a> and we chat a bit. Down in the canyon, where already a few participants are whacking ice, Said asks if I’d like to belay him. <em>Sure</em>. Even if Said is more at home on the 8b routes of the world, he does climb ice just as well. It’s a good example that a good rock climber should have no problems translating his skills to ice. This becomes even more evident when Said tackles the vertical mixed route, which he climbs without problems with crampons and ice axes being natural extensions of his body.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083669015/" title="Said Belhaj checking out the Mixed route at Abisko Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7300/13083669015_93f9d85fcc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Said Belhaj checking out the Mixed route at Abisko Canyon" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Abisko STF Mountain Station, Friday morning, blue sky, -2°C</strong>. I open the curtains in our room and can’t believe that the weather forecast is wrong. Nuolja stands against a blue sky, and the first rays of sun are touching its top. The breakfast buffet at the <a href="http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/en/Discover-Sweden/Facilities-and-activities/Lappland/Fjallstationer/STF-Mountain-station-Abisko/">Abisko STF Mountain Station</a> is worth a visit alone, and after a healthy dose of rye bread, bacon, cheese and scrambled eggs our small group packs our lunches and head out to the cars, which bring us to the first clinic, <em>Efficient multi pitch climbing on ice</em>. <a href="http://www.vertikalguiden.se/concrete/">Stefan</a> and <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/">Martin</a> show us how it’s done, answer our questions, and then let us lose on the ice.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083801763/" title="Efficient Multipitch clinic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3402/13083801763_0193424bc5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="494" alt="Efficient Multipitch clinic" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083989074/" title="Onlookers by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2376/13083989074_6ace5a6d79_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Onlookers" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083702325/" title="Efficient Multipitch clinic tryouts by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2525/13083702325_e117c2ba98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Efficient Multipitch clinic tryouts" /></a></p>

<p>I tie in with Jon, who works at the mines in Kiruna and came up to Abisko for the day. We take turns on the low ice walls establishing belays, belaying the second, and then climbing onwards. After several tries we feel we are ready to tackle on of the larger walls, but first we refuel with hot coffee, sandwiches and chocolate. In between sips of steaming coffee we chat, revealing and hearing more bout our climbing partner. It’s a reoccuring thing on these happenings, and I probably told <em>“My Story”</em> a dozen times over the weekend, and have heard just as many different interesting stories in return. It’s fascinating and the beauty of this happening, which brings people with a common interest to a magnificent place and lets them tie in and whack ice together.</p>

<p>Now knowing more about each other, Jon and I give a higher wall a try. I try to go first, but half-way between our supposed belay spot and the ground confidence leaves and I climb back down. Jon takes the lead, establishes a belay and I climb up. While it feels like we’re climbing the Mont Blanc du Tacul route we’re hanging a mere five meters above the ground, and energy leaves. While I’d now feel confident to go for the top, Jon suggests we take a break and then continue. I rappel down, Jon follows, another bread &amp; cuppa and we are back. This time Jon climbs the whole line and belays me from the top, while I clean the route. We high five on top of the cliff, and realize that we’re the last ones here. Anna waits with the shuttle bus at the road and smiles to us - <em>“Take your time!”</em>. We walk off the cliff, pack up, and ride back to the station. Beer time. Sauna time. Dinner time. Presentation time. Northern Lights. Sleeping time.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13084146604/" title="Aurora Borealis by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3758/13084146604_f3c1d7042d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Abisko STF Mountain Station, Saturday morning, blue sky, -3°C</strong>. With the heating up in our cozy room it was too hot for me. Aleksi and me head together with Torbjörn &amp; Robert from Sweden up to the breakfast buffet. The talk goes to past adventures and future plans, but today we look forward to building abalakov and different belay stations before heading up to Nuolja. At <em>Kurva</em> Stefan teaches us again, and I’m glad we have such experienced and friendly instructors here at the Festival, who are happy to loan you their personal gear and answer your questions, even if they’ve answered the same thing already five times that day. We build different belays, which even at 20 cm above the ground gets the sweat flowing - especially if you forget to take off your down jacket. Building an abalakov is always exciting, and I’m happy as mine works on the first try. Then things go fast.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083875035/" title="Abalakov clinic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7428/13083875035_9797ee2d6c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Abalakov clinic" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Nuolja, Saturday afternoon, blue sky, -2°C</strong>. The hike up to Nuolja is more strenous as expected, and 40 minutes later our little group stands below the cliff. While some set off to lead, others are waiting for the top rope to be set up. And while I’d feel confident enough to climb one of those WI3 slabs, all the lines are taken. Done with setting up the TR Stefan comes down and inquires what I’d like to do. <em>A lead climb would be nice</em> I reply. <em>Lets go and see the fall to the right</em>. Stefan, Andreas and me walk on the 50° hard snow to the base of the climb, and standing in front of it I see that this is closer to WI4, even if it’s relatively short with just 20 meters. <em>You lead, we second?</em> I suggest. <em>OK</em>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083804033/" title="Nuolja by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2147/13083804033_036382b0f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="408" alt="Nuolja" /></a></p>

<p>It’s a proper alpine adventure route, with lots and lots of snow, and topping out on top felt great. I walk a tad further up and coil my rope while Andreas climbs up. The helicopter which flew the other group to Kaisepakte flys by and snaps photos of us on top, and with Andreas on top we stroll to the rappel anker. As we wait for our turn to rappel down Torbjörn just tops out on his first lead climb, exhilarated about the achievement. On the way down I see Robert make the final moves to the top, and am happy for the two to have succeed on their first lead route.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12902230384/" title="Torbjörn topping out on Nuolja by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2815/12902230384_dfa1885dd3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Torbjörn topping out on Nuolja" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Abisko STF Mountain Station, Saturday evening, clear sky, -4°C</strong>. Hiking back to the road, Sara just pulls up to the parking lot as I arrive. We catch up while the others slowly come down from the mountain, and then we head back to the STF Mountain Station, where the Drytooling Competition is just about to start. Stefan, David and the Arctic Guide Team have built a sweet rig for us to compete on. Hang from the wooden block without touching the ground - the rules are simple, but even in the qualifying round some already fail. It’s the next round, with the wooden block moved further away, that sees only five succeed, and so the final is a thrilling event, and at the end we have one winner. After a quick shower and changing clothes the Festival Dinner starts. We’re treated to a three course meal which lets us taste some Swedish delicacies, which are accompanied by glasses of wine and beer. The mood is cheerful, everyone had a great day and got some good climbing in, and slowly we stroll to the After Lounge Bar, where Said treats us to a presentation about his 20 years as a climber. It’s a great story, filled with places and names which will demand the attention of any climber, communicated in Said’s friendly, down-to-earth way. Accompanied by good tunes we travel the globe from one great climbing destination to the next, and after Said plays the Digeridoo to finish off a long applause commences. On the way to the ski hut, more Northern Lights dance across the fjells and the lake, while the stars glow in the dark firmament.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13083996244/" title="Drytooling Dyno Comp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3016/13083996244_637b4e7d65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Drytooling Dyno Comp" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Abisko Canyon, Sunday morning, clear sky, -2°C</strong>. Also on the third day the Breakfast Buffet offers new tastes to explore, though the favouries of bacon, eggs and cheese on dark rye bread couldn’t be missed. We descent to the Abisko Canyon, where a clinic of Traditional Scottish Mixed is on the schedule. Stefan, who has over 20 years of experience of climbing mixed - often in underground caves in central Sweden - shows our little group the ins and outs, before we eagerly tie in the Top Ropes to try climbing with our tools and crampon on the rocks. The fun ends just too quickly, as I head back up to the sun to interview Anders for an article I’m writing for the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/trekking-magazin/">trekking Magazin</a>. Slowly also Aleksi and Andreas come up to the sun, after having enjoyed more Mixed &amp; Ice climbing, and we pack up the last bit of our gear to bring it to the car. It’s noon and the sun shines down on Lapporten, the gate to the Kungsleden, as we say our good byes to new and old friends. Another long ride is in front of us, but we’re certain we will return to the friends and ice of Abisko in the future.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12901907133/" title="Aleksi rocking the Traditional Scottish Mixed clinic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3805/12901907133_164536017c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Aleksi rocking the Traditional Scottish Mixed clinic" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12902193184/" title="Swedish Version of Scottish Mixed Climbing by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7305/12902193184_cfc8b9587d_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Swedish Version of Scottish Mixed Climbing" /></a></p>

<p><em>Enroll for next year’s event at <a href="http://www.abiskoiceclimbing.com/">Abisko Ice Climbing</a> and stay up to date at the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/AbiskoIceClimbingFestival">AICF</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/arcticguides">ArcticGuides</a> Facebook Pages. There’s a good chance that a Piolets d’Or 2014 nominee will be the Guest of Honour in 2015, so plan well ahead if you’d like to tie-in with one of the world’s greates alpinists.</em> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157641794355415/">More photos</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.relaa.com/sisalto/artikkelit/abiskon-komeat-j%C3%A4%C3%A4putoukset-haastavat-kiipeilij%C3%A4n">Read Aleksi’s account and see how cool heli climbing is</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T09:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In three weeks the second <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> kicks off, and it’s set to be pretty amazing again. In case you’re still on the edge about going - I will give you plenty of good reasons to travel to the northern most Ice Climbing Festival!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553149630/" title="Lapporten ice climbing"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8380/8553149630_34b8f7fee8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lapporten" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html">Last year’s AICF</a> was fantastic and I learned a lot. It’s not every day that you can pick the brains of Alpinists like Robert Jasper and the guys from Petzl, so as the 2nd AICF was announced, with a pretty fantastic line-up of instructors and clinics, it was an easy decision to travel north to Abisko this year again.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553049416/" title="Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8086/8553049416_5a073d5199_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Canyon" /></a></p>

<p>Like last year, the AICF is something for everyone: From the complete novice who has never climbed ice to advanced climbers, who want to hone their skills. You can loan all the ice climbing gear, and will be very well instructed on its use and technique. Accommodation is in the very nice <a href="http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/upptack/Omraden/Lappland/Fjallstationer/STF-Abisko-Turiststation/">STF Turiststation Abisko</a>, and if you travel with the family: There’s plenty to do there for kids and partners, from sledging and snowshoe walks to skiing and watching Aurora Borealis.</p>

<p>For the climbing, this year’s clinics include <em>Traditional Scottish mix lead</em>, <em>Efficient multi pitch</em>, <em>Basic Ice/Mix</em> as well as <em>Efficient and safe belay</em> and <em>Ice strength/ belay/ rappel/ abalakov</em>. There’s going to be a competition, the relaxed After Climb sessions, and which is surely going to be spectacular, the “Petzl night with Said Belhaj”. Said had just a big feature in the current Rock &amp; Ice 216 (great read, go get the Magazin!), and I met him briefly last year at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">Outdoor</a> so am very much looking forward to climbing with him. But there’s more, Stefan Lindblom and Krister Jonsson as well as UIAGM Mountain Guide &amp; Organizer Anders Bergwall are again along to teach you about proper crampon &amp; tool techniques, and show you how multi-pitch climbing is done well. And they’ll let you pick their brains from years of climbing on ice and mixed and other outdoor shenanigans!</p>

<p>As you see, there’s really plenty for everyone, and the four days surely will fly by way too fast. You can read all the details on the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Arctic Guides</a> website, and then it’s time to <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/wp-system/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/AICF-2014-Prices.pdf">book your festival pass</a> and plan the trip north! You can also <a href="https://www.facebook.com/AbiskoIceClimbingFestival">follow on Facebook</a> and keep an eye on the new <a href="http://www.abiskoiceclimbing.com/">Abisko Ice Climbing</a> website which will launch soon. See you in Absiko!</p>

<p><em>If you’re coming from Finland, we still have one seat free in the car from Vaasa (via a night in Rovaniemi on the way up), if you want to drive with us - <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">be in touch</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577421940/" title="Stefan leading by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8089/8577421940_6db928fa2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stefan leading" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ice Climbing in Korouoma]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T10:41:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Korouoma has been for a long time on my list of places to visit. A long canyon with up to 100 m high cliffs, Golden Eagles soaring above in the sky, and a good dozen of icefalls to climb make this the best ice climbing destination in Finland.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595259601/" title="Boulders by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8241/8595259601_a2a1080513_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Boulders" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>My fast &amp; light trip to Korouoma started Friday afternoon as Heini, Mikko and their dog Alli picked me up in Vaasa, before us an eight hour drive to the north. After a late dinner at one of the countless ABC Stations along the road I dozed off on the backseat, awakening once in a while as we drove on empty roads further towards <a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Home">Posio</a> and <a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Places-to-visit/Nature-destinations/Korouoma-Nature-Reserve#.UVK1k1tQhGQ">Korouoma</a>. It was past midnight as we arrived on the parking place, and in the light of our headlamps and the moon we gathered our gear to start the descent towards the canyon. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587936563/" title="All packed up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8365/8587936563_6ac57e172b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="All packed up" /></a></p>

<p>It’s very late as we arrive down at the Kota which the rest of the group is already sleeping in, and Heini and Mikko head inside while I sleep outside. It’s so late, the weather is clear, so I just roll out my pads and the new Tyvek quilt cover I have on test and slip in my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/01/katabatic-gear-sawatch-quilt.html">Katabatic Gear Sawatch</a> while the moon shines over the valley. My watch says it’s -15°C but inside my quilt and down hoody I am warm and soon fall asleep.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8589038686/" title="First night bivy by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8513/8589038686_3efd441cb9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="First night bivy" /></a></p>

<p>I wake up as at sun rises close to 6 o’clock, though as no one else is yet up I turn around and sleep a bit more. By seven o’clock the sun shines on my bivy spot and so I get up, a hot coffee - a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos bottle</a> is a must on these trips - and I’m off exploring the surroundings, waiting for my climbing friends to wake up. No Alpine Start, it seems. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587935987/" title="Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8229/8587935987_4e7d8db06c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Camp" /></a></p>

<p>To be productive I pitch my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review.html">Khufu</a> eVent II and sort all my climbing gear for the day ahead, and a bit past eight Mikko and Heini appear outside with Alli. We have breakfast together, and finally around ten o’clock Mikko and me set off to the icefalls. We pass Ruskeavirta, the longest and steepest icefall, but which we won’t climb yet. We walk onwards to the Mammutti icefall, a smaller and slightly easier climb for the start of the day. A group of people is already at the fall, and they have their first walking with crampons &amp; iceclimbing lessons while Mikko and me look for a route.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596493414/" title="Mikko by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8529/8596493414_81e25043d1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mikko" /></a></p>

<p>After we found a good line which suits us both, and offers a good belay &amp; rappel possibility, Mikko is leading while I belay him. The wind is cold but the sky is clear, and behind us the sun is throwing long shadows across the canyon. As the majority of the climbs are on north-facing walls, we get no sun, though - it’s in the shadows where we climb.</p>

<p>Six ice screws later Mikko topped out and established a belay spot, and I follow. I make my way up, cleaning up the ice screws and quick-draws he installed, and top out after a good climb. The view from up here, some 30 m higher now, is superb - we can see wide into the canyon to each side. The sun looks warm on the other side of the valley, while up here the wind &amp; shadow keep us cold. Mikko lets me down and then follows with a rappel. </p>

<p>Tea time. We snack and drink while discussing the next line. The other group climbed on a very wet fall and would like to climb our more dry line, so we let them and move more to the right. Steeper but a bit shorter, with a more exposed belay at the bottom, Mikko again sets off. While he climbs a Golden Eagle soars above us through the canyon, a majestic sight with its long, wide wings. Arriving at the ledge Mikko sets up a belay and I start my climb up. I arrive at the edge of the ledge with cold hands after having again collected all screws and quick-draws, slowly getting a hang of how to sort them on my harness so that they’re not in the way, as Mikko again lets me down. The plan was to build an Abalakov and abseil, though I was carrying the Abalakov tool and forgot to give it to Mikko. D’oh! Happily the other group is close enough with their toprope to Mikko, and so he is able to just clip into it and rappel down. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596482264/" title="Abseiling by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8226/8596482264_59b61e5f03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abseiling" /></a></p>

<p>We switch to the Revontuli icefall next, further down the canyon. The approach down in the valley is fast, as a well established trail leads through the snow, which at times is over a meter high. The walk up to the cliff is also easy, as two members of our group were just climbing there =) After two Lämmin Kuppi hot soups, chips and nuts I’m again warm and in good spirits, as is Mikko. Again we discuss the route, and decide that Mikko would climb to a ledge, then I follow and then we continue. </p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/62851129?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Mikko, who climbs his third season on ice this year, gets up to the ledge, though as I follow the cold hands, a sure sign of gripping my axes to hard, return, and just as I arrive at the ledge I get a cramp in my left leg. Demotivated, I get down after I handed Mikko the ice screws and belay him further. After an exciting climb - Mikko droped an axe (<a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-double-spring-2-0.html">leashes</a> on Multipitch routes are handy!) and I provided him with a new one - we pack up and head back to camp, passing some of out friends who are still climbing. I take it slow, and photograph along the way. I head up to the foot of Ruseka Virta, from where one has a fine view over the valley looking south-east, and arrive after a nice walk at the Kota and my Khufu. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595387013/" title="Khufu-&amp;-Kota by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8385/8595387013_f40fefb2c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Khufu-&amp;-Kota" /></a></p>

<p>Slowly all the members and friends of Vaasa’s climbing club <a href="http://www.highsport.fi/">High Sport</a> arrive at the Kota. With a few Trangias and gasstoves on, as well as the oven in the centre of the hut, the temperature inside soon rises to sauna levels, while outside the thermometer again drops towards -15°C. Good conversations take place, though after a long day of climbing we are all rather tired, and by ten o’clock I slip into the Khufu, zip the door closed and fall asleep.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595374377/" title="Khufu-eVent-II by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8525/8595374377_49e7f2d121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Khufu-eVent-II" /></a></p>

<p>A new morning and there’s again no Alpine Start, so I too sleep in till 8 o’clock. Coffee and breakfast in the kota, while I am thawing my shoes a bit by the oven. And of course more talk of where to climb today. Mikko and I settle on a small ice fall not far from camp, and a tad after ten o’clock walk over the snowshoe established trail direction north-west, until we reach the Enkeliputous ice fall. It’s a pretty fall, quite short but it’s still untouched and that also means we need to get through the snow till the base of the cliff. </p>

<p>Which is easier said than done. Somehow if one carries ice climbing gear and a rope my elven skills of walking over the snow disappear, and I’m hip deep at times making my way to the cliff. We pick an easy starter route for the morning up the right side, and we both have great fun (see the video) on the route, for me it was easily the best climbing. We set a toprope for two of our friends, and then I rappel down, getting ready for a much steeper climb.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596473480/" title="Liisa by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8237/8596473480_a6035fa5dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Liisa" /></a></p>

<p>And steep it was. While Mikko made his way up without problems, for me it was a real Suffer-Fest to get the steep ice up - crampons or axes blew out, I barn-doored a time or two, and felt like just going down a couple of times. But it’s mind over matter, and so I made it up, over the ledge and euphoric feelings of success were the reward. I made my way further up to Mikko and the belay spot, where we built an abalakov to abseil. <em>Will it hold?</em> went more than once through my head, though as I made my way down, and also Mikko abseiled after me, we both knew that we built a good abalakov. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595377849/" title="Enkelliputous by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8252/8595377849_c28d4b2303_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Enkelliputous" /></a></p>

<p>I toproped once more, and then packed up and headed back to the Kota to get my camping gear and head back to the car. A long walk up back to the parking lot later, which put the Gore Tex Active Shell membrane to a good, final test, I arrived in the sunshine on top. Storing gear, driving, eating at an ABC Station, and arriving before midnight in Vaasa - a superb trip. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587938931/" title="Trail by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8236/8587938931_023b7dfb47_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trail" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If you’re into ice climbing, life or visit Finland, then a visit to Korouoma is a must. With it’s superb infrastructure (short approaches, free lean-tos, fire places, toilets as well as rental cabins) and the beautiful surroundings ice climbing in Korouoma is an experience you won’t forget. You can climb up to 14 different ice falls of different heights and difficulties in the canyon, all within about an hour of walking distance from the free lean-to shelters which are a mere 200 m from Ruskeavirta. Some of the ice falls even offer paths for setting topropes if you’re not yet leading or want to first get a feeling for the fall. All in all I’m certainly returning next winter, and with the ice climbing season at Korouoma going from November till April (depending on the weather each year, obviously) maybe even more than once.</p>

<p>Even if you’re not an ice climber Korouoma is worth a trip. You can ski and snowshoe in winter, and enjoy the gorgeous scenery of the canyon with its unique flora and fauna. Golden Eagles, herbrich forests and great views are worth a trip at any time of the year, though I imagine in autumn when the leaves turn golden and red it is especially worthwhile.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633086621480/">More photos on Flickr</a></p>

<p>A very useful <a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2012/03/korouoma-derby-2012.html">map with all ice falls in the canyon</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.climbingextreme.com/2009/02/korouoma-best-spot-for-ice-climbing-in-finland/300">Info on routes and some beta</a>, and some <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/korouoma">more beta</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Activities/Winter-activities/Ice-climbing#.UVK1xVtQhGQ">General info on ice climbing at Korouoma</a>, and more <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/otherprotectedareas/korouoma/Pages/Default.aspx">information on Korouoma</a>.</p>

<h2 id="information">Information</h2>

<p><strong>Getting there</strong> is easiest by car. Alternatives are flying to Rovaniemi or Kuusamo and taking a bus to Posio, from where one can take a Taxi to the Korouoma Parking lot. Ot rent a car in Rovaniemi/ Kuusamo to get there.</p>

<p><strong>Accomodation</strong> is either own shelter/ tent, the free lean-tos which are all along the canyon, or some of the rental cabins of which the <a href="http://www.lomarengas.fi/varaamo/villipohjola/mokki/posio-piippukota-erakamppa-10694?villiPohjolaLevel=&amp;mapAreaIDs=&amp;maxPrice=&amp;startDateString=&amp;endDateString=&amp;persons=&amp;code=&amp;name=&amp;customSearch=&amp;noElectricity=&amp;shower=&amp;wc=&amp;heating=&amp;waterSupply=&amp;swimmingShoreShallowAndHard=&amp;allowPets=&amp;maintainedSkiingTracks=&amp;fishing=&amp;canoeing=&amp;hunting=&amp;snowmobiling=&amp;hikingTrail=&amp;suitableForDisabled=&amp;accessByCarDuringSummer=&amp;accessByCarDuringWinter=&amp;holidayCenter=&amp;newLocale=en_EN">Piippukota</a> is for climbers the best option as it is some 400 m from Ruskeavirta. There’s a gas stove at the Piippukota and some pans &amp; pots, too.</p>

<p><strong>Food</strong> you can buy in Posio, which is 30 km from Korouoma. If you stay at the Kota you can almost bring normal food and cook and don’t need to rely on trekking meals. I recommend Bacon &amp; Eggs on bread for breakfast - my MYOG Müsli was OK but bacon and eggs would have been much better =) </p>

<p><em>Happy trails &amp; climbing!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2013 Experiences]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-21T20:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having been invited to the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2013</a> was an opportunity I couldn’t resist. A four hour ferry ride to Umeå and a nine hour train ride to Abisko later I arrived in one of Sweden’s Northernmost trail towns, which offers stunning Aurora Borealis, downhill skiing, husky tours and superb ice climbing.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553149630/" title="Lapporten by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8380/8553149630_34b8f7fee8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lapporten" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>“Hendrik?”</em></p>

<p><em>Yes.</em></p>

<p><em>“Welcome to the Abisko Ice Climbing Festival! I see you’re already wearing your climbing shoes, just drop your stuff here and head down to the canyon, you can get all the gear at the Petzl tent and the Demo Session is soon starting!”</em></p>

<p>After this friendly welcome from Anders Bergwall, UIAGM/ IFMGA Mountain Guide, owner of <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/">Arctic Guides</a>, and Organiser of the AICF I quickly changed into my climbing pants and headed down to the Abisko river canyon, where indeed already a lot of people where climbing and chatting. But before I could climb I needed some gear, and so I went into the huge Tentipi tent and got from the friendly employees from <a href="http://www.c2safety.com/">C2 Vertical Safety</a> a pair of crampons (Petzl Darts), a pair of ice tools (Petzl Quarks), a harness (the new Petzl Sama) and a helmet (the new Petzl Sirocco, wonderfully light!). Well equipped I headed down to the canyon and started to chat with some of the other climbers while I was waiting for my turn.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8544509865/" title="Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2013 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8238/8544509865_6caa945cb0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2013" /></a></p>

<p>It didn’t take too long and after a quick introduction and a buddy check with my belayer Rafael Jensen I was up the ice. The route was not too difficult, and already pretty hewn out from previous climbers, but for someone who was already travelling for about 12 hours it was just right. Back down Rafael gave me a few tips, and then I was already again knotting a Figure 8 knot and going up the second route. </p>

<p>After getting in five climbs it was time to check out the Demo Session from the Petzl climbers. They showed some nice Mixed climbing on a vertical cliff and ice climbing on an impressive waterfall further back in the canyon. But I was getting hungry, so I returned most of the Petzl gear as I brought my own, and just held on the the Sirocco helmet, which is wonderful. At the <a href="http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/sv/upptack/Omraden/Lappland/Fjallstationer/STF-Abisko-Turiststation/">STF Turist Station Abisko</a> I relaxed till Dinner started, and then headed shortly to the cabin to drop my backpacks before heading back to the presentations.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8551930773/” title=”Robert Jasper</td>
      <td>Mixed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8111/8551930773_b4d37a11a8_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”625” alt=”Robert Jasper</td>
      <td>Mixed”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.robert-jasper.de/">Robert Jasper</a>, a German Alpinist, had a presentation about his ascent of the Eiger Northface by the Japanese Route, Erwann from Petzl showed us a video of a truly impressive ice climb up a waterfall which he can see from his office (<a href="http://youtu.be/xLsFUtbX51Y">see it here</a>) while Alban told us more about the new Petzl gear we could try this weekend. After such a long day it was time to hit the hay, and I went with my room mates back to the cabin. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577557260/" title="Robert Jasper Presentation by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8088/8577557260_2ae285196d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Robert Jasper Presentation" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553057432/" title="Beginner's Wall by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8112/8553057432_beb9b3473a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Beginner's Wall" /></a></p>

<p>Friday morning I got up early and headed for breakfast to the STF Station. In case you haven’t been there, the breakfast alone is a good reason to visit - it was superb! Delicious, freshly baked breads, scrambled eggs &amp; bacon, porridge and different berry soups guarantee a great start into the day. After we made our own lunches from the breakfast buffet, with a few tasty additions like GORP, Chocolate and drinks, it was gathering the gear and heading to the Lounge, waiting for the cars. </p>

<p>Todays climbing was at a nearby roadside cliff, which had about ten frozen waterfalls waiting for us. We were quickly separated into different groups while a few of the Pros set up Topropes for us, and then it was ice climbing time! </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553065820/” title=”Anders</td>
      <td>Proper Crampon use by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8370/8553065820_a802df0044_b.jpg” width=”680” height=”1024” alt=”Anders</td>
      <td>Proper Crampon use”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>I was with the Beginner group, and Anders from Arctic Guides started off with telling us about proper crampon use. After that we traversed in half a meter height along a ice fall, while the Guides checked on how we used the crampons and gave us tips on how to do it better. After this it was time to get climbing on topropes, first at the beginner’s wall, then, as confidence, technique and skills increased on the intermediate wall.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8551950715/" title="Intermediate Wall by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8368/8551950715_f738b9cd1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Intermediate Wall" /></a></p>

<p>In between there were some more clinics, and especially the “How to create an Abalakov thread” one was very interesting. By using an ice screw you create a V shaped channel in solid ice, through which you then thread a cord or the rope directly to abseil. It allows you to leave no expensive gear behind (and with a single <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/eisschrauben.html">ice screw</a> costing upwards of 50€, that’s very welcome indeed!) and if done correctly is very safe.</p>

<p>After six hours of intense climbing and clinics we were shuttled back to the STF Station, but some of us still had enough energy left and so headed down to the Abisko Canyon. Together with Sanna, a local Skiguide, we climbed in the canyon, first on the same wall as the previous day, then we decided to try our skills on the waterfall behind the open pool where the advanced climbers were climbing the previous day. </p>

<p>Sanna went first, and standing next to the flowing water on a thin strip of frozen ice I was belaying her. She climbed the route until she was out of sight, topping out on a small ledge. Over the roaring of the water we communicated, and I abseiled her down, we both psyched that she did this hard route! I knotted in and set off, though half way up I needed to get down - my hands were pumped and to my defence I can say that Erwann from Petzl needed to go up the route to clean it - it was already late, and we were the last ones climbing =) </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577417208/" title="Looking down by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8238/8577417208_9a6ebc7f66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Looking down" /></a></p>

<p>In the After Climb Lounge <a href="http://www.kristerjonsson.se/Kristerjonson/International_Mountainguide_because_of_his_great_passion_for_Mountains_and_People.html">Krister Jonsson</a> took us to Kyrgisiztan, where he climbed   in 2012 for three weeks with his fiancée magnificent peaks and walls in a superb setting.  After a good Dinner the presentations continued, taking us on a expedition to Patagonia and ice climbing in China, both very inspiring. But Saturday we would start early, so it was to bed early, too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576322159/" title="Great Ice! by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8251/8576322159_bf671406fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Great Ice!" /></a></p>

<p>The Alarm rang at six o’clock, and an half hour later the great breakfast was enjoyed again. I joined Alban &amp; Erwann from Petzl and Robert Jasper in their car as we journeyed to Spansdalen in Norway. It was a fun trip, and all of us were in awe: As soon as we passed the Swedish - Norwegian border high peaks rose upward,  much higher and steeper than anything we had seen to date in Sweden. Later the Swedes told us that it indeed seems to be along the complete Border this way - the round fjells on the Swedish side, the high peaks on the Norwegian side. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576525701/" title="Norway by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8509/8576525701_d6ae3f091d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norway" /></a></p>

<p>We arrived in Spansdalen, the “Valley of Ice” in Norway and dropped the Pros and Advanced climbers at Henrikkafossen, a 8-Pitch route which looked like superb fun. We drove a bit further up the valley to more moderate climbs, and while the first four groups set off to climb various Multipitch routes others stayed behind and took part in a few more clinics - from building belay stations to different alternatives of rappelling. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576320223/" title="Rappeling Clinic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8516/8576320223_933ccd7e4b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rappeling Clinic" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576321517/" title="Intermediate Wall by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8378/8576321517_603b5b90bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Intermediate Wall" /></a></p>

<p>After a while it was Sara and my turn to go climbing, and we joined Stefan Lindblom from <a href="http://www.vertikalguiden.se/concrete/">Vertikal Guiden</a>. Stefan lead climbed on a half-rope so that he could belay Sara &amp; me from the belay ledge, and once he set up his belay Sara &amp; me simu-climbed up to him. The belay was on an exposed ledge and the wind was blowing coldly, so it was good that I brought my belay vest along to stay warm. </p>

<p>Sara belayed Stefan this time on the 2nd pitch, which was a lot harder than the first one, with a very steep vertical section. My hands pumped, the cold wind blowing, I pushed on, taking out the ice screws &amp; quick-draws Stefan placed, until I finally made it to the top. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577421940/" title="Stefan leading by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8089/8577421940_6db928fa2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stefan leading" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577422832/" title="Sorting ropes by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8250/8577422832_61f31c64b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sorting ropes" /></a></p>

<p>Up on the top Stefan belayed Sara till she too made was with us. If you go up, you also need to get back down and so we sorted ropes and set up everything for abseiling back down. We used the new <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-reverso-4-belay-device.html">Petzl Reverso 4</a> to go down, and abseiling the 45 m ice fall was good fun. After we were all safely back at the start of the climb it was time to coil ropes and head back to the car, as it was getting late and we had still a 1,5 hour ride back to Abisko in front of us.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577735844/" title="Petzl Reverso 4 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8234/8577735844_86d4c770cb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Reverso 4" /></a></p>

<p>But what should have been 1,5 hour ride became a 3 hour ride, as we were waiting for 1,5 hours to cross the pass back into Sweden. Because of the strong winds the road was closed and one could only pass it in a convoy. There also was an accident, and so we sat in the car, chatting and waiting for the support vehicles to arrive and escort us across the pass. As we crossed the pass in the convoy the wind was blowing strongly, though I still spotted a few skiers on the loipes, heading back to their huts or cars.</p>

<p>Back in Abisko we enjoyed a presentation from Stefan, who ice climbs a lot in abandoned mines in his region, rather interesting places with many curious stories connected to them. After the Festival Dinner we listened closely as Rafael Jensen told of the first Swedish expedition to K2, a very touching story as three of the six members who stood on the summit of this Himalayan peak died on the descent. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576458309/" title="Abisko Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8392/8576458309_581552ba62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abisko Canyon" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576458643/" title="Petzl Laser Ice Screw by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8098/8576458643_fee6677709_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Laser Ice Screw" /></a></p>

<p>On Sunday we started a bit later than the previous days, and I headed after nine to the Abisko canyon for the final ice climbing of the weekend. It was a beautiful, sunny day with temps in the -14°C range. Stefan and Anders set a few topropes for us, and so we soon started to climb again. I tried various mixed routes that day, where one climbs rock &amp; ice with tools &amp; crampons, and while I was sceptical at first I enjoyed it immensely. It is a whole new sort of climbing, in parts easier, in parts harder than pure ice climbing or rock climbing. Heading up a steep wall with fine cracks, and only here and there ice features, is something every climber should try - it is great fun, and pushes your thinking to new levels. </p>

<p>But all good things come to an end, and so slowly the participants from near and far started to depart, catching trains, buses, planes or car rides down south. I myself stored my ice climbing gear away and got my Hyperlite Mountain Gear Porter, a pair of Dynafit Broadpeak skis and TLT5 boots and headed for the Kungsleden. But that’s another story.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157632964937798/">View more photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p>Did this get you psyched about ice climbing in Abisko and surroundings, trying out new gear and learning from the Pros? Then follow the Arctic Guides on <a href="http://www.facebook.com/arcticguides">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/arcticguides">Twitter</a> to hear about the AICF 2014, or visit one of their <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/courses/isklattring">ice climbing courses</a>.</p>

<p>I’d like to thank all the awesome participants of the AICF, especially Anders &amp; Merja from Arctic Guides, Stefan, Rafael, Robert and Krister for teaching &amp; guiding us, my room mate Dorian for the good company, Lo for letting me sleep at her place, Sara &amp; Mikeal from C2 Vertical Safety as well as Alban &amp; Erwann from Petzl for the possibility to loan great gear. I’m looking forward to climbing with you again next year!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577415840/" title="Clinic with Robert Jasper by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8369/8577415840_05ea7e4ca0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Clinic with Robert Jasper" /></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Climbing Ice]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/climbing-ice.html"/>
    <updated>2013-02-21T20:53:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/climbing-ice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Want to go ice climbing this weekend?</em></p>

<p><em>Anyday.</em></p>

<p><strong>And so they went.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8486288705/" title="Ice curtains by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8096/8486288705_e0a48a3430_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Ice curtains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’ve been itching to go ice climbing since winter 2011/ 2012. Last winter things didn’t work out (new born babys tend to demand a lot of attention and wives are less willing to let one go away for long trips) so the plan to go ice climbing was renewed this season. In anticipation of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/01/abisko-ice-climbing-festival.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> I was hoping to be able to visit a <a href="http://www.adventurepartners.fi/pirunkallio.aspx">course</a>, but things got in the way. And even as my local climbing club offered a <a href="http://www.highsport.fi/">course</a> I was too busy to attend. </p>

<p>So when <a href="http://www.valppaus.com/">Joni</a>, whom I met at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/banff-mountain-film-festival-world-tour-helsinki.html">Banff Mountain Film Festival World Tour</a> in Helsinki last autumn, asked if I’d be interested to go to the local quarry for some ice climbing I didn’t need to think long. Saturday evening I was packing gear, adjusting crampons, and packing a lot of food before it was off to bed early. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8496127564/" title="Going up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8112/8496127564_66c5626533_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Going up" /></a></p>

<p>We started early on Sunday, and after we drove to the quarry we walked in the short bit, though the deep, puffy snow made going forward quite a task - skis or snowshoes would have been easier. After checking out the spots we decided on one cliff and geared up. Equipped with ropes we walked to the top of the cliff and set up ropes, here Joni decided for me that we’re now going to rappel straight down - as I haven’t climbed in a bit, I was planning to walk back, but in the end all went well and it was a nice experience to rappel down past icicles. Then it was my turn to make a figure eight knot and start the journey upwards. After a few instructions on ice tool and crampon use I was off. </p>

<p>It was fun. It was difficult. It <em>is</em> addicing.</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/60198868?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="607" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The first time going up was the hardest. But with every climb I got better, remembered the ingrained way the body should behave - stay close the the ice, legs straight, heels down, one axe after the other, use the holes from the tools for the crampons. Joni didn’t mind if I needed a break or was hanging like a sack of potatoes in the rope because I forgot to use my legs or blew the crampons out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8486287141/" title="Tendon Rope by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8372/8486287141_7f341247e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Tendon Rope" /></a></p>

<p>It was a great session, and I learned a little bit about ice climbing. The road ahead will take me to Sweden next week where I should learn a bit more, and if fortune smiles on me, Korouoma in March. Before that hopefully a weekend in Helvetinjärvi, and as often as possible at the local quarry. <em>It is addicing.</em></p>

<p>A big <strong>Thank You</strong> to Joni for having the patience to teach me ice climbing. I’m looking forward to more adventures together in the future - be they on frozen or liquid water!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157632825137162/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="gear-geekery">Gear Geekery</h2>

<p>The ice climbing gear already arrived last December, and I have been playing with it at home, hoping to get to try it outdoors soon. A pair of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-g20-cramp-o-matic-steigeisen.html">Grivel G20 crampons</a>, (848 g for the pair or 424 g per crampon), <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/scarpa-phantom-ultra-bergstiefel/">Scarpa Phantom Ultra boots</a> (1845 gram for the pair or 918 g per shoe, Size 42,5)  make for a very light ice climbing setup. A pair of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-nomic-eisgeraet.html">Petzl Nomic Ice tools</a> (608 g per tool). Additionally I used my existing <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/ultralight-climbing.html">climbing gear</a>: A <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/tendon-master-97-mm-einfachseil/">Tendon Master 9,7 mm Single rope</a>, a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-speed-kletterhelm/">CAMP Speed Helmet</a> (NEVER climb ice without helmet!), a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-verso-sicherungsgeraet/">Petzl Verso</a> belay device as well as a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/mammut-smart-sicherungsgeraet-brg-3.html">Mammut Smart</a> belay device and my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-r-320-hueftgurt/">Arc’teryx R 320</a> harness. I was wearing <a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">POC Iris 3P Googles</a>, the superb <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-research-alibi-pants-softshellhose/">Outdoor Research Alibi Pants</a> and the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-felsturm-half-zip-jacket-hardshelljacke/">Mammut Felsturm jacket</a>, an <a href="http://aclima.no/">Aclima</a> Woolnet baselayer underneath and the gloves of the <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/gloves.html">Rab Modular Mitts</a>; my belay jacket was the <a href="http://paramo.co.uk/en-gb/garments/detail/index.php?pgc=NIKWAXINSULATORLTPACKAGETORRESUNISEX">Paramo Torres</a>. All gear was carried in a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/gregory-alpinisto-50-rucksack-alpine-gold.html">Gregory Alpinisto</a> backpack. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8495028095/" title="Boots n Crampons by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8093/8495028095_4273ee70a4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Boots n Crampons" /></a></p>

<p>The gear performed flawlessly on this outing, some of it has seen plenty of action before, for other it was the first time at the fresh air. I might tell more about it once I get more time on the ice with it under my belt, until then you should do your research at <a href="http://coldthistle.blogspot.com">Cold Thistle</a> and <a href="http://www.nicktruax.com/">Nick’s blog</a>.  </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
