<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: RocTrip 2014 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/roctrip-2014/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-23T19:48:30+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Petzl RocTrip 2014 - Eastern Europe]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/petzl-roctrip-2014-eastern-europe.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-28T18:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/petzl-roctrip-2014-eastern-europe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Romania, Bulgaria, Macedonia, Greece and Turkey are host to the 2014 Petzl RocTrip which this year takes the form of a road trip. Come and join this great event and hang out with the likes of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">Ueli Steck</a>, Saïd Belhaj, Dave Graham, Mélissa Le Nevé, Nina Caprez and many more while exploring the crazy good climbing that can be had in Eastern Europe!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14843495327" title="Petzl RocTrip 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14843495327_53dc68084a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl RocTrip 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The first time I became aware of the <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en">Petzl RocTrip</a> was in 2011, when I saw some photos from the event in China. Then in 2012 the video of the event was published and it was mind-blowing. I still love to watch it, and if you have a moment watch it here.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/EcU255XBlcI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In 2013 the Petzl RocTrip traveled to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QllWNEGBKic">Argentina</a> and it was equally inspiring. In 2013 it returned closer to home to the Gorges du Tarn, and now in 2014 the event is back and takes a new, unique format: A road trip across five countries in Eastern Europe. This is a great idea on so many levels, as it promotes what climbing is about in many ways: Travel to new crags, explore new countries, meet new people, climb new types of rock, experience different cultures. In a way it is promoting the dirtbag lifestyle, in a slightly more comfortable way! The teaser sets the mood well:</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/92311979?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>What is special about the RocTrip are the low costs for taking part in the event: It’s just 15€! Comparing that to the costs of some other events this is <em>very affordable</em>. It’s well organized (<a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/practical-information">check the practical information</a>) and you get the opportunity to climb in some unique locations with members of the <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/news/spend-time-your-favorite-athletes-during-2014-petzl-roctrip">Petzl Pro Team</a>. </p>

<p>Interested? Then <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/join-us">pre-register until August 31th, 2014</a> to one (or all!) of the camps you would like to join. <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/practical-information#Transport">Organize your transportation</a>, for example join the carpool or get a ride in the Petzl bus. Book your flights (I’m flying to Antalya which is a smooth connection if flying from Helsinki, Stockholm or Oslo). Then start your <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html">climbing training</a> so you’re fit for the hundreds of routes which will be waiting for you! The Petzl Roctrip website has a lot more information available, so check it out, pick the locations you want to join and pre-register! </p>

<p>I will be joining the Roctrip on the last two stops in <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/base-camp/geyikbayiri-turkish-style-columns">Geyikbayiri</a> and <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en/base-camp/olympos-climb-sky-fall-water">Olympos</a> and you’ll be able to read about it here and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>. But I really hope to meet some of you in Turkey =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/en" title="Petzl RocTrip 2014 website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5593/14867744620_2815c6ed8c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="640" alt="Petzl RocTrip 2014 website" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
