<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sony | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/sony/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-09T13:57:49+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony RX100 IV Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/sony-rx100-iv-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2016-10-24T23:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/sony-rx100-iv-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What camera do you use?</em> is probably the most common question I am asked when out on a trip or when someone sees my photos, and an astounding expression is often the result when I show my Sony RX100 IV - a pocket camera. But because size &amp; weight matter ever less in the fast evolving world of photography, the results of this small camera speak for it - be it here on the blog or in print magazines. <em>A comprehensive Field Report.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30417082542/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5818/30417082542_bc653b28b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100 IV" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p><em>The Sony RX100 IV is the camera you want to document your adventures when you prefer light weight, a small size and superb image quality.</em></p>

<h2 id="what-i-want-from-a-camera-and-how-i-ended-up-choosing-the-rx100-iv">What I want from a camera (and how I ended up choosing the RX100 IV)</h2>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: I bought the RX 100 IV myself and have no affiliation with Sony.</p>

<p>This blog started out about my backpacking trips in Finland &amp; my journey to lighten up the load on my back when outdoors, and has morphed into what I call an Outdoor Adventure Travel Blog nowadays. But I remember my Ultralight roots in everything I start, from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/bikepacking-in-pirkanmaa.html">bikepacking</a> to mountaineering, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/ultralight-climbing.html">climbing</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring.html">ski-touring</a>. I have dabbled with big, heavy cameras, used M43s like the still superb <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/04/panasonic-lumix-gf1-field-report.html">Panasonic Lumix GF1</a>, graduated to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Sony A7R full-frame camera</a>, had a short affair with the Olympus OM-D E-M5 and its successor and then just simply returned to what I consider the best camera for outdoor enthusiasts &amp; photographers who are outside, the subject of this article, the Sony RX100 IV. I enjoyed its predecessor, the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html">RX 100 III</a>, but haven’t pulled the trigger on my RX100 IV till last year December, when I ordered it on <a href="http://amzn.to/2eUfshc">Amazon</a>. </p>

<p><em>Why did I buy the RX 100 IV?</em> you might ponder, a valid question as do I own some other <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/photography/">cameras</a> too. Well, that’s where the ultralight thought comes up again. I wanted something that I can put in a pocket and is light. While I love the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture Pro</a> I have been out a lot in weather which has been anything than sunshine &amp; blue sky, and while I could add a <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/covers/shell/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Shell Cover</a> I prefer to keep it simple. And what is simpler than putting your camera into the chest pocket of your hardshell? After this lengthy introduction, let me quote myself:</p>

<p><em>“I’m still looking for the *Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> in terms of photographic equipment. It’s the camera which has only advantages, satisfies all my needs and is good enough for all my requirements”*:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Print-quality photographs</li>
  <li>Nightshots possible</li>
  <li>Video capable</li>
  <li>Tiltscreen</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
  <li>Weatherproof</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25866478752/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Flag"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/2/1690/25866478752_fd77e5ee83_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Flag" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bad">The Bad</h2>

<p>Before delving into these points and others in detail, let me first highlight the disadvantages of the RX 100 IV: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Only F11</li>
  <li>No hotshoe for a microphone or similar</li>
  <li>The Video Microphone is not good in real wind</li>
  <li>Included Flash in underpowered</li>
  <li>Menu is a bit unorganized and could be clearer</li>
  <li>No touch screen</li>
  <li>Tedious to switch focus point at times</li>
  <li>Back screen scratches easily</li>
  <li>No charger included</li>
  <li>Camera has sometimes difficulties with very bright or grey skies</li>
</ul>

<p>Now lets look at these in a bit more detail.</p>

<p><em>Only F11</em>. That might not seem like a big complaint, but for someone like me who loves sun stars F11 is often not enough. Add  some clouds or something to the sky and you can pretty much be sure that the RX100 IV is gonna make it a glowing white ball in the sky. When the sky is clear, however, it does produce acceptable sunstars: </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28044201296/in/album-72157669978279411/" title="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7797/28044201296_a750b77c3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>No hotshoe for a microphone or similar</em>. I really, really, really wish Sony would have said <em>We don’t need no underpowered flash in this camera, but lets put on a Hotshoe</em> because honestly, for me this camera is aimed at professionals, videography and photography enthusiasts who have the accessories which would need a hotshoe. This goes hand-in-hand with the next two complaints: </p>

<p><em>The Video Microphone is not good in real wind</em> and <em>Included Flash in underpowered</em>. Watch the underneath video and wait five seconds after the intro and see how useless the microphone is in real wind - and this is with wind cancellation et al. activated. If I would have been able to attach my beloved <a href="http://amzn.to/2eAihzK">Rode VideoMic</a> you could have understood me clear like in an empty studio, but so the wind is pretty much drowning me out completely. Also the underpowered flash is next-to-useless and I’d rather would not have it on the camera - I have NEVER used it - and have the possibility to attach a real flash via a hotshoe. I hope that in Version VI of this camera Sony will give it a Hotshoe, because that would make it even more versatile.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1ZN99LOKqjQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The <em>Menu is a bit unorganized and could be clearer</em> is something most camera manufacturers seem to have problems with if I read or watch reviews. It’d be nice to be able to create an own “My Menu” point where I could add these Menu points which are important to me so that I can access them fast instead of trying to find them in the buried Menu structure. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29900767693/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV Menu"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5608/29900767693_c7380e2ab6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sony RX100 IV Menu" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That there’s <em>No touch screen</em> is a problem if you want to again quickly navigate through the Menu, or, even more important, set the Focus point somewhere. Because it can be <em>Tedious to switch the focus point at times</em> as you a) need to be in the right Focus Mode and b) then need to push the button and then navigate it with the wheel to where you want it. With a touchscreen I ideally would put my finger where I want the focus to be and <em>Voilá!</em> I could shoot. So I often need to try very fast to switch the focus point when my subject is moving. </p>

<p>Lets stay with the back of the camera for one more moment, as the <em>Back screen scratches easily</em>. It’s purely optical - probably the protective layer on it - but it’s still a bit annoying. After all this is a 1.200€ camera, and you’d expect that the screen is scratch resistant - it is a pocket camera, after all. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30417089442/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV Scratched scree"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5542/30417089442_7990889a3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sony RX100 IV Scratched scree" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>What really has me scratching my head is why Sony did not <em>include a charger</em> in the package. You can <a href="http://amzn.to/2emViNX">buy one</a> but it feels strange to spend almost 20€ on something that should be included. You can charge the battery otherwise via the included USB cable, but that also means you can not use the camera to shoot. This is a short-sighted and unfriendly customer policy which I really don’t like, and I hope the next RX100 cameras will come with a charger included. </p>

<p>Which bring me to the final complaint, and here we enter the technical capabilities of the camera. It <em>sometimes has difficulties with very bright or grey skies</em> aka <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_range#Photography">Dynamic Range</a>, or in layman terms: If there’s a dark foreground and a very bright background (or vice versa). While the Sony RX100 IV has a built in, electronic ND Filter which can help with making the image better, it only helps so much (and you need to remember to switch it on). Happily this is something I usually am able to fix in <a href="http://amzn.to/2eJtrTR">Lightroom and Photoshop</a> afterwards as I always photograph in RAW. If you can’t fix it then images come out like this, though:</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30497509756/in/dateposted/" title="High Dynamic Range Anyone?"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8618/30497509756_a663420ddf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="High Dynamic Range Anyone?" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Which looks OK but you have no idea what’s happening in the foreground. </p>

<h2 id="the-good">The Good</h2>

<p>So, these are my complaints about the camera, which I hope Sony will fix in the next versions of this camera. Thus onwards to the positive sides of the RX100 IV, which really shine. </p>

<p>Print-quality photographs ✓</p>

<p>Besides Hiking in Finland I write for over a dozen of magazines and while that could be an excuse to splurge on a Full-Frame camera and some fancy lenses it really isn’t needed nowadays. The RX100 IV produces superb photos for print, with all the details and colours you’d want. Even if I was out on an assignment for clients I just stood by the fact that I have this wee camera and not a heavy DSLR to shot for them, and once they saw the images there never has been a complaint. I know that I am very lucky with my clients which are open-minded, and that sometimes you just have to show up with a DSLR to a gig to look the part, but as I usually work on my own I really don’t need to impress anyone with the size of my camera. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160876304/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="Fjord sunset"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/2/1489/26160876304_454bd5c53c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fjord sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Nightshots possible  ✓</p>

<p>I love me some pretty night shots. Standing out in the cold and dark, starring at the stars, maybe shivering a wee bit - that’s me feeling alive, small, happy and behind my camera, taking photos of these stars and Northern Lights. Or of impressive city scapes, like last December as <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/arcteryx-workshop-tour.html">I visited Arc’teryx in Vancouver</a>. It sometimes feels a bit like hit-and-miss with the focus, but if the focus is spot-on then the tiny camera produces great images of nightscapes.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29902998894/in/dateposted/" title="Vancouver at night"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8571/29902998894_25c96d4288_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vancouver at night" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30446319961/in/dateposted/" title="Night in the Dolomites"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5805/30446319961_84734d2be7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night in the Dolomites" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Video capable ✓</p>

<p>The Sony RX100 IV can shoot 4K Movies, which is the next step up from 1080 HD. It’s pretty heavy on the Memory Cards (you might want to bring a 128GB card or three) but if it is something you need you will be delighted to know it is possible. I shot at 1080 HD and that’s plenty good, too, and is a lot friendlier for data storage. You can see the <a href="https://youtu.be/1ZN99LOKqjQ">MSR Access 2 Video</a> above for an example of the camera’s video capabilities. I have to say that I find it annoying that Movies can only be recorded when the tiny red Movie button on the back is pushed AND the programme wheel is in Movie mode - if the latter is e.g. in Manuel mode you’ll get a warning on the screen. I would like that I also could start videos by push the shutter button, as that would make sense if the programme wheel is on Movies. </p>

<p>Tilt-able screen? ✓</p>

<p>While I always carry a tripod and a remote Selfies are a great way to be up-close in a photo, and for videos it’s very useful to see yourself when you’re filming. The screen on the RX100 IV can be tilted fully up which is great for Selfies and filming. It can be tilted around 45° downwards which makes it useful for shooting over your head, for example if you’re in a crowd and want to get a good angle from thw back</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30235575070/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV with screen fully up"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5644/30235575070_192148fce5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100 IV with screen fully up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30417085852/in/dateposted/" title="Selfie on Seekofel"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5539/30417085852_4c94913803_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfie on Seekofel" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Long battery life ✓</p>

<p>Oh wow, the battery life. Is. <strong>AMAZING</strong>. When other reviewers complain about the poor battery life of the RX100 IV I can only wonder what they’re doing, but I took in winter, at -5°C outside temperature, 1.200 photos with the RX100 IV on the mountain and the camera’s battery was still half full. On the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/autumn-backpacking-in-the-dolomites.html">Dolomites trip</a> this month I used one battery on average for three days and around 1.500 photos. These are amazing stats for me as I know that with a full battery in the camera and a back-up battery in the chest pocket of my baselayer I can be out a full day and shoot whatever comes my way without needing to worry to run out of juice. I even can browse the photos in the evening and send a shot or five via the in-built Wifi to my phone where I can edit it in the Lightroom and Photoshop Apps before uploading the days shot to <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>. Seriously, the battery life is out-of-this-world and if you’re an occasional shooter you probably can go on a week long trip and shoot all you want to shoot without needing to worry that the battery runs out. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24373293681/in/album-72157663594014166/" title="Sunrise on the Baltic!"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1527/24373293681_a8bfcc613e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Sunrise on the Baltic!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Easy to use ✓</p>

<p>One of the main reasons to get a small camera is that it is easier to use, especially for people that don’t want to dive into deep Menus. The Auto Mode on the RX100 IV is really good and I occasionally use it with great success - often indoors when the lightning is difficult, but also outdoors it produces very good images. You can put it on Auto Mode and give it a friend in the hand and he’ll be fine to take good photos. Pop-up the EVF if it’s bright out there and they will be able to compose the shot via it without problems. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24772101730/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="Powder Shower"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1441/24772101730_36bd02d8e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Powder Shower" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Lightweight ✓</p>

<p>The camera without SD Card and battery is 262 g light, an original Sony battery weighs 24 g and the SD card is 2 g, which means the functioning camera weighs 288 g. I added a wee hand lop which weighs 3 g, so that brings it up to 291 g. Lighter is just using a phone camera (which are not even close as good as the RX100 IV, see further underneath) or no camera at all. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634869063/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Cave Gorna Slatinska 13"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7265/26634869063_296b974bce_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Cave Gorna Slatinska 13" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Weatherproof ✓</p>

<p>While Sony doesn’t advertize the RX100 IV as highly weatherproof it has been just that in my experience. I had it out in snow and rain storms - and because that’s when you’re getting the best photos I of course also had the camera out in that weather. It has no problems with getting wet, and even when moisture has collected on the lens and the extendable lens, I never had a failure on it. Sure, this all has been with care and I wouldn’t hold the camera under a waterfall, but for quick shots in the snow and rain the RX100 IV is more than enough weatherproof. I also don’t have a case for it - I 99% of the time carry it in my hand or chest pocket, so that’s all the weather protection it has had over the last ten months. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24460363514/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="I love me a nice cabin!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1466/24460363514_7edaab5590_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I love me a nice cabin!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another advantage is that the camera has an Electronic Viewfinder. This makes the camera look more like an old-fashioned film camera, which is really useful in street photography when you want to shoot people and not awaken the impression it’s a digital camera. Also for portraits I find the EVF great as it allows the subjects to take you more serious &amp; relax while you’re behind the camera, instead of looking on a screen in front of you. It’s also so small that I can hold it in my hand and shot from the hip, or place it inconspicuously on a table and take a photo of a situation.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30446312051/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV with Flash &amp; EVF open, from behind"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/6/5795/30446312051_11e87408d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100 IV with Flash &amp; EVF open, from behind" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29902998494/in/dateposted/" title="Social Me time"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5463/29902998494_c6a07d2a46_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Social Me time" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24442006569/in/dateposted/" title="Week 4"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1605/24442006569_4b17663d4e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Week 4" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>One thing I love is the possibility of sending via In-built Wifi photos from the camera to my phone, where I can edit it in Lightroom &amp; Photoshop and upload it to Instagram. Gone the times where one needs to first upload everything to the Mac, then edit it there and then transfer it somehow back to the phone. The App and Wifi work great once set up, and is used often and with pleasure. </p>

<p>Where I’m already talking about my phone: <em>How’s the Sony RX100 IV in comparison to the iPhone 6S?</em> you might ponder. I bought the iPhone 6S (800+€) because I thought the camera in that phone finally has reached a level which is great. How wrong I was. Sure, the iPhone 6S is still lighter and smaller than the Sony camera, but there’s World’s between these two devices in photographic terms. I am very disappointed by the quality of the iPhone 6S photos as I expected a lot better quality, but especially in the above mentioned High Dynamic Range situations - think sunsets and sunrises - the iPhone 6S comes not even close in quality to what the Sony RX100 IV can do. The iPhone simply overburdened with a lot of photographic situations, and even if Apple tries to make us think otherwise - I wouldn’t spend so much money on an iPhone ever again. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26741128546/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1508/26741128546_756a100b4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Bikepacking with the Sony RX100 IV is great. I had it along on a few trips where I was riding tours for magazine stories, and capturing the environment &amp; action while on the bike, hands on a handlebar, is still a bit different than hiking, ski-touring or climbing. I stored the camera in my <a href="http://www.ovejanegrathreadworks.com/12-packtrade-frame-bag.html">Oveja Negra 1/2 Pack</a> where it fitted in with all the other kit I have in there. It’s very easy to get out of there - with one hand! - and allows me to capture situations from the bike in around 15 seconds max. I also can fit in my tripod and remote in the 1/2 Pack, and can set things up in a minute or two, which is great for those photos where I + bike need to be completely in the frame. I have experimented with a few cameras on bikepacking &amp; cycle-touring trips and the RX100 IV has been my favourite by far because it is so convenient to use when on (and off) the bike. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22836352233/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Mandatory cycling selfie"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5817/22836352233_1fb4de4f0d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mandatory cycling selfie" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And at the end, still some words on durability. I now have the RX100 IV since December 2015 in use, and it has been with me on at least 14 trips where it has been in the cold, bumped against rocks while climbing, hiked in the sleet and snow of the Dolomites, endured 35°C in Greece and two trade fairs. I have shot well over 27.000 images with it in these ten months, and while it feels that it doesn’t start up as fast anymore as when it was new it still functions as great as on Day one. I expect that I’ll get another year or two of use out of this camera - although I am tempted to update to the RX100 V which was announced a couple of weeks ago as it fixes some of my complaints. But even if I don’t update, I think that a small camera like this one, which has seen so much use and the only <em>“damage”</em> it has taken are scratches on the back screen and some chipped paint, is speaking for the high quality of the Sony RX100 IV.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30235574520/in/dateposted/" title="Field Notes x Sony RX100 IV"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5596/30235574520_5d0d6a1605_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Field Notes x Sony RX100 IV" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-accessories">The Accessories</h2>

<p>Accessories I carry along include always a second <a href="http://amzn.to/2emiMQU">SanDisk Extreme 64GB SDXC Card</a>, as they have an amazing price-to-quality ratio and the write speed of 90MB/ second is great for long bursts. 64GB can last for up to a week of being outdoors and a wee video in between. If I know I will shot more video or lots, and lots of photos, then I’ll take two or three extra cards along - at 30€ a card I consider them pretty affordable (I wish <a href="http://amzn.to/2eJBvUV">External Storage</a> would be as cheap!).</p>

<p>My <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod.html">Velbon V-Pod</a> is still usually along as I might want to take night photos, videos or need to be in the photo and have no-one around to take a photo of me. I also bought a <a href="http://amzn.to/2eAjUzM">Pixel RW221 Remote</a> which is very good - you can be up to 100 m away and still operate the camera, which is great for all kind of photos. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30446316381/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV Ports open"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5344/30446316381_0f082d6397_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100 IV Ports open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then I own three extra batteries and a charger for them. I bought two original <a href="http://amzn.to/2eeYQy1">Sony NP-BX1/M8 Lithium-Ion X Type Batteries</a> and one <a href="http://amzn.to/2eJ8reG">Bundlestar battery</a> as the latter was half the price. The Bundlestar battery feels like it usually last a bit shorter than the original Sony ones, but I haven’t tested this in-depth to see it. The Bundlestar battery works just fine, so if you’re on a budget and need more power take it. The charger I bought is the <a href="http://amzn.to/2emViNX">Charger for Sony NP-BX1 Bundlestar Baxxtar</a> which seems to also be available under different names, usually costing around 16€ or double that with two batteries included. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30497922806/in/dateposted/" title="Accessories"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5528/30497922806_f61b441a91_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Accessories" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bottomline">The Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Sony RX100 IV is not cheap - at almost 1.000€ it is amongst the most expensive pocket cameras you can find and chances are that you don’t need this good a camera. If you’re, however, a passionate photographer &amp; outdoor enthusiast who likes to document his adventures and be able to possibly print large photos of them, then the Sony RX100 IV is worth considering. Also for professional photographers who want to go lighter or need a high-quality back-up camera the RX100 IV is worth a look, as it shots RAW and 4K Video.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748741131/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Bodensee"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8007/29748741131_a681170dde_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodensee" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With this cave-eat out of the way: This is the camera you want to document your adventures. When you’re heading out on a once-in-a-lifetime trip, like hiking a long trail, visit the Annapurna Basecamp or go ski-touring on Svalbard, then you want to have the Sony RX100 IV along to make photos of your adventure. Superb image quality with an impressive 16.0 FPS you can shot face-paced action like skiing, climbing and trailrunning, while the small size allows for shots from the hip for street photography. The EVF lets you operate the camera in the brightest sunlight without problems, and the colours and images this little ultralight camera produces are simply superb and often on-par with much larger &amp; more expensive DSLRs. Did I mention how light and small it is and that I usually carry it in my chest pocket? This is the ultralight backpacking &amp; climbing camera to rule them all. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is the camera you want to document your adventures. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>By the way: On my many trips with athletes which create images and videos for their own Social Media channels, the Sony RX100 IV (or an earlier version) is what they carry. I have friends who ski, climb, mountaineer and trailrun professionally, and like me they carry this wee camera along on their adventures, because they too consider it the best tool to create content for their Social media presences while not carrying too much weight.  </p>

<p>Convinced and want to take a Sony RX100 IV along on your trips? Then buy one via one of these affiliate links: <a href="http://amzn.to/2eYWA1p">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/2eUfshc">Amazon.de</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/2emVv3K">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p><em>More photos of the camera and its details on <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157675534458596">Flickr</a>.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148754883/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="What a view!"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/2/1694/26148754883_8441890563_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="What a view!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Sidenote: If you want a relative light weight camera with the absolute best possible image quality I would recommend getting a Full-Frame camera like the <a href="http://amzn.to/2eZqouN">Sony A7RII</a> with a <a href="http://amzn.to/2eZvk2z">great all-round lens</a>. It is just that that combo costs you upwards of 5.400€ and weighs at least 1.511 g, which is more than five times what the RX100 IV puts on the scales. And honestly, unless you’re going to print A1 prints or larger you likely won’t need the power the A7RII has.</em></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>:  <em>There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony RX100III Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T18:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You want to go lighter than a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Full Frame Camera</a> but still want to have superb images for online and print? Then the Sony RX100III is what you want - an Ultralight Backpackers &amp; Climber’s Dream.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033934580" title="Sony RX100III Size Comparison with a Field Notes notebook by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7571/16033934580_a455c13d76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III Size Comparison with a Field Notes notebook" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’m still looking for the <em>Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> in terms of photographic equipment. It’s the camera which has only advantages, satisfies all my needs and is good enough for all my requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Print-quality photographs</li>
  <li>Nightshots possible</li>
  <li>Video capable</li>
  <li>Tiltscreen</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
</ul>

<p>That are <strong>MINE</strong>. Yours might be different. Mine are from a perspective of someone who needs high-quality photos for articles in magazines and online, likes to shot videos once in a while and does not like to carry heavy. I have plenty of colleagues who think like me, while others prefer something more substantial in terms of cameras. There’s no wrong or right and it always depends on your needs, and add in that I like to experiment and you can see why I was happy to give the <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/cyber-shot-kompaktikamerat/dsc-rx100m3">Sony RX100III</a> a spin when Sony asked me to. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033806418" title="Sony RX100III with EVF open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/16033806418_f4324c7d8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III with EVF open" /></a></p>

<p>Like usual this is no pixel-peeping review. <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-cybershot-dsc-rx100-m3">DP Review</a> does a good job looking at all the tech inside, I prefer to take the camera along outdoors and see how it performs in the field. So, 80% of the photos in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">Höga Kusten Trip Report</a> where shot with the RX100III, which means I got a full four days of photos out of the RX100III, or a total of 632 photos on one fully charged battery. That’s significantly above what is claimed (that would be 320 on one battery charge), and given that the weather on the Högakustenleden was cold and wet I find it a superb performance. It ticked one need of my list, so lets see how the others fared.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601476623" title="Sony RX100III in Selfie Mode by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8646/15601476623_65c5770695_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III in Selfie Mode" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033910680" title="Sony RX100III side with screen open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7476/16033910680_49c341d4d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III side with screen open" /></a></p>

<p>Tilt-able screen? ✓</p>

<p>The screen can be tilted fully up, great for Selfies, or at an angle, which is great if you want to shoot very low or from above your head. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033949750" title="Sony RX100III handling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7462/16033949750_519d7a2c36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III handling" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219705131" title="Viewing the view stop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7514/16219705131_dd6c0e5321_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the view stop" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601446823" title="Sony RX100III with Flash open and EVF on by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7573/15601446823_fea0a0e911_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III with Flash open and EVF on" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601438203" title="Sony RX100III taking a photo with the EVF by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7479/15601438203_b4d5205bc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III taking a photo with the EVF" /></a></p>

<p>Easy to use? ✓</p>

<p>Yeps, it is. Give it a mate in the hand who is not a camera geek and he will be able to make a great photo of you &amp; be delighted about the lightweight and easy to use camera. Sun is shining? No problem: Pop up the EVF and use it to take a photo. Although it does look a bit funny if you put that tiny camera up to your face to take a photo. </p>

<p>Print-quality photographs? ✓</p>

<p>Yes, it does produce stunning photos which have and will be printed in magazines from me. It can shoot in Sony’s Raw format which is fully supported by <a href="http://amzn.to/1LLfGPC">Lightroom</a> which makes it a great choice for professional photographers, too - I even have colleagues which only use this camera for all their photos. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15598868014" title="Sony RX100III front with open battery compartment and battery &amp; SDHD Card out by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/15598868014_e442886a44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III front with open battery compartment and battery &amp; SDHD Card out" /></a></p>

<p>Lightweight ✓</p>

<p>The RX100III is 290 g with the battery inside, with an extra 9 g for the <a href="http://amzn.to/1LLgc01">SanDisk Extreme 16GB Memory Card</a> I use. Which tips the scales at less than 300 g. Which is superb. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034258558" title="Night Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8603/16034258558_8d5ccdb6a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night Selfie" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15306067413" title="Helsinki Adventure Night by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15306067413_6fb9848e71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Helsinki Adventure Night" /></a></p>

<p>Nightshots possible ✓</p>

<p>You might think that a small and lightweight camera like the RX100III might need to have some things it does not excel at. Low light and night time photography is difficult already, usually requiring high ISO capabilities and large sensors. I wasn’t sure what I could expect from this little camera, but was positively surprised at the photos it produced in low light and at night. That Night Selfie was just after dusk, and while it’s not 100% sharp it’s a fine image, capturing the rain well, giving it a nice atmosphere. Also the indoor shot at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/helsinki-adventure-night.html">Helsinki adventure Night</a> came out superb, which ticks this point for me. Sadly I wasn’t able to try star photography with it, though I am positive that it should be possible.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220528902" title="Sony RX100III back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8624/16220528902_74fa472068_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III back" /></a></p>

<p>Video capable ✓</p>

<p>Yes, the RX100III also shoots some crisp, fine videos. It’s a bit counter-intuitive to shoot video after you took a photo, as you need to turn the dial on top into the Video mode to be able to record something. I also found the Record button at a strange location, and operating it with anything else than super-thing liner gloves is something where you can learn patience. Once it is rolling you can make adjustments to settings, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220497942" title="Sony RX100III handling with index finger on trigger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7524/16220497942_678635c6ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III handling with index finger on trigger" /></a></p>

<p><strong>And then for some further usability thoughts on it.</strong> I used the RX100III with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> and the <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/leash?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Leash</a> which I found a superb combo. I bought the <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/microplate?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Micro Plate</a> for it which is ideal with it and allows me to have the small &amp; lightweight camera securely attached to me. Speaking of small &amp; light: If you’re used to large &amp; heavy cameras this will be quite a change. I use usually cameras which are slightly bigger in size so having such a tiny camera, which easily fits in even the smallest chest pockets, is something I first needed to get used to. But then it was great.</p>

<p>Because the camera is so small people with large hands also might it difficult to operate. I have probably Medium-sized hands and found it OK to use with one hand, but usually used two. One with the finger on the trigger, the other to slightly stabilize it. Taking Selfies with the camera is easy as pie, and the Flash and EVF which can be stored away are good, too. The Focal length is 24–70 mm and the Aperture is a magnificent F1.8 - F2.8 which I liked a lot. The lens is from ZEISS which means it’s high-quality, take a look at the photos in some of the mentioned articles above or Albums underneath and you’ll see. </p>

<p>I found the battery life superb, sadly you can charge the battery online inside the camera via an USB cable, which is crap if you want to take photos with it while it loads. There’s an external Sony car charger available so at least if you’re on the go you can charge it, as well as several third-party chargers. For longer trips I’d always take an extra battery or two along, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033758968" title="Sony RX100III top and On by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16033758968_295fa5532c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III top and On" /></a></p>

<p>But are there problems with it? Well, I’m again hard-pressed to say something negative about the camera. Sure, looked at some things in isolation you could find some errors. But if I keep in mind that this is a 290 g, super-compact camera which produces superb images and has a long battery life then complaining about things like little buttons seem senseless. At 900€ the RX100III isn’t cheap, either, but there’s only a handful of cameras which play in the same league than it, and those all are a tad heavier and more expensive. </p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong>. If weight is at a premium in your pack or on your harness, but I still want to take great photos, then the RX100III would be my choice. I have <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/the-sony-rx100/">discussed with Jacob</a> about the different iterations of the RX100 before and agree that the high price might be what might keep most people getting it. But once you have it and take it on a trip, see how it performs on the trail and on the rock, in sunshine and rain, and the fine photos it takes you’re very unlikely to leave it at home. If only the lightest and best image quality does the job for you, consider the RX100III. For me it is the closest to an <em>Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> yet. </p>

<p>View <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157649751997029/">more photos of the Sony RX100III on Flickr</a> and more photos shot with it in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157648982512379/">Höga Kusten Album</a>.</p>

<p>You can support Hiking in Finland and buy the RX100III at your flavour of <a href="http://amzn.to/1BUbRPZ">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1DESZa3">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1DET2Ta">Amazon.de</a> or get it from your local <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/sony-dsc-rx100m3-kompaktikamera.html">photography shop</a> or directly from <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/cyber-shot-kompaktikamerat/dsc-rx100m3">Sony</a>. And if you think that you won’t need the latest Sony RX100 camera then you’re in luck: The <a href="http://amzn.to/1BUdbCp">RX100II</a> can be found in a tasty bundle for as low as $600 and the still great <a href="http://amzn.to/1yGsLAC">RX100</a> I found in a sweet bundle for as low as $400. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035685067" title="Views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8682/16035685067_1c22604b18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony A7R Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T06:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A 407 g Full Frame camera? Yes please. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15457679781" title="Sony A7R without lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3935/15457679781_9874095671_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R without lens" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Earlier in the year I had the pleasure of test-driving the latest creation from <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/kamerat">Sony</a>, their <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/jarjestelmakamerat/ilce-7r">A7R camera</a>. I’ve been a user of Sony cameras since over three years and while my Sony NEX-5n is still a trusty companion on many trips, I’m in the market for a new camera. So having being able to use the A7R in what I usually do was a superb opportunity that I wasn’t going to pass up, even if our love affair only was to last for several weeks and I knew saying good bye to it would hurt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460816735" title="Sony A7R and Sony NEX-5n by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15460816735_9cda8d1df7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R and Sony NEX-5n" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re looking for pixel-peeping and very detailed technical information, I’d like to send you to <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-alpha-a7r/">DP Review</a> who do a rather spectacular job with that sorts of things. If you’re an outdoor photographer, journalist or writer who wants to know how the A7R performs in the outdoors, I invite you to stay for a while and read my thoughts on this camera. I will delve first a (little) bit into the technical details and how the camera handles, and then discuss in detail how the camera works in the field.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274063999" title="Sony A7R - Back view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3934/15274063999_ae9d765df2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R - Back view" /></a></p>

<p>First off: At a suggested retail price of 2300€ for the body only and a good lens setting you back another 800€, the A7R is in my opinion a camera for people who earn a living with photos. Sure, if you have the spare change to buy a 3000€ camera you could get it, but chances are you either way don’t know how to use its full potential. And a lot of potential she has, the A7R.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15458998652" title="Sony A7R - Having a good grip on it by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15458998652_82cf23ce8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Having a good grip on it" /></a></p>

<p>The camera lays beautiful in the hand and it is easy to operate the different controls and functions with one hand. The sealed alloy and composite body is weatherproof and allows for a good, reassuring grip, even with gloves on. The 3-inch tilting LCD turns up and down and makes shooting e.g. Macros easier, although the XGA electronic viewfinder is where it’s at. The viewfinder eyepiece is large and comfortable, and far enough away so that you also can use it with (sun) glasses on. I have been sceptical of viewfinders in the past as (good) LCD screens are more than adequate in composing photos, but as my photographic needs evolve I come back to viewfinders and find them increasingly a necessity for my kind of shooting.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272647760" title="Sony A7R - View on top with thumb on the trigger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5601/15272647760_fddc5ae121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - View on top with thumb on the trigger" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272582069" title="Sony A7R - Thumb access to different buttons on the back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15272582069_311a4c0d93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Thumb access to different buttons on the back" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re a control freak you will love the possibilities the A7R offers: Three customizable buttons and four dials (front, rear, exposure compensation &amp; an additional rear dial around the four-way controller), and several buttons for accessing different settings (Menu, Trash, Playback, etc.). If you shot Manual the front and rear dials allow you to adjust shutter speed and aperture, while the directional controller lets you set the drive mode, white balance mode and what’s displayed on the screen. The shutter button sits above the On/ Off switch which I found comfortable in use - I could switch the camera on with my index finger and then have my thumb immediately on the shutter. The camera did need a moment to start up, something that might be better nowadays with an updated Firmware.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272723658" title="Sony A7R - Back view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3934/15272723658_9fc99380d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Back view" /></a></p>

<p>On the right side of the body you see in the above photo the dedicated movie recording button (red), which for my liking was a bit far in the back. The A7R has Full HD video recording capabilities which makes it a mighty fine video camera to produce super-sharp HD videos.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/QUHHBay1x14?list=UU927vE_KkPy6pFJboaJ9Lig" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>On the left side you have four ports behind two plastic doors: Micro, Headphones, Multi (allows you to charge the battery) and micro-HDMI. On the top there’s a Hotshoe which accepts an external flash or <a href="http://amzn.to/1yJHYWK">Microphone</a>. The A7R uses the NP-FW50 Lithium battery like the NEX-5n, which was very useful for me as I so could use my charger and spare batteries on tour. The default charging method is via the USB port which I think is a hassle, so I recommend getting the external charger or the battery grip.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274058359" title="Sony A7R - Side I/O ports with the Rode Video Pro on top &amp; connected by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3936/15274058359_b578a549e7_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Sony A7R - Side I/O ports with the Rode Video Pro on top &amp; connected" /></a></p>

<p>The A7R has an E-Mount like my NEX camera which means I can use E-Mount lenses - though they will crop the photo it’s useful if you already have a NEX camera - and with an <a href="http://amzn.to/1pMVoI0">adapter</a> also allows you to use Canon, Nikon, Pentax and other lenses. This could make it interesting for people who are switching from Nikon or Canon but want to keep to use their glass. With an adapter you’re also able to use other Sony A-mount lenses. To really get the most out this full frame sensor you’ll want to invest into a (few) Sony FE-series lenses. I used the <a href="http://amzn.to/1xl9bKL">35mm F2.8 Carl Zeiss</a> and found it a superb lens, though for outdoor photography I would have found a faster 16 mm or 20 mm lens even more useful.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460475032" title="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15460475032_be1fa0e188_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens" /></a></p>

<p>With 36 megapixels and a max resolution of 7360 x 4912 it are photos where the A7R really shines, so lets have a look how the camera handles in the field.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274057619" title="Sont A7R - Composing a photo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15274057619_9d2c7a6105_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sont A7R - Composing a photo" /></a></p>

<p>Together with the Carl Zeiss 35mm F2.8 lens (120 g) the A7R weighs 585 g (including battery, which is 58 g). With this lens it is a compact package that fits into large jacket pockets and comfortably under the jacket in bad weather. It’s also light enough to not bother you when wearing around your neck, though I would update the strap to one from <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/slide?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design</a> for more functionality. </p>

<p>The first time I used the camera was at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a>, which was a good test for it. Lots of white in different shades, colourful clothing, early dusks, northern lights. It performed well, and would have been outstanding if I would have had the functions dialled in better. With gloves on the camera was easy to use, but things like smaller buttons where more difficult to control. That meant either setting White Balance, ISO, Aperture et al. before hand or take the gloves off to fine adjust settings.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445682176" title="Sony A7R - Roadtrippin&#x27; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15445682176_9e35c9589d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Roadtrippin&#x27;" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15282159468" title="Sony A7R - Ice climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15282159468_f9a430f0c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Ice climbing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465648641" title="Sony A7R - Aurora Borealis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15465648641_46952da3d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p>In warm daylight the camera was a pleasure to use and produced almost perfect images without needing much post processing. Colours were bright and true to colour, and given that this can be a very hard environment for good photos, with all the snow and ice, I was very happy with the output. The LCD screen is great to review photos on the fly and it’s fast to delete bad shots, but also works well to compose a photo if you can not/ don’t want to use the Viewfinder. The Viewfinder is great in use, and helped in the bright and snowy environment of Northern Sweden to compose a few good shots.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15281893779" title="Sony A7R - All Smiles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15281893779_8c91a81b2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - All Smiles" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465644681" title="Sony A7R - Getting schooled by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15465644681_f1772308e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Getting schooled" /></a></p>

<p>The Magnesium Alloy Body didn’t get very cold, and bumps against the ice and rock didn’t bother it. Something that did bother me was the shutter sound, which I didn’t manage to silence. I like stealth photography and even if large landscapes aren’t scared away by the sound, animals are, and also during street photography it’s something that can give you away. The shutter also seemed to be slow, taking a good moment to make its <em>“Clack”</em> sound to take a picture. While I got used to it, it’s something I’d very much would like to be seen improved. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445745166" title="Sony A7R - Snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15445745166_75ff8416ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Snow" /></a></p>

<p>One of the big benefits of the A7R is obviously that it is a full frame. The detail you get from the camera is pretty amazing and  allows you to reduce the resolution in post or crop aggressively. The example of this lonely reed against a late March afternoon sky is a good example:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465621521" title="Sony A7R - Reed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5597/15465621521_cd0f005fa2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Reed" /></a></p>

<p>And now the crop of the above photo:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468757625" title="Sony A7R - Reed Crop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3932/15468757625_5293bd9a0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Sony A7R - Reed Crop" /></a></p>

<p>The amount of sharp detail you get is wonderful and gives you a lot more creative options when working with this camera. You can include a lot more of the subject’s environment and still capture plenty of detail which is highly useful if you decide to crop the photo later, which is great if you are in a hurry to capture a unique moment but can’t compose the image perfectly.</p>

<p>The A7R also has a good Auto Focus/ Facial Recognition, even if the subject isn’t 100% to be identified. Take this <em>“Portrait”</em> I shot of myself for a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/trekking-magazin/">trekking Magazin</a> article as an example:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445671636" title="Sony A7R - &quot;Portrait&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5598/15445671636_c449958015_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - &quot;Portrait&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>This photo has not been touched in post, but with a few easy adjustments was perfect for my article. However, I really loved how good the camera put the focus on me (and I wasn’t standing behind the Viewfinder, obviously =) and blurred out the background. The colours again are rich and lush out of the camera and details like the Ripstop pattern on the windjacket are clearly to be seen.</p>

<p>Night and low-light shooting is something that you really need to put an effort in to get it right, but with a good camera and a good lens things get easier. I think one could get some really nice illuminated-shelters-in-the-hills with the A7R + 35 mm lens, sadly I didn’t have time for such a test so this twilight shot from town needs to do. With focus peaking on it’s easy to get the stuff sharp that matter, and it’s something I highly recommend always using - also in daylight shots.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468453232" title="Sony A7R - Twilight by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15468453232_b2c0eedd0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Twilight" /></a>
ƒ/2.8, 2 seconds, ISO 800</p>

<p>The pine has a lot of detail and the stars that you can see are nice and crisp. I edited it lightly in <a href="http://amzn.to/1vL8VDP">Lightroom</a> to bring out some details and added a bit of clarity, but even in camera on the screen it looked already good. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468786525" title="Sony A7R - Waterdrops by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15468786525_8408833471_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Waterdrops" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15284760469" title="Sony A7R - Scarpa Rebel Ultra Gtx in the snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3941/15284760469_052c55e581_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Scarpa Rebel Ultra Gtx in the snow" /></a></p>

<p>Taking product shots is something I do quite a bit for the blog and the magazines, and also here the A7R performed very satisfying. On the top you see clearly that the focus is on the water drops on the pants, and in these you can see how they reflect their surroundings - the kitchen windows, in this case. Underneath we again have a difficult case: Patterned orange and snow. A combination which gives some of my other cameras a headache, but the A7R produced a perfect image.</p>

<p>Also indoors the A7R did very well, and I snapped some nice shots at the Art Museum here in Vaasa at an exhibition earlier in winter. Again colours and sharpness are outstanding and as the full frame sensor records so much detail it would have been easy to crop this composition if needed (but it wasn’t, I was quite happy with this shot).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468829345" title="Sony A7R - Art Museum by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2950/15468829345_b99c8ecb23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Art Museum" /></a></p>

<p>In conclusion I can say that my experiences with the Sony A7R were nothing but superb. Sure, it took a second longer to start up as I’d like, it took a moment between shots to be ready again, the shutter was a bit loud, there’s still just a fairly limited selection of FE lenses out, and yes, it’s pricey. But the plusses outweigh these small complaints for me. The biggest advantage is that with the 35 mm lens you have a Full Frame camera which is less than 600 g. In comparison: The Canon EOS 5D Mk III is 950 g for the body only, and the Nikon D800 still puts 900 g for the body only around your neck. </p>

<p>Then there’s the weatherproof body that withstood at least light impacts on ice and rock and had no problems operating in light minus temperatures this winter. The layout of the dials and buttons needs some getting used to, but once you have internalized the layout you’ll be able to use the camera with your eye to the viewfinder.  I loved that it had a regular sized Microphone port, and if I ever get a phone with NFC I’m happy to know that I can just touch it against the A7R and have the two linked, being able to send photos from the camera to the phone very easily. </p>

<p>A large plus is also that thanks to various adapters you’re able to use a massive variety of 35 mm lenses with no field-of-view crop, and if you’re already a Sony NEX camera user you will be able to use your E-Mount lenses on the A7R (with field-of-view crop, though). What’s nice about the 35 mm lens possibility is obviously that many of these lenses can be bought cheaply, and as I have used a few old lenses on my NEX-5n I know how wonderful it is to use a manual lens. Sony is set to release some more FE lenses in 2015, and also Zeiss just announced at the photokina a very nice pair of manual Full-Frame lenses for the A7R and its siblings. </p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline:</strong> The Sony A7R is a lightweight, compact camera that produces outstanding photos and video. If you’re an (outdoor) photographer, journalist or writer who needs high-quality photos with lots of details and the ability to crop the A7R will appeal as it’s such a portable camera and won’t weigh you down when you’re hiking and climbing far off the beaten track.</p>

<p>I recommend you go visit your local camera shop to have a look at the camera and the lenses. If you’re in Finland, <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/sony-ilce-7r-runko.html">Rajala</a> has the A7R right now on offer for 1600€ for the body only. </p>

<p>You can see <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157643203488075/">more photos of the Sony A7R and photos taken with it on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460817595" title="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15460817595_676a7bca38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
