<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rab | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/rab/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-05T13:16:00+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lightweight Hiking Pants]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-pants.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-28T18:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-pants</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Together with a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts.html">lightweight shirt</a> you’ll need something lightweight to cover your legs - unless you like sunburn, nettle and mosquito stings, and dust - lots of dust because you are so fast &amp; light!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6966862963/" title="Seven-legged hiking pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7176/6966862963_aa9a9fffb2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Seven-legged hiking pants" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Pants =/= Pants. I didn’t think so in the beginning, but have realized through much experience since that lighter pants are a lot more comfortable than <em>“heavy”</em> pants. I don’t have objective proof that they make you hike faster and better, but a well fitting, light pants just makes the hiking in my experience more comfortable. All pants underneath I have picked with durability, windproofness, comfort and quick-drying in mind and they’ve seen years of use, so if you’re looking for a new pair of pants - check these out! <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157629182054730/">More photos of all pants on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-palisade">Arc’teryx Palisade</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 307 g</td>
      <td> Material: 94% TerraTex—nylon, 6% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>My go-to pants since they arrived three years ago. Have they held up well in those years? Absolutely. The only damage to them is a tiny burn hole in the leg as I was sitting too close to the fire and a spark burned through it, but other than that they’re still in tip-top shape. And I haven’t been kind to them: Backpacking, bouldering, climbing, bikepacking, hiking, and because they’re so comfortable I’ve also worn them during “normal” activities whenever I could get away with it. All pockets are zipped which is superb, because that way your phone, wallet, keys and whatnot stays inside and doesn’t fall out of your pocket while you hike, run, climb or sit. They are absolutely windproof, dry very quickly, are a slim fit and very minimalistic in their appearance so fit well under a pair of rain pants. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Get a pair at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-palisade-pant-graphite.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/10Fk74J">Backcountry.com</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13XfHu6">CampSaver.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870574360/" title="Arc'teryx Palisade pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7291/8870574360_d19a99c37e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arc'teryx Palisade pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="backpacking-light-thorofare-pants">Backpacking Light Thorofare Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: M</td>
      <td> Weight: 113 g</td>
      <td> Material: 100% Nylon (I guess)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The Thorofare pants get’s a honourable mention - not because it’s the lightest pants I own, but because it ain’t available anymore (unless you happen to pick one up on Gear Swap). Windproof, light like a feather, quick drying, two pockets and two cargo pockets, and an elastic “belt” to keep the pants up (don’t overload those pockets thus). In hot environments where there’s no wind going they might be a tad hot, but other than that they’re excellent. If you can get your hands on one, get a pair for those SUL trips where the lightest pants is what you want.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870106505/" title="BPL Thorofare pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5453/8870106505_333a97a2a7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="BPL Thorofare pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-traverse-pants">Rab Traverse Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 295 g</td>
      <td> Material: 93% Polyamide, 7% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The second-most worn pants, the <a href="http://rab.uk.com/">Rab</a> Traverse pants also sports zipped pockets, which in my book is always good as it is just a bit safer. It has a push-button closure, which is very comfortable and is bomb-proof. UPF 35 gives plenty of UV protection for your legs, and if you only carry one pant and want to wash it on the trail - the Traverse pants will be dry again in no time. A very comfortable fit that’s also excellent for acrobatic climbing moves, this is a pants that is great in the backcountry as well as in town. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870099019/" title="Rab Traverse Pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2880/8870099019_9bc4a6648d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab Traverse Pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="patagonia-zip-off-pants">Patagonia Zip-Off Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 326 g</td>
      <td> Material: 96% Polyamide, 4% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>A Zip-off pants?</em> Yes! <em>Why?</em> Because in very hot &amp; humid environments I like shorts. So instead of trapping my athletic calves in polyamide, I let them taste the sun and wind. It’s getting too windy? Just zip them back on. Patagonia was extremely smart when making the zippers for this pants: They’re two different colours, so no more mixing up left &amp; right legs. Also this pant is durable, windproof and dries very fast, and if you walk a lot in environments where the weather lets you wear shorts during the day while in the evenings a long pair of pants is preferable, check these out.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-nomader-zip-off-hose-stone.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/18x7PAt">Backcountry.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870750934/" title="Patagonia Pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3783/8870750934_9dcbf1d205_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fjllrven-greenland-trousers">Fjällräven Greenland Trousers</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 44</td>
      <td> Weight: 537 g</td>
      <td> Material: G-1000 aka 65% polyester, 35% cotton</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>Fjällräven pants?</em> Yes, because I still own a pair. The defacto standard trouser for the outdoors man &amp; women population in Scandinavia, it feels like it’s the pants you gotta wear when you go to the Fjell. I thought so too when I was a young grasshopper, but not anymore. If you waxed them before you head out they’re OK waterproof-ish, though they will soak through in a deluge just as much as the other pants above. And then they need more time to dry. They got seven pockets, which would mean an SUL backpacker could just carry his gear in this pants. I also needed a belt with these pants, as the sizing of them is even in the smallest size too big for me.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/s/fj%C3%A4llr%C3%A4ven/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/fjaellraeven-trekkinghose/">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13Xglb4">Backcountry.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870061787/" title="Fjällräven Greenland trousers by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8546/8870061787_7a2846ab8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fjällräven Greenland trousers" /></a></p>

<p>There are a lot more pants - but I haven’t worn them and hence can’t judge them. The most worn ones for me are the Arc’teryx and Rab pants, as I like their zippered pockets, I know that they’re super-durable and allow enough movement for climbing and bouldering, they’re windproof and dry quickly if they get wet. Oh, and they look both also rather good! <strong>What are your favourite lightweight pants?</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lightweight Hiking Shirts]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T18:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Summer. What better time to be outdoors: The sun shines, a breeze goes through the grass, a light pack is on your back, butterflies fly by, and you wear a light shirt to keep you cool.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bmp_creep/8698798735/" title="2012-08-02 00.40.02 by b.m.p., on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8268/8698798735_4a8df70265_b.jpg" width="1024" height="679" alt="2012-08-02 00.40.02" /></a>
© <a href="http://hikesinatra.blogspot.com/">bmp</a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="patagonia-mens-capilene-1-silkweight-t-shirt">Patagonia Men’s Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: M</td>
      <td> Weight: 94 g</td>
      <td> Material: 100% Polyester</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>If you look for the lightest shirt with the best environmental credentials and great looks, then you won’t need to look further than the Patagonia Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirts. I love mine and its probably my most-worn shirt if I hit the trail. It dries in mere minutes in the sun, the funk (<em>that’s informal American English for smelly</em>) is minimal and 15-UPF sun protection keeps you from burning (although it could be more). It’s surprisingly durable for being so light, climbing and bushwacking didn’t pull a single thread from it, and it’s been in use since two years already. It feels very good on the skin and you’ll look good with this shirt on the trail as well as walking the dog in town.  My go-to shirt, if it’s not in the wash!</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-capilene-1-sw-graphic-t-shirt.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-capilene-1-silkweight-stretch-t-shirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.patagonia.com/us/product/mens-capilene-baselayer-1-silkweight-graphic-t-shirt?p=45321-1-791">Patagonia</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13nUCrw">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/18qa7T1">REI</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/13nUQ1Z">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717114654/" title="Patagonia Men's Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7425/8717114654_2ecd5b0f2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Men's Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt" /></a></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-ether-crew-ss">Arc’teryx Ether Crew SS</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 108 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 100% Polyester</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This shirt has been updated since I got it (it’s the problem of testing gear long-term, ya see!) and now sports mesh underarm panels, which does seem like a very nice improvement. However, my “old” shirt is still looking good as it is quite durable. It’s a good looking shirt, though after a few days wearing it on the trail it needs a wash as the guff (that’s informal Scottish for smelly) is tangible. It’s UPF Rating of 50+ keeps your skin aristocratic white, while the flatlocked seams add much comfort to the wearing experience. The fabric comes in a bunch of nice colours, and once you’ve hiked up a mountain in 35°C and the shirt is drenched in your sweat the fabric’s quick-drying capabilities will kick in and you’ll have a dry shirt in no time (well, maybe about 10 to 15 minutes).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/16OIeod">Backcountry</a> </td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-ether-comp-crew-ss-funktionsshirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717116334/" title="Arc'teryx Ether Crew SS by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7328/8717116334_8431851723_b.jpg" width="1024" height="546" alt="Arc'teryx Ether Crew SS" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-meco-120tee">Rab MeCo 120 Tee</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 111 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 65% Merino, 35% Cocona</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>A shirt made of <em>ethically sourced Australian Merino wool and recycled polyester with Cocona technology</em> which has gotten a lot of positive reviews. I have found them great shirts, the 120g/m² fabric is light and dries very fast, rivalling the synthetic shirts above. They do pill a bit, but it’s just a cosmetic thing and doesn’t affect it’s durability. Speaking off, I used mine for climbing, hiking, cycling and everyday use for over 12 months, and they still look great. The reflective details are a nice touch which cyclists and pedestrians will appreciate, and the flatlock seams make them comfortable to wear. They also do not easily smell, I can wear mine for five days and more and they still don’t reek. If you’re looking for the best of both worlds - that’s merino &amp; synthetic combined - then you’ve found it with Rab’s MeCo garments. Here’s more <a href="http://rab.uk.com/reference/technology/baselayer/meco.html">info on Cocona</a> if you’re of the curious kind.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/10lOht7">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/baselayer/meco-120-tee.html">Rab</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/rab_meco_120_tee.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8715999439/" title="Rab MeCo 120 Tee by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7339/8715999439_0eccb79614_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab MeCo 120 Tee" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-meco-120ls-tee">Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 148 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 65% Merino, 35% Cocona</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The same material and properties than the Rab MeCo 120 Tee above, I have used this longsleeve on colder days in spring and autumn, and as a layering piece in winter. Because it dries so fast it is in winter quite nice to wear, but not on its own - an Aclima Woolnet longsleeve underneath it is a great combination. Also for summer use, if you want to protect your arms a bit more from the sun or easily get cold in a stiff breeze, this longsleeve fits the bill. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/11eqJNm">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/baselayer/meco-120-long-sleeve-tee.html">Rab</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/rab_meco_120_long_sleeved_tee.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717116892/" title="Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/8717116892_7af29e03fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee" /></a></p>

<h2 id="icebreaker-tech-t-lite-short-sleeve-lancewood">icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 138 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 100% Merino</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>It’s a fancy name, but then it’s a fancy shirt as well! The only 100% Merino summer shirt in my closet at the moment, this is a great T-shirt in so many respects: Even after a week on the trail it doesn’t reek (maybe just a tiny bit), it dries reasonably fast (slower than the synthetic shirts, though), it’s very comfortable on the skin and it too looks superb. Where the synthetic shirts dry fast, the Merino one needs a bit longer to get dry, though that also can be a benefit if you’re hiking in sweltering heat - in that case the shirt provides a bit more cooling. If you’re hiking on a trail where you’ll be in the company of a lot of other people (staying in huts, for example) this one might be your best choice - you’ll smell less and look good =)</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/10lFBTB">icebreaker</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/icebreaker-sf150-tech-t-lite-lancewood-funktionsshirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Ficebreaker-tech-lite-stripe-mountain-t-shirt-short-sleeve-mens">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10008&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Ftech-t-lite-short-sleeve-men-s">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/icebreaker-tech-t-lite-ridge-stealth.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8715996421/" title="icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7322/8715996421_6cca361558_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood" /></a></p>

<p>Of course these aren’t all lightweight shirts that are available. You can get good shirts from <a href="http://www.chocolatefishmerino.co.uk/">Chocolate Fish</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/17JcA9E">The North Face</a>, <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.eu/mens-shirts-tees/mens-tops,default,sc.html?prefn1=productSubcategory&amp;prefv1=Short%20Sleeve&amp;prefn2=activity&amp;prefv2=024">Mountain Hardwear</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/or-gear/shirts.html">Outdoor Research</a> (which also make <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/or-gear/shirts/mens-echo-sentinel-l-s-crew.html">Insect Shield</a> shirts!), <a href="http://www.salomonrunning.com/ir/segment/trail-running-tees.html">Salomon</a>, <a href="http://marmot.com/catalog/mens/shirts/ultralight/216-132-185--4?ft=185">Marmot</a> and many more.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8716001087/" title="Lightweight hiking shirts by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7389/8716001087_df160b3591_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lightweight hiking shirts" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hoodylicious]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/hoodylicious.html"/>
    <updated>2012-11-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/hoodylicious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The venerable hoody - a longsleeved shirt with an attached hood. It’s a great garment because you can never lose your hood - unlike your hat or cap - and thus always have something to keep your neck and head warm. It’s great between spring and autumn, when it allows you to leave your sleeping hat at home; but really shines in winter, when cold wind and sub-zero temperatures dig into your skin and you’re happy to pull that hood over your head and zip it closed, so that there’s less skin exposed to the elements. </p>

<p><strong>Five different Hoodys compared. Cthulhu approved.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6820744542/" title="Hoodylicious by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7200/6820744542_779254c4b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hoodylicious" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="smartwool-midweight-hoody">Smartwool Midweight Hoody</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170145800/" title="DSC03780 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7124/8170145800_3ab6a28c2e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Smartwool Midweight Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/smartwool-midweight-hoody-wollhoody/">Smartwool Midweight Hoody</a> appeared last year in La Maison Morkel, and has been worn a lot since. Skiing, hiking, cycling, walking with my son - it’s a trusty companion between September and May. Made of 100% Merino Wool it hugs you with all that soft warmness, as if you’re lying down next to one of them fine Merino Sheep who donated its wool to make it. The Merino used is a thicker weave than in the BPL Beartooth, which makes it 37 gram heavier - and a lot warmer. The hood is great, it has thumbloops, and a deep zipper for good ventilation when you’re running warm. The thumbloops are the best in my opinion, they warm your hands up quickly, are super-comfortable and easily layer over/ under gloves. My favourite Merino hoody for winter.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170155422/" title="P1050407 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8209/8170155422_ac252d058f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Smartwool Midweight Hoody" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170128593/" title="DSC03782 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7271/8170128593_eb616c2957_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Smartwool Midweight Hoody" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Facts</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Weight: 287 gram in Size S</li>
  <li>Material: 100% Merino Wool</li>
  <li>Smellyness: Little when worn moderately, after a week of use it starts to smell a bit more</li>
  <li>That Dry Feeling: Nope, but because it’s Merino it still keeps you a tad warm, even when moist</li>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Price: 105€</td>
          <td>100$</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Buy it at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/smartwool-midweight-hoody-wollhoody/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
          <td><a href="http://goo.gl/XIV9x">Backcountry.com</a></td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="rjk-tvister-helmet-hood">Röjk Tvister Helmet Hood</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170148248/" title="DSC03765 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7122/8170148248_a14ea4da33_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DSC03765" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://rojk.se/index.php/en/tvister-helmet-hood-3">Tvister Helmet Hood</a> from Röjk has my favourite hood from the bunch; it thus is no surprise that it won the <em>Best Design and Innovation at the Innovation for Extremes Awards</em>, too. It’s a damn fine hood, creating a nice tunnel and thus more protection from wind, snow and rain; and unlike its brethern in this article, doesn’t hang down your back when you’re not wearing it, but stands nicely there, keeping your neck warm. I lament the absence of thumbloops, though Jan assured me that in the next reincarnation it will have those. No zip means no venting, but their unique Tvister Fabric - a <em>half-layer insulation</em> fabric is supposed to keep your temperature just right, which is not the case for me - I just run warm and to cool down need to open the outer layer. They’re ethically made in Europe, and come in swell colours. My favourite hoody for day hikes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8182938136/" title="Röjk Tvister Helmet Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8344/8182938136_c3b63ebb59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Tvister Helmet Hoody" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170302711/" title="Röjk Tvister Helmet Hood by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7111/8170302711_4ef5f87ebb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Röjk Tvister Helmet Hood" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Facts</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Weight: 325 gram in Size M</li>
  <li>Material: 5% Span, 40% Recycled Polyester, 55% Polyester</li>
  <li>Smellyness: Oh yes. Smelly after a couple days usage, after a week you will need to keep a secure distance to others</li>
  <li>That Dry Feeling: Nope, but still fairly warm when moist</li>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Price: 995 SEK</td>
          <td>115€</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
  <li>Buy at one of these <a href="http://rojk.se/index.php/en/retailers">Röjk Retailers</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="rab-baseline-hoody">Rab Baseline Hoody</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170147444/" title="Rab Baseline Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8207/8170147444_61641b1f52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab Baseline Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>The Rab <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/baselayer/baseline-hoodie.html">Baseline Hoodie</a> is a hoody made from Polartec Power Dry. That’s a mad material, let me tell you: It wicks the moistness away from your skin, and even if the complete garment is drenched in your sweat, you feel dry. I was utterly surprised when I undressed after some skiing last winter to find out that I felt dry, but that the outsode of the hoody was moist. Genius. The zippered chest pocket keeps an energy bar or two, the zip goes acceptably deep for ventilating, just the thumbloops could be improved - they’re OK, but not as comfy as others here. If I go out skiing in winter, this is the hoody I’m most likely wearing.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170123225/" title="Rab Baseline Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7106/8170123225_f3b14a83db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rab Baseline Hoody" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170333416/" title="Rab Baseline Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7113/8170333416_1fc0e90b15_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rab Baseline Hoody" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Facts</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Weight: 352 gram in Size S</li>
  <li>Material: 93% Polyester, 7% Spandex</li>
  <li>Smellyness: A little after a few days, a little more after a week</li>
  <li>That Dry Feeling: Superb. The best, actually - go running in it, sweat like mad, but feel dry - thanks to the Polartec material.</li>
  <li>Price: 75£</li>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Buy at one of these <a href="http://rab.uk.com/stockists.html">Rab Retailers</a></td>
          <td> <a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/rab_baseline_hoodie.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a></td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="silkbody-cellular-pilot-top">Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170159564/" title="Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7113/8170159564_f654efa13c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top" /></a></p>

<p>For over two years I hike, ski &amp; snowshoe in this hoody, and there have been a lot of questions about it. The <a href="http://www.silkbody.co.nz/man/outdoor/cellular-pilot-top-men-only.html">Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top</a> has a lot of great details going for it: sunglasses slots, off-centre front zip, thumb loops, flat seams and a ninja hood. It’s also unique because it made from 80% Silk (and 20% Merino), making for a comfortable feeling. It keeps you warm when you need it to, and cool when the heat would allow you to fry eggs in your Ti pan (without fire). The superb Ninja hoody goes over your nose, so no need for a Balaclava with this one; and thanks to the off-centre zip and stormflap behind it nothing rubs against your skin. An year-round usable hoody, though in deep winter it needs something extra over it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170331766/" title="Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8479/8170331766_28522c2cd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170301151/" title="Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7279/8170301151_684d0c2a65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Facts</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Weight: 236 gram in Size S</li>
  <li>Material: 80% Silk, 20% Wool</li>
  <li>Smellyness: Very little smellyness, even after a week</li>
  <li>That Dry Feeling: Nope, but still OK warm when moist</li>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Price: 125€</td>
          <td> NZ$250</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Buy at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/silkbody-womens-cellular-pilot-top-hoodie/?searchparam=silkbody&amp;listtype=search">Bergfreunde</a> (Female Version!)</td>
          <td><a href="http://www.silkbody.co.nz/man/outdoor/cellular-pilot-top-men-only.html">Silkbody</a> (Mens!)</td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="backpacking-light-beartooth-hoody">Backpacking Light Beartooth Hoody</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170161034/" title="Backpacking Light Beartooth Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7266/8170161034_20eec737e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Backpacking Light Beartooth Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>The out-of-production BPL Beartooth Hoody is probably THE ultralight hoody. It’s a lovely garment, and there isn’t really a hoody available yet that has replaced it. It’s a thin and fine Merino weave, but surprisingly warm - though I’d not wear it in deep winter, to be honest. But I find it perfect from spring to autumn, where it is the perfect package - a deep zip for venting, thumbloops for extra warmth, and a good hood which also works great for sleeping. It’s my pick for cold spring and autumn trips. If you’re able to get one, take it!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170298563/" title="Backpacking Light Beartooth Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8197/8170298563_93b2b6dc2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Backpacking Light Beartooth Hoody" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170163564/" title="Backpacking Light Beartooth Hoody by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7128/8170163564_ec5f04ae57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Backpacking Light Beartooth Hoody" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Facts</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Weight: 250 gram in Size S</li>
  <li>Material: 100% Merino Wool</li>
  <li>Smellyness: Like the Smartwool hoody, a few days are no problem, but after a week it starts to smell</li>
  <li>That Dry Feeling: Nope, but still OK warm when moist</li>
  <li>Price: ~100$</li>
  <li>Buy at <a href="http://www.backpackinglight.com/cgi-bin/backpackinglight/forums/display_forum.html?forum=19">BPL GearSwap</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-ultimate-hoody">The Ultimate Hoody</h2>

<p>The Ultimate Hoody is ethically made (wherever, but fair wages are paid and working conditions are excellent) from renewable and recyclable materials. It wicks the sweat away like the Rab Baseline Hoody, has the thumbloops of the Smartwool Midweight Hoody, looks as good as the Silkbody Cellular Pilot Top and makes use of their off-centre zip (which will be deeper for better venting) and combines their Ninja hood with the Röjk Tvister’s hood. It’s as light as the BPL Beartooth, and comes in a host of fresh colours.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157629182049156/">More photos of all the Hoodies</a></strong></p>

<p><em>There are <a href="http://goo.gl/SknjS">other</a> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-r1-hoody-fleecehoody/">Hoodies</a> <a href="http://goo.gl/eBqdN">around</a>. I don’t own them, and hence they were not compared here.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8170155950/" title="Tidy. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7134/8170155950_05e9372c7b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Tidy." /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rab Cirrus Wind Top]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/rab-cirrus-wind-top.html"/>
    <updated>2011-09-30T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/rab-cirrus-wind-top</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
Windshirts are one of the epitome of lightweight &amp; ultralight backpackers, though increasingly traditional outdoor folks start to see the benefits of a wind jacket. The &lt;a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/soft-shell/cirrus-wind-top.html"target="_blank"&gt;Rab Cirrus Wind Top came out in 2010 and is made of Pertex Quantum 15D mini ripstop, has a full size zipper, two big mesh hand pockets and a hood, and after a few months of usage it is time to let you know how I like it.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/xbnsFW8sCk4RmSdUCdtVHi1f5D_7H56A-s5v_WoeRhE?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-NecjmGUQHU4/ToSBc71IbrI/AAAAAAAAFY8/3AdDIRYa9WA/s800/_DSC2395.jpg" height="533" width="800" /></a><br /><br /><b>Time</b><br />Rab sent me the Cirrus Wind Top in May this year, and I've been sporting it since it during week-long expeditions, day trips, overnighters, mountain biking, travelling, working as a Guide, and in the city. So far no wear and tear on it, and I have used the jacket a lot when going grocery shopping (think 8+ kg of groceries being carried). Also some bushwacking was no problem for the jacket, so I think it will be going strong for many more months (hopefully years!). I reckon spring, summer and autumn are the optimal seasons for this garment, though I will try it out also in winter when skiing and snowshoeing.<br /><br /><b>Update 20.03.2012</b>: I have now used it various times in winter for skiing, where it performed very well. I took it down in low double digits temperatures (max -15°C) on sunny days with some wind, and it was working very well in those conditions. In strong wind on cloudy, colder days I would prefer the extra warmth of a hardshell, too for spring skiing and mild midwinter days nothing speaks against saving some weight and using this windjacket.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/_jAXqbj4F-9_3HQ96GUx1i1f5D_7H56A-s5v_WoeRhE?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-iB5fxkTkjkQ/ToSBMmQsBbI/AAAAAAAAFYc/UmXK_SuEOXY/s800/_DSC2386.jpg" height="800" width="533" /></a><br /><br /><b>Function</b><br />A wind jacket should keep the wind out, and possibly a bit of rain. The Pertex material is fascinating, it is thin like baking paper yet it doesn't let any wind through, and even in a drizzle it is sufficient to keep you dry. If it rains a lot, the material is wetting through (or that is how it felt as I was wearing a T-Shirt under it). As Tampere is the "Windy City" of Finland a wind jacket is a useful garment in the wardrobe, and the Cirrus was very often the wind jacket of choice for any walk or trip. Small enough to fit in my pant's cargo pocket, it is easy to store, and you also can just turn one of the mesh pockets inside out and stuff the jacket in there. It is soft and comfortable on the skin, fine if you just wear a short sleeved shirt under it and need a light jacket to keep the wind out/ the bugs off. If you are only wearing a T-Shirt under your wind jacket though, you might get a little cold when the wind pushes the material against your skin. If it is warm &amp; sunny, the material starts to feel a bit clammy in high exertion activities - best to pack it away then, and enjoy the warm weather!<br /><br /><b>Features</b><br />An "Under the Helmet hood" which works very nice, the elasticized hood sits snug around your face and protects your ears and the rest of the head from wind. The two mesh handpockets are good - set a bit higher so you can wear it with a harness. The pockets are easy to open with one hand, even with a gloves on; super roomy, you can store plenty of stuff in them. The hem has a drawcord which works better than many drawcords in hems I have used, a pull with one hand is all that's needed. The hem stays about average time down - as usually, after some time it wanders up. The elasticated cuffs function well to keep the wind out of your arms and not make them look like monster sausage arms.The front zipper works smooth, though the slider is tiny and I would recommend adding a short piece of string to make it easier to pull up/ down with one hand. The zipper even has an internal storm flap and at the top on the inside there's a little piece of fleece for extra comfort against your chin or beard.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/3ZqADMRRDhKj_NhcL1ZGui1f5D_7H56A-s5v_WoeRhE?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ONPhrDY6EX8/ToSBRvZXqoI/AAAAAAAAFZI/g0xNT3BYrdE/s800/_DSC2388.jpg" height="800" width="729" /></a><br /><br /><b>Technical Innovations</b><br />Possibly the usage of Pertex Quantum as a fabric material. Making a jacket with a full zipper and two hand pockets and a hood for 112 gram is quite a nice achievement, too.<br /><br /><b>Quality</b><br />The jacket is made in China, and the quality is topnotch. All seams are clean, there are minimal small ends of thread standing over at some seams, the zippers run smooth and the size is good. Minor bushwacking was no problem for the jacket, as was carrying 8+ kg of groceries in a backpack two to three times a week for four plus months.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/DMJb0IxzyBZyeXB79YFelS1f5D_7H56A-s5v_WoeRhE?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-P_L8WI0yzv4/ToSBaQPZ4qI/AAAAAAAAFY0/3y8yMNz8Tg0/s800/_DSC2393.jpg" height="533" width="800" /></a><br /><br /><b>Weight</b><br />The original weight of <b>my Size S was 112 gram</b>, though after taking out the labels and cutting of the buckle to roll up the hood I brought it down to <b>109 gram</b>. Not bad at all considering all the features it sports.<br /><br /><b>Sustainability &amp; Recyclablity</b><br />&lt;a href="http://rab.uk.com/about-us/environment.html"target="_blank"&gt;Rab addresses on it website sustainability issues, which is a step into the right direction. They invite their customers and interested parties to communicate with them via Email if they have questions, and the designers proclaim to work hard on finding <i>ways of balancing longevity, sustainability and affordability</i>. Digging a bit deeper (I haven't written them, might do that in the future) I fail to find information on possible Environmental Management Systems, working together with organizations which want to make the supply chain more sustainable (e.g. using recycled materials/ Cradle-to-Cradle thinking) or if they contribute to nature conservation organisations. However, Rab being a UK company, and the UK legislation requiring more and more such considerations, plus Rab itself needing the outdoors to continue to exist I am certain we will see more positive developments in that direction.<br /><br />Being made of Pertex Quantum I checked the &lt;a href="http://www.pertex.com/"target="_blank"&gt;Pertex website, and sure enough they have a short blurb on Ecological considerations, proclaiming the usual stuff. Recycling wise I would probably try to sneak it into the Patagonia Common Threads programme at the end of its life, or before that pass it on to someone.<br /><br />The Cirrus being made in China, I also would welcome some information on labour standards in the factories which produce the garments. I am certain Rab has very carefully chosen its suppliers in China (ensuring no child labour, fair wages, decent working hours, safe working environment, etc.), though for concerned consumers it might be worth to communicate these factors on the website.<br /><br /><b> Competing products</b><br />The &lt;a href="http://www.montane.co.uk/products/men/windproof/lite-speed-jacket/46"target="_blank"&gt;Montane Lite-Speed jacket (Claimed 175 g/ Size L) is the Cirrus' closest rival, being also made of Pertex. The &lt;a href="http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2010/07/arcteryx-squamish-hoody-first-look.html"target="_blank"&gt;Arc'teryx Squamish Hoody (141 g/ Size S; own weight) is made of an other material, has no hand pockets but has a hood with a good visor. The &lt;a href="http://www.patagonia.com/eu/enIT/product/mens-houdini-full-zip-jacket?p=24017-0-472"target="_blank"&gt;Patagonia Houdini Jacket (Claimed 122 g/ unknown Size) is a fairly popular windjacket, and the &lt;a href="http://www.norrona.com/Products/0752-09/bitihorn-aero60-jacket-m"target="_blank"&gt;Norrona bitihorn aero60 Jacket (Claimed 187 g/ unknown Size) is the newest kid on the full-zipper &amp; hood windjacket market, and has speaking for it that it is made of recycled materials.<br /><br /><a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/qgZw88f_r2II81nDTqFBHS1f5D_7H56A-s5v_WoeRhE?feat=embedwebsite"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Q-P4H9amdYg/ToSBgnN0ZTI/AAAAAAAAFZE/fM9hLupAt54/s800/_DSC2397.jpg" height="533" width="800" /></a><br /><br /><b>What others say</b><br />&lt;a href="http://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2010/11/28/rab-cirrus-pull-on-long-term-test/"target="_blank"&gt;James has reviewed the Rab Cirrus Pull-on and found it a fine piece of kit, though it shows some wear and tear from the long use in the hills. &lt;a href="http://www.petesy.co.uk/rab-cirrus-pull-on-review/"target="_blank"&gt;Also Peter has had the Cirrus Pull-On for months on test and liked it.<br /><br /><b>Bottomline</b><br />A 109 gram full zip jacket which keeps the wind out and keeps you reasonably dry in a drizzle. I can wear it over two baselayers (like a thin hoody and a T-Shirt) and an insulation layer, though also just over a T-Shirt it is a good, tight fit. I love the orange colour, it certainly adds a nice touch to the outdoor wardrobe (which consist for me usually of black). I value it a lot, and during the summer I rarely packed anything else than the Cirrus and &lt;a href="http://thunderinthenight.blogspot.com/2011/09/walking-between-rain-drops-umbrellas-in.html"target="_blank"&gt;an umbrella to keep wind and rain at bay. If you're not yet a convert to wind jackets, then I recommend you &lt;a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/soft-shell/cirrus-wind-top.html"target="_blank"&gt;check out the Rab Cirrus Wind Top and try it yourself.<br /><br />&lt;a href="https://picasaweb.google.com/105306052609390995141/RabCirrusWindTop"target="_blank"&gt;More photos.<br /><br /><b>Where to get it</b><br />I found it at &lt;a href="http://www.webtogs.co.uk/Rab_Mens_Cirrus_Wind_Top_102171-26533.html"target="_blank"&gt;Webtogs for £54 and at &lt;a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/rab_cirrus_wind_top.html"target="_blank"&gt;Ultralight Outdoor Gear in the UK for £55. Other usual suspects don't seem to have it in stock at the moment.<br /><br /><b>Future Updates</b><br />- <s>Info on winter use (Skiing)</s><br />- Additional photos (stuffed in its own pocket)<br /></div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bivy bags]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2009/10/bivy-bags.html"/>
    <updated>2009-10-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2009/10/bivy-bags</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Together with looking for a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2009/09/gear-talk-golite-ultra-20-initial-review.html">tarp</a>, I’m also in need of a bivy bag to keep the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.blogspot.com/2009/09/gear-talk-golite-ultra-20-initial.html">Ultra 20°</a> dry from rain and dampness and increase the warmth rating of the quilt a bit. <br /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381684016/" title="A bike and a bivy. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8148/7381684016_5aefe0f5e9_o.jpg" width="4912" height="3264" alt="A bike and a bivy." /></a>
<br />
I had a look around, and these are the bags I found which would suit my needs. The bivy doesn’t need to be water resistant as I will be under the tarp, so waterproof is enough (I don’t water resistance, though =). It should have good breathability and be light. Pretty much the standards, thus. Use is spring till autumn and in winter to increase the rating. Here the ones I am considering:<br /><br /><a href="http://www.titaniumgoat.com/Bivy.html">Titanium Goat Ptarmigan bivy</a><br />- 164 g in Intrepid/ Silnylon<br />- Mosquito netting, no zipper<br />- 90$<br /><br /> <a href="http://www.rab.uk.com/equipment/bivvis/ultra_bivi---70/">Rab Ultra Bivy</a><br />- 220 g in Pertex Quantum Endurance<br />- short zipper<br />- 65€<br /><br /><a href="http://www.integraldesigns.com/product_detail.cfm?id=821&amp;CFID=1161559&amp;CFTOKEN=57196832&amp;mainproducttypeid=1">Integral Design Micro Bivy</a><br />- 535 g in eVent/ 70 denier coated nylon<br />- hood &amp; draw cord, no zipper<br />- 210$<br /><br /><a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=22&amp;products_id=39&amp;osCsid=16ae04d23cde8a116479ca7d73e31cab">MLD LiteSoul Bivy</a><br />- 125 g in Momentum/ Spectralite .60<br />- no mosquito net, dual zipper<br />- 245$<br /><br /><a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=22&amp;products_id=37&amp;osCsid=16ae04d23cde8a116479ca7d73e31cab">MLD Soul Bivy</a><br />- 195 g in Momentum DWR/ Silnylon<br />- bug netting window, two sets of inside and outside sleep pad strap loops, top can be made in eVent<br />- 205$<br />- I also can imagine the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=22&amp;products_id=38&amp;osCsid=1ae63005ffeaf98b41fc0cf1ebca5d7f">Soul Bivy with a side zip</a><br /><br />I know there’s heaps more out there, and even a MYOG Tyvek bivy, like eg <a href="http://theotherface.wordpress.com/2009/03/11/myog-tyvek-bivy/">The Other Face</a> has made, would be sufficient for my needs, though somehow I prefer to get it in slightly more durable material. As this is again a fairly new topic to me, I am curious to hear which bivy you use.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
