<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Advent Calendar 2016 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2016/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-20T23:56:53+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar 2016 - The Rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/advent-calendar-2016-the-rules.html"/>
    <updated>2016-11-21T07:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/advent-calendar-2016-the-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We need rules to play by, and here they are.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8230998731/" title="HiF Advent Calendar"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8350/8230998731_e265161b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HiF Advent Calendar Logo" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Welcome again to a new Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar! Like in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2014/">years</a> <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2015/">before</a>, a good set of rules makes running the Advent Calendar a lot easier for everyone involved. Read them carefully and everything hopefully will be clear, and for some added benefit check out the <strong>tips</strong> at the end!</p>

<p>This years calendar will run 25 days (= 25 Doors), and behind each door you will find a fine piece of brand-new gear which should make your next outdoor adventure fun and ultralight. Some information on the prizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>All prizes are sent directly from the company providing them (which can mean that you might need to pay import duties when it comes from abroad!).</li>
  <li>Sometimes it is possible that you can choose size, colour and other variables. Where this is the case, it will be mentioned in the text of the Door.</li>
  <li>This means garments can be either female or male, backpacks can be different torso sizes and meals can be vegetarian or with meat. </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-rules">The Rules</h2>

<p>To win something you should check in each day here and enter the raffle. There are a couple of points to keep in mind:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You only can win once. If you don’t win one day, you should try your luck the next day - you got 25 chances!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I am using a paid-for version of <a href="https://www.rafflecopter.com/">Rafflecopter</a> for the Give-Aways. With Rafflecopter you can get multiple entries by following someone on Instagram, Twitter, visit a page on Facebook, follow a Pinterest page or susbscribe to a Mailing List. This increases your chances to win, but is not mandatory. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Rafflecopter Widget is integrated with <a href="http://www.random.org/">Random.org</a> and it choses the winner. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Once you won, I contact you via the provided Email address and you have 24 hours to reply. If I don’t hear from you, I imagine you don’t want the item and will let Random.org chose a new winner.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Posts go online around midnight and the raffles close at midnight - Finnish time. Rafflecopter then will show the name of the winner after I pushed that button, this keeps posts to a minimum.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It is open to everyone. As in from Australia to Zimbabwe, prices are send everywhere (unless noted otherwise).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Possible Import Duty taxes and fees are paid by the winner. If you’re not willing to pay these, don’t compete. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can’t bribe me or anyone involved to win. You use the item(s) on your own responsibility. Use common sense.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="tips">Tips</h2>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You can participate via the Rafflecopter widget by registering with your Email or your Facebook accoount. Please make sure for either option that it’s an Email address you regularly check, so when I contact you you get the email. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There is usually one mandatory option to answer to participate. This can be something fun or a question about the price in question. You should be easily able to answer the question by reading the text or visiting the manufacturer website. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can get additional entries which improve your chances of winning. This could be visiting a Facebook page or following someone on Youtube, Twitter, Instagram and the like. It’s a good thing to do, and also allows you stay up-to-date with news about the HiF Advent Calendar and the company sponsoring the prize.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you think your friends and fans would like to participate - spread the word! Use the #HifAdventCalendar hashtag on Instagram, Twitter &amp; Facebook when you spread the word =)</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That’s it. The Advent Calendar starts tomorrow, the 22nd of November. Subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/105082905705272949032">Google+</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to get an update every time a new door opens.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: All gear is sponsored. Sponsors pay a fee to participate. Partof the income is donated to <a href="The Week In Review">I Love Laufbursche</a> and my 1% For The Planet Partner, the <a href="https://www.johnmuirtrust.org">John Muir Trust</a>. I try to not spend all time in front of a screen so relax if a post goes up a tad late or I don’t reply an email asap.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
