<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: writing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-30T13:54:14+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 01/2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2015/01/trekking-magazin-01-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-12T15:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2015/01/trekking-magazin-01-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first trekking Magazin of 2015 is at the Newsstand - and these great articles are in it!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077458409" title="trekking Magazin 01/2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7568/16077458409_28ba44035a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 01/2015" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>My <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/from-russia-with-love.html">From Russia With Love</a> trip report is still super popular and in the first trekking Magazin issue of 2015 I wrote a trip report auf Deutsch. It’s a great looking article and gives tips to plan your own hike in Karelia, so well worth to pick it up just for that. In my gear column I talk about down jackets and review the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hagloefs-essens-ii-down-weste-noble-blue-s/?pid=81">Häglöfs Essens II Down Vest</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/14pEniz">Arc’teryx Cerium SL Jacket</a>, <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/yukon-down-jacket">PHD Yukon Down Jacket</a> and the <a href="http://bit.ly/1hh35k8">Mountain Equipment Vega Jacket</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262752882" title="trekking Magazin 01/2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7545/16262752882_95e18731f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 01/2015" /></a></p>

<p>There’s still plenty more in there, from fine hikes in Luxembourg and Sweden to a Winter Gear Guide. Pick up the first issue of 2015 at a Newsstand near you or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> to not miss any future issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 06/2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/trekking-magazin-06-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T14:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/trekking-magazin-06-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since last week available is the 06/2014 issue of the trekking Magazin!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15625818987" title="trekking Magazin 06/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5615/15625818987_f2c7bbd7e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 06/2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In the last issue of 2014 you will find in my Gear column a discussion of Hardshell Jackets for hiking. After discussing what a hardshell is made of and what it should have I review five different jackets which I have used this year. Elsewhere there is a company interview with ORTOVOX, tips on buying snowshoes and a visit to the island Elba in Tuscany.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15625820437" title="trekking Magazin 06/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7469/15625820437_4be22622dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="trekking Magazin 06/2014" /></a></p>

<p>There’s still plenty more in there, from fine hikes in Germany to gear news. Thus go pick up the last issue of 2014 at a Kiosk near you or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> to not miss any future issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 05/2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/09/trekking-magazin-05-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-12T09:40:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/09/trekking-magazin-05-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today on the shelves is the latest issue of the trekking Magazin with three articles of your truly!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15213900425" title="trekking Magazin 05/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5579/15213900425_03da672782_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="trekking Magazin 05/2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In this issue I write about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> which I visited in June and give a lot of details about planning your own stay in Chamonix. In my columne I write about five great hiking pants from Houdini to Klättermusen, and then there’s a very long trip report in it about my hike on the Escapardenne Eisleck Trail in Luxembourg which I thru-hiked in May of this year. It’s a beautiful trail with lots to offer and is well suited for those that look for culture, nature and a well-marked trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15213900665" title="trekking Magazin 05/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3886/15213900665_eeed1d365b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="trekking Magazin 05/2014" /></a></p>

<p>And of course there’s still plenty more in there, from fine hikes in Germany to rambling through the hills of Tuscany. Thus go pick up the current issue at a Kiosk near you or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> to not miss any future issue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 04/2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/07/trekking-magazin-04-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-18T13:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/07/trekking-magazin-04-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Available since last week Friday the new trekking Magazin 04/2014 has many great articles in it!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14682971605" title="trekking Magazin 04/ 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5584/14682971605_367afda16b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="trekking Magazin 04/ 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Issue four has two articles by your truly: My <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/lake-district/">Lakeland Trip Report</a> auf Deutsch and in my column I talk about lightweight footwear. Also my colleagues have been busy and write about fine trips from the Black Forest in Germany, the Azores Island Pico, the Dolomites and Austria. Also some <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor 2014</a> is in the mag though I think you’re better off with my articles ;) </p>

<p>Very happy I am that they printed my barefoot and trailrunning columne without changes - in it I write black on white what the majority of you already know: That hiking boots are not the best footwear for hiking and that with a lighter, more minimalist shoe you can have a healthier stride and more enjoyment in the outdoors. I hope there will be many boot wearers who will try out some of the suggested shoes or similar ones!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14496301820" title="trekking Magazin 04/ 2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3879/14496301820_777cac3342_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="trekking Magazin 04/ 2014" /></a></p>

<p>As always there is plenty more in this issue which will keep you entertained for many hours and inspire you to go outdoors. Pick up the current issue at a Kiosk or take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> - this time even with the chance of winning a Sigma SD1 Merrill camera!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[trekking Magazin 03/2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/05/trekking-magazin-03-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-05-20T19:32:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/05/trekking-magazin-03-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s May and the latest issue of the trekking Magazin is on the shelves! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14044348677" title="Trekking Magazin 03/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2915/14044348677_03139a2056_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trekking Magazin 03/2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>This issue features a summer layering guide in my gear column, while colleagues of mine take a look at trekking sandals and how to keep insects at bay in the outdoors. As for trip reports and inspiration, this issue has a massive twenty pages of hiking and backpacking in Italy. The beautiful Trentino is featured, as is the Aosta Valley, the Matterhorn and an island in the Mediterranean sea. If you have kids you will like the story of hiking with kids around the Tegernsee, and if you call sailing a hobby of yours, too, then the story about hiking and sailing will show you how to combine the two hobbies for one fine trip. </p>

<p>And there is plenty more in this issue which will keep you entertained for many hours and inspire you to go backpacking. You can pick the current issue up at a Kiosk, take out a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription</a> or order a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/magazin/probeexemplar">free review copy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14230685474" title="Trekking Magazin 03/2014 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5240/14230685474_79b3e6a7c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trekking Magazin 03/2014" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
