<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OutDoor Fair 2014 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-13T18:14:04+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor 2014 Wrap up & Conclusions]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/outdoor-2014-wrap-up-and-conclusions.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-05T16:49:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/outdoor-2014-wrap-up-and-conclusions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What really stood out at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor 2014</a>? Where there any big trends? These and other questions I try to answer in this Wrap up &amp; Conclusions article.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14717883544" title="Black Diamond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5561/14717883544_1b11907e05_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>My 2nd OutDoor fair was different, and not so different than 2013. This year’s differences included:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Rain all four days of the fair</li>
  <li>Sleeping on a different camping place in a <a href="http://www.heimplanet.com/">Heimplanet Cave</a></li>
  <li>No Overnighter on a mountain before or after the fair :/</li>
</ul>

<p>But there were lots of similarities to 2013, too:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Travelling via Zürich Airport</li>
  <li>Again 8 to 12 meetings each day</li>
  <li>The best coffee still was had at the Scandinavian Outdoor Bar</li>
  <li>Meeting lots of old and new friends which you usually only communicate online with</li>
</ul>

<p>I mixed things up and had several meetings with companies I haven’t met before - Rock Technologies, Sealskinz, Big Agnes, NEMO Equipment, Vargo and NW Alpine, amongst others. Some of them were for the first time at the fair, others I just didn’t had a chance to meet before. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14671316545" title="Camp HEIMPLANET by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3873/14671316545_dfe7e2d07d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Camp HEIMPLANET" /></a></p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<p>I really enjoyed meeting <a href="http://lighthiker.wordpress.com/">Roman</a> and having a chat with him. It was a honour to meet Ron Moak from <a href="http://www.sixmoondesigns.com/">Six Moon Designs</a> and talk ultralight gear with him, as well chat with the owners of fellow Oregon Outdoor businesses <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/">CiloGear</a> and <a href="http://nwalpine.com/">NW Alpine</a>. It was a cool surprise to sit next to Brian <a href="http://www.vargooutdoors.com/">Vargo</a> in the bus to the fair and talk Titanium and ultralight gear with him. And also to meet again <a href="http://www.freiluft-blog.de/">Sven</a> and <a href="http://www.trekking.lu/">Aender</a> whom I have met earlier this year in Luxembourg, as well as <a href="http://www.ausgeruestet.com/">Marcel</a>, fellow outdoor bloggers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14648597180" title="Zlag Board by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5578/14648597180_529d91d928_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Zlag Board" /></a></p>

<p>Equally cool was some of the gear. The <a href="http://zlagboard.com/">Zlagboard</a> is a really awesome approach to a hangboard with a personal trainer included, and shows what’s possible if you combine technology in a smart way with existing products. I’d love one but the price tag of close to 300€ probably will put it out of reach of just the most rich climbers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14646350483" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3868/14646350483_068b962779_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a></p>

<p>I’m not a tent person but the Hilleberg Enan looked very great. A 1,1 kg double wall tent likely will fly off the shelves for Hilleberg as all the traditional backpackers will run to lighten up their packs with one. There were obviously a bunch of other lightweight tent designs, some with good ideas and details, but this one stood out for me.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14431823760" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3850/14431823760_04ee0da90d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear" /></a></p>

<p>I liked the Arc’teryx footwear line. While not a new idea the shoes I tried on and played around with were extremely well made and had a great fit. I can see myself using the Alpha² FL model as its a multiple-use shoe that works for the trail, camp, crossing rivers and should dry fast, which could be great in wet and cold environments.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589445398" title="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3843/14589445398_8ec27437af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX" /></a></p>

<p>And while I’m not a boot person the Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX definitely is on my list of gear-to-try. A sub 400 g boot that’s crampon compatible likely will open up new possibilities for ice climbing, mountaineering and alpinism, and even will be interesting for those people who just like the support of a boot but wouldn’t mind if it’s lighter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624305174" title="MSR Reactor and MSR WindBoiler by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5584/14624305174_b17f444bfc_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="MSR Reactor and MSR WindBoiler" /></a></p>

<p>The MSR Windboiler was an interesting stove design: Fairly light and as there’s no need for a windscreen it makes it useable also in very windy situations without much fussing around. I’m curious to see how it would perform next to the Reactor and the new <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-3.html">Jetboil MiniMo</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14671477415" title="Outdoor Research ActiveIce &amp; Spectrum Sun Sleeves by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3925/14671477415_98ef393272_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research ActiveIce &amp; Spectrum Sun Sleeves" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14484714858" title="Impressions by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5566/14484714858_16f97f8905_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Impressions" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447506168" title="ORTOVOX Rock&#x27;N&#x27;Wool Double Check Shirt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2929/14447506168_633cb20f00_b.jpg" width="880" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX Rock&#x27;N&#x27;Wool Double Check Shirt" /></a></p>

<p>On the garment front there were a few items that caught my interest: I liked the Outdoor Research ActiveIce Sun Sleeves (and would wish I’d have a pair in this weather) and loved the fabric, feel and colours of the new ORTOVOX Rock’n’Wool garments. Also the Haglöfs L.I.M. line is super interesting and I hope that it will be popular as that will benefit us ultralight hikers a lot. </p>

<h2 id="copy-cats">Copy Cats</h2>

<p>I’m usually not shaming stuff or companies - I rather write about what’s really good and worth doing. But seeing two successful products blatantly copied had my blood boiling. Packrafting is growing and attracts a growing number of people from all walks of outdoor life. That’s why it’s pretty shite to see <a href="http://www.alpackaraft.com/">Alpacka Packrafts</a> copied nearly 1:1 by the German company Faltboot. But apparently that wasn’t enough for them - once you start copying it’s apparently difficult to stop. Otherwise I can’t fathom why they also copied the <a href="http://www.orukayak.com/">Oru Kayak</a>, the foldable &amp; lightweight kayak. Worst of all is that the company seems to claim to have had the idea to both these designs and thinks we consumers are stupid and don’t know (well, if you’d see the mainstream media who has picked up e.g. on the “new” packraft, you’d easily could come to that conclusion). While there might be tiny, tiny differences in design or material, for me it was very obvious from where those guys took their inspiration. My advice to all those interested in packrafting and foldable kayaks: Support the original companies with the better designs and materials and avoid the copy cats.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14648685508" title="Packraft and Oru Kayak Rip-Off from Faltboote.de by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5589/14648685508_18733d8713_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Packraft and Oru Kayak Rip-Off from Faltboote.de" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trends">Trends</h2>

<p>There were a lot of single rope belay device on show, and with gym/ sports climbing booming across the globe it’s a logical development. Of the ones shown at the show I liked the Salewa one best, but only using them at the crag will show which one will reign supreme. I’m already using the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-smart-sicherungsgeraet/">Mammut Smart</a> since many years and like it a lot, and the Salewa Belay System improved upon that design a bit in my opinion. We’ll see. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439188508" title="Salewa Belay Device by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3914/14439188508_7e226cb577_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salewa Belay Device" /></a></p>

<p>Cuben becomes mainstream and is picked up by large companies. Both Adidas and Peak Performance have made a jacket (and pants) of breathable cuben which might be the first nail into the coffin of other WPB fabrics. These will be limited numbers I reckon, and pricey, but if they sell out I am sure we’ll see more of it next year. Also otherwise cuben was used for packs and tents, but I wasn’t convinced that those companies knew much about the material - otherwise they wouldn’t have designed e.g. a 90 l backpack with all bells &amp; whistles of it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773743944" title="Peak Performance Cuben Suit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3874/14773743944_3e6a346289_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Peak Performance Cuben Suit" /></a></p>

<p>Kids and children are increasingly recognized as a target group. There’s already family hiking specific magazines so it’s no surprise that we see each year a growing number of companies who garner to the outdoor gear needs of the little ones. Strollers, carriers, packs, sleeping bags and clothes - there’s not much gear that isn’t yet made for kids. But instead of smaller sizes of proven designs this kit is often adapted to the needs of the kids - reinforced knees, seats and elbows on garments, sleeping bags that are warmer &amp; allow for a lot of freedom of movement and comfy carriers &amp; strollers are available, as well as specific gear for moms and dads. It’s an interesting segment and my son &amp; me are curious to see what the future of it holds.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14457708637" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2940/14457708637_e5c809a8b1_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Patagonia" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439966147" title="Thule Glider &amp; Chariot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5589/14439966147_01412b5f1c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Thule Glider &amp; Chariot" /></a></p>

<p>What also changed is that there were less <a href="http://www.outdoor-show.de/od-de/programm/industry-award.php">OutDoor Awards</a>. This year there were 35 OutDoor Industry Awards of which seven were Gold. These OutDoor Industry 2014 Gold Award winners are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Atmos AG 65 from Osprey</li>
  <li>Speed Ascent by Salewa</li>
  <li>HyperSmock 2.0 by Berghaus</li>
  <li>Winter Gas by Primus</li>
  <li>Alpha² FL Men’s by Arc‘teryx</li>
  <li>The Fuseform™ Originator Jacket from The North Face and</li>
  <li>100 % plant-based PES from Toray</li>
</ul>

<p>I think almost all of these deserve the award, as a lightweight backpacker it’s always good to see that innovative, light gear gets rewarded. That Primus Winter Gas probably will be very popular if it works as advertised, and I’m looking forward to try on and test the first 100 % plant-based PES fabric garments from Toray. </p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/100632691?portrait=0&amp;color=ff9933" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In general gear is getting lighter and more durable, but again also increasingly the companies pay attention to the natural and social environment in which they operate. Gear is made closer to where the consumer lives, old locations are getting a second life and also what the gear is made of is not just on the consumer side, but also on the manufacturer side increasingly of importance. Maybe we’ll see silk tarps with a modern twist in a few years, as well as linen pants and hemp shirts!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14642036254" title="Marmot Eclipse Tunnel 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2902/14642036254_c854021611_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Marmot Eclipse Tunnel 2P" /></a></p>

<p>While last years/ this year’s <em>trend sport</em> was trailrunning - which continues to be popular - I felt that climbing is growing even further as a sport, attracting people from diverse backgrounds to try out this wonderful past time. But also hiking and backpacking seem to have a 2nd spring and at least on the company side I feel they’re becoming more popular again. I think we haven’t yet seen the end of the outdoor boom, and with this great weather it’s easy to see why people want to go outdoors.</p>

<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>

<p>It was another interesting, busy fair. Between walking from meeting to meeting there sadly was too little time to check out some of the other companies at the fair - though honestly, with over 900 exhibitors that’s probably impossible either way. I think that I will maintain to make appointments with companies in the future - it’s a lot more useful for me to learn about products in detail in 30 to 60 minutes, try them on and speak with the designer than running from booth to booth trying to take it all in. Already with the meetings the fair is overwhelming at times and things start to look and feel the same, so by taking it in in small doses I feel I’m taking away more. However, maybe next year I will have one day for strolling around. Even if it means I will have fewer USB sticks and catalogues to carry home.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14649325249" title="OutDoor 2014 catalogues &amp; USB sticks by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5569/14649325249_1e5bd51f05_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="OutDoor 2014 catalogues &amp; USB sticks" /></a></p>

<p>There was some good gear on the show that will make climbing, mountaineering, camping, hiking and backpacking more comfortable/ safe/ easy/ hard/ cool/ fun/ whatever in 2015. I saw a few innovative products, smart use of fabrics in garments, nice colours (I’m still not back in black) and a lot of gear that was on a diet and has lost weight. Some of it really might be great while others might not make it past one trip and are deemed not good. Only rigour testing in the outdoors will show us that and I hope that I will be able to put some of the gear presented here through that process. And if I like it, and it’s good, you’ll read about it in a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">gear review</a> in due time.</p>

<p>The far best part of the fair continues to be the people. I missed some friends but met many others and it’s great to grab a beer with them after the day on the floor, talk about what one has seen and get some tips about interesting kit to go check out. I’ve made a bunch of new mates and am looking forward to welcome a handful of them very soon here in Finland. Will I be in Friedrichshafen in 2015? Possibly maybe. It’s an expensive trip for me, time away from my family and also time I could spend outdoors. But it’s a lot of fun, too, and being able to report for you about the latest gear developments is enjoyable. I hope you have enjoyed this years news and read about something you liked.</p>

<p>Remember, you can <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157645582553771/">view all photos in this Album</a>. And if you enjoyed the news from the OutDoor 2014, please follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> and then go buy me a coffee =)</p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14671022722" title="Impressions by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3908/14671022722_d64ff0ed29_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Impressions" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2014 - 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-4.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-29T19:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good beats and good moods on the final day of the 2014 OutDoor fair. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14484700469" title="Impressions by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5567/14484700469_019ddec51c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Impressions" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="supernatural">super.natural</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.supern8ural.com/en/about.htm">super.natural</a> hails from München and they like to combine Merino wool with durable polyester fibres. The result are yarns that offer the best of both materials and these are then sewn into some very nice garments. They have a Women’s Yoga range which looked super comfy while being very stylish - garments that could be used for climbing &amp; hiking in the blink of an eye. But really any of their garments from the Base, Training and Superfly ranges could do well outdoors while still looking good when returning to the city. I tried some garments on and really liked them - good fit, freedom of movement, soft on the skin and they let light.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476789409" title="super.natural by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3915/14476789409_0af1b06133_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="super.natural" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476971517" title="super.natural by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3873/14476971517_abf8babd9f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="super.natural" /></a></p>

<h2 id="true-mountain">True Mountain</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.true-mountain.com/">True Mountain</a> makes gear in the UK from European and British materials. It’s a good effort, helping to re-establish the skills needed to sew and build high-quality kit in the UK, creating jobs and being - thanks to shorter transports - more environmentally friendly. Their gear goes on sale this autumn and will start with functional boxers which will be followed later on by tops, wind jackets and more. You can <a href="https://www.facebook.com/TrueMountainUK">follow their progress on FB</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773741624" title="True Mountain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3898/14773741624_6701cda2e4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="True Mountain" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14772926641" title="True Mountain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3890/14772926641_37d7c8160d_b.jpg" width="870" height="1024" alt="True Mountain" /></a></p>

<h2 id="aarn-packs">Aarn Packs</h2>

<p>All <a href="http://www.aarnpacks.com/">Aarn Packs</a> get a more streamlined, clean look. They’ve been optimized in several ways, and should now be even more suitable to runners, backpackers and hikers alike. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773742274" title="Aarn Packs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3926/14773742274_a78c57a72d_b.jpg" width="796" height="1024" alt="Aarn Packs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589379840" title="Aarn Packs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2930/14589379840_3219995230_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Aarn Packs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589447718" title="Aarn Packs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5579/14589447718_c60712c6e3_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Aarn Packs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773741884" title="Aarn Packs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5582/14773741884_7925be6541_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Aarn Packs" /></a></p>

<h2 id="mountain-network">Mountain Network</h2>

<p>Now something for the climbing gym owners and climbing clubs: <a href="http://www.mountain-network.eu/">Mountain Network</a> has created a climbing wall system that is self-bearing and that can be used indoors &amp; outdoors. Prefabricated elements allow you to build a tower like the one underneath in a day which makes them not just ideal for events, but also for hotels and other places which want to have a climbing wall e.g. over the summer outside and then store it away when the winter comes. It’s not just ideal to build climbing walls but also for bouldering walls. <a href="http://www.mountain-network.eu/klimwanden/klimwanden/driehoek-klimwanden/algemene-informatie/">Check out the video and photos on their site</a>, it’s pretty cool - so cool that it won an OutDoor Award!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773740874" title="Mountain Network by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3866/14773740874_ce1cca0d38_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Network" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589378780" title="Mountain Network by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5595/14589378780_3b1976bf2a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Network" /></a></p>

<h2 id="mountain-hardwear">Mountain Hardwear</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com/">Mountain Hardwear</a> Stretch Ozonic jacket is a 276 g 2.5-layer shell with good stretch. It’s made from the Dry.Q® Active fabric which has a ‘soft shell’ feel with the benefits and light weight of a hard-shell. It felt nice and Mountain Hardwear claims this is a great wet weather hiking jacket, so it could be interesting for those that prefer to walk in the rain and not this hot weather!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589426959" title="Mountain Hardwear Stretch Ozonic™ jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3843/14589426959_cc9d15efc3_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear Stretch Ozonic™ jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Quasar™ Lite Jacket is 340 g light and uses another Mountain Hardwear fabric, Dry.Q™ Elite. It’s also a 2.5 layer shell but has two harness/ hipbelt compatible pockets with a mesh lining that help with venting. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589448528" title="Mountain Hardwear Quasar™ Lite Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3856/14589448528_8cd312f7d4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear Quasar™ Lite Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>Mountain Hardwear uses OutDry in some of their packs, and the newest addition is the Scrambler 30. OutDry makes this pack’s main compartment completely waterproof. It has a 30 l volume and weighs 770 g and can carry between four and 11 kg. The waistbelt is stowable and you can carry your skis, ice tools or trekking poles. A versatile pack that should keep your gear dry in any situation.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589380770" title="Mountain Hardwear Scrambler™ 30 OutDry® by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5559/14589380770_c46164af2c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear Scrambler™ 30 OutDry®" /></a></p>

<p>The Mountain Hardwear Optic tent series gives you grand vistas through the possibility to open two adjacent doors for 180° views. The Optic 6 gives this possibility now to your next family camping trip. Not a lightweight shelter by any means at almost 7 kg, it does offer plenty of space - six adults could sleep in there, but please don’t move much in your sleep then. I think it’d be good for a family with two to three kids. At 500€ it’s certainly cheaper than many other camping tents where you can stand in, and divided between a family it is even lightweight when hiking. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776099795" title="Mountain Hardwear Optic™ 6 Tent by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3884/14776099795_a79fdff3a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Mountain Hardwear Optic™ 6 Tent" /></a></p>

<h2 id="tenaya">Tenaya</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.tenaya.net/index.php">Tenaya</a> makes climbing shoes. I decided to swing by and see what this company from Spain has to offer to us climbers and tried their <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/tenaya-oasi-kletterschuhe/?pid=81">Oasi</a> on. Wow. It’s hands down the most comfy climbing shoe I have worn - and that while also allowing for precision on small holds and hooking. <a href="https://www.facebook.com/AlexanderMegosSportler">Alex Megos</a> wears them, and he certainly knows a thing to two about climbing and shoes. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776098195" title="Tenayah Oasi by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3839/14776098195_1ec22697e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tenayah Oasi" /></a></p>

<p>But the Oasi isn’t new. The Tarifa is. It is a laced shoe and is designed for versatile performance and comfort on rock. It has a Vibram XS Grip 3.5 mm sole and is similarly constructed like the Oasi - I’d say it’s the Oasi with laces instead of the Velcro closure system. Definitely a shoe to try on if you have a chance, as its comfy with great performance. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589600097" title="Tenaya Tarifa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/14589600097_33ea0e0821_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tenaya Tarifa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776098075" title="Tenaya Tarifa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3906/14776098075_999775c4fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tenaya Tarifa" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rock-technologies">Rock Technologies</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.rocktechnologies.co.uk/">Rock Technologies</a> is the UK’s largest manufacturer of loose chalk and chalk balls, as well as several other climbing-related gear. They’re in business since 2001 and Richard, the owner started in his mother’s garage until the business was getting to big and dusty! Now they produce their high-quality chalk products in the UK and Austria, and they use only medical grade magnesium carbonate which minimizes health risks. Other products are a power putty for training and finger tape - I got some of the gear here on test and will report back after use.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14772928251" title="Rock Technologies Sterevive by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3886/14772928251_2bc594715a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Rock Technologies Sterevive" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14799510443" title="Rock Technologies Chalk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5594/14799510443_c9cca7e001_b.jpg" width="960" height="790" alt="Rock Technologies Chalk" /></a></p>

<h2 id="goal-zero">Goal Zero</h2>

<p>Power on the go - with <a href="http://bit.ly/1rXAMAH">Goal Zero</a> no problem. The Rock Out2 Solar Speaker is well suited for those backpacking parties where you don’t have a guitar along but need some tunes. The speaker hooks up via Bluetooth or a audio jack to your phone and gives an adequate sound for your next beach or outdoor party - 20 hours long or as long as the sun shines.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14663080042" title="Goalzero Rock Out2 Solar Speaker by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3854/14663080042_8539a3684b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Goalzero Rock Out2 Solar Speaker" /></a></p>

<p>The Torch 250 is a torch that can be powered via the solar panel or the crank. It has a between 70 and 180 Lumen depending on the mode you choose, and also has a red light. I wouldn’t carry it on a backpacking trip, but if you need a torch in your house or car for emergencies and don’t want to also have many batteries to power it, this would be the best alternative.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476811188" title="Goalzero Torch 250 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5594/14476811188_190f7a35ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Goalzero Torch 250" /></a></p>

<p>A piece of gear that certainly is something for backpackers is the Switch 10 Set. It consists of the Nomad 7 Solar Panel, Goal Zero Switch 10 Recharger and three add-on for the latter: A Ventilator (made from silicone so folds up), a USB to Mini-USB converter and a torch. These connect to the Switch 10 (which packs some more power than the current Switch 8). Weight will be probably a bit over 500 g all included, but if you only take what you need that goes down. The panel itself can store all the gear in a mesh pocket on the back and be strapped to your pack so you can power up while you hike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476815358" title="Goal Zero Switch 10 Set by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5494/14476815358_a17417670f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Goal Zero Switch 10 Set" /></a></p>

<h2 id="pramo">Páramo</h2>

<p><a href="http://paramo.co.uk/en-gb/index.php">Páramo</a> introduced three fleece/ windproof duos that use their innovative combination of Nikwax® Fleece with Nikwax® Windproof fabrics to create a versatile system. On their own both the fleeces and windproofs are water-repellent and able to hold off a rain shower. However, when worn together they provide the equivalent protection to a Páramo Analogy® Waterproof. And all of that PFC-free! Interesting for mountaineers and climbers is the Men’s Enduro &amp; Ladies’ Ventura Fleece/ Windproof Systems, these have an athletic fit, are harness, helmet and glove compatible and both have (aligned) hoods. The Men’s Bora &amp; Ladies’ Zonda duos are for hill walkers and backpackers, while the Men’s Bentu is for the everyday walker. Nice garments, made by a company that takes environmental and social matters serious and makes good efforts to make the (outdoor) world a better place.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589599957" title="Páramo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3870/14589599957_442af65f57_b.jpg" width="862" height="1024" alt="Páramo" /></a></p>

<p>The company also launched an Active Travel Collection, made of cool, protective and lightweight garments. They’re made of the Nikwax fabrics Parameta A and Cotton+ which keep you cool and provide protection against UV rays and biting insects. I imagine this would work well for backpacking in hot regions or just as casual garments in the office and town. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776141234" title="Páramo Men&#x27;s Maui II Cargo Trousers Sedge Cotton+ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5574/14776141234_a1c145483f_b.jpg" width="506" height="1024" alt="Páramo Men&#x27;s Maui II Cargo Trousers Sedge Cotton+" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14591991357" title="Páramo Men&#x27;s Katmai Light Shirt Woodland Check by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3846/14591991357_6483695440_b.jpg" width="986" height="1024" alt="Páramo Men&#x27;s Katmai Light Shirt Woodland Check" /></a></p>

<h2 id="scandinavian-outdoor-group">Scandinavian Outdoor Group</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.scandinavianoutdoorgroup.com/">Scandinavian Outdoor Group</a> not just has the tastiest coffee on the fair at the SOG Bar, but also unites the best outdoor brands from the north. The SOG Press Conference was an interesting event to attend, where 13 companies presented themselves and their newest creations. The SOG also heads out before each fair and tests kit that has been submitted for consideration for the prestigious SOG Award, which this time went again to Röjk and their PrimaLoft Zippen Hood. There were lots of great presentations with heaps of humour, which shows that the North not just builds some high-quality gear but also can have a laugh about themselves =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14776101165" title="SOG Haglöfs Presentation by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5570/14776101165_afd96efe36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="SOG Haglöfs Presentation" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14773743944" title="Peak Performance Cuben Suit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3874/14773743944_3e6a346289_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Peak Performance Cuben Suit" /></a></p>

<h2 id="big-agnes">Big Agnes</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.bigagnes.com/">Big Agnes</a> is still pretty hard to get in Europe so it was nice to check out their gear and meet the team. The Fly Creek UL 2 looked pretty cool and also won a OutDoor Award, and at packed weight of 1.050 g for the 2 Person version it’s a pretty impressive looking shelter. If you are hiking with a tablet or Kindle, install the Entertainment Center Loft inside and you can read or view a movie while lying down or sitting in the tent.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476728320" title="Big Agnes Fly Creek UL 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2900/14476728320_c3dc5d9a36_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Big Agnes Fly Creek UL 2" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14660188781" title="Big Agnes Fly Creek UL 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3891/14660188781_4d7c8e2ba4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Big Agnes Fly Creek UL 2" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14660188691" title="Big Agnes Entertainment Center Loft by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5523/14660188691_aa0fe2bfc7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Big Agnes Entertainment Center Loft" /></a></p>

<p>The Double Z Air Pad will be available as an Insulated version and should keep you warm when it gets cold. Pack size looked good, as did the thickness and size of the pad. It’s gonna be 595 g light in the 183 x 51 cm size and uses PrimaLoft Silver Hi-Loft as an insulation material to achieve an R-Value of 4.5.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14661141894" title="Big Agnes Insulated Double Z Air Pad by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3896/14661141894_49fc01c9fa_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Big Agnes Insulated Double Z Air Pad" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, mtnGlo™ is a really smart way to illuminate your shelter at night. Flexible LEDs are sewn into several of the Big Agnes models available, like the Copper Spur UL2 and UL3, Rattlesnake SL1 - SL4, Ripple Creek UL2+ and several more. But Big Agnes also thought about those tent users who don’t want to buy a new tent but would like to enjoy mtnGlo™ light inside, and that’s where the mtnGlo™ Tent Light Accessory Kit comes in handy. It’s a 254 cm long LED strand with Power pack that you can easily clip into the ceiling of your tent or shelter and <em>Voilá</em> - it’s light! Clips are included, the whole package is 84 g and is powered by three AAA batteries. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476781198" title="Big Agnes mtnGlo™ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3852/14476781198_def1fe84e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Big Agnes mtnGlo™" /></a></p>

<h2 id="salomon">Salomon</h2>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1qffpI5">Salomon</a> presented a sub 400 g, crampon compatible mountaineering boot, the Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX. It uses a carbon fibre midsole that is laterally stable but otherwise flexible. A Contragrip sole, a Sensifit upper with GTX lining &amp; Quicklace closure, this is the shoe for all those that like to run mountains up. I’m generally not a boot type, but this is a boot I’m excited about.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14589445398" title="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3843/14589445398_8ec27437af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14753133576" title="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX Sole by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5588/14753133576_dc60394031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="725" alt="Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX Sole" /></a></p>

<p>Flowtech is Salomon’s idea of venting on strenuous ascents where you don’t want to take the jacket off. Just open the zippers, roll the front up and keep it in place with the bungee cord. Good idea, but how will it work in the field?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14640394336" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5570/14640394336_bc32c5c9d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>The Ellipse Sport W is Salomon’s Women-only shoe. It has a women’s last and design and is from their hiking/ sports line, so could be a suitable hiking shoe for the ladies. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14663377945" title="Salomon Ellipse Sport W by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5544/14663377945_3c5b68268c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon Ellipse Sport W" /></a></p>

<p>The S-Lab Sense 4 Ultra SG goes into round four. The rubber on the sole has been made a bit more durable, so you might now get two Ultras out of one pair ;) It’s still as grippy and light as the ones before it - a fine shoe, slightly better.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14683282353" title="Salomon S-Lab Sense 4 Ultra SG by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3880/14683282353_9ef22fe79d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon S-Lab Sense 4 Ultra SG" /></a></p>

<p>The Speedcross 3 continues to be one of Salomon’s most popular shoes and now get updated colours for 2015, including Camo, which means finally hunters and Bushcrafters can wear them. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476758988" title="Salomon Speedcross 3 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5157/14476758988_afd596acc8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salomon Speedcross 3" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sealskinz">Sealskinz</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.sealskinz.com/UK/?skip_welcome_popup">Sealskinz</a> is also a company which I have read about a lot but have never tried their gear, so it was nice to put on some of their socks and gloves. The socks felt comfy warm and I can imagine them working well in wet weather or in winter when skiing, snow shoeing or ice climbing. The gloves had a good fit and the different models I tried on gave me quickly warm hands! There were a couple of models which I think could work well for winter mountaineering/ hiking and ice climbing, though for me they might be too warm to use in summer. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14775741742" title="SealSkinz by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5573/14775741742_896b5f198f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="SealSkinz" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14772928081" title="SealSkinz by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3871/14772928081_4ea8a75c04_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="SealSkinz" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. More photos you can find on the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157645582553771/">Flickr OutDoor 2014</a> set. </p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2014 - 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-3.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T13:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There was rain, there was sun, then the sky opened up and everyone was happy he had a hardshell and umbrella to stay dry on day three of the OutDoor 2014.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14484713518" title="Impressions by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5033/14484713518_faa92f7317_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Impressions" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="jetboil">Jetboil</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jetboil.com/">Jetboil</a> killed the Sol (Ti) cooking system. The company realized it’s too specialist and that the Ti pot and aluminium heat exchanger didn’t get along well, so the new stove for 2015 is the MiniMo. It’s a 415 g system with a wide, low pot that in my indoor test at the OutDoor boiled 1 l of water in 3:08 minutes. The pot is easier to attach to the stove unit and the stoves valve and regulator have been redesigned and were easier to use and you can put the flame really low - it actually might be possible to cook in it now. There’s still the Piezo ignition on it, and the pot also got a pair of silicone-covered metal handles. Those cozies are interchangeable, and there’s four different ones available from the time the MiniMo hits the shelves. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14634124075" title="Jetboil MiniMo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3846/14634124075_7848cea831_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Jetboil MiniMo" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14633668832" title="Jetboil MiniMo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2900/14633668832_b46321911c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Jetboil MiniMo" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/1roxKFj">Jetboil Joule Group Cooking System</a> is on the shelves and ready to power your next group trek. </p>

<h2 id="ortovox">Ortovox</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.ortovox.de/">Ortovox</a> introduces a really cool looking Cargo Pants which is made from Cordura® Wool - a mix of 55% Merino wool and 45% Cordura with an ecorepel® finish which makes it dirt and water-repellant and is PFC-free. Stretch inserts and an athletic cut mean you’ll have freedom of movement in these, and for very hot summer days there will also be a Shorts available from the same material - also in some cool colours. Supergeil they look, especially in orange. Equally Supergeil is the Rock’N’Wool Double Check Shirt which I sport here. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447506168" title="ORTOVOX Rock&#x27;N&#x27;Wool Double Check Shirt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2929/14447506168_633cb20f00_b.jpg" width="880" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX Rock&#x27;N&#x27;Wool Double Check Shirt" /></a></p>

<p>The 100% Merino wool shirt in a light 133 g/ m2 quality which makes it well suited for summer use. It combines all the good stuff you like about Merino wool with a kickass style - gone the times of boring black shirts. You probably want to wear a pair of Sports Rock’N’Wool Cool socks with the shirt &amp; pants or shorts. What looks like you dressed in a hurry in the morning actually is on purpose: The socks are of different colours. And they employ Tencel which cools your feet, which makes them ideal for the tropic temperatures we currently enjoy in Finland. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447504788" title="ORTOVOX Sports Rock&#x27;N&#x27;Wool Cool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3879/14447504788_0ba8a13d0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="ORTOVOX Sports Rock&#x27;N&#x27;Wool Cool" /></a></p>

<p>On those fresh summer 2015 evening you can put on the Swisswool Light Tec Vest. It’s swiss wool - wool which in the past was treated as waste as the fibres are too short. But Ortovox figured out how to use the wool - as an insulation material in their Swisswool garments. The Vest here will weigh 263 g and has a fine hood, zipper pockets that are sitting high on the vest and thus won’t interfere with your hipbelt or harness.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447701057" title="ORTOVOX Swisswool Light Tec Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5528/14447701057_22de3aa1c3_b.jpg" width="1019" height="1024" alt="ORTOVOX Swisswool Light Tec Vest" /></a></p>

<h2 id="mountain-equipment">Mountain Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.com/">Mountain Equipment</a> from the UK has a few nice pieces coming for the next year. I like off-set zippers so I did enjoy trying on the Squall Hooded Jacket. It’s a climbing softshell jacket, 310 g light and retails for 120€. It’s a climbing specific fit with good freedom of movement, articulated sleeves and a helmet compatible hood. The asymmetric zipper not just looks good, it’s also practical as so the zipper won’t rub against the front of your chin/ face. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447709677" title="Mountain Equipment Squall Hooded Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5471/14447709677_8e3652e80c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Squall Hooded Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Kinesis Jacket will be a 325 g Polartec Alpha garment and from the quick test at the booth convinced me with a good fit, being stowable in its own pocket and a nice waffle fleece lining on the sleeves and hood. It uses the ME Helium 30 fabric as a shell which makes it windproof. It was a good fit and should work well on its own or as a midlayer under a shell/ windjacket for some extra warmth.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447499859" title="Mountain Equipment Kinesis Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5593/14447499859_0f1dd52ef9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Mountain Equipment Kinesis Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Foil Jacket is a 85 g wind jacket with an interesting hem drawstring. It’s going above the butt as you can see underneath, so that the fabric covering your buttocks - which is longer - has some movement. This might mean the jacket won’t ride up as jacket with drawstring at the hem often do - testing will show this in the future. It has thumbloops, articulated sleeves and packs into its own chest pocket.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14633664532" title="Mountain Equipment Foil Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3905/14633664532_26582576e6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Foil Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Aurora Synthetic sleeping bag uses Climashield Apex for insulation, the same material many cottages uses in their quilts. There’s three models available with Comfort ratings of 3°C, -1°C and -4°C and will start at 180€. They have a wind-resistant shell fabric, a 3/4 zipper and a collar, and if the weight is good (don’t know, sorry) these might be interesting for those that prefer synthetic sleeping bags.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14634120375" title="Mountain Equipment Aurora Synthetic Sleeping bag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3861/14634120375_8be8531d7c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Aurora Synthetic Sleeping bag" /></a></p>

<h2 id="primaloft">PrimaLoft</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.primaloft.com/uk/performance/home.html">PrimaLoft</a> showed off their Performance Down Blend material, a material that combines European down (EDFA and ADFC monitored) with PrimaLoft microfibres. The down is given a PFC-free water-repellent coating and then is <em>bound homogenously with the ultra-fine PrimaLoft® fibers that root the water-repellent qualities permanently in the fibers so they cannot be washed out.</em> It’s supposed to retain its structure even when wet and more than 90% of the heat is still stored then, too. It’s bluesign certified and I got a down short with the material here so will put those claims to the test in a bit - right now it’s a bit too hot to wear them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14719184525" title="Primaloft Performance Down Blend Insulation by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5553/14719184525_30a0bf9329_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Primaloft Performance Down Blend Insulation" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab">Rab</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://rab.uk.com/">Rab</a> Guidebook was hands down the best workbook/ catalogue I was given at the entire fair. Five Rab athletes tell stories in it, and Rab highlights six clothing systems in it. Gorgeous photos, superb layout and typography choices, these are the small highlights at the fair which delight me. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14531665589" title="Rab 2015 Guidebook by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3871/14531665589_dc52bccf53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab 2015 Guidebook" /></a></p>

<p>Oh, the gear from them wasn’t bad, either. The Polar Bedding Bag allows you to store your sleep system largely uncompressed on top of your pulka. I can see how you can use this even as a groundsheet in a snow cave or similar - just throw the Polar Bedding Bag in, open the zipper and lay down in bed. It’s a 800 g heavy item, so you really will want to have that pulka to transport it. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447698807" title="Rab Polar Bedding Bag &amp; Pulk Bag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2927/14447698807_98fe2b4331_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab Polar Bedding Bag &amp; Pulk Bag" /></a></p>

<p>The MeCo shirts get updated colours including striped versions, but most importantly now all garments will also be available in a women’s fit. So get ready to give your better half a lovely MeCo hoody, Meco Boxers and MeCo pants.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14634111675" title="Rab MeCo line by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2937/14634111675_387a9d0466_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab MeCo line" /></a></p>

<p>The Vapour-rise family has gotten a couple of additions with the Women’s Vapour-rise Flex Jacket and for men there will be the Vapour-rise Flex Pull-On, Flex Vest and Flex Jacket. These use, as you might guess from the name, Vapour-rise in the front and back with stretch side panels. These are more minimalist and will tip the scales at 180 g for the vest and 250 g for the Pull-On.</p>

<p>The Ventus and Lunar (for the Ladies) Jackets pictured underneath are made from the Matrix SWS fabric with a Polygiene treatment. They’re windshells that are breathable, have an under the helmet hood, thumbloops and weigh 335 g for the Men and 255 g for the Women. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447500928" title="Rab Ventus (front) and Lunar (back) Jackets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/14447500928_214b6ffc6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rab Ventus (front) and Lunar (back) Jackets" /></a></p>

<h2 id="haglfs">Haglöfs</h2>

<p>The Swedes from <a href="http://www.haglofs.com/en-US/">Haglöfs</a> have (re-)discovered L.I.M. and have created an outfit (pants, midlayer, shell jacket, shoes) and backpack with sleeping bag that’s a mighty fine 1.492 g. Throw in your shelter and cooking system of choice and you could end up with a SUL setup. Costs for the outfit and gear will set you back probably an amount similar to the weight, but lets ignore the money for a moment and concentrate on the fact that here’s a global outdoor company that has created a very light outfit, sleeping bag and backpack. While we have seen many UL attempts in the past from several companies it often were stand-alone pieces - a windjacket here, a light pants there. But here you get a complete outfit, in rocking materials and colours if I may say so. That’s pretty nifty.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14532836337" title="Haglöfs L.I.M. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3838/14532836337_c54a6fc73c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs L.I.M." /></a></p>

<p>OK, lets look a bit at the different components. The L:I:M: Down sleeping bag uses a 7D shell fabric and 800 cuin, bluesign certified down. It’s 473 g and has no zipper, but the foot box is open so you could just slip it over your head. Or walk with your sleeping bag outside at night when you can’t hold it anymore (pull it up before you let it run, though). It has a +6°C Comfort rating so is something for those sumer hikes.</p>

<p>The L.I.M. Low shoe weighs 220 g in UK Size 8. It has a 5 mm heel drop, some rear cushioing, a water-repellant mesh upper (water-repellant mesh?) and the idea is, yes, fast hiking. The sole looked and felt grippy and it’s a super flexible shoe.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14739134983" title="Haglöfs L.I.M. Low by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3839/14739134983_d7163b9ce1_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs L.I.M. Low" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14532619168" title="Haglöfs L.I.M. Low by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3887/14532619168_32f0b71853_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haglöfs L.I.M. Low" /></a></p>

<p>The L.I.M. Wind Pull is a 65 g (Size L) wind shirt, made from a 7D fabric. It has a DWR coating so will be a bit water-repellant. It has a hood and a long zipper and even a zippered Napoleon pocket. The 175 g (Size L) L.I.M. II Trek Pant are made from a polyamide/ polyester double weave fabric that’s bluesign certified. UPF 30, quick-drying and comfy, soft feeling on the skin. Nice. Then there’s the Midlayer, the 155 g (Size L, you guessed it)  L.I.M. Power Dry Top. It uses Polartec PowerDry fabric, that awesome material that wicks sweat super-fast away and makes you feel dry and warm. Long zipper, zippered chest pocket. Besides the garments there’s several shell jackets and pants, down and synthetic insulation jackets, a softshell, shorts, T-Shirts and longsleeves and a hoody - all very light: The heaviest L.I.M. garment is the Active Jacket which weighs 350 g. </p>

<p>And then there’s still the L.I.M. backpack. 355 g, frameless, 25 l volume (it felt bigger), a good compression system, a zippered lid pocket and two elastic side pockets, this was a high-riding pack that felt pretty good. How it really carries with a UL load and a week’s food we’ll need to test.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14739136043" title="Haglöfs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5561/14739136043_371e8c4fbf_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs" /></a></p>

<h2 id="suunto">Suunto</h2>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1qInObH">Suunto</a> launched the Ambit3 Peak and Sport. For us outdoor-types the Peak is of interest, though both are Bluetooth compatible. The Movescount app will get an update shortly which will allow you to update Movescount on the go via your iPhone or iPad. The watch itself can also communicate with the new Bluetooth accessories and has the ABC and GPS tools you know from the Ambit already. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14716413881" title="Suunto Ambit3 Peak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3838/14716413881_52151886fa_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Suunto Ambit3 Peak" /></a></p>

<h2 id="la-sportiva">La Sportiva</h2>

<p><a href="http://lasportiva.com/">La Sportiva</a> has won a OutDoor Award with their Primer GTX shoe, which is a 390 g (per shoe) Gore-Tex Surround shoe. The <em>SURROUND technology guarantees unequalled breathability, thanks to the breathable surface that makes up the upper and the midsole</em>. That cool, H.R. Giger-esque look also has some function, and is called a Nano-Cells construction method. These should be breathable cells, give structure to the shoe and promote the elimination of humidity. It’s like you have an alien on your feet! The Primer GTX is a traditional lacing shoe while the Synthesis GTX is amid-cut boot with a quick-lace system (and is 395 g per shoe). Both have Ortholite insoles and Vibram soles that look grippy. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14533217647" title="La Sportiva Primer GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3887/14533217647_dbee305e7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Primer GTX" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14716481631" title="La Sportiva Primer GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2914/14716481631_ce2063e5cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Primer GTX" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14532989860" title="La Sportiva Synthesis GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3902/14532989860_7c1021720b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Synthesis GTX" /></a></p>

<p>The Genius is the Italians latest climbing shoe and is made for sport, trad, free climbing and normal to wide volume feet. The pair is 440 g, it has a 3 mm Vibram XSGrip2 sole and a suede leather combined with microfiber upper. The No-Edge technology means the the shoe adapts better to the rock because of the larger surface of the shoe that comes in contact with the holds.  The asymmetric lacing system should make for a good fit and the P3 stands for Permanent Power Platform which should make the shoe more long-lasting as it helps with keeping the down-turned shape over time.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14716484481" title="La Sportiva Genius by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3890/14716484481_d4ffa00fe8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Genius" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14532991300" title="La Sportiva Genius by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5583/14532991300_b996eaab95_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Genius" /></a></p>

<p>The Mutant is a new Mountain Running shoe. 320 g per shoe, 10 mm drop, a FriXion XF ultra grippy sole and an integrated gaiter, it looked like a very fine shoe for running or lightweight hiking. The lacing system is called FusionGate and allows for volume regulation in the heel and foot adherence. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14719654535" title="La Sportiva Mutant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3914/14719654535_825cd600fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Mutant" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14532987820" title="La Sportiva Mutant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2924/14532987820_b7906fc1bd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Mutant" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, the Helios SR is a 240 g, 2 mm drop shoe. Mesh uppers for breathability, a 4 mm Ortholite Mountain Running Ergonomic insole, again a FriXion XT ultra grippy sole for grip on any terrain and a slip-on construction, it’s an interesting, lightweight shoe.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14739510563" title="La Sportiva Helios SR by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/14739510563_daf06150b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Helios SR" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14719655505" title="La Sportiva Helios SR by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2925/14719655505_d1070cabbf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Helios SR" /></a></p>

<h2 id="montane">Montane</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.montane.co.uk/">Montane</a> has established itself since a while as a serious company when it comes to lightweight, durable and functional garments. Their 2015 line continues with these premises. The Featherlite Shell Jacket with eVent DVStorm membrane technology weighs 298 g in Size M and is a fully featured alpine climbing shell. It will give you the freedom of movement and protection you need during stormy ascents or even climbing the sky, as I so aptly demonstrate here.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14719577775" title="Montane Featherlite Shell Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2922/14719577775_94dd174a9d_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Featherlite Shell Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Habu 22 is one of two new Montane packs for women (the other one is the Yarará 32). It’s 917 g light and is a versatile pack that’s suited to any activity you might want to do with it: Strap your ice tools to it and go ice climbing or take it on a summer ultra distance run. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14717190954" title="Montane habu 22 pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2931/14717190954_cb11afd2a5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane habu 22 pack" /></a></p>

<p>The Rapide Softshell Jacket has a hood that stows away in the collar. On your head it has a snug fit and won’t flap annoying around while you’re running in the drizzle, and it weighs 346 g. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14696579336" title="Montane Rapide Softshell Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3847/14696579336_a95a2dacc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Montane Rapide Softshell Jacket" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14739441003" title="Montane VIA by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5589/14739441003_2bb89e79b7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane VIA" /></a></p>

<h2 id="nemo-equipment">NEMO Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nemoequipment.com/">NEMO Equipment</a> has 8 new tents coming out in 2015, one tarp, and a whole bunch of more gear. The Dagger 2P is a 1,6 kg two person tent with two doors and two vestibules. Features include an overhead pocket light and a privacy panel on the inner tent. It did look nice and 1,6 kg for a 2P tent is reasonable. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14697110576" title="NEMO Equipment Dagger 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5581/14697110576_b2c26b1973_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="NEMO Equipment Dagger 2P" /></a></p>

<p>However, the Blaze 2P (that name reminds me of a club I used to go as a student =) is a 2P tent with a minimum weight of 910 g. That’s already a serious number for ultralighters. Add in that there’s two doors and also two vestibules and it’s much the same as the Dagger above, just lighter! It’s achieved by the pole construction - there’s one pole that goes corner-to-corner while a short pole on top creates a large interior living space. NEMO says they will be waterproof, durable and tear-resistant, so this really could be a interesting 2P tent to check out next year.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14716926531" title="NEMO Equipment Blaze 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3851/14716926531_9fa14bef3f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="NEMO Equipment Blaze 2P" /></a></p>

<p>But NEMO Equipment also makes quilts and sleeping bags. The Tango Solo 30 (there’s a Tango Duo, too) is their new quilt. 810 g light, filled with 330 g DownTek treated 700 cuin down it has a comfort rating of -1°C. Interesting was the hood which you can slide under your pad and then connect the quilt to it via push buttons, this way the quilt stays in place and possibly drafts are minimized.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14697110626" title="NEMO Equipment Tango Solo 30 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3854/14697110626_df8e65e34d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="NEMO Equipment Tango Solo 30" /></a></p>

<h2 id="black-diamond">Black Diamond</h2>

<p><a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/">Black Diamond</a> had a load of new gear so here some highlights. The ladies get a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody.html">Alpine Start Hoody</a> and the Men some new colours.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14533609139" title="Black Diamond Women&#x27;s Alpine Start Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2915/14533609139_3a213a6a2a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Women&#x27;s Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles.html">Distance Carbon Z</a> got a new hand loop and the Distance Carbon FLZ gets a FlickLock Pro in addition, giving it a very compact pack size and an easy way to adjust the length. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14533598410" title="Black Diamond Distance Carbon Z by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3842/14533598410_a1a7a9d110_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Distance Carbon Z" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14740126313" title="Black Diamond Distance Carbon FLZ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5574/14740126313_ec1f593913_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond Distance Carbon FLZ" /></a></p>

<p>The Index is their new ascender. It has a trigger-finger slot to help you manipulate the cam for easier operation, a dual-density grip and a large clip hole lets locking carabiners rotate 360-degrees to eliminate the possibility of cross loading. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14533829157" title="Black Diamond Index by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5588/14533829157_d50b4bdfeb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Index" /></a></p>

<p>The Axis 24 is a technical all-mountain daypack and features a zippered top-loading design and the reACTIV suspension for added comfort. Crampon straps, ice tool pocket and attachment, hydration compatible, removable hipbelt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14717090941" title="Black Diamond AXIS 24 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2900/14717090941_ebd36bbb50_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond AXIS 24" /></a></p>

<p>The Pipe Dream 45 is a crag pack that carrie sall your kir and functions then as a start pad for bouldering or a place to keep your gear spread out and not get dirty.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14697277536" title="Black Diamond Pipe Dream 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3887/14697277536_bdc5fd31fe_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Pipe Dream 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="exped">Exped</h2>

<p>The Swiss brand <a href="http://www.exped.com/finland/">Exped</a> had a wide selection of new gear. The Summit Lite 15 is new for 2015 and is the small brother of the already available Summit Lite 25. The 15 weighs 290 g and the 25 310 g, both pack flat away in the lid in a minute. They’re made of Triple Ripstop Nylon and have Daisychains and once ice axe look, so are well suited to work as a summit pack. There’s even a stretch outside pocket!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14719889682" title="Exped Summit Lite 25 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3926/14719889682_18a3f743da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Exped Summit Lite 25" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14719889332" title="Exped Summit Lite 25 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3907/14719889332_a1342a393a_b.jpg" width="601" height="1024" alt="Exped Summit Lite 25" /></a></p>

<p>The Thunder comes in a 50 and 70 l volume size, and does remind me a bit of past GoLite packs. These 1400 g or 1490 g respectively, three entries to the main compartment stretch mesh side and front pockets and side compressison straps which also can be used across the front. Maybe something for long backcountry trips where you carry a lot of food?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14717014571" title="Exped Thunder 50/ 70 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3849/14717014571_264b458a01_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Exped Thunder 50/ 70" /></a></p>

<p>The Downmat TT is an expedition pad with interchangeable insulation tubes. It’s pretty versatile: You can adjust the width by leaving tubes out choose between down or synthetic tubes for the insulation you need for the trip in question. The regular length (184 cm) is 840 g and has an R-Value of 8. It has five years of warranty and the Octupus Inflation bag is included. You’ll pay 260€ for the M length.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14740047243" title="Exped Downmat TT by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5594/14740047243_8a988fb301_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Exped Downmat TT" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14719883982" title="Exped Downmat TT by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3922/14719883982_945e363f89_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Exped Downmat TT" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14533743397" title="Exped Downmat TT by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5592/14533743397_e44104c693_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Exped Downmat TT" /></a></p>

<p>Lighter and likely more interesting for the majority of readers here is the Winterlite pad. The 180 cm long pad is 495 g light and has the same R-Value as the Expedition TT: 8. It’s claimed to keep you insulated down to -38°C and has a small pack size, too. It comes with a nozzle pump sack which also works as the stuff sack and will start at 220€.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14533742847" title="Exped Winterlite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3910/14533742847_7000b0ed9e_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Exped Winterlite" /></a></p>

<p>The Synmat Hyperlite is 330 g light in 180 cm length and has still an R-Value of 3.1. The pack size is pretty good too as you can see, and it will cost 150€.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14720185875" title="Exped Synmat Hyperlite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3856/14720185875_9558534b17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="430" alt="Exped Synmat Hyperlite" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, SIM Hyperlite is a self-inflating pad that come sin three sizes. An R-Value of 3.2 keeps you warm till -5°C and with a weight of 370 g for the Torso length mat it’s still lightweight (the 183 cm long pad is 520 g). They’ll cost between 80 and 100€.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14720185865" title="Exped SIM Hyperlite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2930/14720185865_1f9ebb0f42_b.jpg" width="1024" height="551" alt="Exped SIM Hyperlite" /></a></p>

<h2 id="nw-alpine">NW Alpine</h2>

<p><a href="http://nwalpine.com/">NW Alpine</a> hails from Portland, Oregon and is one of many innovative companies from that area. The Eyebright Jacket I’m wearing there is a breathable cuben fibre jacket that tips the scales at 140 g. It has a climbing-specific fit and will get some minor updates for the next season. Other new garments include a Polartec Alpha Hoody, Jacket and pants, a couple of normal pants, a new Men’s and Women’s WPB Jacket and several more garments - all made in Portland. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14720887991" title="NW Alpine by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5594/14720887991_aca22fc1b9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="NW Alpine" /></a></p>

<h2 id="vargo">Vargo</h2>

<p>On the shuttle bus from the Airport to Friedrichshafen I had the good luck to sit next to Brian <a href="http://www.vargooutdoors.com/">Vargo</a> and so we had a interesting discussion during the two hour ride to the fair grounds. During the weekend I then swung by to see the new gear he already had told me about on the bus, and it was good stuff. The Ti Flask with an integrated silicone funnel which fold down when not needed certainly was cool and I can see the use of this on long winter treks. Tasty Scottish whisky from a Ti flask? Yes please.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14683328433" title="Vargo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/14683328433_8abe12d25a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vargo" /></a></p>

<p>The Ti running crampons should be around 60 g for one and fold up when not needed. Eight spikes under the front and middle foot give grip on ice and snow and are easy to take off/ put on. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476803118" title="Vargo Ti Running crampons by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5512/14476803118_06276d920a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vargo Ti Running crampons" /></a></p>

<p>The Titanium external Frame with cuben compartment is 940 g light. Certainly a product for a very limited audience but I totally can see a market for it. You can strap a bear canister to the bottom and generally lash gear to the frame. The frame was comfy to wear and is the same as in the <a href="http://www.vargooutdoors.com/ti-arc-backpack.html">Ti-Arc pack</a> which has a pack from another material. Packrafters, hunters and bushcrafters and people who head for long time into the wild are most likely to find this pack attractive. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476979387" title="Vargo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5527/14476979387_b7dd79be8f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vargo" /></a></p>

<p>And then there was <a href="http://www.vargooutdoors.com/apparel.html">Titanium apparel</a>. Sadly it doesn’t make you Iron Man or his Titanium Brother, but it claims it has some good benefits like staying non-smelly and dry. Tests will show if this will be the case, though it’s an interesting development. Every UL backpacker loves Titanium, and the idea to wear it just plain awesome. </p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. More photos you can find on the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157645582553771/">Flickr OutDoor 2014</a> set. </p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2014 - 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-17T11:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Day 2 was busy, busy, busy with lots of cool gear to touch &amp; try on!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14671353515" title="Impressions by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3856/14671353515_b5fe38b0c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Impressions" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-research">Outdoor Research</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/">Outdoor Research</a> is one of the companies I really enjoy visiting as they make very good gear. They make rather good gloves and hats so lets take a look at some of the latter. The Helium Rader is a 12 g rain cap made from Pertex Shield. It comes in nice colours and would be an ideal companion to wind jackets or hardshells that don’t have a hood. On the other side of the weather spectrum the Radar Sun Runner keeps your neck protected when you forgot your sunscreen at home. The cape stows at the centre back and is deployed in less than a minute. The UPF 30 hat weighs in at 75 g and ensures that you’re not becoming a redneck.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14668272351" title="Outdoor Research Helium Raider Rain Cap by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5560/14668272351_719af8fee7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Helium Raider Rain Cap" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14484908148" title="Outdoor Research Radar Sun Runner by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2938/14484908148_aeedc684dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Radar Sun Runner" /></a></p>

<p>The sun sleeves are a really smart item. Available in a ActiveIce &amp; Spectrum Sun Sleeves version, the ActiveIce sleeves cool you down - great for hot days on the hills. The more you sweat, the cooler they get. The Spectrum Sun Sleeves don’t cool you but keep you protected from the sun’s rays, and as either version has a UPF rating of 50+ you can be sure that with them on skin cancer has no chance. A smart piece of gear that is light and is increasingly often found in packs instead of a longsleeve. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14671477415" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3925/14671477415_98ef393272_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a></p>

<p>The award-winning Axiom Jacket got some updates: A Halo Hood™, interior phone pocket and a longer center-back-length - all very useful in the rain. It’s still made from GORE-TEX® Active and now employs YKK® AquaGuard® Vislon Zippers. It’s 418 g in Size L and comes in very nice colour combos. I really liked the Deviator Hoody. It uses Polartec® Alpha® insulation in the front torso area while Polartec® Power Dry® High Efficiency™ in the hood, sleeves and back panel wick moisture quickly away and keep you comfortable. Made from 7D ripstop in the front and side panels this hoody weighs 305 g in Size L and could be a very good piece for backpacking in the shoulder season and winter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14648478526" title="Outdoor Research Axiom Jacket &amp; Deviator Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3905/14648478526_aca7bbd023_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Axiom Jacket &amp; Deviator Hoody" /></a></p>

<h2 id="scarpa">Scarpa</h2>

<p>Visiting <a href="http://scarpa.it/">Scarpa</a> is always nice on the fairs. It still is a family run business &amp; this time I even had the honour to shake hands with one of the owners. Then there’s also great Italian coffee and good vibes, besides all the fine Italian made shoes. And of those there were quite a few new, interesting ones. </p>

<p>The Furia climbing shoe is designed by Heinz Mariacher and a really nice, soft climbing shoe. It has a XS GRIP 3,0 mm sole, a Microfibre upper and will weigh 195 g in Size 40. Made for bouldering, sport climbing or just for fun, this shoe is likely to be very popular.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14665410404" title="Scarpa Furia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3870/14665410404_c5a85edfc8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Furia" /></a></p>

<p>The Oxygen GTX is a multisport shoe that uses Oxygen GTX® with SURROUND™ technology with the new Sock-Fit DVL system. It has a speed-lacing system and weighs 440 g in Size 42 for one shoe. It’s a breathable shoe that is well suited for approaches and hiking in mountain environments, and the new Vibram® Symbios sole looked like it will give good grip.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14687566133" title="Scarpa Oxygen GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3835/14687566133_a73b1b4eb4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Oxygen GTX" /></a></p>

<p>The Scarpa Mojito Fresh is an update on the widely popular Mojito with a new upper. It looked &amp; felt like a super comfy shoe for urban environments and easy hikes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14480987050" title="Scarpa Mojito Fresh by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2915/14480987050_ea5ea8b430_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Mojito Fresh" /></a></p>

<p>The Crux is a approach shoe with all-day comfort. The new Vibram® Vertical Dual Density outsole has a climbing zone in the front and offers good grip on mountainous terrain. At 380 g in Size 42 for one shoe it’s a fairly light shoe that also could become popular amongst scramblers and hikers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14481040728" title="Scarpa Crux by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3853/14481040728_dc4d597dc2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Crux" /></a></p>

<h2 id="therm-a-rest">Therm-A-Rest</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/Therm-A-Rest">Therm-A-Rest</a> continues to be staple in many Ultralight backpackers packs. Those that love their <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">XTherm</a> or XLite but would like it to be self-inflating will surely get the EvoLite mattress, which combines the best of the TAR range. The EvoLite has the lovely comfort of your air mattresses with the convenience of a self-inflating mattress. It uses a new kind of foam which is very light and can be very compressed and the mat design is alternating between foam and air. The result is a 5 cm thick mat that inflates on its own. It will be available in the three sizes S, R, and L, vary in weight from 330 g, 480 g &amp; 650 g and will cost between 100€ and 140€. The R-Value is 2.1 and it’s made in Ireland! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14625938522" title="Therm-A-Rest EvoLite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5573/14625938522_3cc1e4ebc4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Therm-A-Rest EvoLite" /></a></p>

<p>The other NeoAirs have been updates with a soft non-slip fabric on top which makes them more silent - and I can confirm that’s really the case, though I have never found the mats to be noisy in the first place. A new version of the XTherm is the MAX which is just the XTherm in a square format. </p>

<p>The sleeping bags now employ Nikwax Hydrophobic Down and a aluminium, heat reflective layer in the bags, making them warmer and less suspect to moist environments. All the down bags have got this treatment, which also makes them warmer with less down. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439795499" title="Therm-A-Rest sleeping bags by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2925/14439795499_5d18df8624_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Therm-A-Rest sleeping bags" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14625934842" title="Therm-A-Rest Nikwax Hydrophobic Down by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5595/14625934842_58d5ca10ab_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Therm-A-Rest Nikwax Hydrophobic Down" /></a></p>

<h2 id="norrna">Norrøna</h2>

<p>The Norwegians from <a href="https://www.norrona.com/">Norrøna</a> re-launched the bitihorn line as a lightweight trekking line. It now encompasses the waterproof bitihorn dri3 jacket and pants which use the dri™3 fabric and will weigh 324 g for the jacket and 309 g for the pants. The idea behind the bitihorn line is that it offers protection, insulation and breathability with lightweight fabrics in all products. It’s a colourful line and I’m sure we’ll see more some of these garments find their way into lightweight packs. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14645734383" title="Norrøna by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2911/14645734383_5181e99af4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna" /></a></p>

<p>The fjørå line is a cycling line and now also girls will be able to wear it. It’s their most sold-out concept each season so it makes a lot of sense to add women’s specific cuts to it. Female riders will surely approve!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439199418" title="Norrøna fjørå by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2905/14439199418_9a4a1fa194_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norrøna fjørå" /></a></p>

<h2 id="osprey">Osprey</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/">Osprey</a> got an OutDoor Gold Award for their Atomos AG65 packs. They’re around 2 kg (there’s a 50 l and 65 l version) and now are sporting an all-new mesh air back panel that continues into the hipbelt. It’s a fairly comfy pack to carry - the one I’m wearing there has some weight in it - so I definitely see how this got the Award. It has quite a few pockets to keep you organized, comes in a few nice colours and will cost under 200€. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14646348263" title="Osprey Atmos 65 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2895/14646348263_2f959906c4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Osprey Atmos 65" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439819428" title="Osprey Atmos 65 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5507/14439819428_21cf1928f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Osprey Atmos 65" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14646344523" title="Osprey Atmos 65 backpanel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3917/14646344523_e83a043fba_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Osprey Atmos 65 backpanel" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14625938592" title="Osprey Atmos 65 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3909/14625938592_38c835b2cb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Osprey Atmos 65" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hilleberg">Hilleberg</h2>

<p>Imagine my surprise as I went to visit <a href="http://www.hilleberg.se/?set_lang=1">Hilleberg</a>. I didn’t have an appointment. But there was that tent there, and it looked like a Moment in Dark Green and Red. With large vents. So I spoke to the young lady next to it - it turned out it was the designer of the tent! - and was rather pleasantly surprised by what I heard. Modeled on the ever-popular Akto chassis, the new Yellow Label Enan is a 1,1 kg Hilleberg tent that lives up to the company’s standards. It spacious, easy to pitch, uses a new Kerlon 600 material that’s still fairly weatherproof and is sold as a 3-Season tent. More Specs: Minimum weight 870 g,  packed weight 1,1 kg, inner height 95 cm (it was good for me), 1.7 m² inner space and 0,8 m² vestibule space. It uses one 9 mm pole to pitch. Lots of good design details in this tent, so expect to read more about it soon.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14646350483" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3868/14646350483_068b962779_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14476649970" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2904/14476649970_1f5258d38e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14646351603" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2936/14646351603_505f0d8704_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14662957122" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3907/14662957122_501de69dc8_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a></p>

<h2 id="adidas">Adidas</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.adidas.de/outdoor">Adidas</a>. terrex. Stealth rubber. Sponsoring some of the top climbers and outdoor athletes of the world. Of course I went and visited them! The terrex line will get a few notable additions like the the terrex Agravic Wind Jacket (105 g in Size 50), the terrex Agravic Tee (120 g in Size 50, made from 50% Merino wool and 50% ThermoCool) and the terrex Agravic Shorts 65 g in Size 50, made from Pertex Equilibrium), which together weigh just 300 g. That’s pretty neat. There’s also 3L jackets and pants, longsleeves, down jackets, insulated pants, and much more. But you’ll still need shoes, and that’s where the terrex Boost comes in. The lightweight mountain running shoe features the BOOST™ cushioning technology, which provides more energy return than any other cushioning material in the industry. It will weigh 330 g for one shoe in UK Size 8 and cost 160€. Too bad it doesn’t have the Stealth rubber sole.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14640649046" title="adidas terrex by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2920/14640649046_60f80a19fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="adidas terrex" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14640649306" title="adidas terrex by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5554/14640649306_caf8a6c004_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="adidas terrex" /></a></p>

<p>Cuben? Yes! Adidas makes with the terrex AllAlpine Jacket a 3-layer Cuben &amp; Dyneema jacket that’s also breathable and lightweight. With that another very big player has discovered cuben as a material for garments. We can look forward to this will pan out in the future!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14649180176" title="adidas terrex AllAlpine Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2924/14649180176_f75175b971_b.jpg" width="774" height="1024" alt="adidas terrex AllAlpine Jacket" /></a></p>

<h2 id="thule">Thule</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.thule.com/">Thule</a> is a Swedish company that is well know for their superb transport solutions for your gear - be it your bike, skis or surf board, they help you to get your kit safely to the trailhead, beach and anywhere else. But from 2015 onwards, they also will be happy to accompany you along on the trail with their new line of backpacks. There are three lines: The Guidepost, the top of the line carry-all-pack; the Capstone is the weekend backpacking pack and the Capstone Daypacks, which carry your gear on a day out. Not unmentioned shall be the Sapling series, a child carrier that’s super-fast and easy to adjust in size so mom and dad can switch carrying their precious load.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14623169351" title="Thule Capstone by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5565/14623169351_64707d9b14_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Thule Capstone" /></a></p>

<p>The Capstone above is a nice pack for up to a week long hikes with a tensioned mesh back panel for breathability, a quick access shove-it pocket and a built in rain cover. You can lash gear to the outside, and the MicroAdjust suspension system transfers the weight to your hips and lets you adjust the size in seconds. They’ll weigh 1,3 kg for the 32 l pack up to 1,5 kg for the 50 l pack, are made from Cordura and come with a 25 year warranty. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14674668565" title="Thule Women&#x27;s Guidepost 65 l pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3920/14674668565_cee4997b54_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Thule Women&#x27;s Guidepost 65 l pack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14694552013" title="Thule Women&#x27;s Guidepost 65 l lid-pocket pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/14694552013_bd328ec2d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Thule Women&#x27;s Guidepost 65 l lid-pocket pack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14625917222" title="Thule backpacks size adjustment system by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3899/14625917222_e50ce0d739_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Thule backpacks size adjustment system" /></a></p>

<p>The Guidepost pack above - it’s the 65 l Women’s model - is 2,7 kg empty, also made of Cordura and again comes with a 25 year warranty. It has a TransHub suspension system which with a single aluminium stay and spring steel wire frame transfers the pack’s load to your hips. The hipbelt can be removed with the push of a button and turned around - great for transport. You can easily access through a large J zip side access panel your gear inside, which is cool for fishing out the hardshell when it starts to rain. I was impressed by the lid pocket pack: The Thule Guidepost lid transforms into a 24L summit backpack with proper shoulder straps. It’s a nice thing to have along if you hike in to a basecamp and then are off for day hikes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439792229" title="Thule Sapling size adjustment system by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2913/14439792229_d7ae19dbfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Thule Sapling size adjustment system" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14603397906" title="Thule Sapling size adjustment system by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5593/14603397906_d1afa65be0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Thule Sapling size adjustment system" /></a></p>

<p>The Sapling Child carrier has a brought range of features and comes in an Elite and normal version. The Elite has an extra daypack along, as well as a viewing mirror and extra large hipbelt pockets. On both models is a sunshade, a breathable back panel, a hydration reservoir pocket and the fully adjustable back panel and hipbelt make the transition between parents quick and easy. At 3,6 kg for the Elite or 3,3 kg for the normal Sapling they’re not particularly lightweight, though.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439966147" title="Thule Glider &amp; Chariot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5589/14439966147_01412b5f1c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Thule Glider &amp; Chariot" /></a></p>

<p>And for the sporty moms and dads Thule has brought out the Glider, a sports stroller with a lightweight aerodynamic design which allows you to get the most out of your run on any terrain. It’s 9 kg light, has a hand brake, rear suspension, a padded seat and a multi-position canopy for sun and rain protection. It’s fast and works well on forest roads, as a member of the Thule Adventure Team assured me!</p>

<h2 id="rjk">Röjk</h2>

<p><a href="http://rojksuperwear.com/index.php/sv">Röjk</a> is from Sweden as you know from my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/hoodylicious.html">Hoody review</a>, and the guys have a hand for making winning products. Their PrimaLoft Zippen Hood has won the SOG overall award on the fair and is a hoody that combines the benefits of Merino wool with PrimaLoft polyester. It’s very comfy and has great attention to details - zippered side pockets with hem adjusters inside, a protective hood and thumbloops. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14671714481" title="Röjk PrimaLoft Zippen Hood by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3908/14671714481_f3360b33e8_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Röjk PrimaLoft Zippen Hood" /></a></p>

<p>There’s plenty more of good garments coming from them, including a beautiful Merino Helmet Hood (100% Merino!), the super chic SuperTees (also 100% Merino) which have cool art prints on them, the SleeveLess Vest and the Atlas Shorts. All of these will be available for guys and girls, and their hats and socks are Unisex either way =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14488458737" title="Röjk SuperTee by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/14488458737_32e30152b4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk SuperTee" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14488232700" title="Röjk Atlas Shorts by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3878/14488232700_660f458995_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Atlas Shorts" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14488248459" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2921/14488248459_4cd8d5119f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14674907665" title="Röjk Everyday Socks by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3837/14674907665_5d6a49306c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk Everyday Socks" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14651903226" title="Röjk PrimaLoft Hiker Socks by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3853/14651903226_1bb88029cf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Röjk PrimaLoft Hiker Socks" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-north-face">The North Face</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.thenorthface.eu/">The North Face</a> had several interesting news. At the top is of course their FuseForm™ Originator Jacket which uses the new FuseForm™ construction in which fabrics are not taped and sewn together but fused, making for lighter weight while still having a high abrasion resistance. The Originator is a HyVent™ 2.5L jacket, part of the Summit Series and hence made for the mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14633678422" title="The North Face FuseForm™ Originator Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3863/14633678422_c3b9fb45dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The North Face FuseForm™ Originator Jacket" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447718687" title="The North Face FuseForm™ Originator Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5523/14447718687_321889ce9c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The North Face FuseForm™ Originator Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The ThermoBall Hybrid Hoodie is from the Hike Collection and uses, as the name implies, the Thermoball™ insulation to keep your core warm. Stretch softshell sides and side panels make sure you don’t overheat. On the back this Gentlemen is wearing the new Litus 32 pack, a 879 g rucksack that’s good for <em>multi-day adventures</em>, as TNF says.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14447475250" title="The North Face ThermoBall Hybrid Hoodie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3903/14447475250_17efa83af6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The North Face ThermoBall Hybrid Hoodie" /></a></p>

<p>The Ultra MT shoe will weigh 580 g in Size 9 for the pair and uses a new Vibram® Mega-grip outsole and a breathable Ultra Airmesh over the quarter. It’s a light shoe with a sole design which I <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/salomon-speedcross-3.html">have seen somewhere before</a> so it could well be that this is going to be a very popular shoe amongst trailrunners and backpackers alike. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14633674142" title="The North Face by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3865/14633674142_3956c19d89_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The North Face" /></a></p>

<h2 id="merrell">Merrell</h2>

<p>It felt a bit like <a href="http://www.merrell.com/">Merrell</a> was moving away from low drop/ barefoot style like shoes. While the drop in the AllOut Charge underneath is just 6 mm it does have 20 mm cushioning. It’s a Vegan shoe and has an improved UniFly sole. It got reflective details for those dusk till dawn runs and those lugs are 5 mm deep - that’s serious grip in crap terrain - and has a HyperWrap lacing system which should give a snug fit while maintaining agility. One shoe is 283 g in Size 9.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14670977632" title="Merrell AllOut Charge by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2927/14670977632_21b2a98cee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Merrell AllOut Charge" /></a></p>

<p>The Capra Series is classified for <em>Speed Hiking</em> so fastpackers will rejoice. There’s a Mid and a low-cut shoe, with and without Gore-Tex lining. The low-cut Sport is 383 g heavy with a Vibram Mega Grip sole (3,5 mm deep lugs). Smelly feet or shoes will be eliminated with the M-Select FRESH odour control treatment while the UniFly midsole cushions hard impacts. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14484652858" title="Merrell Capra by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/14484652858_1440cf10da_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Merrell Capra" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14484827477" title="Merrell Capra sole by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5576/14484827477_4a849cf372_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Merrell Capra sole" /></a></p>

<h2 id="real-turmat">REAL Turmat</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.drytech.no/">REAL Turmat</a> has two new meals for the hungry backpacker: Chocolate Müsli for breakfast and Chicken Tikka Masala for dinner. I haven’t tried them yet, but I have a sample of either so expect a post on them in the future. Nom nom. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14683526103" title="REAL Turmat by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3876/14683526103_73ba89a540_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="REAL Turmat" /></a></p>

<h2 id="msr">MSR</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/en/msr">MSR</a> is slowly but steadily becoming an ultralight company. The MSR Windboiler is a further development of the Reactor and uses a radiant burner design and is completely enclosed - no windscreen needed. Weight? The 1L pot with cozy, lid, cup and pack towel is 284 g, claimed minimum weight with the stove unit is 432 g. MSR gives a boil time of 4,5 minutes for 1l of water. It stands higher than a Reactor, will have a Hanging Kit and Coffee Press Kit available with it and the set will be 130€. Playing around with it at the fair I can say it is a nice stove and I’m looking forward to try it out on future trips. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14625930622" title="MSR WindBoiler by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/14625930622_4e9349fc1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MSR WindBoiler" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14646335193" title="MSR WindBoiler Stove by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2919/14646335193_96f99f034f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="MSR WindBoiler Stove" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624305174" title="MSR Reactor and MSR WindBoiler by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5584/14624305174_b17f444bfc_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="MSR Reactor and MSR WindBoiler" /></a></p>

<p>Another trend one was able to see at the fair was that big companies figured out that one can use trekking poles as tent poles. There were a few companies presenting shelters that employ trekking poles, and the MSR Flylite looked to me like one of the better designs. It has a minimum weight of 710 g and a claimed packed weight of 1.020 g. It’s a nice design - it remembers me of our Laavus here in Finland - and some smart details: Pockets for the trekking poles at the roof, large mesh windows in the back, front and side, small storage pockets inside, large entry. It will cost 350€, which is <em>slightly</em> more expensive than many UL shelters.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14477024448" title="MSR Flylite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2912/14477024448_43ba1039e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MSR Flylite" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14660433701" title="MSR Flylite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3874/14660433701_fe4d1dbc4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MSR Flylite" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624303634" title="MSR Flylite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5504/14624303634_f1f2587cec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MSR Flylite" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624303064" title="MSR Flylite trekking pole pocket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3859/14624303064_7956a42c2f_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="MSR Flylite trekking pole pocket" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14683550123" title="MSR Flylite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2920/14683550123_da4e04bc71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MSR Flylite" /></a></p>

<p>On the MSR Hubba NX front we’ll see now also green as a colour option. </p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. More photos you can find on the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157645582553771/">Flickr OutDoor 2014</a> set. </p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor News 2014 - 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-1.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T19:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s that time of the year again. But where <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">last year</a> was sunny and hot, this year it was rainy and cold. Here’s what’s new, cool, lightweight and caught my attention on Day 1 of the 2014 OutDoor Fair!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14632583213" title="eVent booth by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5154/14632583213_243b1c6447_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="eVent booth" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="arcteryx">Arc’teryx</h2>

<p>The big news from <a href="http://www.arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a> is their new line of footwear. If you know the Canadians you know that they only enter a market if they think they can do something innovative and disrupt the status quo. Their new line of footwear - which I saw already last month in Chamonix - includes eight shoe styles and is divided into low-cut approach shoes (Alpha) and mid-cut hiking and trekking boots (Bora). Both have the Arc’teryx Adaptive Fit which is a separately manufactured inner and outer shoe which enables a great fit, high breathability and weather protection. The outer is a seamless one-piece upper that’s constructed from four layers of technical and hydrophobic materials, and amongst the eight models there are Gore-Tex and non-lined models.</p>

<p>Very interesting are the Alpha² FL and Bora² FL models - both have a removable liner (think a sock or little booty you can remove). This makes them ideal for multi-day outdoor activities as the shell is made from hydrophobic materials and so dries quickly, while the Gore-Tex liner you can take inside your sleeping bag to dry them over night. There’s a lot of interesting tech in these shoes, from 3D molded toe and heel pieces to Gore-Tex up to the collar of the shoe. They’re made in China, have a 14 mm drop, are available from February 2015 onwards and will cost from 175 € for the Alpha FL shoe to 250€ for the Alpha² FL and 300€ for the Bora² FL boot.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14431823760" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3850/14431823760_04ee0da90d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14438951698" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5551/14438951698_e666203a98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear" /></a></p>

<p>Arc’teryx also renewed the complete harness line-up. There’s now five harnesses - two women, two men, one unisex. The Warp technology has been further developed, female-specific designs have been introduced and on the inside the mesh has been replaced by a soft lining. Great colours, too!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14440404000" title="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3922/14440404000_160b561972_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14440655907" title="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5157/14440655907_68bdb52784_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14604057436" title="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3846/14604057436_1ba20c92b5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624955214" title="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5483/14624955214_45f01d6d37_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14440459959" title="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2914/14440459959_221ea1eb97_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx climbing harnesses" /></a></p>

<h2 id="marmot">Marmot</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://marmot.com/">Marmot</a> Crux Jacket is made of the NanoPro MemBrain and is an alpine shell. 241 g light with freedom of movement and very good breathability, this could become a very popular shell jacket for ultralight backpackers. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14457805547" title="Marmot Crux Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3913/14457805547_867e455abe_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Marmot Crux Jacket" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14642037684" title="Marmot Crux W&#x27;s Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2938/14642037684_30021b3bb9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Marmot Crux W&#x27;s Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Pingora Pants is a Schoeller softshell pants which is made for the mountains. Reinforced seat, knees and cuffs, zippered pockets so nothing falls out and freedom of movement, it looked &amp; felt like a very comfy pants that also would do well on spring and autumn hikes in the Fjells of the north.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14664118523" title="Marmot Pingora Pant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3906/14664118523_d0e2e13305_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Marmot Pingora Pant" /></a></p>

<p>The Nitro 1 P and 2P are lightweight tents that are pitched with trekking poles. Made of an inner and a flysheet, these looked like interesting tents. High in the front so you can sit in them, with the possibility of the inner being used on their own during clear, mosquito-infested nights. It has a small porch so the pack can be stored in it, and the 2P version has two doors - one on each side of the trekking pole. Weight is 765 g for the 1P and 1049 g for the 2P and they will set you back 290€ to 350€ respectively.</p>

<h2 id="edelrid">Edelrid</h2>

<p><a href="http://edelrid.de/">Edelrid</a> introduces a new version of their Fraggle children’s harness, which offers safety, the ability to grow with the kid and comes in bright colours which will delight the little rock climbers. Also the new chalk bag, shoes and helmet for kids will surely make the Junior climbers happy to go to the crag!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439405767" title="Edelrid Fraggle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/14439405767_5fdb7a3567_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Edelrid Fraggle" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14623708664" title="Edelrid Kids Chalkbag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3894/14623708664_e6f778f8c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Edelrid Kids Chalkbag" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439197278" title="Edelrid Kids climbing shoes and helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3856/14439197278_dcddaa8f54_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Edelrid Kids climbing shoes and helmet" /></a></p>

<p>Also new is the new Rap Line II which is 6.5 mm think. It’s a hybrid of light, low-stretch aramid and energy-absorbing polyamide while offers many benefits over conventional rap lines when abseiling and hauling. I’m sure we’ll see this Rap Line on a lot of fast &amp; light alpine adventures in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602800566" title="Edelrid Rap Line 6,5 mm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2919/14602800566_c18004f934_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Edelrid Rap Line 6,5 mm" /></a></p>

<p>The Jul 2 is a single rope belay device - there have been several of these on the fair - which works with ropes between 8,4 and 11 mm. Made for gym and sports climbing the Jul 2 weighs 87 g.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14623707524" title="Edelrid Jul 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3910/14623707524_697dc0ca45_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Edelrid Jul 2" /></a></p>

<h2 id="salewa">Salewa</h2>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://www.salewa.com/">Salewa</a> is obviously their new corporate image. It’s a great design and after some initial time that I needed to get used to it I now really like it. But there’s also plenty of new stuff on the gear front. Very interesting is the Ergo BS - BS stands for Belay System. It’s a good take on dynamic belay devices and works very well. Even if you would put the rope wrongly in it you still could use one of the grooves to lower your partner safely. But that’s just when you don’t pay attention and also your partner sleeps during the cross-check! It’s easy to give out rope to a leader, and lowering the climber is also easier as with a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-smart-sicherungsgeraet/">Mammut Smart</a> as your hand which releases the slack is closer to your body. It will be available next year for 65€ together with the HMS carabiner you see in the photo.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14439397467" title="Salewa Ergo BS by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5576/14439397467_4762b00119_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salewa Ergo BS" /></a></p>

<p>Salewa also updated several of their packs, shoes and garments. The Alpine Speed jacket for example will be the official X Alpes 2015 jacket, Michi Wohlleben helped design a fast &amp; light alpine pack which looked very good, and some of their classics like their <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/salewa-wildfire-approach-shoes.html">Wildfire</a> shoes got a few improvements and new designs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602793266" title="Salewa Alpine Speed jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5033/14602793266_b5b0c60d7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salewa Alpine Speed jacket" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14623697414" title="Salewa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3841/14623697414_ae468ab3dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salewa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14626593112" title="Salewa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2938/14626593112_dcc5ed83c1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salewa" /></a></p>

<h2 id="petzl">Petzl</h2>

<p>Lots of new gear from <a href="http://petzl.com/">Petzl</a>! Orange continues to be the colour of the high-end products, and the new Hirundos is all orange. It uses the FUSEFRAME technology, is 280 g light in Size M, has four gear loops, two CARITOOL slots and a rear haul loop. It’s Bluesign certified and will be between 80 and 90€. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14438979259" title="Petzl Hirundos by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3905/14438979259_41a1086308_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Hirundos" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14438979479" title="Petzl Hirundos by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5499/14438979479_14187fc76e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Hirundos" /></a></p>

<p>The Aquila is a completely new harness and represents the high-end mountaineering and ice climbing harness from Petzl. Adjustable leg loops, FUSEFRAME technology, 345 g in Size M, around 100€. FUSEFRAME is a thermo-formed foam which produces a slim, clean harness without pressure points. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14438972168" title="Petzl harness line-up 2015 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3841/14438972168_94b651a79b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl harness line-up 2015" /></a></p>

<p>Macchu is an adjustable kids seat harness, uses the Endoframe technology and allows your child to have a harness like mom or dad. Available in one colour with a waist belt between 54 and 64 cm and leg loops between 34 and 44 cm. With it goes the Body Chest Harness.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14625576705" title="Petzl Macchu Kids harness + Body by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3849/14625576705_ddec922e03_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Macchu Kids harness + Body" /></a></p>

<p>All the ice axes from Petzl have been renewed. The Glacier Literide is a compact ice axe for ski mountaineering &amp; touring, is 50 cm long and hence should even fit inside most packs. It’s 320 g and has a B rating. The Summit Evo ice axe has a waterjet-formed tube shaft, weighs 400 g in 52 cm length, has a B rating and is the top-of-the-line technical mountaineering axe from Petzl. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14626551422" title="Petzl Glacier Literide by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3918/14626551422_207daf3b86_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Glacier Literide" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14438982209" title="Petzl Summit Evo ice axe"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/14438982209_bf71a2eb71_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Summit Evo ice axe" /></a></p>

<p>Also the lamps have seen some updates - the NAO now has 575 Lumen and a slightly updated design. A top-notch headlamp that just got better! The MYO is new for 2015 and has 280 lumens which go up to 370 lumens in Boost mode and could be a popular lamp for trailrunners, climbers and hikers alike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14625574495" title="Petzl Nao by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3861/14625574495_f215489555_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Nao" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14625097012" title="Petzl MYO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3912/14625097012_c6802c3de3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl MYO" /></a></p>

<h2 id="vaude">Vaude</h2>

<p><a href="http://vaude.de/">Vaude</a> celebrates it’s 40th Anniversary this year, but also has a few other impressive numbers to show: It’s HQ is powered by 100% renewable energy, 69% of the products are bluesign certified and it has 35% women in managing positions. Oh, and it’s the first Outdoor company which has launched a report according to the GRI (Global Reporting Initiative) - Respect! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14643756652" title="Vaude by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3864/14643756652_c42255259a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude" /></a></p>

<p>Gear-wise the Germans have launched a quilt - the Finsuit. It’s a smart quilt dressed up as a sleeping bag, which should make the idea of quilts more accessible to a wider audience. You can use it as a double quilt or a sleeping bag, add a hood or go without, have a the footbox open or closed - good ideas there, and all for a very low price.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14644168005" title="Vaude Finsuit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3896/14644168005_4e189f433a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude Finsuit" /></a></p>

<p>There were several new packs with interesting new ideas, like mesh backpanels which can be adjusted and go from a lot of space for good airflow to almost flat for more warmth. Being able to adjust packs was overall improtant and some good ideas have been presented in the pack lines. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14457764287" title="Vaude by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5501/14457764287_bf83c67c79_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14621195956" title="Vaude by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5512/14621195956_1b7064f2b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14457568608" title="Vaude by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2905/14457568608_228b82e4f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaude" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fjllrven">Fjällräven</h2>

<p>Also <a href="http://www.fjallraven.com/">Fjällräven</a> has discovered the bearable lightness of garments and comes out with a brand new “High Coast” line. The garments are made from 54% polyamide and 46% cotton and should be airy, quick-drying and wind-resistant. You also can impregnate them with the Greenland Wax to make them more water-resistant. There will be an Anorak (270 g in Size M, 199,95 €) and a Jacket (320 g in Size M, 169,95 €). In addition there will be High Coast Wind Trousers (210 g in Size 48, 109,95 €) and Trousers (365 g in Size 48, also 109,95 €) as well as shorts, tops and a dress. So if you like the brand with the Polar Fox but didn’t like their heavy stuff, you’re in luck with the High Coast line!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14623876901" title="Fjällräven High Coast line by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5524/14623876901_886af803ff_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Fjällräven High Coast line" /></a></p>

<h2 id="patagonia">Patagonia</h2>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a> is launching a rock climbing backpack line. The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">Ascensionist</a> pack has been very well received and the new Crag Daddy 45L pack should be just as popular for sports and trad climbers. The smaller Cragsmith Pack 35L lets you access the inside via the top or back panel. Finally, the Linked Pack 16L is a streamlined climbing pack built with burly fabrics which withstand abuse on the wall and should be perfect for lead climbers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14457435390" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5512/14457435390_ff42e2d752_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Patagonia" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14664006403" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2909/14664006403_330a799af9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia" /></a></p>

<p>The Men’s and Women’s RPS - which stands for Rock, Paper, Scissors - is the lightest climbing pants the Californians make. It’s super soft on the inside, durable on the outside and gives you the freedom of movement that you expect from a climbing pants. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14457503138" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3900/14457503138_3167e4c2c6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Patagonia" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14457692577" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2912/14457692577_9dbf137379_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Patagonia" /></a></p>

<p>The Houdini family had a new addition: The Houdini Anorak. Even lighter than the Houdini jacket which you love already, this piece from the trailrunning line surely will become popular in ultralight backpacking circles, too!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14457711627" title="Patagonia Houdini Anorak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2922/14457711627_556535edac_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Patagonia Houdini Anorak" /></a></p>

<h2 id="primus">Primus</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.primus.eu/">Primus</a> has launched a new winter gas that’s claimed to work well till -22°C. They also add a Summer gas and so you now can choose from their classic Power Gas, the Summer Gas and the new Winter Gas. The gas won an OutDoor Industry Award and will be available as a 230 g and a 450 g cartridge. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14611674612" title="PRIMUS Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5488/14611674612_e895a9cb85_b.jpg" width="1024" height="556" alt="PRIMUS Gas" /></a></p>

<p>Love your <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/primus-omnilite-ti.html">OmniLite Ti</a> but don’t like the noise? With the Silencer you finally again can hear the Nightinglae sing. It reduces the perceived loudness by a factor of four, and is equivalent to the sound of a conversation. It’s 17 g light and will be available from spring 2015 onwards for 59,95 €. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14425680688" title="OmniLite Silencer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2913/14425680688_6cf1680482_b.jpg" width="1024" height="769" alt="OmniLite Silencer" /></a></p>

<p>The Eta Lite is now the Lite+ and got a G-1000 heat-resistant sleeve with felt lining - available in five colours. The Lite XL is a 1 l pot for “real” cooking as Primus says. In both you can fit the stove and utensils as well as a 100 g cartridge. They will cost 129,95 € and 149,95 € respectively.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14609065361" title="PRIMUS Lite+ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3889/14609065361_1a18bb77a1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="290" alt="PRIMUS Lite+" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>. More photos you can find on the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157645582553771/">Flickr OutDoor 2014</a> set. </p>

<p><a href="http://ko-fi.com?i=8d16909703c77d0" target="_blank"><img style="border:0px" src="http://ko-fi.com/img/button-1.png" border="0" alt="Buy Me A Coffee :) @ ko-fi.com" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
