<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: laavus | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/laavus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-21T11:47:19+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tulikartta - A Map of Wilderness Shelters in Finland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/tulikartta-a-map-of-all-open-shelters-in-finland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-31T09:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/tulikartta-a-map-of-all-open-shelters-in-finland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Open Wilderness Huts, Laavus, Kotas and Fireplaces are something I dearly love about the outdoors experience in Finland. It’s just very sophisticated to be able to plan a backpacking trip and rely on laavus and huts for sleeping, or know that there will be a fireplace in the mid point of the hike for a nice lunch break by the fire. <a href="http://www.tulikartta.fi/">Tulikartta.fi</a> set out to index all public shelters - from Laavus and Kotas over Wilderness Huts to Fireplaces - in one easy to use map, which makes it an excellent tool to plan an overnighter!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16799797338" title="Lankojärvi Hut by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8690/16799797338_3621ec6343_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lankojärvi Hut" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="prologue">Prologue</h2>

<p>In the past and still in the present <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/">Outdoors.fi</a> and <a href="http://www.retkikartta.fi/">Retkikartta.fi</a> have been the digital services I have used to plan a trip in Finland. The former lists all National Parks, Wilderness and Hiking Areas in the country, with information on history, how to get there, history and services available. Retkikartta is a highly detailed map which you can use to create routes, measure distances and look up coordinates to huts up to a scale of 1:2500, save and print out directly from the browser or export to your <a href="http://bit.ly/1Dk1sCb">GPS device</a>.</p>

<p>Outdoors.fi overview of destinations in Finland
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16366737023" title="Outdoors.fi Destination Search by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7607/16366737023_517394ba86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="627" alt="Outdoors.fi Destination Search" /></a></p>

<p>Outdoors.fi “detailed” map of a National Park
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16799142908" title="Outdoors.fi Map by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8720/16799142908_3867f425e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="628" alt="Outdoors.fi Map" /></a></p>

<p>Retkikartta.fi detailed map overview of the same National Park as above. This one can be zoomed in up to a scale of 1:2500!
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16985510292" title="Retkikartta.fi Map of trails, sights and shelters by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8711/16985510292_60a38cdaea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="627" alt="Retkikartta.fi Map of trails, sights and shelters" /></a></p>

<p>This is a good way to plan a backpacking trip, but if you wanted to find a shelter for a day trip it would have been a bit too involved. Enter Tulikartta.fi which facilitates finding a shelter a lot!</p>

<h2 id="an-introduction-to-tulikarttafi">An introduction to Tulikartta.fi</h2>

<p>A couple of weeks ago I read a tweet with a link to <a href="http://www.tulikartta.fi/">Tulikartta.fi</a> and I was immediately intrigued. A map of fire? Click, and I was there.</p>

<iframe src="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16985487862/player/" width="1024" height="626" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>It didn’t take me more than a look and a bit of reading to figure out what I had in front of me: A superb tool to plan overnighters and backpacking trips in Finland where I don’t want to carry a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shelters/">shelter</a> or might, for extra comfort and because I love a nice fire, camp close to a hut, fireplace or laavu. I set out to experiment a bit with it and see what kind of outdoors infrastructure the map listed around Vaasa, my home town. </p>

<iframe src="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16364468064/player/" width="1024" height="640" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Plenty of options to take the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">bike</a> and head to one of these places, make a fire and sleep outside. I also saw that a few fire places, bird towers and laavus were missing on the map, but happily the people who developed Tulikartta also thought of that and you can add a listing yourself. </p>

<iframe src="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16985487622/player/" width="1024" height="628" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I need to say it is one of these services where you might think “Why has no-one thought of this before?”. I like it alot already and it has given me plenty ideas for adventures close to home in-between the bigger trips this year. Using the existing infrastructure allows me to go ultralight with the bike and leave a shelter and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/stoves/">stove</a> at home and make use of a nice Lavvu by a lake and grill a bread and sausage over a fire. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16366741123" title="Laavus in Finland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7647/16366741123_af56d6f95c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="628" alt="Laavus in Finland" /></a></p>

<p>Right now the service is only in Finnish but it should be easy enough to use also if you don’t speak this beautiful &amp; easy language. To get you started: Laavu = an open shelter, Autiotupa = a open, free-to-use Wilderness Hut, a Kota = a native Saami tent, similar to a tipi from wood, Päivätupa = A Day Trip Hut and Nuotiopaikka = a Fireplace. The shelters usually also have a fireplace and a dry toilet close by to them, too, along with a woodshed and the obligatory saw and axe. Now that you know where to find the next shelter &amp; fireplace head out and enjoy the Finnish nature!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16801327849" title="Fireplace by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7634/16801327849_43d2aa66b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fireplace" /></a></p>

<p><em>Liked this? Let your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a> also know about Tulikartta and share this article!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
