<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gestalten Verlag | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gestalten-verlag/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-22T16:55:23+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Wide Open]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Wide Open</em> has the byline <em>New Outdoor and Landscape Photography</em>. If it is really new and if you should get a copy, you read in my review.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968932345/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/319/19968932345_8fc222df65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gestalten-verlag/">Gestalten Verlag</a>. They make cool coffee table books with great photos and texts, so when <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">The Great Wide Open</a> appeared on my radar I was eager to check it out. An email and a few days later the heavy book slammed on my porch, ready to be browsed. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19780862558/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3665/19780862558_72b216d413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>However, opening the book the euphoria quickly ended. Sure, there are very fine images in there, but just as much of them look like they’re shot on an iPhone for Instagram and not for a large coffee table book. It feels like every other photo is a grainy mess that looked great on your Instagram feed when seen on a smartphone but shouldn’t have been printed in such a large format. Speaking of Instagram, if you’re on it and follow some landscape photographers then you’ll have seen the vast majority of these images in one form or another already. Another disappointment was that you could clearly see in many images that they have been taken not far away from a road or civilization - given that the Prologue of the book refers to <a href="http://amzn.to/1SFXAis">Ansel Adams</a> and how he would set off on long expeditions to capture expansive, wild landscapes that feels a bit wrong. Oh, and if you don’t like Chris Burkard - don’t get the book. Half the images are from him, and while they’re technically very good I personally find them a bit boring. On ther other hand, if you love him - get the book!</p>

<p>But for all that there’s also some very great &amp; inspiring photos in the book. The pictures from Anki Grøthe, Kilian Schönberger, Jimmy Chin, Logan Watts and a few others are crisp, sharp and with a fresh perspective on the outdoors. Add in the small stories and anecdotes from the photographers, athletes and outdoor folks and you get a book that will inspire you at least for one afternoon. Well, maybe a couple more. And if you like Instagram photos and would love to see them in a big book, you’ll probably read it every day! So if you feel like you want to give The Great Wide Open a chance and browse it yourself then order it directly at <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">Gestalten</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1RXDe9B">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJyEz">Amazon.co.uk</a> &amp; <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJFzT">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968931705/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/374/19968931705_29152e803e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/hide-and-seek.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-24T20:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/hide-and-seek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s weekend so its time to head outdoors, to the cabin. Got none? <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> will give you plenty of cabins to dream of over the weekend and inspire you to dream up your own.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17066651669" title="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7606/17066651669_6213274751_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Friday is the day where the mind starts to wander to a lonely log cabin in the woods, by the lake, heated by a wood stove, no electricity. Or is it more a luxurious cabin by the sea? Maybe a sleek mountain hut that looks old and ramshackle from the outside but that’s modern and cool inside? <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> has them all: Coastal cabins, mountain cabins, open range cabins and the wood cabin, nicely sorted into four chapters of the finest cabins the authors could find. And they have searched far and wide, from the Isle of Skye to New Zealand and Finland to Chile, there’s bound to be a cabin for everyone in this book, Gestalten’s 2nd Cabin book after <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/rock-the-shack.html">Rock the Shack</a>.</p>

<p>The book presents the cabins &amp; their interiors of people who don’t want to give up life in the city but want to be able to escape to nature. And as unique as we are as humans, so unique are the cabins, their surroundings and interiors in this book. The focus clearly is on small living spaces in nature, because the outside in front of the window is your living room in many cases, your entertainment, TV and internet. The book aims to inspire you to dream up your own cabin, but you’ll not find plans or construction tips in this coffee table book. However, in the index at the end of the book you can find out more about the architects of the cabins, so that gives you a good starting point.</p>

<p>Sadly we don’t have a own cabin by the sea or lake, so a book which inspires the mind for a more simple life away from home certainly is a good way to relax. I found the book interesting, though I saw a trend to very minimalistic, modern, almost similar looking cabins - with just the scenery changing from the coast to the mountains to the forests. There was a lot of wood, concrete, steel and stones used, all in similar shapes &amp; designs, often with straight lines. Standing out were really only Steve’s Thailand Dome House, the Tree Tent, the Cocoon and the Tree Snake Houses in terms of its design - that was fresh &amp; organic architecture. While I liked most cabins in the book, I missed more organic, natural and rustic cabins and interiors - which there shouldn’t be a shortage of. Personally I also would have liked a more inhabited look in the interior photos, many had the sterile-looking feel of a Modern Art Museum.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17065096818" title="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7601/17065096818_c322948cab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs" /></a></p>

<p>Despite this I would recommend this coffee table book to anyone who likes huts &amp; cabins and can’t get enough of them. You’re bound to have seen some of the featured hide-outs in the book if you follow <a href="http://cabinporn.com/">Cabinporn</a> but there’s a host of new &amp; fresh cabins featured which will get you dreaming about a weekend (or life!) away in them. It’s a beautiful book with high-quality paper and photographs, very legible typography and a clear layout which makes for a satisfying experience when reading &amp; browsing. There’s all in all 80 cabins and hide-outs in the book on 250 pages, and the nature &amp; scenery around the hide-outs and cabins is just as gorgeous as the huts themselves. I’m now off to dream up my own hut, if you need some weekend inspiration grab the book at your local book store or order it online from <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Gestalten</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1KbYSiH">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1duc68Y">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1ElTl8s">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Oh, and in case you’re wondering: My favourite hut probably is <a href="http://robinfalck.com/nido/">Nido</a> from Robin Falck.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outsiders]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/the-outsiders.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-25T13:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/the-outsiders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Going <em>Outdoors</em> is a big trend right now. So Gestalten Verlag went outdoors to meet <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/outsiders.html">The Outsiders</a>, a group of successful outdoor and lifestyle entrepreneurs, bloggers, writers, hikers, surfers, skiers - in short: People who love to be outside. The result is a book which portrays in a gorgeous way the growing outdoor trend - from hiking over cycling to paddling &amp; surfing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13981714206" title="The Outsiders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/13981714206_6177d493ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Outsiders" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There come quite a few coffee <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">books</a> across my desk, but The Outsiders was different. While many have captivating photos, I felt that each page of the The Outsiders was crafted with love &amp; attention to detail. Everything fits: Beautiful fonts, captivating photos, interesting interviews, short bios of outdoor folks and highlighting some cool products. Did I mention the inspiring photos? Oh. OK. Good.</p>

<p>What I liked a lot about the 272 page thick book was that there were a lot of familiar names and faces featured in it. There was Cass from <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/blog">While Out Riding</a> and Joe from <a href="http://joecruz.wordpress.com/">Pedaling in Place</a>, <a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/">Wanderlust Equipment</a> gear and <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> was seen on a few pages, and a couple more people &amp; brands that you have heard about if you’re interested in the outdoor scene. Overall there was a very good balance of the known &amp; trendy and the unknown and cool in all categories.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14024833953" title="The Outsiders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2898/14024833953_cdffce8fbd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Outsiders" /></a></p>

<p>There’s six “chapters” in the book: Hiking, Surfing, Cycling, On The Road, Snow and Water. All that comes after an Intro from Jeffrey Bowman, one of the authors of the book, and Erling Kagge, the first human to reach the South Pole, North Pole and stand on the summit of Mt. Everest. Add in interviews with Vincent Stanley from Patagonia, the Hoepner brothers who cycled from Berlin to Shanghai, designer Geoff McFetridge, amongst others, and you will have a hard time to put this book down. And even after you have read it back-to-back you will pick it up again, browse through the different sections to be inspired, or look up one of the cool kit pieces or blogs on the internet. And then you’ll want to go outside.</p>

<p>It’s a beautiful book for rainy days at home. You can get it directly from <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/outsiders.html">Gestalten</a> or order it from your favourite taste of Amazon: <a href="http://amzn.to/1faj21y">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1ikFiQV">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1rralzY">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rock The Shack]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/rock-the-shack.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T07:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/rock-the-shack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Want to leave the city behind? Then <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/rock-the-shack.html">Rock the Shack</a> will give you the inspiration you need to build your own beautiful cabin in the mountains, by the sea or in the forest!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13290864674/" title="Rock The Shack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7315/13290864674_6172e5b767_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock The Shack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Most of us outdoor folks dream about a cabin in the middle of nowhere. A place where we can go for a walk right from the door sill. Where the only noise is the wind blowing through the trees and the birds singing. Where you chop wood to fire your stove. A sauna by the lake. Wide views across mountains and forests.</p>

<p><a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/rock-the-shack.html">Rock The Shack</a> is a dangerous book for those who long to be closer to nature, living in their own cabin. Showcasing on 240 pages <em>“shacks”</em>, which range from self-sufficient sheds in the hills to luxurious hide-outs at the coast. There are wooden constructions, packed clay huts to combinations of brick, steel and glass. The forms range from organic leaf-like structures and cocoons to rather futuristic expressions of a shed. </p>

<p>The book takes you on a journey across the globe and shows the most inspiring cabins, from Japan over Chile and the USA to Sweden, Finland and Norway. As diverse the locations and cabins are, so similar are they in what they portrait: A place for people to be away from the city and in nature. A place where you can relax, meditate, be with your family and friends or just by yourself. Where the next hike, climb or swim is just a few steps away.</p>

<p>Not just architects and designers will find this book superb, also outdoor folks that are looking for ideas for their own shed. It has given me plenty of ideas for our garden shed, and further inflamed the desire to have a cabin out in the forest by a lake. It’s a beautiful book that helps you dream of your own little space, and is perfect to escape to when you need to relax for a few moments. Have it next to you on your work desk for those long office days. It definitely will be a conversation starter, but I’m not sure if it will get you a raise - although, who knows, maybe your boss dreams about a shed in the mountains, too?</p>

<p>You can <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/rock-the-shack.html">order it directly from Gestalten</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/OF8fzT">Amazon.de</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1duc68Y">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13290862584/" title="Rock The Shack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3828/13290862584_fe094d8f1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock The Shack" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
