<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Trad climbing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/trad-climbing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-26T00:06:34+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Petzl Sirocco Helmet]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T09:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An important piece of safety gear, every climber should wear a helmet when going to the crag. The Petzl Sirocco is the lightest helmet on the market at 165 g - so light that you sometimes forget you’re wearing it!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13425504763" title="Petzl Sirocco Helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3824/13425504763_dd5c008052_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Sirocco Helmet" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Since last year I have been wearing a beautifully lightweight orange helmet when <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/climbing/">climbing</a> - the <a href="http://www.petzl.com/en/outdoor/mountaineering-and-climbing-helmets/sirocco">Petzl Sirocco</a>, also known as the world’s lightest helmet. At 165 g it really is so light that I have been wearing it and forgot that I had it on - a short touch to the head made sure that indeed I was wearing it. That alone should make you delighted when you are in need of a helmet, but it doesn’t stop there - the Sirocco is the full package that doesn’t skimp on features to be lightweight! You can attach the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-vizion-elios-meteor-iii-visier/">VIZOR visor</a> to it and it has two hooks and rear elastic for attaching a headlamp . Oh, and plenty of ventilation openings, which allow you to attach e.g. your <a href="http://bit.ly/1juyPd3">helmet camera</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13425769644" title="Petzl Sirocco Helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2888/13425769644_f0f4e4c2fc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Sirocco Helmet" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13425521733" title="Petzl Sirocco Helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2808/13425521733_86771d869a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Sirocco Helmet" /></a></p>

<p>Constructed from a monobloc shell of expanded polypropylene (EPP) it comes in two sizes - my large size with a head circumference of 53 - 61 cm weighs 165 g, while the smaller size (48 - 56 cm) weighs just 145 g. It has a Velcro attached padding which can be washed, and makes for soft, comfy fit. The straps allow you to size the helmet to your needs, and are quickly adjusted when you’re for example wearing a hat or two in winter. Finally, the magnetic buckle can be operated with just one hand - even with thick gloves on - and is sitting to the side, which is more comfortable than a buckle right under your chin. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12902195714/" title="Selfie. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/12902195714_b00a507fda_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Selfie." /></a></p>

<p>Now you might think - <em>damn, that’s a light helmet, but can it take an impact?</em> I’ve fallen with this helmet and crashed into a wall and had plenty of ice drop down on it - and my head and helmet are still in one piece. Actually, the helmet still looks like new, and I haven’t been soft on it. And with a guarantee of three years, you can be sure that Petzl has designed and built this helmet to take plenty of abuse. You probably have seen this helmet also elsewhere - <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/ueli-steck-interview.html">Ueli Steck</a> is wearing it, Chris Sharma is wearing it, pretty much everyone who is climbing hard alpine, trad or sport is wearing it! I can’t think of a better endorsement, really.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13425760314" title="Petzl Sirocco Helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7247/13425760314_a78132641a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Sirocco Helmet" /></a></p>

<p>The bottomline is simple: If you go climbing outside, be it ice, trad or hard sport, you should wear a helmet. And you might as well wear the lightest helmet on the market, because it is very comfortable &amp; safe without missing out on essential features. It’s great for summer rock climbing, alpine climbing and ice climbing, truly a helmet for all seasons. Attach your headlamp to it, put the camera on record, and go climb! <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157642949520913">More photos</a>.</p>

<p>Get yours at <a href="http://www.mountainshop.fi/kauppa/index.php?cPath=45&amp;osCsid=ff946279d9a4fda41b978c56adc5e7cb">Mountain Shop</a>, <a href="http://camu.fi/pages/kiipeily/kalliokiipeily/kyparat/siroccooranssi.html">Camu</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-sirocco-kletterhelm/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-sirocco-kletterhelm/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1apnPXN">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1juxGT0">REI</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1pyyAvb">EMS</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9189664731" title="How To Build A Trad Rack™ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3772/9189664731_fe85a07cab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="How To Build A Trad Rack™" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DMM Dragon Cams]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/dmm-dragon-cams.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T22:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/dmm-dragon-cams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Besides being <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts.html">nuts for climbing</a>, for Trad also a set of Cams was needed. I sticked to the brand I trust, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/dmm/">DMM</a>, and got myself <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/dmm-dragon-cam-friend-00/">six little Dragons</a> to play with. Easy to place and reliable when it counts, after a season of use I couldn’t be more happy with them! <em>A living review.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12779771294/" title="DMM Dragon Cams by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7328/12779771294_ff146a6f7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Dragon Cams" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>Six <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/dmm-dragon-cam-friend-00/">DMM Dragon Cams</a> found their way to me in spring 2013, and I had them out on several outings to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/on-the-rocks.html">local crag</a> and to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/climbing-at-havukallio.html">Havukallio</a>. I also carried them along a couple of times to mixed climbs, but they stayed unused. All in all they have been out on seven outings.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12779778254/" title="DMM Dragon Cams by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3682/12779778254_642516b579_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Dragon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>Unlike nuts cams, or friends as they’re also know, are pieces of active protection. While the nuts and hexes have no moving parts, cams do have moving parts. This enables them to suit a wider range of cracks - where you might need to carry one or more different nuts to place them in a crack, a cam’s lobes can be moved by pulling on the trigger, which makes them narrower and thus you can enter it in a crack. Release the trigger and the lobes will wedge themselves into the rock, being, if placed correctly, a solid pice of protection. They are also versatile in the sense that you can use them passively - that is that you just place the cam as it is into a crack, much like a Nut, without pulling the trigger. What’s special about the DMM Dragon Cams is that in passive mode they have the same strength as in active mode.</p>

<p>Unlike Nuts you usually already equip the cams with a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/karabiner/">carabiner</a>, I like to use the <a href="http://dmmclimbing.com/products/phantom/">DMM Phantom</a> as I can colour-match them with the cams. What’s also unique about the DMM Dragons is that they have an extendable dyneema sling, which allows you to extend it to your needs. This helps to save weight as you don’t need to carry extra slings or quickdraws, too.</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/40654007?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The Dragon cam is a lightweight single stem design with dual axles and a thumb grip and trigger bar. It’s easy to handle and the extendable Dyneema sling is genius. It uses the original 13.75° camming angle and the cam lobes are hot forged. The plastic-covered stem is very flexible yet very durable.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12787616243/" title="DMM Dragon Cam by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2810/12787616243_535aba862f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="361" alt="DMM Dragon Cam" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>I could wax on lyrically about how awesome Dragons are and their design process, or I could just let DMM tell it themselves. It’s an awesome video, well worth watching!</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/U-C21qAwLQQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>They’re superb. As with most everything from DMM there went a lot of design thought, testing, re-designing, more testing, and high-quality manufacturing into making the product you see in front of you. It’s a great piece of kit that will serve you well. If you need to get the Dragon’ Dyneema sling re-done, you can send the Dragons to Wales where DMM will fix them for a reasonable price.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12779466743/" title="DMM Dragon Cams by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7407/12779466743_56641802b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Dragon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>Friends are heavier than Nuts but you can carry less to cover the same range as a set of nuts. </p>

<ul>
  <li>DMM Dragon Friend 4, 149g (177 g incl. Phantom ‘biner)</li>
  <li>DMM Dragon Friend 3, 123g (152 g incl. Phantom ‘biner)</li>
  <li>DMM Dragon Friend 2, 114g (143 g incl. Phantom ‘biner)</li>
  <li>DMM Dragon Friend 1, 101g (129 g incl. Phantom ‘biner)</li>
  <li>DMM Dragon Friend 0, 87g (112 g incl. Phantom ‘biner)</li>
  <li>DMM Dragon Friend 00, 78g (106 g incl. Phantom ‘biner)</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>TOTAL:</strong> 652 g (819 g incl. ‘biners)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12779341615/" title="DMM Dragon Cams by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3728/12779341615_c318664d1e_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DMM Dragon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>DMM manufactures their Cams in Wales, which makes the transport to us in Europe short. Aluminium, steel and plastic, the main components, can be easily recycled - just drop them at your scrap yard, and depending on the size of your rack you even might get enough money to go buy a pint in the pub afterwards. Aluminium has a large electricity footprint, but the alternative would be to climb free solo. While DMM doesn’t lose a word about possible sustainability programs they adhere to, they have a page on their <a href="http://dmmclimbing.com/about/quality/">Quality management</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12779472173/" title="DMM Dragon Cams by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7324/12779472173_da162a26a4_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DMM Dragon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I got the two sets of Sizes <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/dmm-dragon-cam-friend-set-00-0-1/">00, 0 and 1</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/dmm-dragon-cam-friend-set-2plus3plus4/">2, 3 and 4</a> which covers a good range for the climbing I do here in Scandi-land. Maybe I will add a Size 5 and 6 in due time to complete the rack, especially if that trip to Norway will happen.</p>

<p>The small rack of Dragons weighs just a bit over 800 g including carabiners, which is very good. As a Trad climber you’re carrying usually already a large amount of gear - Nuts, QDs, Slings, Nutbuster, etc. - so saving a bit of weight is nice. Add in that you can leave some QDs and slings behind as the slings on the Dragons extend and at once you have the chance to save quite a bit more of weight. Which for the few Multi-pitch routes here is maybe not that of note, but head over to Sweden, Norway or the Alps and things start to look longer and hence saving weight is a feasible thing to save energy.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12779353765/" title="DMM Dragon Cams by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7346/12779353765_b1b6cb69a0_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DMM Dragon Cams" /></a></p>

<p>As with the Nuts, I tested placing the Cams at the bottom of the crag, seeing which sizes fit which size of crack, and then roped up and started climbing. Placing the Cams is intuitive - pull the trigger, enter the cam into the crack, release the trigger, adjust the position if needed, clip the rope, climb on. It’s a fairly quick process, maybe a few seconds faster than placing a nut as you don’t need to clip a QD before you clip the rope, so on long climbs (or at the start of the season when you’re not as fit) it gets you less pumped. </p>

<p>If you already have a cam rack, lets say of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-camalot-c4-gr-0-3/">BD Camalot C4s</a>, you might need some getting used to with the DMM thumb stop which differs a bit from the BD thumb loop. For me, this being my first cams, it was no problem at all and I like the ease of use on this design, but I see how long-time BD users might need to switch their thinking. The Dragons are also a tad shorter than the Camalots. The slightly shorter design might be especially difficult for those that second and need to clean up, but that’s where a Nutbuster comes in useful.</p>

<p>Most of the DMM Dragons have a strength of 14 kN in every configuration, be it active or passive or slings extended or not, which will give you some peace of mind when you’re climbing above your last piece of protection and worry about a fall. I myself fell on the 00 cam (rated only at 9 kN, but I had a Nut close by) and the cam held the fall without a problem. I was a bit shaken, but otherwise fine. Even getting it out after the fall was easy, unlike the nut which needed the Nutbuster to get out. </p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a whole range of competing products, some a bit more affordable, others more expensive than DMM. <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-camalot-x4-gr-0-1/">Black Diamond</a> is a very well-known cam maker, as are <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/wild-country-helium-friend-set-0-5-1-5-2-5/">Wild Country</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/omega-pacific-link-cam-0-5/">Omega Pacific</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/metolius-offset-master-cam-gr-00-0/">Metolius</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/climbing-technology-anchor-friend-set-1-5/">Climbing Technology</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/lacd-lunatic-cam-gr-0-5-red/">LACD</a>. Similar in function are the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/camp-tricam-set-0-125-2/">CAMP Tricam</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/camp-ball-nuts-gr-1/">CAMP Ballnuts</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/kong-gipsy-klemmgeraet-set-4-6/">Kong Gipsy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12779310285/" title="DMM Dragon Cams by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7365/12779310285_04708acbe5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Dragon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.ukclimbing.com/gear/review.php?id=3213">Toby compares the DMM Dragons to BD Camalot C4s</a> and finds both are pretty awesome, <a href="http://www.gearinstitute.com/climbing/item/dmm-dragon-cams">Chris</a> rates them very high and <a href="http://blistergearreview.com/gear-reviews/dmm-dragon-cams">Dave</a> also is really liking them.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12779760424/" title="DMM Dragon Cams by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3719/12779760424_ba615946a0_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DMM Dragon Cams" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If you’ve read till here and want to build a Trad Rack™ my recommendation is to get a set of Dragon Cams to accompany your passive protection. But first go to your local Trad guru and quiz her/ him about which sizes you should get for your area, as it could be that you maybe will need only very narrow cams and hence better double up on the smaller sizes instead of a complete rack. I love the extendable Dyneema sling, a really smart idea that lets me carry less slings and QDs. I find placing them easy and as I fell on one I know that they’re safe to hold a fall. Also cleaning them up if you second is usually easy, and it’s seldom that one would need a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/dmm-nutbuster-keilentferner/">Nutbuster</a> to help with removing a strongly placed cam. Overall a beautifully made piece of gear that functions extremely well, and while not making you a better climber it will help you to feel safer on sketchy climbs.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157641529514203/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-dmm-dragon-cams">Where to buy the DMM Dragon Cams</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/dmm-dragon-cam-friend-00/">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/1cwLvxf">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/1nDDVAi">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Long-term usage updates &amp; photos</li>
</ul>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/12779316885_1cb963831e_b.jpg#tl-497818612300513282;1043138249" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DMM Wallnuts]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-20T22:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/02/dmm-wallnuts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“You’re nuts!”</em> Might be, but then <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional_climbing">Trad Climbing</a> requires a set of nuts (amongst other things, as you will see), as in this style of climbing you place the protection yourself, instead of relying on pre-installed bolts (as in sport climbing). <em>“Can such a nut hold a fall?</em> you might be wondering. I didn’t plan to try, but then things don’t always go according to plan.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7343/12653319555_1974bbe70d_b.jpg#tl-493035256320884738;1043138249" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I got my set of <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-wallnuts-klemmkeile/">DMM Wallnuts</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-offset-nuts-klemmkeile/">DMM Offset Nuts</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-torque-nuts-klemmkeile/">DMM Torque Nuts</a> in spring 2013, and had them out on several outings to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/on-the-rocks.html">local crag</a> and to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/climbing-at-havukallio.html">Havukallio</a>. I carried them along a couple of times to mixed climbs, but sticked to ice. All in all they have been on about seven outings.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9250664167/" title="A Rack of Nuts"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3694/9250664167_11334210a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="A Rack of Nuts" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>A Nut is a metal - usually aluminium - wedge threaded on a wire which you place in a crack on your climb. You then clip a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/express-sets/">Quickdraw</a> into the nut’s wire, and clip your rope through it. They’re know as passive protection, as there is no moving parts (well, you can move the steel wire a bit, as well as the Dyneema cord, but really, they’re passive) - as opposed to active protection like Cams, which have moving parts.</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/58429069?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Available in 11 sizes for the Wallnuts, five sizes for the Alloy Offsets and four sizes of the Torque Nuts, the first two sets are colour coded for easy recognition (it pays off to practice with them at the bottom of the crag and learn which colour fits which size of crack), and are compatibility with other brands, too. The Torque Nuts have a double dyneema sling which can be extended, while the larger nuts have holes in them to make them lighter. Take a look at these three videos, which explain them pretty well.</p>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/33283858?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=cc0033" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/48514100?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=cc0033" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//player.vimeo.com/video/40287948?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=cc0033" width="1200" height="675" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations--quality">Technical Innovations &amp; Quality</h2>

<p>All three sets are Made in Wales, and have undergone much trying and testing on the cliffs and crags of Snowdonia before ending up in our hands. The Wallnut shape has been enhanced by adding a scoop to improve security in shallow placements, which does work well, and the sizes generally match well, as you could see in the above video. Really smart ist the extendable Dyneema sling on the Torque Nuts: Keep it short at the base, extend it further up to reduce rope drag or when placing it deep in a crack. The quality is superb, as you know it will be from DMM.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12654150594/" title="Torque by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://s2.yimg.com/sk/3741/12654150594_d0216f216d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Torque" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>In the big picture, Nuts from Black Diamond, Wild Country, CAMP and DMM weigh pretty much the same. Some companies have a couple of larger or smaller sizes so a set will weigh more, but overall a modern standard rack will be the same weight.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Wallnuts:</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 11, 68g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 10, 57g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 9, 51g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 8, 46g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 7, 39g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 6, 37g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 5, 33g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 4, 29g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 3, 27g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 2, 25g</li>
  <li>DMM Nut 1, 16g</li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>TOTAL: 428 g</strong></p>
  </li>
  <li>Offset Nuts:</li>
  <li>DMM Offset Nut 11, 55g</li>
  <li>DMM Offset Nut 10, 45g</li>
  <li>DMM Offset Nut 9, 37g</li>
  <li>DMM Offset Nut 8, 29g</li>
  <li>DMM Offset Nut 7, 27g</li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>TOTAL: 193 g</strong></p>
  </li>
  <li>Torque Nuts:</li>
  <li>DMM Torque Nut 4, 144g</li>
  <li>DMM Torque Nut 3, 100g</li>
  <li>DMM Torque Nut 2, 72g</li>
  <li>DMM Torque Nut 1, 55g</li>
  <li><strong>TOTAL: 371 g</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>And the DMM Nutbuster is 54g. Which makes the whole passive protection part of the Trad Rack™ <strong>1.046 g</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>DMM manufactures their Nuts in Wales, which makes the transport to us in Europe short. Aluminium and steel, the main ingredients of the Nuts, can be easily recycled - just drop them at your scrap yard, and depending on the size of your rack you even might get enough money to go buy a pint in the pub. Of course Aluminium has a large electricity footprint, but the alternative would be to climb free solo. While DMM doesn’t lose a word about possible sustainability programs they adhere to, they have a page on their <a href="http://dmmclimbing.com/about/quality/">Quality management</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12653297895/" title="DMM Wallnuts"><img src="https://ycpi-farm6.staticflickr.com/5512/12653297895_1d94424453_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Wallnuts" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>After watching several videos on <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/rock-climbing-for-beginners.html">how to place nuts</a> I took my shiny new gear to the crag and started placing them, to get a feel for which colour fits into which width of a crack. The learning was pretty straight forward, so upwards I went. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12653798953/" title="Busting"><img src="https://v4s.yimg.com/so/7372/12653798953_fa271a8837_b.jpg" width="1024" height="455" alt="Busting" /></a></p>

<p>The placing of the nuts while being 15 m high was, thanks to having practiced it, fairly simple. Of course it’s slightly more challenging to place a piece of gear when you’re keeping yourself up with one hand, search with the other hand for the right size of nut, unclip it from the ‘biner, add a QD and then clip the rope. But it’s just a question of training a far as I am concerned. The colour-coding helped me well to find the nut I needed quickly - <em>“That crack looks like a red offset”</em>. </p>

<p>And then the opening question: Can a Nut take a fall? Yes, it can (if well placed). On the last climb of the weekend at Havukallio, some 2 meters from the top out I slipped about a meter above my last placement and took a fall of around three meters. The Nut and Cam held like a bomb, and while I was startled I was happy that my placements held. It helps to build up trust in your [placement] skills, and probably makes you a better climber. Although I rather wouldn’t have fallen, and just topped out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12653813324/" title="DMM Torque Nuts"><img src="https://ycpi-farm8.staticflickr.com/7406/12653813324_52cdbf0c72_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Torque Nuts" /></a></p>

<p>Even when I thought I placed a nut well, it has happened that one has moved out of the crack. This was more the case with the regular Wallnuts than with the Offsets, but could really have been just a case of “sloppy placement”. Or that the rope drag played the nut loose. This isn’t a big deal on relatively safe routes, but could be a serious safety concern on run-out routes. In that case either make damn well sure your placement is bomber, or use a piece of active protection.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>You can have a whole rack of Nuts from many different manufacturers. Black Diamond, Wild Country, CAMP, Climbing Technology and Metolius all make various kinds of Nuts. I chose DMM because they’re Made in Wales, are high-quality, and are very light. And the complete set is fairly affordable, too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12653305435/" title="DMM Alloy Offset Nuts"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3739/12653305435_2189bba15c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Alloy Offset Nuts" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.ukclimbing.com/gear/review.php?id=1066">UK Climbing</a> rates the Alloy Offsets as good (probably very good now that they’re “fixed”). The DMM Wallnuts received 4.68 out of 5 Stars at <a href="http://www.rockclimbing.com/gear/Essential_Equipment/Protection/Passive/Nuts_and_Stoppers/Wallnuts_5416.html">rockclimbing.com</a> and also the <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Climbing-Nut-Reviews/DMM-Wallnut">Outdoor Gear Lab</a> rates them very high.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If you’re planning to start Trad Climbing this year, you can not go wrong with set of DMM Wallnuts, Offset Nuts and Torque Nuts. While the latter is here in Finland not that often needed, a basic set of Nuts is THE key ingredient to your <em>Trad Rack™</em>. Getting the DMM Wallnuts and Offset Nuts gives you all the passive protection you’ll need to start practicing traditional climbing and lets you find out what you should get next. The DMM Nuts are high quality, lightweight, Made in Wales, and look pretty damn sweet. Though that’s only while they’re new, so go climbing &amp; get them scratched up!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157641258035604/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-dmm-nuts">Where to buy the DMM Nuts</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/dmm/klemmkeile/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/1dQp6te">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/NdlOpC">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Long-term usage updates &amp; photos</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9189664731/" title="How To Build A Trad Rack™"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3772/9189664731_fe85a07cab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="How To Build A Trad Rack™" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
