<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Finland | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/finland/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-28T22:07:35+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pirkan Taival Travel Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/pirkan-taival-travel-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-17T10:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/pirkan-taival-travel-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Where to go backpacking this year?</em>, it’s the same question each spring. I have for five years being advocating hiking in Finland, and since last year you can now take my <a href="http://www.conrad-stein-verlag.de/p/verlag/show_book.html?isbn=978-3-86686-319-4&amp;edition=1&amp;t=1395048047963">Pirkan Taival Hiking Guide</a> along on your trip on this wonderful trail in the heart of Finland. Reason enough to introduce you to the book and encourage you to come backpacking on the Pirkan Taival!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9537611324/" title="Dusk by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7312/9537611324_1787dd85ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dusk" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Writing a book, even a little one like my Pirkan Taival Travel Guide, is a lot of work. First there’s the hiking and collecting data: 300 km of trails were hiked several times, XC skiing trails were explored in the winter, and I went off-trail over frozen lakes with snowshoes and through blooming forests to find the best spots and areas to showcase in the book. After all that outdoors time it’s time to distill it all into a smart format, organize maps, work with the local authorities, find photos from my extensive library, and then put it into a logical whole. </p>

<p>However, I was lucky that I didn’t need to take care of the layout, printing, and drawing maps - that’s what the fabulous team from the <a href="http://www.conrad-stein-verlag.de/p/verlag/verlag_home.html">Conrad Stein Verlag</a> took care off, who is my Publisher. They got the book looking really great and into the book stores across Germany, Austria and Switzerland, from <a href="http://www.freytagberndt.at/rtc-freytagberndt/805">Freytag &amp; Berndt</a> to the <a href="http://geobuchhandlung.eshop.t-online.de/epages/Store3_Shop37170.sf/de_DE/?ObjectID=15498754">Geobuchhandlung Kiel</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/conrad-stein-finnland-pirkan-taival/">Bergzeit</a> - walk into any of the thousands of book stores in Germany and you can either pick up the book right away or get it the next day.</p>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/Y9r5yz" title="Finnland: Pirkan Taival book by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5514/9156957955_7af63cca08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Finnland: Pirkan Taival book" /></a></p>

<p>For me it was a great pleasure to go hiking on the Pirkan Taival and write about it: I often was accompanied by good friends and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/guided-trips/">clients</a> on the trail with whom I could share my love of the outdoors. I saw the trail in each season - in early spring I was hiking through knee-deep snow, on dark and rainy autumns I listend to the rain on my tarp, during sunny summer nights the call of Swans was echoing over the lakes and sitting besides a warm fire in winter. With the book you’re able to plan and hike the Pirkan Taival yourself in any season, and see all those beautiful places along the trail. It’s easy to reach by public transportation, and you can be within half a working day from your door step to the start of the trail in Finland, which makes it excellent for even just a long weekend hike if you need a Nordic outdoor-fix.</p>

<p>But don’t just believe me: Hear <a href="http://outdoorseite.de/trekking-in-finnland-mit-hendrik-durch-den-pirkan-taival/">what Axel has to say about my book</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.de/product-reviews/3866863195/ref=dp_top_cm_cr_acr_txt?ie=UTF8&amp;showViewpoints=1">read the reviews</a>, then <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/touren/pirkan-taival-erholung-pur-im-suden-finnlands">read my trekking Magazin article</a> and browse my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/destinations/">trip reports</a>. </p>

<p><strong>Then</strong> you can go and get the book from your local book shop in Austria, Switzerland and Germany, online from <a href="http://www.freytagberndt.at/rtc-freytagberndt/805">Freytag &amp; Berndt</a>, <a href="http://geobuchhandlung.eshop.t-online.de/epages/Store3_Shop37170.sf/de_DE/?ObjectID=15498754">Geobuchhandlung Kiel</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/conrad-stein-finnland-pirkan-taival/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/Y9r5yz">Amazon.de</a> or directly from the <a href="http://www.conrad-stein-verlag.de/p/verlag/show_book.html?isbn=978-3-86686-319-4&amp;edition=1&amp;t=1395048047963">Conrad Stein Verlag</a>. </p>

<p><em>The book is in German! I might write an English or Finnish version in the future =)</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8147054635/" title="Tampere"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8468/8147054635_b8c6085a5f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tampere" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Koli National Park | Ultralight Summit 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/01/koli-national-park.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-14T18:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/01/koli-national-park</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m not a big fan of November backpacking. Though somehow that hasn’t hindered me in the last years to plan week-long backpacking trips in what I find the worst time of the year. And to top things off, I always manage to convince other people to join me on the trips. These time my companions came from as far away as Japan and the United States of America, to experience what Finland (<em>does not</em>) have to offer in November. <em>An Ultralight Summit trip report.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943410053/" title="UL Summit 2013 View?"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2842/11943410053_ca62a790f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 View?" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We had big plans for the Ultralight Summit last year. That we’d be hiking in November in Finland wasn’t part of it, but if you manage to </p>

<ul>
  <li>Keep busy</li>
  <li>Still want to meet with your friends</li>
  <li>Need to write a story about <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/koli/Pages/Default.aspx">Koli</a></li>
  <li>Said friends want to go hiking in Finland</li>
</ul>

<p>Well, you catch my drift. Benjamin, Jotaro, Takashi and Hideyuki arrived in early November in Helsinki, and on a Monday morning at 7:12 o’clock we sat in a train to Joensuu. Four and half hours in a train with free Wifi, electric outlets and a decent Board Restaurant can still be long, and it was nice to stretch the legs shortly in Joensuu before getting a ride from a good friend to Koli. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943558004/" title="UL Summit 2013 Koli Visitor Centre"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7335/11943558004_7205d851ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Visitor Centre" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943394843/" title="UL Summit 2013 Ukko-Koli view by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5538/11943394843_395f411f1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Ukko-Koli view" /></a></p>

<p>And then we are there. Nearly at the top of this 400 something metre high hill, there’s a sweet looking hotel (although in cold wind probably any hotel looks sweet &amp; inviting) and a visitor centre - which, with our luck, was closed. Good timing, there. We tried to reach Takashi and Hideyuki who traveled here already a few days earlier, but as we couldn’t reach them we set off towards Ukko-Koli, Akka-Koli and Paha-Koli, the three peaks from where one has very nice views over the lake towards <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/from-russia-with-love.html">Russia</a>. It’s as we stand on the third peak that I get a message from Takashi - they’re at the hotel now, where shall we meet? Ten minutes later - Takashi and Hideyuki ran <a href="http://www.theomm.com/events/">The OMM</a> in Wales before they came to Finland - we meet, and agree to get together at the first camp spot later. </p>

<p>While Ben, Jotaro and me set off, the weather is changing from cloudy and windy to cloudy, windy and drizzly with increasing Darkness™. We descent from the Koli peaks, past pastures of old, over soft grass fields, along a bit of road until we ascent and head for the Kota at Ryläys. It’s pitch black and snowing as we hike via duckboards over a hanging bog towards the Kota, and are quite relieved as we see the humble abode for the night.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943963106/" title="UL Summit 2013 Joulu Olut"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5495/11943963106_7b2fd9c207_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Joulu Olut" /></a></p>

<p>We saw and chop wood and the fire is just going as Hideyuki &amp; Takashi arrive. We welcome them to our massive shelter for the night, put on a couple more logs, and I finally can get the heavy load I carried till here out: To celebrate this first night I brought a <a href="http://www.olvi.fi/web/fi/68">Olvi Joulu Olut</a> for everyone along - well over 1,6 kg! I reckon this makes the first night sort of a <a href="http://www.backpackingnorth.com/2013/07/brovernighter-with-korpijaakko.html">Brovernighter™</a>. Anyway. Fire. Shelter. Snow. <a href="http://locusgear.com/products-2/bivys/pneuma-bivy-event?lang=en">A new bivy</a>. After eating well I decide to take the new bivy outside into the snow and sleep there - it’s the perfect, safe opportunity to do so. I slide into the red bivy, snow falling strongly around me, zip it almost closed, change socks, and fall asleep. Three hours later I wake up, and decide that it was enough - the top of my <a href="http://bit.ly/18Wo3Sr">sleeping bag</a> was a bit moist, and I rather have a completely dry sleeping bag, so I pack the whole shebang up, sneak inside, put another log on the fire so I see something, and fall asleep next to my fellow lightweight backpacking friends.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943566324/" title="UL Summit 2013 Kota"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2816/11943566324_02f2cf419c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Kota" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943133225/" title="UL Summit 2013 Warm &amp; comfy"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2875/11943133225_52edba0b99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Warm &amp; comfy" /></a></p>

<p>The next morning we’re in winter wonderland. Everything is white - the trail, the kota, the trees, the ground. We smile. Light the fire. Eat breakfast. Enjoy the silence of the snow, the mist in the tree tops, we wander around the cozy Kota with its warm fire inside. But even the cosiest Kotas can not hold back eager backpackers, and so a while later five hikers emerge from the wooden structure, around them the snow melting &amp; dripping from trees. The thermometer has slipped just a degree or two above Zero, enough to make the snow starting to melt and dribble on us. </p>

<p>We ascent the hill we’re on, upwards to the look-out tower with the broken ladder. It’s so misty that we wouldn’t have seen further than 50 m from up there either way, and so we walk a bit further, have a group photo at the “Waterfall of Rocks” (hidden in the mist) and continue. The trail winds along the top of a ridge, goes a bit down into the forests where we cross fast flowing small streams by jumping from tree roots to tree roots, and then ascents again a few dozen meters, back to hard, wet granite under our trail runners. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943394503/" title="UL Summit 2013 Reflections"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5475/11943394503_24d07604b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Reflections" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943117845/" title="UL Summit 2013 Early winter"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3798/11943117845_e8977fa4e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Early winter" /></a></p>

<p>Then comes the moment that Hideyuki &amp; Takashi need to turn back. As they came before us, they will leave us already today. I show them on the map that it might be faster to come with us another few kilometres to one of the forest roads, which should be quicker to hike back to the Visitor Centre. But the two, quite rightly in hindsight, decide to hike the same way back we just came. They just finished The OMM, so this certainly isn’t a problem for them. As we say our good byes, it always feels a bit sad to say bye to people whose company you enjoy, but that’s life. We’ll hike again together this year.</p>

<p>Ben, Jotaro and me carry on, the mist and dripping snow our constant companion while we walk high. As we descend, the snow is largely gone, we can see further, and the trail gets wider. We hike for a while on a forest road, but also here we encounter no one. It’s far past noon as the three of us arrive at a laavu - or the ashen remains of it, all that is left standing a oven in front of the burnt down structure. The wind is blowing strongly from the lake and the fire doesn’t really want to bring our pots with water to a boil, even more wood and a windshield do little to improve the situation. After what seems like forever warm drinks &amp; soups are hungrily consumed, jokes are made, pots cleaned, the fire is put out, and we walk back to the adventure centre. </p>

<p>That’s the desolated adventure centre. A wet hammock swings in the wind, the camping ground - pitching your tent here costs 10€ - is flooded, and the small cabins are all locked. We walk down to the strait, where a rope between two pulleys, connected to a raft, is drifting in the middle of it. We pull the raft to our side of the strait, board it, and while I take action photos of the crossing Jotaro and Ben bring us safely to the other side. There we stand, laughing about this interesting way to cross a water body, take a few more photos, and then head onwards. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943959786/" title="UL Summit 2013 Pull!"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7333/11943959786_e793dccfd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Pull!" /></a></p>

<p>The path on the island goes very closely along the shore, and often is either flooded, muddy, or both. At a fire place in the centre of the isle we look north from the shore, seeing the mountains we stood on the day before, grey clouds and mist hanging not far above their summits. Water drops from leaf-less twigs paint circles as they hit the lake. We snap photos, have a kuksa of lake water, and continue. The other strait is crossed via a lovely wooden bridge, and we walk along signs telling us that we should stay on the trail. Obvious the summer cottage owners right next to the path have had their fair share of hikers pick their berries.</p>

<p>We hike on as dusk is setting in. It quickly gets dark in the forest, and every time we cross a glade it gets lighter again, the eyes try to adjust, but we’re so quickly in the dark of the trees again, they don’t have time. As we reach the final clearing at Lakkala, it is the camping place we will stay at this night. An old crofters lodge, with various stables, fields and little laavus for the sheep who graze here in the summer is where we will pitch our pyramids this night. Once we found dry spots, that is.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943576414/" title="UL Summit 2013 Birch? by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3767/11943576414_1719dff5fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="341" alt="UL Summit 2013 Birch?" /></a></p>

<p>The field which is designated as a camping place for pitching tarps and tents is ABOUT 75% flooded. Nevertheless, Ben, Jotaro and me find each a spot where our pyramids go up, with enough dry space to unroll our sleeping pads, bivies and quilts. Then the task of making a fire begins. I carried a first load of split logs to the flooded fire circle, and start the task of making feather sticks and building the fire, while Ben &amp; Jotaro carry each a couple of arms full of wood to me. In this rain &amp; wind, we’ll need fuel. Armed with two hands of dry birch bark and half a dozen of feather sticks the fire is roaring in no time. We keep it going strong, the wind blowing in gusts from the lake while the rain keeps falling at a steady pace. Dressed in eVent and Gore-Tex we sit around the fire, split logs as little footstools to keep our soaked trailrunners out of the puddles around the fire. </p>

<p>Despite the miserable weather we sit there, eat, drink and laugh. We put more logs on the fire, trying to find the optimal spot for out titanium pots to boil one more cup of water, and then at 19 o’clock head each to our shelters. In the glow of my headlamp I read a couple more chapters of Terry Pratchett’s latest novel, before I switch the Nao off and lay down. The wind howls over our little shelters, and pulls at the cuben and dyneema cords. But everything holds, and in the next morning I awake as I hear Jotaro’s camera shutter opens and closes. It’s still dark, it’s still wet, and there’s still wind going. Eventually I slip out of my warm down cocoon, into wet socks and shoes which are quickly warmed up by running a few hundred meters on the trails. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943405823/" title="UL Summit 2013 Lakkala Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3672/11943405823_65a06d3b20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="UL Summit 2013 Lakkala Camp" /></a></p>

<p>A fire is started again in the middle of that puddle while grey clouds race over the sky, giving glimpses of blue. We’re so absorbed with looking at the fire and eating that we are surprised as the sun sends a few rays through the forest in our back. We pack up what is dry, though our shelters are not in that category. We’ll return via another ridge to Ukko-Koli today and a campground close to the town, and as we shoulder the packs, now wonderfully light as less and less food is carried, the sun illuminates the hills on the opposite shore. </p>

<p>The trail is nice today, it changes between hard granite and softly-cushioned pine needles with a few duck boards in between. We get glimpses from the top to the surrounding lakes, forests and hills, but are blasted by a relentlessly cold wind and I’m happy to wear a fleece under my softshell. It doesn’t take us long to come to a crossroad, where we stash the packs behind a tree and hike the kilometre and a bit to the Devil’s Church, a 33 m deep cave in a Z form. Without packs the pace is fast as we hike steadily down. We cross a wide forest road and descent wooden stairs to the cave, and climb in. It is moist, green moss grows on the walls. We spend a little time in there before we head back, all the way up to our rucksacks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943134585/" title="UL Summit 2013 Green"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5537/11943134585_1138e4fd01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Green" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943124865/" title="UL Summit 2013 Inside the Devil's Church"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7384/11943124865_8a0a215fd0_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="UL Summit 2013 Inside the Devil's Church" /></a></p>

<p>On the next stretch it feels like we spook up Western Capercaillies with every third step. These large birds of the grouse family are in such abundance here that thoughts of a Capercaillie hunt cross my mind. But without a bow &amp; arrows, this idea stay in the realm of fantasy, while the realities are boiling water for soups-in-a-cup with bread and snacks. After our last lunch on the trip, at a fire pit which offered so wet wood that we were well smoked afterwards, we continue for a bit on a forest road. As we come to a junction, where the trail takes a turn into the forest and heads uphill, Jotaro &amp; Ben tell me they’d prefer to continue on the road to the campground. It’s easy enough, so I leave the two and head up the ridge to Mäkrä hill. </p>

<p>I run parts of the trail, happy to go at my own speed, and also in a hurry because the Golden Hour is about to begin any moment now, and I’d rather see it from the top than from the middle. My speed pays off, and I see how the sun sends its last rays towards Russia, while it sinks down behind Sweden, Norway and the lands beyond. The forest opposite of the lake is illuminated by the light, a pulsating movement as clouds whisk by the sun, that descends further and further. I walk along the ridge, more Western Capercaillies taking flight as I approach, and as the western horizons is adorned with an orange band, I take a last look East, then West, and descend. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943389463/" title="UL Summit 2013 Golden Hour view towards Russia"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5538/11943389463_1a71e8fe90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Golden Hour view towards Russia" /></a></p>

<p>I emerge out of the forest at the Mäkränaho clearing, and choose the wide trail back towards the Visitor Centre. Along the trail I pull the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/petzl-nao-headlamp/">Petzl Nao</a> once again out of my <a href="http://www.zpacks.com/accessories/backpack_lid.shtml">ZPacks Multipack</a> as darkness engulfs me. It does not take long for me to reach the Parking Lot of the Visitor Centre, and I run the stairs up to the Hotel &amp; Visitor Centre, where the trail to Turula continues. Again I hike down a wide, well-maintained trail and as I arrive at the campsite Ben &amp; Jotaro have already pitched their shelters. </p>

<p>We gather wood once more from the close by wood-shed, fully-loaded with split logs and generous amounts of birch bark, and soon sit again, with our wet shoes propped up on a log close by the fire, around it. Water we get from a nearby well at a farm-house, but only on the second try we locate the right well - the first one we filled our Platypus bottles up from had E.coli bacteria, as the owner of the house informed us. We sit long around the fire, and are a bit startled as a trailrunner runs past us and our shelters, the beam of his headlamp jumping along the field and roads until it disappears. Before heading to sleep I give my <a href="http://bit.ly/1bcnz0i">NeoAir XLite Sleeping Pad</a> a few additional puffs, before I slip into the <a href="http://bit.ly/18Wo3Sr">Therm-A-Rest Antares sleeping bag</a>. The wind gives a few kind tugs at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">UltaMid</a>, and a few raindrops hit the cuben, though overall it is a silent night. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943409303/" title="UL Summit 2013 Ben tending his fire"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3782/11943409303_4663af0f36_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="UL Summit 2013 Ben tending his fire" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943122365/" title="UL Summit 2013 Delicious breakfast"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7386/11943122365_156f2899fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="UL Summit 2013 Delicious breakfast" /></a></p>

<p>The next morning Ben and Jotaro are well up before me, and I lay long in my sleeping bag. The sound of fire, which Ben started, finally rouses me and I join the two outside. Starbucks Via and a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/trek-n-eat-muesli-schweizer-art-mit-vollmilch/">Trek’n Eat Swiss Müsli</a> are for breakfast, and especially the latter is superb. I’ve tried many ready-made trekking müslis, and non were good which is why I usually made my own, but this one was so tasty that it’s a serious alternative to MYOM-üsli. </p>

<p>Sleep systems and gear are again packed, shelters shaken to make them a bit less wet, and we set oFf towards the Koli Village. I arranged for a Taxi to pick us up there at 11, but the two kilometres from the campsite to the village, along old Farm buildings on what is in winter a skiing track, does not take us long. We have so much time till the Taxi comes that we sit down in the Café and order salty crepes and coffee, skim through Finland’s worst outdoor magazine, and enjoy being indoors in the warmth after all the snow, rain &amp; wind outside.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943400053/" title="UL Summit 2013 Stream by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3794/11943400053_2af4f9524e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Stream" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943111545/" title="UL Summit 2013 Last bit by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3831/11943111545_7e62193630_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 Last bit" /></a></p>

<p>Back in Joensuu, civilisation has us back. We visit a lunch place and supermarkets, have coffees and wait till the train takes us back to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html">Helsinki</a>, where Ben &amp; me will meet <a href="http://www.valppaus.com/">Joni</a> for an overnighter in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/run-or-die-nuuksio-classic-trail-marathon.html">Nuuksio</a>. <em>But that might be another story.</em></p>

<p>More photos on <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157637917534175/">Flickr</a>. The UL Summit 2014 will be in Nippon. Watch this space and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> if you’d like to join.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11943571914/" title="UL Summit 2013 The Crew"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7412/11943571914_2af055e3e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Summit 2013 The Crew" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Urho Kekkonen National Park]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T15:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>One National Park</li>
  <li>Two brothers</li>
  <li>Three Lenses</li>
  <li>Four Feet</li>
  <li>Five Nights</li>
  <li>Six Days</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html" title="Fire"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2889/9763148185_31286687eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The travel up north started in Tampere, the rainy city which welcomed us with sunshine. A good omen? Possibly. Re-packing, dinner, beer, and off to the night train. A cabin was paid for, 30€ extra well spent as it meant we arrived rested in Rovaniemi. Also here: Sunshine. A stroll to the waiting bus, backpacks down into the luggage compartment, and off we went. We turn right past the glass igloos and arrive four hours later at Kilopää Station, a packed parking lot letting us wonder how many people we would meet this week. But once we passed the bus-loads of pensioners on their way up to the Kilopää summit and back down, people got fewer. And once we left the marked trail behind, they disappeared.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763646456/" title="Wideangle"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5462/9763646456_3764c0da5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wideangle" /></a></p>

<p>At the Rautulampi hut we drink tea. We meet a few people, but it being so early we decide to push on. A short bit on trail, before we leave it behind again. After the yellow birches: Wide views. We arrive at the hut, and decide to stay in it. Water is boiled, food eaten, drinks drunk, fire made. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763854414/" title="Navigation in autumn can be colourful"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/9763854414_9995bc480b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Navigation in autumn can be colourful" /></a></p>

<p>We leave under a grey sky the next morning, but the sun comes through once in a while. The trail disappears at times, but we arrive at the first bridge after a couple of hours, lunch, tea, and off into the wild again. Traversing a mountain till we reach the other “bridge”. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763631271/" title="Bridge"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3809/9763631271_9270fc0f99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bridge" /></a></p>

<p>Easier trails follow. Even the sun comes through more often. Up another hill, and more wide views.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763850285/" title="Sun &amp; Clouds"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7335/9763850285_bbb51e324f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sun &amp; Clouds" /></a></p>

<p>Another night in a hut. The morning brings rain, and a German-Finnish doctor on his way back to civilization. We chat for a long time, waiting for the rain to stop. With hardshells on, we leave, but soon enough the sun comes through and we switch back to windjackets.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763991044/" title="That way"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2809/9763991044_e50a703e0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="That way" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763769821/" title="Moody I"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3708/9763769821_ed2d1baeab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Moody I" /></a></p>

<p>Paradise Gorge is beautiful indeed, and a nice scramble up. I pitch the TrailStar for a tea break, before we head to the second highest summit. A rainbow hangs in the sky to the left as we descend to the Devil’s Gorge, and on the way to the break hut a short rain shower sees us putting the hardshells on again.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764143326/" title="Up Paradise Gorge"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3770/9764143326_5c798e849b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Up Paradise Gorge" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764147934/" title="Paradise Gorge"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7348/9764147934_fe3a0854f1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Paradise Gorge" /></a></p>

<p>As we arrive at Muorravaarakka hut the sun shines down from a blue sky again. A Dutch family tells us that we <em>just missed the rain</em> and then set off to Anterinmukka hut. We pack the hardshells away for the 2nd time today, eat, refill our bottles and then set off again. Twenty-five minutes later we catch up with the family, who have a coffee break at the top of the hill, enjoying the view. “See you at the hut. We’ll keep the Sauna warm for you!” we tell them.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764301996/" title="Devil's Gorge"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2828/9764301996_cbb1cfb5a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Devil's Gorge" /></a></p>

<p>The sauna is still warm, so we pitch the shelters, grab the whiskey, kuksas and towels and head in. The river water is cold, refreshing. As we go back up, the Dutch family has just arrived, and they happily head to the warm sauna.</p>

<p>We sleep under Silnylon and Cuben, cocooned into our warm quilts and sleeping bags. The next morning brings a grey sky yet again, but it looks like it will stay dry and get sunny. Coffee and müsli is our fuel, we pack and leave on a Quad trail onwards, following the river up in which we swam last night.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764208401/" title="Fireplace"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7316/9764208401_fe3dd21a8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fireplace" /></a></p>

<p>At a lone fireplace we again leave the trail behind, following another river until we reach its origin, where it splits: One part goes east, the other west. We head north, across extensive boulder fields, through a lost valley of Eden, and up even more boulder fields. Sokosti, Eastern Finland’s highest summit, is our goal, but it’s ugly: A radio tower, two support huts and an array of solar panels crown it, but no rest place for hikers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769576353/" title="Towards Sokosti"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7429/9769576353_1cdd00a4b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Towards Sokosti" /></a></p>

<p>The descent is an exercise in finding the path. We give up, make our own, and before we reach the tree line sit down for the last tortilla and cheese lunch. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764088782/" title="There's the Sauna?"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2836/9764088782_aa74826384_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="There's the Sauna?" /></a></p>

<p>At Luirojärvi another Sauna waits, and images worth of postcards. We enjoy the warmth of the sauna, the coldness of the lake, before we head on to pitch the TrailStar, make a fire, boil the chantarelles I found earlier in the morning, and enjoy this fine, starry evening.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769497594/" title="Mirror Image II"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3665/9769497594_ee42f5826b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mirror Image II" /></a></p>

<p>The morning brings fog and sunshine. It’s a spectacle worth seeing every time, and under a blue bird sky we pack and start the longest stretch of the journey. Hills covered in red, orange and yellow, wide moors and Rock Ptarmigans accompany us. It is so warm, we hike in T-Shirts, and I enjoy the opportunities to wade through cold rivers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769573263/" title="Mirror image by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5447/9769573263_d2796379b3_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Mirror image" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769608944/" title="Autumn trail"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/9769608944_765f986ac6_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Autumn trail" /></a></p>

<p>Kilometers fly by, and we encounter more and more people heading in the opposite direction. Heavy-loaded external frame backpacks are still the norm, as are complaints by their bearers about aching knees and blisters. We load up on water, leave the gathering at the laavu behind and head up.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769707276/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7412/9769707276_aeb0f94db0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid" /></a></p>

<p>The sun sets, but the blood red sky at the horizon lingers on for what seems like forever, until darkness from the east consumes it and shrouds the sky into its black cloak with blinking white stars. No Northern Lights, though, no matter how long I sit outside watching the sky.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769778313/" title="X"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3748/9769778313_e05e51f5af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="X" /></a></p>

<p>Mist is moving across distant mountain tops in the morning, while the sun tries hard to break through the clouds. As it finally does, we start to walk. By the time we reach the Station at Kilopää we already have encountered more than two dozen hikers and backpackers. Yes, the wilderness definitely lays now behind us, and civilization has us back again.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769750802/" title="Grey, yellow, blue"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7328/9769750802_cbfe175257_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Grey, yellow, blue" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157635543361552/">More photos</a>. Read more about it in the upcoming issue of <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/">trekking Magazin</a>.</p>

<h3 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h3>

<p>Flying is the fastest and often also the cheapest choice. There’s connections from Helsinki to Ivalo, and from Ivalo airport you take the bus south to Saariselkä, Kilopää or Koilliskaira.</p>

<p>More environmentally friendly and a lot more time consuming is the train + bus combo. Head on the night train to Rovaniemi, get a cabin, sleep, then hop in the morning on the bus to Saariselkä, Kilopää or Koilliskaira to start your adventure.</p>

<p>Saariselkä has an <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/saariselka">Partioaitta</a> outdoor shop where you can get gas canisters and gear. The village also has a few supermarkets which will let you shop for food. If you have spare time in Rovaniemi, head to the <a href="http://www.prisma.fi/market/prisma?a_Visit:rajaa=1&amp;osuuskauppa=ARINA&amp;pageName=Main&amp;b_haku.paikka=Rovaniemi">Prisma</a> there for a very wide variety of outdoor gear and food at more reasonable prices.</p>

<p>The National Park is divided into four zones with different regulations in terms of wild camping. Outside of the Basic Zone trails are not marked, and you should know how a compass works, best in conjunction with a map. Speaking off, the Koilliskairan ulkoilukartta map is the best map if you want to explore the wild side of the National Park. Sadly it’s just a crappy paper map and will fall apart after a week of use.</p>

<p>There’s six Saunas in the National Park, plenty of huts, both free (<em>Autiotupa</em>) and reservable (<em>Varaustupa</em>), as well as two dozen laavus and several turf huts. The price of a reservable hut is 10 euro/ night/ bed and all beds will be sold if there’s demand. Daytrip huts are not for overnight stays, and if you go to the dry toilet throw some of the wood stuff from the box over your business. You can drink water everywhere, though if you have a sensitive stomach boil it first.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/urhokekkonennationalpark/Pages/Default.aspx">Urho Kekkonen</a> NP page with more Information.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.retkikartta.fi/index.php?lang=en&amp;id=868">Digital map</a> for planning.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.vr.fi/en/index.html">Train schedules</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="www.matkahuolto.info/lippu/fi/connectionsearch">Bus schedules</a>.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.backpackingnorth.com/p/gear-rental.html">Packraft rental</a> at Backpacking North.</li>
</ul>

<p>Don’t want to go on your own? Keep an eye on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/guided-trips/">Guided Trips</a> as there will be winter and packrafting tours in UKK in 2014.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southern Finland Bouldering Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/07/southern-finland-bouldering-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-02T10:07:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/07/southern-finland-bouldering-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Finland not only has superb hiking, backpacking and paddling to offer, thanks to the ice age, which stopped here 10.000 years ago, the country also has plenty of superb boulders for climbing - many of them in Southern Finland. If you visit Helsinki for business or pleasure, make sure to take along your climbing shoes and a copy of the Southern Finland Bouldering Guide to check out the local rocks!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9127157903/" title="Southern Finland Bouldering Guide by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3718/9127157903_1e45a24e1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Southern Finland Bouldering Guide" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The Southern Finland Bouldering Guide came out earlier this year, and is a completely self-published book. As I know how much work goes into making a book, it is great to see that the three authors have produced such a high-quality book which certainly will set standards for bouldering guides in Finland. Alone that it is bilingual - Finnish and English - is a superb accomplishment which needs to be applauded! <a href="http://media.boulderkeskus.com/media/pdf/bouldertopo_demo.pdf">Take a look in the book here</a> and see for yourself how well made it is!</p>

<p>The book starts off with a brief introduction, followed by the Everymen’s Right and a <em>How to use this book</em> page and an explanation of the icons et al. If you’re new to bouldering outdoors, a <em>Falling for dummies</em> page tells you about spotting. After that it already jumps in and gives you a bit more background on bouldering in Helsinki and the area within Kehä III. There’s some fantastic spots here, with problems ranging from 4s to 8B+ - so really something for any skill level.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9129396210/” title=”Southern Finland Bouldering Guide</td>
      <td>Overview by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5448/9129396210_e67c847fc5_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”680” alt=”Southern Finland Bouldering Guide</td>
      <td>Overview”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Sectors start with a short overview, telling about the location and how to get there. At least in Helsinki you can get to most spots via public transportation, which is great news for those who visit the city on holidays. A good map helps you find the boulders then, and often also includes bus stops and other information which are useful. </p>

<p>Then the book jumps in and shows the different boulders, with the problems as lines on them - just like you might know it from <a href="http://27crags.com/">27crags.com</a> - which, btw, the books recommends for updated and new problems, too. The photos are good, though some really stand out as superb and get you very excited about the rocks. There’s no or little beta, so you can Flash the problems, too!</p>

<p>Besides Helsinki and the Metropolitan area you will also find chapters on Hämeenlinna, “the Rest of Southern Finland” and Åland, which is widely considered one of the most beautiful and best boulder destinations. Looking at the photos and problems of the latter, I definitely see why!</p>

<p><strong>Bottomline:</strong> An excellent bouldering guide, jam-packed with exciting problems to add to you tick list. If you’re only faintly interested in bouldering in Finland, get this book. It will help you plan your boulder holidays in Finland, or lets you find problems in your neck of the city for a little evening entertainment. Whenever I head south, this book, my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/scarpa-feroce-climbing-shoe-parrot.html">climbing shoes</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-c40-chalkbag-bf/">chalk bag</a> and possibly my <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/paddy-dominator-496254.html">crashpad</a> come along, so that I can combine business &amp; pleasure!</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9129352350/” title=”Southern Finland Bouldering Guide</td>
      <td>Problems by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2881/9129352350_0b07ed6be6_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”680” alt=”Southern Finland Bouldering Guide</td>
      <td>Problems”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Got curious? Hop on a ferry or plane to Helsinki and start bouldering! You can buy or order the book at <a href="http://camu.fi/shop/kiipeily/kalliokiipeily/lehdet_ja_videot/etelasuomenbouldertopo.html">Camu</a>, <a href="http://shop.boulderkeskus.com/fi/kauppa/kirjallisuus/etelasuomenbouldertopo.html">Boulderkeskus</a>, <a href="http://www.mountainshop.fi/kauppa/product_info.php?products_id=1087">Mountain Shop</a> and <a href="http://www.kletterfuehrer.net/product_info.php?language=en&amp;info=p989_Southern-Finland-Bouldering-Guide.html">Kletterführer</a>. Don’t forget your <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/crashpads/">crashpad</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ice Climbing in Korouoma]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T10:41:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Korouoma has been for a long time on my list of places to visit. A long canyon with up to 100 m high cliffs, Golden Eagles soaring above in the sky, and a good dozen of icefalls to climb make this the best ice climbing destination in Finland.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595259601/" title="Boulders by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8241/8595259601_a2a1080513_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Boulders" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>My fast &amp; light trip to Korouoma started Friday afternoon as Heini, Mikko and their dog Alli picked me up in Vaasa, before us an eight hour drive to the north. After a late dinner at one of the countless ABC Stations along the road I dozed off on the backseat, awakening once in a while as we drove on empty roads further towards <a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Home">Posio</a> and <a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Places-to-visit/Nature-destinations/Korouoma-Nature-Reserve#.UVK1k1tQhGQ">Korouoma</a>. It was past midnight as we arrived on the parking place, and in the light of our headlamps and the moon we gathered our gear to start the descent towards the canyon. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587936563/" title="All packed up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8365/8587936563_6ac57e172b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="All packed up" /></a></p>

<p>It’s very late as we arrive down at the Kota which the rest of the group is already sleeping in, and Heini and Mikko head inside while I sleep outside. It’s so late, the weather is clear, so I just roll out my pads and the new Tyvek quilt cover I have on test and slip in my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/01/katabatic-gear-sawatch-quilt.html">Katabatic Gear Sawatch</a> while the moon shines over the valley. My watch says it’s -15°C but inside my quilt and down hoody I am warm and soon fall asleep.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8589038686/" title="First night bivy by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8513/8589038686_3efd441cb9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="First night bivy" /></a></p>

<p>I wake up as at sun rises close to 6 o’clock, though as no one else is yet up I turn around and sleep a bit more. By seven o’clock the sun shines on my bivy spot and so I get up, a hot coffee - a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos bottle</a> is a must on these trips - and I’m off exploring the surroundings, waiting for my climbing friends to wake up. No Alpine Start, it seems. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587935987/" title="Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8229/8587935987_4e7d8db06c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Camp" /></a></p>

<p>To be productive I pitch my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review.html">Khufu</a> eVent II and sort all my climbing gear for the day ahead, and a bit past eight Mikko and Heini appear outside with Alli. We have breakfast together, and finally around ten o’clock Mikko and me set off to the icefalls. We pass Ruskeavirta, the longest and steepest icefall, but which we won’t climb yet. We walk onwards to the Mammutti icefall, a smaller and slightly easier climb for the start of the day. A group of people is already at the fall, and they have their first walking with crampons &amp; iceclimbing lessons while Mikko and me look for a route.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596493414/" title="Mikko by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8529/8596493414_81e25043d1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mikko" /></a></p>

<p>After we found a good line which suits us both, and offers a good belay &amp; rappel possibility, Mikko is leading while I belay him. The wind is cold but the sky is clear, and behind us the sun is throwing long shadows across the canyon. As the majority of the climbs are on north-facing walls, we get no sun, though - it’s in the shadows where we climb.</p>

<p>Six ice screws later Mikko topped out and established a belay spot, and I follow. I make my way up, cleaning up the ice screws and quick-draws he installed, and top out after a good climb. The view from up here, some 30 m higher now, is superb - we can see wide into the canyon to each side. The sun looks warm on the other side of the valley, while up here the wind &amp; shadow keep us cold. Mikko lets me down and then follows with a rappel. </p>

<p>Tea time. We snack and drink while discussing the next line. The other group climbed on a very wet fall and would like to climb our more dry line, so we let them and move more to the right. Steeper but a bit shorter, with a more exposed belay at the bottom, Mikko again sets off. While he climbs a Golden Eagle soars above us through the canyon, a majestic sight with its long, wide wings. Arriving at the ledge Mikko sets up a belay and I start my climb up. I arrive at the edge of the ledge with cold hands after having again collected all screws and quick-draws, slowly getting a hang of how to sort them on my harness so that they’re not in the way, as Mikko again lets me down. The plan was to build an Abalakov and abseil, though I was carrying the Abalakov tool and forgot to give it to Mikko. D’oh! Happily the other group is close enough with their toprope to Mikko, and so he is able to just clip into it and rappel down. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596482264/" title="Abseiling by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8226/8596482264_59b61e5f03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abseiling" /></a></p>

<p>We switch to the Revontuli icefall next, further down the canyon. The approach down in the valley is fast, as a well established trail leads through the snow, which at times is over a meter high. The walk up to the cliff is also easy, as two members of our group were just climbing there =) After two Lämmin Kuppi hot soups, chips and nuts I’m again warm and in good spirits, as is Mikko. Again we discuss the route, and decide that Mikko would climb to a ledge, then I follow and then we continue. </p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/62851129?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1080" height="608" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Mikko, who climbs his third season on ice this year, gets up to the ledge, though as I follow the cold hands, a sure sign of gripping my axes to hard, return, and just as I arrive at the ledge I get a cramp in my left leg. Demotivated, I get down after I handed Mikko the ice screws and belay him further. After an exciting climb - Mikko droped an axe (<a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/grivel-double-spring-2-0.html">leashes</a> on Multipitch routes are handy!) and I provided him with a new one - we pack up and head back to camp, passing some of out friends who are still climbing. I take it slow, and photograph along the way. I head up to the foot of Ruseka Virta, from where one has a fine view over the valley looking south-east, and arrive after a nice walk at the Kota and my Khufu. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595387013/" title="Khufu-&amp;-Kota by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8385/8595387013_f40fefb2c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Khufu-&amp;-Kota" /></a></p>

<p>Slowly all the members and friends of Vaasa’s climbing club <a href="http://www.highsport.fi/">High Sport</a> arrive at the Kota. With a few Trangias and gasstoves on, as well as the oven in the centre of the hut, the temperature inside soon rises to sauna levels, while outside the thermometer again drops towards -15°C. Good conversations take place, though after a long day of climbing we are all rather tired, and by ten o’clock I slip into the Khufu, zip the door closed and fall asleep.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595374377/" title="Khufu-eVent-II by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8525/8595374377_49e7f2d121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Khufu-eVent-II" /></a></p>

<p>A new morning and there’s again no Alpine Start, so I too sleep in till 8 o’clock. Coffee and breakfast in the kota, while I am thawing my shoes a bit by the oven. And of course more talk of where to climb today. Mikko and I settle on a small ice fall not far from camp, and a tad after ten o’clock walk over the snowshoe established trail direction north-west, until we reach the Enkeliputous ice fall. It’s a pretty fall, quite short but it’s still untouched and that also means we need to get through the snow till the base of the cliff. </p>

<p>Which is easier said than done. Somehow if one carries ice climbing gear and a rope my elven skills of walking over the snow disappear, and I’m hip deep at times making my way to the cliff. We pick an easy starter route for the morning up the right side, and we both have great fun (see the video) on the route, for me it was easily the best climbing. We set a toprope for two of our friends, and then I rappel down, getting ready for a much steeper climb.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8596473480/" title="Liisa by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8237/8596473480_a6035fa5dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Liisa" /></a></p>

<p>And steep it was. While Mikko made his way up without problems, for me it was a real Suffer-Fest to get the steep ice up - crampons or axes blew out, I barn-doored a time or two, and felt like just going down a couple of times. But it’s mind over matter, and so I made it up, over the ledge and euphoric feelings of success were the reward. I made my way further up to Mikko and the belay spot, where we built an abalakov to abseil. <em>Will it hold?</em> went more than once through my head, though as I made my way down, and also Mikko abseiled after me, we both knew that we built a good abalakov. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595377849/" title="Enkelliputous by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8252/8595377849_c28d4b2303_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Enkelliputous" /></a></p>

<p>I toproped once more, and then packed up and headed back to the Kota to get my camping gear and head back to the car. A long walk up back to the parking lot later, which put the Gore Tex Active Shell membrane to a good, final test, I arrived in the sunshine on top. Storing gear, driving, eating at an ABC Station, and arriving before midnight in Vaasa - a superb trip. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587938931/" title="Trail by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8236/8587938931_023b7dfb47_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trail" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If you’re into ice climbing, life or visit Finland, then a visit to Korouoma is a must. With it’s superb infrastructure (short approaches, free lean-tos, fire places, toilets as well as rental cabins) and the beautiful surroundings ice climbing in Korouoma is an experience you won’t forget. You can climb up to 14 different ice falls of different heights and difficulties in the canyon, all within about an hour of walking distance from the free lean-to shelters which are a mere 200 m from Ruskeavirta. Some of the ice falls even offer paths for setting topropes if you’re not yet leading or want to first get a feeling for the fall. All in all I’m certainly returning next winter, and with the ice climbing season at Korouoma going from November till April (depending on the weather each year, obviously) maybe even more than once.</p>

<p>Even if you’re not an ice climber Korouoma is worth a trip. You can ski and snowshoe in winter, and enjoy the gorgeous scenery of the canyon with its unique flora and fauna. Golden Eagles, herbrich forests and great views are worth a trip at any time of the year, though I imagine in autumn when the leaves turn golden and red it is especially worthwhile.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633086621480/">More photos on Flickr</a></p>

<p>A very useful <a href="http://www.rollomixed.com/2012/03/korouoma-derby-2012.html">map with all ice falls in the canyon</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.climbingextreme.com/2009/02/korouoma-best-spot-for-ice-climbing-in-finland/300">Info on routes and some beta</a>, and some <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/korouoma">more beta</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://matkailu.posio.fi/en/Activities/Winter-activities/Ice-climbing#.UVK1xVtQhGQ">General info on ice climbing at Korouoma</a>, and more <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/otherprotectedareas/korouoma/Pages/Default.aspx">information on Korouoma</a>.</p>

<h2 id="information">Information</h2>

<p><strong>Getting there</strong> is easiest by car. Alternatives are flying to Rovaniemi or Kuusamo and taking a bus to Posio, from where one can take a Taxi to the Korouoma Parking lot. Ot rent a car in Rovaniemi/ Kuusamo to get there.</p>

<p><strong>Accomodation</strong> is either own shelter/ tent, the free lean-tos which are all along the canyon, or some of the rental cabins of which the <a href="http://www.lomarengas.fi/varaamo/villipohjola/mokki/posio-piippukota-erakamppa-10694?villiPohjolaLevel=&amp;mapAreaIDs=&amp;maxPrice=&amp;startDateString=&amp;endDateString=&amp;persons=&amp;code=&amp;name=&amp;customSearch=&amp;noElectricity=&amp;shower=&amp;wc=&amp;heating=&amp;waterSupply=&amp;swimmingShoreShallowAndHard=&amp;allowPets=&amp;maintainedSkiingTracks=&amp;fishing=&amp;canoeing=&amp;hunting=&amp;snowmobiling=&amp;hikingTrail=&amp;suitableForDisabled=&amp;accessByCarDuringSummer=&amp;accessByCarDuringWinter=&amp;holidayCenter=&amp;newLocale=en_EN">Piippukota</a> is for climbers the best option as it is some 400 m from Ruskeavirta. There’s a gas stove at the Piippukota and some pans &amp; pots, too.</p>

<p><strong>Food</strong> you can buy in Posio, which is 30 km from Korouoma. If you stay at the Kota you can almost bring normal food and cook and don’t need to rely on trekking meals. I recommend Bacon &amp; Eggs on bread for breakfast - my MYOG Müsli was OK but bacon and eggs would have been much better =) </p>

<p><em>Happy trails &amp; climbing!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
