<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Salewa | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/salewa/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-09T16:21:22+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Salewa Wildfire Approach Shoes]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/salewa-wildfire-approach-shoes.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-07T12:35:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/salewa-wildfire-approach-shoes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Approach shoes are what climbers wear when approaching a crag, but this sort of shoe is becoming more popular as a footwear choice amongst backpackers and hikers, too. After having used the <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/">Salewa</a> Wildfire in both it’s GTX and unlined version for hundreds of kilometres the verdict is out.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983871004/" title="Salewa Wildfire GTX &amp; Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7418/12983871004_5fa773a2c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire GTX &amp; Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/product/tech+approach/wildfire+gore-tex+man">Salewa Wildfire GTX</a> arrived with me in the end of the winter of 2013, while I picked up the unlined <a href="http://www.salewa.com/product/footwear/wildfire+man">Wildfire</a> version at the OutDoor. Both have been on several trips in the Alps, Germany, Sweden and Finland. Overall I estimate the GTX version have seen around 500 km of use, while the unlined Wildfires have seen a bit more than half of that.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12984685694/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7332/12984685694_97b3ddbd21_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>An approach shoe’s function is to bring you safely up to the start of your climb, where you change into your climbing shoes and start climbing. They’re made for scrambling, and can be tied pretty tight, so that you have a tight fit on more demanding scrambles. Finally, they also help to make a statement in public that you’re a climber =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12984401983/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3518/12984401983_31d36aef08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Salewa packed a whole lotta featuers into this shoe, which is in their <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/footwear/tech%20approach">Tech Approach Line</a>, where you also find the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/salewa-firetail-approachschuhe/">Firetail</a>. </p>

<ul>
  <li>3F SYSTEM EVO, which offers freedom of movement and support</li>
  <li>CLIMBING LACING gives accurate lacing in the toe area </li>
  <li>MFF+ MULTI-FIT FOOTBED gives you the ability to adjust the footbed of your shoe</li>
  <li>SILVERIZED for non-smelly shoes</li>
</ul>

<p>Salewa recommends these shoes for <em>Via Ferrata, Hiking, Mountain inspired urban lifestyle and Approach</em>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983865344/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2033/12983865344_54398d6579_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>

<p>Out of the box they fitted me well, and something interesting that was included in the box were two more insoles (for a total of four yellow ones and two black ones). The black part connects via Velcros to the yellow insole. That way you can add more cushioning  &amp; volume in the heel and front, to suit your needs. Me, I didn’t see a need for it and have used them with low volume insole they came with. The toe box is reasonably wide, so for people who like that there’s enough space for their toes without them being jammed together, this shoe will be a good choice. Also the heel cup has a good fit, and tightens when you lace up the shoe.</p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The above mentioned MFF+ Footbed system is a pretty interesting solution which lets the user adapt the shoe’s insole to his need, and you’re thus able to make them fit better. It’s a smart way as in this way Salewa can make one shoe and with the insole you can adopt it to your needs. </p>

<p>The Salewa EXA shell technology is basically a plastic grid on top of the mesh, which helps to protect it while still being flexible. It adds protection to the shoe and makes it more durable.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12986019963/" title="Salewa Wildfire MFF+ Footbed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7419/12986019963_3748452f1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Salewa Wildfire MFF+ Footbed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The quality is very good. Salewa are an old Italian company with a long tradition in making gear for use in the mountains, and their athletes help develop their gear. I have put these shoes through a lot of walking on asphalt and the Vibram sole still looks almost like new. Also the uppers have been through rock fields, on scrambles and hikes, and have not much to show for it except those splatters of mud which I didn’t want to clean (gives them a more authentic look, ya see!). </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983444905/" title="Salewa Wildfire GTX on top, Salewa Wildfire on the bottom by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7371/12983444905_db48769d7b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire GTX on top, Salewa Wildfire on the bottom" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>They’re heavier than <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/shoes/">shoes I usually wear</a>, but I was curious to see if approach shoes work for me. They do feel heavier, but not too bad.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Wildfire GTX 888 g for the pair in EU Size 42,5 or 444 g per shoe</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Wildfire 878 g for the pair in EU Size 42,5 or 439 g per shoe</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Salewa has a <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/csr">CSR</a> page and their 2013 CSR Report can be read <a href="http://csr.oberalp.com/">online</a>. The company is member of the <a href="http://www.salewa.eu/csr/fairwear%20foundation%20(fwf)">Fairwear Foundation</a> and is working on becoming greener, like much of our industry. As for the shoes, the easiest way for you to recycle them is to drop them in a shoe/ garment recycling bin in your town. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983433815/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3380/12983433815_29f580ddf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>Alrighty then, the most important part. I started wearing the Wildfire GTX in the end of the winter of 2013, and they quickly became a shoe I wore when walking with my son, cycling to work, doing day hikes and walking to the grocery store. The GTX version, as well as the unlined version, are - at least in black - pretty warm shoes, so after a day walking in hot weather expect to have very sweaty feet. I find them in warm weather unbearable hot and will not wear them in temps above 20°C as they’re just too hot for me. For winter they’re very good, as you can wear them with mid-weight socks and still have toasty feet.</p>

<p>I wore them on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/sul-in-the-swiss-alps.html">Swiss SUL trip</a> and while they were fine, I more than once wished I would be wearing a shoe with more grip. While the Vibram Tech Approach EVO sole is durable, I don’t find it has as much grip as other soles and as it’s stiff it also does not let you feel the underground very well. The lugs on the sole are narrow and tight together, which became especially evident when crossing frozen snow fields high up. Where e.g. the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/salomon-speedcross-3.html">Salomon Speedcross 3</a>’s lugs dig into the snow and give you a save grip, the Wildfires were a bit sketchy. Also on gravel and wet surfaces they don’t offer as much grip as competing shoes. On the plus side, the sole is very durable and shows little signs of wear, and because it is so stiff it’s a good shoe to cycle in, too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12984258655/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7375/12984258655_36f77a4412_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<p>Speaking of cycling, while the shoes weren’t made for biking, the sole stuck pretty well to the pedals on my bike and the stiff sole was good for power transmission when riding. For walking I would wish that the sole would be more flexible - it barely flexes - which makes a natural stride more difficult (but not impossible). Both versions, but especially the GTX version, are also great on windy days or when you ride fast as you won’t get cold feet. </p>

<p>The weight of the shoes is higher than what I’d normally wear, but it’s not too bad. For the increase in weight you get a more durable shoe, though I think Salewa should remove some of the lining to <strong>a)</strong> make the shoe less warm and <strong>b)</strong> make it lighter. Especially the GTX version would benefit immensely from that, and I think if the shoes could be pushed down to sub 400 g per shoe they’d very popular amongst hikers that look for a durable shoe.</p>

<p>The 3F System Evo technology which is employed in the shoe, which is supposed to support and offer freedom of movement, well it’s in a shoe like this a given. I can see why the technology would be useful in boots, but in low shoes it feels a bit like they’re just slapping another label on top. It helps with a good heel-fit, though, if that’s something you’re looking for in a shoe.</p>

<p>Climbing in the shoes is OK. I personally rather slip into my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/ultralight-climbing.html">climbing shoes</a>, but for scrambles on hikes, approaching the crag, and easy climbs they’re good. Keep in mind that you won’t have as much control and feeling in them as in a pair of climbing shoes. Finally, the shoes look pretty good and I often wear them to the city with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/outlier-woolback-og.html">Outlier pants</a>, which makes for a smart, casual look but you still can go for a scramble if the need arises.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a whole host of approach shoes, for example the <a href="http://bit.ly/1f5nL2u">Patagonia Rover</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/garmont-dragontail-lt-approachschuhe/">Garmont Dragontail LT</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/scarpa-zen-pro-approachschuhe/">Scarpa Zen Pro</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/O0GSzT">La Sportiva Xplorer</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1g50Yno">The North Face Verto</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/five-ten-camp-four-schuhe-dark-shadow-uk-5/">Five Ten Camp Four</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-womens-needle-approachschuhe/">Mammut Needle</a> and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/hagloefs-roc-legend-q-gt-approachschuhe/">Haglöfs Roc Legend GT</a>, amongst <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/approachschuhe/?_artperpage=96">plenty more</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983603993/" title="Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3102/12983603993_2dd522ac7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.keithfoskett.com/the-3-shoe-review-salewa-wildfires/">Keith</a> thinks they could be 1.000 km hiking shoes, <a href="http://www.examiner.com/review/salewa-wildfire-approach-shoe-a-new-generation-alpine-footwear-review">Erica</a> gives them 5 Stars and <a href="http://www.climberism.com/gear-review-salewa-wildfire-approach-shoe/">Jeremy</a> finds they blend into his life’s rhythms seamlessly.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983873444/" title="Salewa Wildfire GTX by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3654/12983873444_07b2c5b008_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire GTX" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I have used the Salewa Wildfires pretty much daily since they arrived, and have walked on two outdoor fairs with them. The main reason for that is that walking on my trailrunning shoes in the city eats up their sole at an alarming rate, and to save my wallet the Salewa Wildfire with their very durable Vibram sole are an excellent alternative, and I’m still ready for the trail or a scramble. They work well for hiking and I think for people that are transitioning from boots to lightweight footwear these are prime candidates to try. They combine the benefits of boots - durability and a stiff-ish sole - with the benefits of trailrunners: light weight, strengthening the foot muscles and allowing for a more natural movement.</p>

<p>If you’re an ultralight backpacker these might not be the shoes for you, unless you spend a lot of time hiking on rock which naturally eats up rubber pretty fast. Also if you’re on a budget and don’t want to buy more than a pair of shoes a year, these are a good choice for you. On the other hand, if you’re a climber who looks for a new pair of approach shoes, or are a backpacker transitioning to lightweight footwear, then these should be on the top of your list. The are durable, light, look pretty fetching (especially in green!) and work also well in the city. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157641987117703/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-salewa-wildfire-approach-shoes">Where to buy the Salewa Wildfire Approach Shoes</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/salewa-wildfire-gtx-w-s-schuhe-black-sulphur/">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/salewa-wildfire-approachschuhe/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/1gd4SXt">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/1g3t427">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/1gVsTDX">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Long-term observation and photos</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12983462515/" title="Salewa Wildfire GTX &amp; Salewa Wildfire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7323/12983462515_bbc5ac4129_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Wildfire GTX &amp; Salewa Wildfire" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assorted Ice Climbing Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/assorted-ice-climbing-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-19T21:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/04/assorted-ice-climbing-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Besides boots, crampons, ice axes and a backpack there’s a few more pieces of gear an ice climber needs - ice screws, belay devices, slings, quick draws, and and and. In this article I highlight some of the assorted ice climbing gear which I have used during this years ice climbing exploits.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661762203/" title="Assorted climbing gear by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8250/8661762203_070d206c29_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Assorted climbing gear" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="black-diamond-express-ice-screws">Black Diamond Express Ice Screws</h2>
<p>The Gold Standard in ice screws, the Black Diamond Express have the best price/ quality ratio and perform superbly on the ice. Easy to screw into the ice with one hand thanks to the crank and with to two carabiner holes to clip in, the Express ice screw helps you to secure yourself quickly when the going gets tough. Petzl will bring out a similar design next winter which performs very well, and Grivel’s <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-ice-screw-360-kurbeleisschraube/">360 ice screws</a> too is great. However, at the moment Black Diamond makes the lightest screws and they’re very well priced, thus these excellent ice screws shouldn’t be missing on any ice climbers rack.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-express-ice-screw-eisschraube/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-express-ice-screw.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15pvcgK">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115SnGQ">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJ4OcT">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587935487/" title="Secured by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8241/8587935487_cc1e3ed8d0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Secured" /></a></p>

<h2 id="slings">Slings</h2>
<p>Slings are an important piece of gear when climbing ice whenever you don’t toprope. A 120 cm sling is essential to build a belay station together with two ice screws, and a daisychain or another 120 cm sling are needed to secure yourself at a belay station. They also can be very useful when setting screws and taking care that the rope isn’t making a wide curve (Imagine it a bit like this sign <strong>&lt;</strong> where the three points are ice screws and the line is the rope. With a sling and two ‘biners in the middle point you can make the rope run in a more straight line). Also when rappeling down slings come in handy, and they of course also can be used in rock climbing. A piece of gear that definitely needs to come along.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schlingen-reepschnur/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/schlinge-reepschnur.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15ptb3X">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/Zv14fB">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115RtdF">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662799740/" title="Slings &amp; Daisychain by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8245/8662799740_908fe80d94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Slings &amp; Daisychain" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quick-draws">Quick draws</h2>
<p>When you’re leading a climb you’ll need quick draws (Read Tomás superb article on <a href="http://www.scandinavian-hiking.com/2011/08/relatively-ultralight-quickdraws-petzl.html">Ultralight Quick Draws</a>). As so often, lighter quick draws means you either can take more or then safe a substantial amount of weight for the same performance. Some clip in easier and are better handled with gloves, so keep that in mind when building your rack.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/express-sets/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/express-sets.html?priceMin=&amp;priceMax=&amp;query=&amp;sort=&amp;_artperpage=">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15puIat">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176mNNe">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176mZw0">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662796740/" title="Quick draws by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8259/8662796740_9938e7249a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Quick draws" /></a></p>

<h2 id="carabiners">Carabiners</h2>
<p>I thought I’d be set with my two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-phantom-schraubkarabiner/">DMM Phantom</a> locking ‘biners, though I was wrong. And so I bought a few more locking carabiners, in slightly bigger sizes, because they’re easier to operate with gloves on. If you’re not toproping then a about five locking carabiners are good to have along: Three to set up a belay, one to clip yourself in with a sling, and one if you’re belaying someone else. A spare or two in these situations can’t hurt, either.</p>

<p>As for non-locking carabiners, I have been using the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-phantom-schnappkarabiner/">DMM Phantom gate ‘biner</a> and still think they’re superb. The gate opens easy, they’re light yet strong - a great biner to have along to rack gear.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schraubkarabiner/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/karabiner.html?Limit%5B%5D=Schraubkarabiner&amp;Limit%5B%5D=HMS-Karabiner&amp;priceMin=&amp;priceMax=&amp;query=&amp;sort=&amp;_artperpage=&amp;f=1">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZAAOxi">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJ9vn8">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115W5QI">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662797582/" title="Carabiners by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8251/8662797582_9b811ef47f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Carabiners" /></a></p>

<h2 id="camp-speed-helmet">CAMP Speed helmet</h2>
<p>I used the CAMP Speed helmet during all climbing, and really like the comfort of this helmet - light and protective, easy to adjust the size when I wear a beanie or not, not to hot nor too cold. I can wear shades or my googles underneath them, a Headlamp like the Petzl Nao fits easily on it, and it also fits under all my jacket’s hoods. However, with the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-vapor-hybridhelm/">Black Diamond Vapor</a> and Petzl Siricco helmets available, the Speed is no longer the lightest option, something too keep in mind when you’re buying a helmet (I used the Petzl Siricco and really like it, especially the magnetic closure that’s easy to operate with one hand is very good).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-speed-kletterhelm/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/camp-brg-5.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176wpYi">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661816397/" title="CAMP Speed Helmet by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8258/8661816397_2b4e3ce0b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="CAMP Speed Helmet" /></a></p>

<h2 id="poc-iris-3p-googles">POC Iris 3P Googles</h2>

<p>Because my helmet doesn’t have a visor to keep ice and water from flying in my face, I was wearing the comfortable <a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">POC Iris 3P Googles</a>. They have a superb view and while they on occasion were fogging up, the fog cleared up quickly. I can wear them with my Speed Helmet without problems, but had problems to get a comfortable fit with the new Petzl Helmet. The googles’ lens are antiscratch and have a oleophobic &amp; hydrophobic treatment which means it keeps fat and water off your lens very easily - a very welcome function when climbing ice where you sweat and ice is coming at you. A great pair of googles that I can recommend if you climb ice or ski.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">JK-Shop</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176xmjq">Backcountry</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662911976/" title="POC Iris 3P Googles by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8266/8662911976_1d5db327e1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="POC Iris 3P Googles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="petzl-reverso-4">Petzl Reverso 4</h2>
<p>I usually use a Petzl Verso, though enlightenment struck as I tried the Reverso 4. It’s only a tad heavier than the Verso but offers so much more functions: You can secure two climbers that are climbing after you, and connect it to your belay with the ring. As with the Verso, you can belay and rappel. When not toproping then definitely a piece of gear to take along. </p>

<p>There’s plenty of belaying devices around, though one to consider is the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/s/Mammut--Smart----Alpine/kategorie--klettern/">Mammut Smart Alpine</a> which offers similar functionality as the Reverso though has the added benefit of breaking the rope dynamically in the case of a fall. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-reverso-4-sicherungsgeraet/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-reverso-4-belay-device.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZABoLu">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/11m0gIL">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13qZm2O">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577735844/" title="Petzl Reverso 4 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8234/8577735844_86d4c770cb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Reverso 4" /></a></p>

<h2 id="tendon-master-97-rope">Tendon Master 9.7 rope</h2>
<p>A superb rope for toproping, also on ice. It’s my rock-climbing rope which I diverted from its intended use to toproping on ice. Super smooth handling, light, great knot-ability, and with a middle marking, this is a great piece of kit which does the job very well.</p>

<p>For lead climbing on ice a twin or half rope is needed, though, and also there the market offers plenty of great ropes for us ice climbers. I used a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beal-ice-twin-golden-dry-77-mm-zwillingsseil/">BEAL rope</a> which were very great to handle and didn’t soak out, and if you’re serious about ice climbing then you won’t get around getting a twin or half rope (<a href="http://www.highinfatuation.com/blog/straight-from-the-mammoths-mouth-half-ropes-are-not-twins/">Here’s an explanation on the difference</a>!).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/tendon-master-97-mm-einfachseil/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/tendon-master-9-4-complete-shield-kletterseil.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r7uA8">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r6YCt">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/17sOoX6">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8486287141/" title="Tendon Rope by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8372/8486287141_7f341247e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Tendon Rope" /></a></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-r320-harness">Arc’teryx R320 harness</h2>
<p>The Arc’teryx R320 has been my harness of choice and I like the racking capacity it has - plenty of gear fits on the four gear loops. For ice climbing a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-caritool.html">Petzl Caritool</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-ice-clipper.html">Black Diamond Ice Clipper</a> would have been useful, though I made work without this season. It’s comfortable, the leg loops are big enough to step through in case you put on your crampons before your harness (happens!) and with it’s good design it feels well over pants and jacket. If one is serious about ice climbing, the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-i340a-klettergurt/">Arc’teryx I340A</a> of course would be a nice harness to have, though for the time being the R320 is very good for my needs and can be used all year around.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-r-320-hueftgurt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-r-320a-klettergurt.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJanYJ">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/Z1PB8H">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/11m0I9Q">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="black-diamond-ice-box">Black Diamond Ice Box</h2>
<p>A backpack is the best way to get your gear from home to the ice fall. But what when between the ice fall and home there’s a airplane? Backpacks with the sharp tools outside aren’t great for travelling - enter the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633281180152/">Black Diamond Ice Box</a>. It fits four tools, one pair of crampons, up to ten ice screws, a mesh compartment for drying gear and still has plenty of space left for small stuff. For me very important too, is that its perfect to store the ice climbing gear safely and using minimal space at home, out of the reach of an exploring toddler. A great piece of kit for ice climbers that travel a lot and want to store their gear safely when not in use.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ice-box/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/17sM0zG">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r3DTL">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662893104/" title="Black Diamond Ice Box by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8248/8662893104_f8e2087b75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond Ice Box" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661794319/" title="Black Diamond Ice Box by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8260/8661794319_4c98c70443_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ice Box" /></a></p>

<p><em>Most of the ice-climbing related gear has been used for a week of ice climbing this season. These short reviews thus should be considered as an initial review, which will be updated during the next winter season when I have used the gear more. If you have questions, please use the comments to ask!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576458309/" title="Abisko Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8392/8576458309_581552ba62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abisko Canyon" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaiming the Disclaimer</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
