<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rock climbing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/rock-climbing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-29T11:50:54+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DMM Classic Rope Bag]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/dmm-classic-rope-bag.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T22:22:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/dmm-classic-rope-bag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>If you have a rope, you should have a rope bag</em> was what I was told on my lead climbing course earlier this spring. There’s some good reasons for that: It’s easier to transport your rope plus it stays clean &amp; sorted at the crag. I settled for the <a href="http://www.dmmclimbing.com/">DMM</a> Classic Rope Bag, which holds a lot more than just a rope, and is very comfortable to carry.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9172652567/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag + Petzl Sirocco by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5473/9172652567_188bae6cd2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag + Petzl Sirocco" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’m a sucker for <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/dmm/?_artperpage=96">DMM</a>’s high quality gear, so it was an easy decision to get their <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-classic-rope-bag/">Classic Rope bag</a>. Being a Finnish climbing association member I even got a nice 10% discount on the bag as I bought it at <a href="http://camu.fi/pages/kiipeily/kalliokiipeily/kaysipussit/classicropebaggreen.html">Camu</a> down in Helsinki. You can choose from four nice colours, and I settled for the green one. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208491026/” title=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>As backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2809/10208491026_175c2b5215_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”680” alt=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>As backpack”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208604863/” title=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>Over the shoulder by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7320/10208604863_d8997f2a9f_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”680” alt=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>Over the shoulder”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The Classic Rope Bag can be worn as a backpack or over the shoulder. It’s very easy to transform the backpack into a shoulder pack (or the other way around) - one of the shoulder straps has two buckles which you undo and then connect to the two matching buckles which keep the main compartment compressed. Lemme walk you through it:</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208531396/” title=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>Backpack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7349/10208531396_d41d9e6a06_b.jpg” width=”680” height=”1024” alt=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>Backpack”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>That’s the pack in backpack mode. The left shoulder strap, as you can see, has a buckle on top and at the bottom. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208624003/” title=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>Transformation into shoulder bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7425/10208624003_314f58c406_b.jpg” width=”680” height=”1024” alt=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>Transformation into shoulder bag”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Buckles are easily opened. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208502985/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Transformation into shoulder bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8269/10208502985_b8744e1fe7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Transformation into shoulder bag" /></a>
The closed top which helps to compress the content. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208498915/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Shoulder bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8140/10208498915_9bd21475ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Shoulder bag" /></a>
<em>Magic</em>. Nah, not really. The shoulder strap is now connected to the buckle which you saw in the above photo.</p>

<p><em>“Why would I need a backpack that can become a shoulder bag?”</em> you might be wondering. Well, for a sport climbing day at the crag you can fit your rope, harness, shoes, a set of QDs and water in there, as well as a Topo Guide - all you need. Then you can wear it in backpack mode to the crag. </p>

<p>However, if you want to go Trad climbing, you will need a tad more gear - cams, nuts, torque nuts, which all takes more space. In that case you can either stuff all that gear in the DMM Classic Rope Bag, as I do, and transform it into the shoulder bag and take an additional backpack along for other stuff - water, sandwiches, camera gear - and then you can carry both without problems. Because it’s a lot more comfortable to carry a backpack and a shoulder bag instead of two backpacks.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10203094383/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5518/10203094383_96059dd427_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9253426672/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7312/9253426672_513d0e3ceb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag" /></a></p>

<p>The tarp is a good size - 110 x 130 cm - and has four colour coded loops so the rope(s) stay in order, even twin/ half-ropes. Speaking of ropes, the bag can take a 80 m rope without problems with room to spare. I have used my 70 m <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kletterseile/">rope</a> and all my trad gear in there. The tarp (and backpack) has a 1000 mm hydrostatic head, so keeps moisture and wetness away from the rope when the ground is wet.</p>

<p>Once you have climbed enough (does that ever happen?) and it’s time to go, packing is easy with the Classic Rope Bag: Fold the tarp with rope together, stuff it neatly into the bottom of the pack, add all your other gear, close the durable zipper, pull the compression straps tight, and <em>Voilá</em>, you’re ready to hike back. It looks like this:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208433354/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Tarp and all gear out by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2829/10208433354_9b9770de23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Tarp and all gear out" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208648633/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Tarp and all gear out by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3809/10208648633_c55507a996_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Tarp and all gear out" /></a>
Tarp with rope folded together.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208446594/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag | All gear out by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2830/10208446594_dedcd703ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag | All gear out" /></a>
And in the bag.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208551665/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Plenty of space by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8275/10208551665_5313b8dfc4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Plenty of space" /></a>
Add gear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208558085/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Holds a rope and a trad rack! by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7416/10208558085_a0b5cd59c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Holds a rope and a trad rack!" /></a>
And more gear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208676163/" title="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Closed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3718/10208676163_ac1071daa6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="DMM Classic Rope Bag | Closed" /></a>
Close the zipper, pull the compression straps tight, go to the Pub and have a beer.</p>

<p>In case you don’t want to throw in your smartphone, keys and wallet in the main compartment, DMM has thought ahead and added a zippered valuables pocket. It will hold all your valuable and not so valuable stuff away from metal gear which might scratch it otherwise.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10208581406/” title=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>Valuables pocket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8412/10208581406_4e06818dac_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”680” alt=”DMM Classic Rope Bag</td>
      <td>Valuables pocket”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>That’s it, really. There are plenty of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/seiltaschen-seilpflege/">rope bags</a>, some are lighter, some are cheaper, sometimes you even can get a free one if you purchase a rope, but the durability, quality and ease of use of the DMM Classic Rope Bag are hard to beat. It comes at a good price, too. I’m really happy with it, and look forward to many years climbing with it. Two thumbs up.</p>

<p>You can buy one at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-classic-rope-bag/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://camu.fi/pages/kiipeily/kalliokiipeily/kaysipussit/classicropebaggreen.html">Camu</a> and ask for it at <a href="http://bit.ly/Wi4tZS">Backcountry.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/131V0vk">CampSaver.com</a>. And now go climbing.</p>

<p><em>If you do a lot of Trad climbing, maybe consider waiting for the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/outdoor-news-iv.html">Vector trad pack</a>. It allows for easier trad gear organising!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On The Rocks]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/on-the-rocks.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-22T21:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/on-the-rocks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The sun was shining, it was a balmy 11°C and I was sitting on the backseat of a car, heading away from the coast. The conversation was about <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-dragon-cam-klemmgeraet/">dragons</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-demon-cam-klemmgeraet/">demons</a>, and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-starters-nut-set-klemmkeile-set/">nuts</a>, and I was full of anticipation for the first outdoor rock climbing session of 2013.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669659242/" title="001 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8404/8669659242_0564544c50_o.jpg" width="4121" height="2975" alt="001" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We took a left and were on forest road, passing fields and hay barns, until Minna parked the car and declared “<em>We’re here.</em>” All four of us got out, grabbed our backpacks from the trunk and headed along towards the crag. It was the first time I was at Falkin Kallio in Ylistaro, and I immediately liked it: A nice short approach, and great routes for every taste. We put our harnesses and helmets on and then Mikko was off on a bolted route. Once up, he installed a top rope for Minna and me, while he and Outi practiced a few things further on the left. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669647942/" title="Mikko catching a glimpse of the cranes which flew by by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8401/8669647942_c3629f968d_o.jpg" width="4912" height="3264" alt="Mikko catching a glimpse of the cranes which flew by" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669637440/" title="Nice cracks by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8379/8669637440_840ca54e9b_o.jpg" width="3264" height="4409" alt="Nice cracks" /></a></p>

<p>Minna let me go first, and so I got my climbing shoes on, made my Figure 8 Knot, and got up on the rock. Yes, it was dry. But it also was cold. And there were no big jugs as easy holds like at the gym - small cracks, tiny crimps, and some slippery moss here instead. I slowly made my way up, remembering what I have learned in the past. I also wasn’t afraid to fail, because only when you fail, you get better. On the final few meters I burst out laughing: As I moved my foot over a ledge to get up the final few meters my leg started to shake rapidly. “<em>Elvis has entered the building</em>” Mikko laughed after I told them. I took a small break, relaxed my arms, and then made the move without problems. The scariest part of any climb with a new person is for me the being let down part. “<em>Will they be able to hold me? How do I get over the ledge?</em>” are the thoughts going through my head. I know I shouldn’t hold on to the rope, but it’s a reflex with each first abseil with a new person. But Minna let me down safe and comfortable, and I thanked her. Her turn, my belay. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669612936/" title="Mammut Smart &amp; Tendon Master = Awesome by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8388/8669612936_4e851867b9_o.jpg" width="3264" height="2448" alt="Mammut Smart &amp; Tendon Master = Awesome" /></a></p>

<p>We each climbed the route a couple of times, and then all four of us sat down for some coffee and snacks. More talks about cams and nuts, climbing destinations near and far, future climbing trips. Then we geared up, and tried a new route - a small crack running top to bottom. At the bottom water was running out of a crack, and I duly slipped. Minna caught me, and suggested I try the dry rock on the right. Much better. Crack climbing is utterly new to me, and it was immense fun. Fun now, that I think about it, but back there I was wondering how to get further up. Fingers jammed into cracks where I wondered what will happen to them if I now fall. I was halfway in a hard move as Minna informed me that the rope is stuck. </p>

<p>Exquisite. It’s the stuff you want to hear when your fingers are jammed in a crack and you’re trying to work out how to get further up. I looked up, and saw that the rope was twisted. “<em>Hold me</em>” I told Minna, as I was untwisting the rope by crawling underneath it and stepping back over it. “<em>How is it now?</em>” I inquired. “<em>Still stuck</em>” came the reply. Just as well. “<em>I will go a bit further and see what’s the problem</em>” I let her know, and after a bit of fresh chalk on my fingers I jammed my fingers back in that crack and pushed myself up. “<em>Stuck in a crack</em>” I called down - “<em>Now is good again</em>” came the reply. I finished the climb, sat down in my harness, hands by my side, while Minna expertly let me down. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669729870/" title="The routes of the day by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8388/8669729870_37d41fd3b4_o.jpg" width="3264" height="2448" alt="The routes of the day" /></a></p>

<p>After Minna did the crack route we headed a bit further along to a slab with a couple of bolts to practice lead climbing. With snow still at the bottom and plenty of moss on the rock it looked a bit sketchy, but it was nice and easy. Well-sized pockets made for good holds, and for me it was a great first experience at lead climbing. The kind of thing were you can get a taste for it, build up the skills and confidence, so that when the harder routes are to be lead you can look back and think “<em>Yeah, I can do this. And failing isn’t a problem, either.</em>” We each lead the two different routes, before it was again coiling up the rope, getting into my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/salewa-wildfire-gtx-approachschuhe/">approach shoes</a>, packing up and heading back to the car. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669616136/" title="Minna leading by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8398/8669616136_2e79d2fc14_o.jpg" width="4912" height="3264" alt="Minna leading" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8669602724/" title="Second lead by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8394/8669602724_8791c1a90b_o.jpg" width="4912" height="3264" alt="Second lead" /></a></p>

<p>Five fine outdoor climbs, the first of the season. New rocks, new routes, new friends, new experiences. This summer sure looks like it will be a lot of fun =)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
