<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ISPO 2015 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-03T13:24:41+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-4.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-10T23:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A bunch more new gear for the trailrunner, the backpacker, the climber, the skier, the cyclists and simply anyone who likes the outdoors, or gear, with a look at trends, a dozen other blogs that reported on the fair and a final conclusion of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">2015 ISPO</a> in München.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695647012" title="Audi &amp; Heimplanet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8581/16695647012_b34d002d69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Audi &amp; Heimplanet" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Late to the Party? Read the other updates for more Gear News: <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html">Part 1</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2.html">Part 2</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">Part 3</a>.</em></p>

<h2 id="petzl">Petzl</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578475520" title="Petzl Sitta harness by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8731/16578475520_e272aca434_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Sitta harness" /></a></p>

<p>There were four big news for me at <a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The new Sitta Harness</li>
  <li>The new RAD System</li>
  <li>The new positioning lanyards</li>
  <li>The updated headlamp line-up</li>
</ul>

<p>Lets look at these in detail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578288858" title="Petzl Sitta harness by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7609/16578288858_3e832e66ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Sitta harness" /></a></p>

<p>The new harness obviously immediately had my interest, as it’s lighter yet again as the Hirundos (that I have here and which is already damn light at 280 g in Size Medium) - the Sitta will be 250 g in Size Medium and a sweet 230 g in Size Small. The Wireframe Technology which this harness uses uses Dyneema strands in the waistbelt and leg loops and which replaces webbing and foam in normal harnesses. It’s a very compact harness with a beautiful design that’s slim but still packs all you need from a harness: Two rigid front gear loops, two flexible back gear loops, two Caritool slots and a rear loop for a haul rope. It’s made of Bluesign® approved fabrics, too. Psyched about this one!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764794052" title="Petzl RAD System by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8718/16764794052_1aa2dcaae5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl RAD System" /></a></p>

<p>The new RAD System, (<strong>R</strong>escue <strong>A</strong>nd <strong>D</strong>escent) is an all-in-one set for skiers that allows you to set up an crevasse rescue, rappel or rope up on a glacier. The set contains three Attache carabiners, one storage bag, one Tibloc, one Micro Traxion, one 120 cm sling and the 30 m RAD Line, a newly developed 6 mm cordage which allows you to do a crevasse rescue, rope up on a glacier or rappel. The whole set weighs in at 1.045 g which is quite a bit lighter as other options, and also very compact. The cord tips the scales at 660 g for the 30 m, that’s 22 g/ m. It’s a static cord with less than 2% stretch which makes it great for rappels and rescue actions and minimizes yo-yo effects. It’s something any backcountry skier usually will carry, though nothing yet packs down as compact and light as the RAD (4 l pack size!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143568884" title="Petzl Positioning Lanyards by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8580/16143568884_0dd68a1709_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Positioning Lanyards" /></a></p>

<p>The Positioning lanyards are interesting. They aim to replace your Daisychain/ 120 cm sling with which you clip into the belay station. The Connect Adjust is made for sports climbing and mountaineering, while the Dual Connect Adjust is for Multi-Pitch routes and mountaineering. You attach them with a girth hitch to your tie-in point and then clip them out of the way until you need them. The magic happens when you arrive at the belay. With the locking carabiner (not included in the sets) you clip in to the belay, and then can easily adjust the length of the lanyard with the Adjust ascender. The lanyard is a dynamic rope which can reduce the force in case of a short fall. The Connect Adjust tips the scales at 125 g and the Dual Connect Adjust at 160 g, and will need one or two locking carabiners respectively. Knowing how much discussions we have in our climbing club about slings/ daisy chains/ <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/metolius-personal-anchor-system-black/?pid=81">Personal Anchor Systems</a> I reckon these will be hotly discussed, too. Personally I think they are great ideas which can make adjusting the length at the belay a lot easier and possibly safer, though they’re a tad heavier than normal systems (which in turn are a lot heavier than just tying in with a Clove hitch).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578285888" title="Petzl Headlamps by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7593/16578285888_8def09b8d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Petzl Headlamps" /></a></p>

<p>The headlamps line got a refresh, and many models got more power (= Lumen) and there’s also a hole bunch of new, fresh colours. The Tikkina, Tikka and Zipka headlamps went up to 80, 100 and 100 Luen respectively, the Tikka + and the Tikka XP went to 160 and 180 Lumen and the Tactikka + and Tactikka +RGB are headlamps in more toned down colours (all black, desert and camo) are for hunters and fishermen. Both come with 160 Lumen output and have different light options which allow for stealth and keeping your night vision.</p>

<h2 id="scarpa">Scarpa</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765869135" title="Scarpa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8568/16765869135_77370356c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://scarpa.it">Scarpa</a> goes wild with the Mojito Wild. The upper is made of spotted or plain color “cavallino” leather and the sole is the Spider Trek sole in all black. They’re probably going to be wildly popular, as I imagine the Mojito Patchwork will be, where every shoe will be totally unique as they are hand-sewed, with each square being different thus making every upper completely unique. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578271698" title="Scarpa Alien 2.0 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7632/16578271698_070961ef9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Scarpa Alien 2.0" /></a></p>

<p>On the other hand you have the Alien 2.0. It is a race boot that employs the Tronic technology – a ski/ walk mechanism that automatically blocks the cuff to the shell simply by inserting the boot into the binding which should give you an advantage during a race when every second counts. It has an internal gaiter and a full carbon shell and cuff and it is closed with the Alien Fast Buckle Closure and the Boa Closure System. </p>

<h2 id="the-omm">The OMM</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143535204" title="The OMM Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8646/16143535204_c40b372fa7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The OMM Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System" /></a></p>

<p>I really like to stop by at the guys from <a href="https://theomm.com">The OMM</a> as there is always cool gear to be seen. Take the Mountain Raid Jacket &amp; PA 1.0 Sleep System above. Both garments are filled with Primaloft Gold and weigh 390 g for the Jacket and 235 g for the half-bag. The Half bag connects via push buttons on the inside of the jacket to it to create one versatile sleeping system that weighs in at 625 g. The half-bag also has a draw string to pull it tighter and packs a mighty fine 16 x 11 cm when its in your pack. This will be a hot item for runners and (S)UL Backpackers alike I think, it’s a great execution of the <em>“Multi-use”</em> idea.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16739960016" title="The OMM Rotor Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7637/16739960016_563fa0f204_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="The OMM Rotor Vest" /></a></p>

<p>The Rotor Vest tips the scales at 135 g and is filled with Primaloft Gold in a 40 g weight variation. It packs rather small as I show above when you don’t need it, but when you put it on you’ll be toasty. It has a zipper so you can dump heat, a hem drawstring and the chest pocket also functions as the stuff sack. The Purple colour above also looks superb!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764773562" title="The OMM Kamleika Race Smock II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7621/16764773562_ee7d0c4cd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The OMM Kamleika Race Smock II" /></a></p>

<p>The Kamleika Race Smock II above isn’t new but the colour combo is and I’m totally in love with it. </p>

<h2 id="extreme-food">Extreme Food</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765859435" title="Extreme Food Booth by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7599/16765859435_dae4ba6952_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Extreme Food Booth" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.extreme-food.eu">Extreme Food</a> had one of the most fun booths on the show. It was simple, but the juxtaposition of fine porcelain, sterling cutlery and wine glasses with a fine course of freeze dried food in a bag was just great. The food is made in the UK from high quality natural ingredients with no artificial colourings or preservatives, and I have seen some UK tweeps already tasting it and finding it delicious. And what’s pretty awesome about these meals is that breakfasts, mains and desserts all have a superb weight-to-calorie ratio: A minimum of 4.8 kcal per g! That means each pouch weighs 102 g and gives you 500 kcal, which is pretty lightweight. Best of all, they’re <a href="http://www.extreme-food.eu/stockists.html">available already</a>!</p>

<h2 id="salomon">Salomon</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076604673" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8673/16076604673_f38509f1e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.salomon.com/">Salomon</a> had so much new stuff on the show that it’s hard to narrow it down. Lets start with the shoes, shoes at Salomon are always worth checking out, because they’re damn good.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510388979" title="Salomon X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8640/16510388979_1e088bcaa5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe" /></a></p>

<p>The X Alp GTX M Approach Shoe is the small sibling of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-4.html">Salomon S-Lab Alp Carbon GTX</a>, the mountaineering boot I already found awesome at the OutDoor 2014. It also employs a carbon midsole that is laterally stable but otherwise flexible, so should be great on these Approach shoes. They should arrive for test this week, so keep an eye on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for some tidbits on them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076575143" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8664/16076575143_c4dd257abc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074215914" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16074215914_94ffd2974a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>The Salomon S-Lab gear is probably some of the most advanced kit on the market and Kilian Jornet’s thoughts and feedback go into it. The S-Lab Wings above is a universal shoe for your trail runs that excels on the way down. This gives you more protection on the downhill and has a great fit in the heel thanks to the combination of Descent Control and the SensiFit-System, so that your foot doesn’t move to the front or sides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509153630" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16509153630_8f0df0d707_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510408099" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8623/16510408099_88b6153059_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>Shoes for less serious trailrunning were abound, too. The Speedcross Vario is the shoe for harder trails in dry weather, while the Speedcross Pro is great on wet and soft terrain (= MUD!). They’re built on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/salomon-speedcross-3.html">Speedcross 3</a> model with different soles and thus if you love the Speedcross 3 but need a shoe that’s better in soft and moist terrain, grab the Pro, or if you run usually in dry, desert-like terrain on hard trails the Vario will be for you. Why? Well, the Vario’s profile is larger and hence gives more friction on the ground, and there’s also more cushioning. The Pro on the other hand has the Mud &amp; Snow Contragrip sole, with smaller and more aggressive cleats. In the Pro your foot sits deeper in the shoe for a better ground feeling, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510422379" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8648/16510422379_2fff5b2640_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a></p>

<p>The Carbon Ski enthusiast will be delighted by this combo. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696559455" title="Salomon Skitracer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8620/16696559455_15231a99b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon Skitracer" /></a></p>

<p>And the Freerider/ Powder enthusiast might consider a Skitracer the next time he drops into 3 meters of fresh pow and loses a ski. Because with the skitracer he’s able to find the ski again when it has hidden in that sweet powder.</p>

<h2 id="klttermusen">Klättermusen</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558580277" title="Klättermusen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8641/16558580277_eba0b13136_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Klättermusen" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://klattermusen.se/">Klättermusen</a> now entered the leguminous plants business. I think that’s rather smart, beans are after all super tasty and if you can make shell material out of them instead of oil - hey, that might mean some idiot oil company might not need to go and ruin the Arctic for us and the polar bears! The Nylon in their new insulation garments is made of Castor Seeds, which Toray and Klättermusen have developed together. At the moment the Nylon is made out of 60% plant-based raw materials but both companies work hard to bring this up to 100%. The plant-based nylon is supposed to have the same qualities as crude oil nylon, and at least trying them one and checking them out I wasn’t able to tell a difference, which is positive. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695481312" title="Klättermusen Castor Seeds Nylon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8595/16695481312_0f6ac6ec97_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen Castor Seeds Nylon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695203101" title="Klättermusen Bore 2.0 Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8583/16695203101_27fc10abf2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen Bore 2.0 Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Bore 2.0 Jacket that Malin models above packs 300 g of 800+ cuin goose down and Primaloft Silver ECO in the shoulders and back of the arms. Its shell is made from the new “Bean Nylon” and has a PFOA-free DWR finish on it, is made in a box wall construction and to minimize seams and cold spots the pockets have been moved in line with the side seams. It’s a super-toasty jacket that has a very nice cut, though the price tag of 500€ is pretty steep. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509118970" title="Klättermusen Frö 2.0 Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/16509118970_cfb512ab41_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Klättermusen Frö 2.0 Vest" /></a></p>

<p>The Frö 2.0 Vest is a midlayer piece for winter use with an Primaloft Silver Active insulation. At 250€ it’s more affordable than the Bore 2.0 Jacket but of course not nearly as warm! The high collar keeps chilly winds from your neck and throat, you can adjust the arm openings to be closed for keeping the warmth inside or open them for a bit of ventilation. The asymmetric zipper is perfect (all zippers should be asymmetric at the top in my opinion) and if you’re not a Vest-kind-guy-or-gal then you also can get the Frö 2.0 as a jacket. </p>

<h2 id="onoo">onoo</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764802102" title="onoo Jackets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/16764802102_60c5935639_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="onoo Jackets" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://onoo.de">onoo</a> is a young start-up from Munich which gathers to the urban cyclists. It was a bit of luck that I met them and I did like what they had to show. The three jackets all have a cycling specific fit and are from materials that are not worried if rain, dirt and abuse is coming its way. I had fun trying them on and speaking with the founder, and do agree with what he said: People know which jacket will suit them. I tried that one above on first and really like how it looks and feels, and while <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558587877/">this one</a> is pretty swell as well it’s maybe a tad less my style?! <a href="http://onoo.de/collection/">Check their collection</a> and pick the jacket which suits yours!</p>

<h2 id="vibram">Vibram</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695377681" title="Vibram Megagrip by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8681/16695377681_42a821081c_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vibram Megagrip" /></a><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510345879" title="Vibram Megagrip by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/16510345879_0724a351fc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Vibram Megagrip" /></a></p>

<p>Getting a meeting at <a href="http://vibram.com">Vibram</a> has been on my agenda for a looooong time, so I was happy that after three years of trying I finally was deemed worthy. The big news at Vibram was their Megagrip sole, which has apparently pretty awesome grip on wet granite. At least they had a nice test parcours built up where you could try that out, but as I was already running around for six hours on the fair I was a bit shy in sharing my sweaty feet smell with others and so kept my shoes on. I’m sure some Megagrip shoe will appear at HiF HQ some day in the future, though, and as we have lots of granite in Finland and also no shortage of rain I will see if it performs as claimed =) If you too want to have Megagrip, you’re in luck: A whole bunch of shoe companies, from Scarpa to Salewa &amp; Arc’teryx, have used the soles in their 2015 shoes which are just hitting the stores, so go and get a pair!</p>

<h2 id="vaude">Vaude</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16145939523" title="Vaude Alphapro Bib Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8743/16145939523_9186a9abb6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude Alphapro Bib Pants" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.vaude.com">Vaude</a> is the “small” Family business which still turns out a lot of new gear. Not everything is ultralight though what Vaude really knows is environmentally friendly production. Lots of good stuff they are doing, and either I’m getting older or they’re getting younger in their styles because I did like quite a few pieces from them. The Alphapro Bib Pants above are Winter Cycling insulation Pants with Polartec® Alpha insulation in them and an Vaude Eco Finish DWR. Mesh suspenders keep the bib in place and a Men’s Advanced Cycling seat cushion ensures you can sit long in the saddle. It will weigh around 440 g and is an ISPO Award winner.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16579728219" title="Vaude Primasoft Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7627/16579728219_bb717ea6e7_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaude Primasoft Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Primasoft Jacket is a ISPO Gold Award winner and another cycling jacket. It combines Primaloft insulation materials with softshell materials in 3 different zones and is aimed at mountain bikers who like to ride in winter (Wait, aren’t they called Fatbikers?!). It has Primaloft Silver in the front and back, breathable inserts under the arms and in the back, a softshell material with a membrane in the front and kidney area and reflective details so you’re seen between dusk &amp; dawn and tips the scales at 485 g. </p>

<h2 id="hestra">Hestra</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16578458280" title="Hestra Gloves Moon Mitt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8740/16578458280_8c9da35550_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hestra Gloves Moon Mitt" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://hestragloves.com">Hestra Gloves</a> make awesome gloves. The Moon Mitt above has a Primaloft insulation, a lambskin palm so you can pick up the kettle and has a liner, too. Toasty hands guaranteed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373244439" title="Hestra Gloves - Bark Powder Tanning by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7436/16373244439_7e472f0544_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Hestra Gloves - Bark Powder Tanning" /></a></p>

<p>New too is their vegetable tanned leather. It has been tanned using natural tannins such as bark powder. The method produces a supple leather with a unique brown colour and is the oldest known way of tanning. As the Press Release reads, <em>“The look and feel of a vegetable tanned leather is hard to beat and it ages naturally in a beautiful way.”</em> and yes, I agree. These vegetable tanned gloves were pretty, and the Abisko and Helags Junior Mitt above were very sweet indeed. </p>

<h2 id="madshus">Madshus</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764783932" title="Madshus IntelliGrip Skin by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8610/16764783932_451518694e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus IntelliGrip Skin" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://madshus.com">Madshus</a> has been making the IntelliGrip Skins, a special climbing skin for XC skis, since five years. Other than the full-length skins for alpine touring skis, IntelliGrip has the climbing skin only in the grip zone of the ski – just like wax or klister. The entire front part is made from polyethylene, the same material as the base itself, and since it worked so well, Madshus now integrates IntelliGrip into the base of skis. The first model is the Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic, a ski made for ambitious cross-country skiers eager to take advantage of a high performance waxing ski but who want to avoid the disadvantages of a conventional NoWax-ski. It
never requires the application of grip wax and avoids the typical disadvantages of NoWax-skis: the glide is much better than on any kind of fish-scale patterns and there is no rattling noise in an icy track.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143559784" title="Madshus Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic Ski by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7283/16143559784_7e473db14e_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Madshus Terrasonic IntelliGrip Classic Ski" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143551434" title="Madshus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8677/16143551434_31fa052024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16143540654" title="Madshus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7619/16143540654_56f8d9dda7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764801372" title="Madshus Glittertind BC Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7631/16764801372_d8c8563f68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Madshus Glittertind BC Boot" /></a></p>

<p>More interesting for the ski-touring/ backcountry cross-country skiing enthusiast, the Backcountry skis from Madshus got a face-lift and now looks freshers as <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">my old ones</a>. Also the Glittertind BC Boot got a small update as the cuff is now a lot higher and is made of MemBrain® softshell material, which I think is a good development. </p>

<h2 id="millet">Millet</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16765840625" title="Millet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7650/16765840625_8e13df02a9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Millet" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.millet.fr/en/">Millet</a> showcased their Triology Series, which is made for alpine pursuits in winter: Ice climbing, mountaineering, winter ascents, mixed climbing. Inspiration for the line comes from the winter ascents of the Eiger, Matterhorn and Grandes Jorasses North Faces of Eric Escoffiers in 1987. The garments are made of the most modern materials available and the “ingredients list” reads like a who-is-who: Polartec® Power Wool™, Polartec® Thermal Pro® Highloft, Tecnowool®, Gore-Tex® Pro, Gore-Tex® Helios Stretch, PrimaLoft®, Windstopper®, Schoeller® Wool Naturetec and K DRY™ - you see these garments will be made for cold, harsh weather and will keep you toasty and dry. Just climbing you need to yourself!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16764693751" title="Millet Trident Winter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7598/16764693751_001e6b1e7f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Millet Trident Winter" /></a></p>

<p>The Trident Winter Mid from Millet is an ISPO Gold Award winner and a lightweight winter boot for all you winter activities - from snow shoeing to glacier hikes, the Trident does it all and keeps your feet toasty thanks to a Primaloft insulation. It’s waterproof and breathable, too, with a DRYEDGE Membrane, and a Vibram sole to give you grip. It is crampon compatible and should be ideal for snowshoeing. </p>

<h2 id="trends">Trends</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509125580" title="Klättermusen by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16509125580_3756bb738e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klättermusen" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074209864" title="Salomon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8606/16074209864_6e71e31b71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16701345681" title="Montane by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8635/16701345681_59f8599c6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Montane" /></a></p>

<p>I think about half of the garment manufacturers I visited had these cuffs where the stretchy rim which keeps the sleeve in place was a few centimetres inside, and not at the end of the sleeve. This does make a lot of sense: It’s easier to put gloves on, or have “free” hands when the gloves are off but at the same time they bring the insulation point further down over the wrist and make the end of the sleeve straighter. The cuffs themselves also should get less dirty and it also might mean warmer wrists as he puffy layer covers them rather nicely. I think it’s a nice development and I’m curious to see if it is better than the traditional cuffs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558575287" title="Scarpa Alien 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8568/16558575287_a6c24294df_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Scarpa Alien 2" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16592948772" title="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8572/16592948772_a6ec53441e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557739541" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8580/16557739541_ecb01807ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.boatechnology.com">Boa Closure System</a> has found its way at this ISPO into a lot of shoes, ski and mountain boots. I tried it on a few shoes and it was indeed very nice to get a good, tight fit and easy to “open” the shoe again. Kamik even used this technology in kid’s boots, which could make it easy for kids to close their shoes on their own. But also trailrunners, hikers, Cross Fitters and Skiers will be able to use the Boa technology, and I reckon it will increase even more in the coming year.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696398812" title="Ortovox Merino Fleece &amp; 260 Merino Ultra Net Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16696398812_bcc607ff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox Merino Fleece &amp; 260 Merino Ultra Net Hoody" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936837154" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7449/15936837154_b9fb3230a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a></p>

<p>Body Mapping isn’t really anything new, but quite a few companies have made some nice efforts with their garments. It just makes a lot of sense that some garments are windproof in the front and super breathable in the back, with stretchy sides for freedom of movement and warm, toasty hoods. There was, however, still a lack of aymmetric zippers in the face area. Lets hope a designer or two reads this and pleases me with asymmetric zippers in the 2016/ 2017 line-up!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557706791" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8660/16557706791_2827d34acb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937067704" title="Salewa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7421/15937067704_fac8cdc72c_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salewa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16372133760" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16372133760_09e8029623_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533491386" title="Haglöfs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7445/16533491386_7bcbb1c691_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs" /></a></p>

<p>The development of Urban (Outdoor) Styles and collections also is on the rise. As I’m myself am getting more interested in this area you might be able to see some more articles on this topic in the future, but for now: If you’d like to wear a Gore-Tex coat because it pours cats &amp; dogs, there’s a handful of outdoor companies which make those - and many more casual outdoor garments - in urban styles, so you don’t need to wear your bright green hardshell to the next client meeting. This will only be of interest to those who really need to look the part when they go to clients, or those who simply don’t want to wear their “outdoor uniform” in the city. Although, then fellow citizens might not think you’re an <a href="http://www.der-postillon.com/2014/12/mann-mit-jack-wolfskin-jacke.html">Extreme Mountaineer</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16074253404" title="Petzl Sitta by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8682/16074253404_1884e493af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl Sitta" /></a></p>

<h2 id="other-ispo-reports">Other ISPO Reports</h2>

<p>There was a host of other great bloggers at the ISPO and I was fortunate to meet many of them. Here’s in no particular order the outdoor bloggers who also wrote about the ISPO 2015: <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2015/02/weltgroesste-sportmesse-ispo-2015-bunt-wars.html">Outdoor Mädchen</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Wandervideoblog">Wander Video Blog</a>, <a href="http://klimbingkorns.de/ispo-2015-munchen-trends-and-happenings/">Klimbing Korns</a>, <a href="http://www.auf-den-berg.de/outdoor-ausrustung/auf-der-ispo-2015/">Auf-den-Berg.de</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoor-blog.com/ispo-2015-eindruecke/">Outdoor Blog</a>, <a href="http://www.zwerg-am-berg.de/tag/ispo/">Zwerg am Berg</a>, <a href="http://linaluftig.de/impressionen-von-der-ispo-2015/">Lina Luftig</a>, <a href="http://www.uptothetop.de/2015/02/06/ispo-2015-fuer-trailrunner/">Up to the Top</a>, <a href="http://www.wusaonthemountain.at/2015/02/ispo-2015-neuheiten-und-bewahrtes-ein.html">Wusa on the Mountain</a>, <a href="http://www.gipfel-glueck.de/ispo-2015-die-gipfelglueck-highlights/">Gipfel Glück</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoor-blog.org/ispo-2015-meine-erlebnisse/">Outdoor-Blog</a>, <a href="http://wandersuechtig.de/outdoor-news-neuheiten-aus-dem-outdoor-bereich/item/1056-die-ispo-2015-das-top-thema-war-die-nachhaltigkeit">Wandersüchtig</a> and <a href="http://www.airfreshing.com/messe/ispo">airfreshing.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696486635" title="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8565/16696486635_d884e3755a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ispo-2015-conclusions">ISPO 2015 Conclusions</h2>

<p><em>“Have you seen something new yet?”</em> / <em>“No, pretty much all the same just with a new marketing twist on it”</em></p>

<p>I had close to 40 meetings in three full days, so you get slightly blind to the stuff you’re being presented. Some stuff is really nice, innovative and cool, while other things are just the same old in a new colour. There are these companies who are honest about that fact, while others do as if they re-invent the wheel every year anew. This can get rather tiring if you get to see yet another synthetic/ Merino wool fabric mix that’s supposed to be the best thing yet and hasn’t been done before. Strangely I have been wearing that kind of garments since a while, though they didn’t have the XYZ Logo on it but were from ABC. Ah well, better take another sip of that good Espresso so I have enough processing power for the rest of the meeting(s).</p>

<p>Similar feelings I get with <em>“Our Responsible Down Standard”</em> being flavoured in yet another new name you haven’t heard of before and a totally fascinating story, which, thanks to the coffee you just had, happily doesn’t make you yawn. I’m not working for one company, so I get to see a bit more. I also read (BOOKS! Magazines! Imagine, death trees) and am curious, trying to question some things. So that’s why I don’t make somersaults if presented the best new thing for 2015 since, ähem, yeah, wait, since when exactly?</p>

<p>Four weeks after the ISPO closed it’s gates I’m hard-pressed to tell you what super-duper awesome new gear should be on your must-watch list - but to be honest, already on the fair I had difficulties with that, as the intro sentence maybe showed. Nevertheless, looking back through my <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157650454379737/">ISPO photos</a> and re-reading my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">ISPO 2015 posts</a> I can say that yes, there has been some interesting new outdoor gear on the show and my top five would be (in no particular order):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ortovox SAM 3D</li>
  <li>The DPS Tour 1 ski touring skis</li>
  <li>The Arc’teryx gloves that can be layered</li>
  <li>The Petzl Sitta harness</li>
  <li>The OMM “sleep system”</li>
</ul>

<p>Except the first one - the Ortovox SAM 3D - nothing utterly blew my mind, but as I wrote in my post about the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">Ortovox</a> news and the SAM 3D, I think this is a superb invention which was - when you see it - so obvious that one can but wonder why something like this hasn’t been thought of before. It’s a very nice executed thing that brings the outdoors indoors and makes your time in the mountains more safe and fun. And that’s what it’s all about, in the end, isn’t it? </p>

<p>And if you liked The ISPO News articles, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> and then share it with your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>, because <strong>sharing is caring</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16372182530" title="VAUDE by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7362/16372182530_d165a44357_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="VAUDE" /></a></p>

<p><em>Ah ja, wait: I was handed a prototype of a fluffy thing that my ideas and feedback has been going in to since last year and which I have tested sicne I’m back home. That is a pretty neat thing, which definitely should be on your list of “things to watch” if you like fluffy warm things.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-03T21:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Where there is gear, there will be gear nerds.</em> ISPO News 3.0 - enjoy this edition responsibly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695183181" title="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/16695183181_479778a57b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ISPO 2015 Gear Finds" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rab">Rab</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076720273" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/16076720273_ea53aff4b5_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://rab.uk.com">Rab</a> had a bunch of really excellent kit on display. The eye-catcher at the start of the booth was the new Expedition 8000 Suit which comes as a Jacket &amp; Salopettes combination (1.340 g and 850 g respectively) or as a suit (1.990 g). Kit for seriously high peaks or when the next ice age comes, but not for this rubbish winter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509074268" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16509074268_1bce8e8408_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>Kit that is more suitable for this winter is the new Rock/ Lifestyle collection which comes with a mighty fine Rab hoody, cool shirts and nice trousers for climbing and chilling at the crag. Women and men will be equally able to dress up in these garments, which already now are very popular with the Rab athletes. The Headwall Hoody above (539 g) feels great, but I liked even more the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076700173/">Elevation Pull-On</a> which had a really nice hood design. The Rockover Pant (305 g) could also become popular with hikers, but it’s made for climbing and allows for freedom of movement.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695361681" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8639/16695361681_19203731d9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>But lets move on to more technical garments, and there was no shortage of these. A big news was that Rab now uses Fluorocarbon-free Hydrophobic Down in all their down garments, which is good news for those of us who use their down garments in cold &amp; wet environments. I tried on a handful of them and they had the Rab-typical great, alpine fit. Many down-garments also now get a body-mapping construction with using different baffles constructions in different areas, like the Electron Jacket pictured above (470 g) which has a Pertex Endurance shell and has Stitch-through Midi baffles in the torso, back and hood and smaller Stitch-through Mini baffles on the side and arms - if you look closely you can see the different baffle sizes in the photo. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16670728016" title="Rab Paradox Pull-On by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16670728016_2d12aeb551_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab Paradox Pull-On" /></a></p>

<p>But it ain’t all down. The Paradox Pull-On uses Polartec® Alpha™ insulation  with a super-stretchy lining and shell. A deep zipper helps with dumping heat on fast ascents or runs, and if you don’t need it the 360 g top packs away small. This was a really nice piece and would be great as a autumn layering piece or on its own on cool days.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509065258" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16509065258_987eed6411_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695337601" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/16695337601_74ef7c6005_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509251460" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8676/16509251460_80916e78a3_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Rab" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076708763" title="Rab by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8591/16076708763_f2d4130b34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rab" /></a></p>

<p>There was a bunch more really innovative backpacking/ hillwalking/ climbing/ mountaineering &amp; lifestyle garments to be seen, so you can start saving your $€£ for the coming winter because you’ll want to pick up some of these.</p>

<h2 id="dps-skis">DPS Skis</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16670544676" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8617/16670544676_b52b5f54f1_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a></p>

<p>What I love about these trade fairs is meeting the people who love what they can do with their products. At <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com">DPS Skis</a> I asked my contact which of these he’s riding. <em>“I love the <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com/en/skis/all-mountain-mixed-snow/wailer-99.html">Wailer 99</a> with <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/dynafit-tlt-radical-st2-anniversary-touring-binding-90mm/?pid=81">Dynafit Radical bindings</a> and a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/la-sportiva-syborg-tourenskischuhe/">La Sportiva Syborg</a> boot”</em> he told me, and then and there I knew that we’d get along just fine! That’s a pretty awesome and lightweight setup, and best of all: You too could get it! Because unlike other manufacturers DPS Skis sells their brand-new and ISPO Award winning <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com/en/skis.html">Tour 1 Skis</a> already now. So the Tour 1 are lightweight (1.350 g for the 176 cm Wailer 99!) backcountry touring skis which also perform very nicely on the way down the mountain. Because you shouldn’t invest energy in long tours if you can not enjoy the descent!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076525313" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16076525313_102f653bcf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509082860" title="DPS Skis Tour 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16509082860_2ee66fff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Skis Tour 1" /></a></p>

<h2 id="patagonia">Patagonia</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695584932" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8650/16695584932_5080e45b2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a> Backcountry Experience collection is divided into five lines: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Lift Access, for quick-strike, done-in-a-day missions</li>
  <li>Free Tour, for more committing powder missions that require traveling a little deeper into the backcountry</li>
  <li>Steeps, for descents extreme enough to require technical climbing skills</li>
  <li>Alpine Touring, for traveling deep and extensively through the snow-covered backcountry</li>
  <li>Approach, for when climbing is the primary objective and skis are necessary tools for access</li>
</ul>

<p>These lines have been developed in cooperation of the Snow and Alpine Teams from Patagonia, and what I saw at the fair looked really swell. Technical fabrics, functional fit and design, all made with the Patagonia-typical environmental thoughts in mind. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076667093" title="Patagonia by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8588/16076667093_4063b2fdd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia" /></a></p>

<p>Another big news is the completely renewed baselayer line-up. The collection is structured into four categories: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Daily, for the stuff you wear each day to the office or grocery shopping by bike in winter</li>
  <li>Lightweight, having the lightest-weight, fastest-drying and best-wicking baselayers</li>
  <li>Midweight, being the most versatile baselayer with the greatest comfort range</li>
  <li>Thermal Weight, the warmest, most breathable baselayer with minimal bulk</li>
</ul>

<p>This is applicable to both the Merino and Capilene® baselayers. Capilene® got an updated fabric that is made from recycled Polyester with better odour control and wicking. The fit has been made the “Slim Fit” across the last three categories (Lightweight, Midweight, Thermal Weight) and everything is recyclable through the Common Threads recycling programme. The baselayers felt soft and nice to the touch, but of course only wearing them one could start to make an opinion on them. The Merino line is made from Patagonian wool and has very nice stripe designs and also felt great. And as you can see above - the whole packaging has been renewed. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510473569" title="Patagonia Denim by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8658/16510473569_ae4d2de148_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Denim" /></a></p>

<p>And then there are Jeans. I haven’t worn a jeans in probably five years but it’s still the de-facto pants for many people. I know that Jeans/ Denim manufacturing is a filthy business, so it’s good to see that Patagonia is setting out to change that. Patagonia® Denim uses 100% organic cotton grown without polluting fertilizers, poisonous pesticides or herbicides. A low-impact dyeing process enables them to dramatically reduce water, energy and chemical use and produce less carbon dioxide. Patagonia also never distress their denim with harsh chemicals or other methods. And the garments are Fair Trade Certified™ for sewing, which makes Patagonia Denim the way denim should be made. Here you can read more about the <a href="http://www.google.fi/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;ved=0CCAQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.iswa.org%2Findex.php%3FeID%3Dtx_iswaknowledgebase_download%26documentUid%3D3184&amp;ei=RW71VPe1D-LXyQOetoDACA&amp;usg=AFQjCNHqwl6f-JkE2wcteEE4OLckX1xvWA&amp;sig2=PCCiF7jMnwRhXQBpOAYj9A&amp;bvm=bv.87269000,d.bGQ">Environmental impact of denim product</a>.</p>

<h2 id="marmot">Marmot</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16489359707" title="Marmot Cerro Torre Jacket, Quasar Hoody &amp; Alpinist Bib by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/16489359707_25edc395ba_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Marmot Cerro Torre Jacket, Quasar Hoody &amp; Alpinist Bib" /></a></p>

<p>The Cerro Torre Jacket from <a href="http://marmot.de">Marmot</a> got a full technical revamp and now promises even better performance than its predecessor. Made from the new 3-layer Gore-Tex® C-Knit fabric the jacket is super-light and stays durably waterproof and windproof. The C-Knit gives it a soft feel and an improved breathability rating, which means even better wear comfort. A snug fitting hood, pockets positioned above the level of a backpack waist belt or climbing harness, extra-long Pit-Zips and a two-way front zipper make this a versatile jacket that’s equally well-suited for hiking, trekking, all mountain skiing and freeriding.</p>

<h2 id="lundhags">Lundhags</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16510378169" title="Lundhags Cobbler Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8680/16510378169_b0dc6473cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lundhags Cobbler Boot" /></a></p>

<p>It was my first visit at <a href="http://lundhags.se">Lundhags</a> and it was very nice. I got a pair of their superb <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/lundhags-guide-bc-backcountry-skischuhe/">Guide BC Boots</a> last year for Nordic Touring Skating and skiing and really like them, so it was good to see more of their gear. The big news at the Swedish company was their introduction of casual footwear. I like the look of the Cobbler Boot above, which has a mid height shaft that’s very flexible. I would have liked a more minimalist sole myself, but I reckon the majority of people will like it just as it is - after all, The Beatles wore shoes like this! </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509112040" title="Lundhags Termik Jacket and Termik W&#x27;s Anorak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8674/16509112040_77a9bb082c_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Lundhags Termik Jacket and Termik W&#x27;s Anorak" /></a></p>

<p>The Termik Jacket and Termik W’s Anorak above are made of Lundhags Polycotton material that has a parafin wax layer. The material has a 16.000 g/ m2/ 24h breathability rating (minimum) and a 20.000 mm hydrostatic head. The Anorak has a separate inner pocket in the large chest pocket, and a long zipper for easy entry/ exit as well as ventilation. It’s a classic-looking garment made of modern fabrics (well, Polycotton has been around a bit under other names) that surely will find a lot of fans.</p>

<h2 id="ortovox">Ortovox</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16671498646" title="Ortovox SAM 3D by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8598/16671498646_6178105b7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox SAM 3D" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://ortovox.com">Ortovox</a> is a company I also really like. Creative &amp; innovative products, great materials and colours, friendly and passionate people - what’s not to like? Take the <a href="http://www.ortovox.com/accessories/e_329113">SAM 3D mountain model</a>: It’s a 3D mountain model for avalanche education that they created after a Mountain Guide contacted them and said <em>“Look, I have an idea”</em>. This model allows you to recognize and interpret topography, understand contour lines, lets you estimate slope steepness and and and. It comes with a map, a set of water-based markers, a handbook and a Clinometer. This is such an awesome and much needed product that one can actually just winder: Why hasn’t anyone thought of this before? That’s what the ISPO also thought and made it a Gold Winner!</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Kbok5Ie4Z4o" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696398812" title="Ortovox Merino Fleece by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16696398812_bcc607ff32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ortovox Merino Fleece" /></a></p>

<p>Alright, that’s not all though. The Merino Fleece Plus Jacket on the left use 350 g/ m2 of wool fleece and is mighty warm and looks stylish, too! Then there’s the Merino Ultra Net Hoody on the right above is a finely woven Merino shell and a large-mesh lining this should be bomber warm in really cold weather as it will trap a lot of air next too skin. The hoody will tip the scales at 300 g and because I love hoodies this one is high on my list of <em>“Wanna try!”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077491093" title="Ortovox Piz Palü Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8622/16077491093_50ab54c97a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Ortovox Piz Palü Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Piz Palü Jacket rounds out the layering system from Ortovox and is a super-technical jacket. It uses Pertex Microlight, schoeller naturetec, Swiss Wool and Merino wool to create one athletic touring jacket. It weighs 424 g and has a body-mapping construction which places the mentioned materials there where they make the most sense.</p>

<h2 id="black-diamond">Black Diamond</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509300620" title="Black Diamond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/16509300620_330b2ab9c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond" /></a></p>

<p>Since <a href="http://eu.blackdiamondequipment.com/en/homepage">Black Diamond</a> entered the apparel market they have been going from strength to strength, refining each season their line and making the garments better and better. This kind of approach is rewarded, and so their Misson Pants with Pieps Pocket won an ISPO Gold Award. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16509299980" title="Black Diamond Viper Ice Tool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8599/16509299980_c69edd9bde_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Viper Ice Tool" /></a></p>

<p>I did like the Viper Ice Tool which weighs 570 g with the Hammer or 595 g with the Adze and has an adjustable FlickLock Pommel - which, yes, employs the same FlickLock system as you already know it from BD Poles. It has a Titan pick and the head is modular, so on days where you need two Hammers or Adzes you can leave the other one at home (saving 80 g/ 105 g respectively, which yes, means, the “naked” tool weighs 490 g). This makes it the lightest BD ice tool yet, and being made from hydroformed aluminium these will last, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16695655422" title="Black Diamond Vapor Carbon 1 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8565/16695655422_8091aeb8cd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Vapor Carbon 1" /></a></p>

<p>The Vapor Carbon 1 poles weigh 310 g for the pair which makes it one of the lightest ski poles on the market. It’s a one-piece pole that’s made for ski-mountaineering - but that shouldn’t hinder the dedicated gram-weenie to use them for backpacking and pitching his shelter! Available in lengths of 115 to 145 cm in 10 cm steps they can be equipped with Powder Baskets and Freeride Baskets.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16696687575" title="Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 32 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8634/16696687575_5c7ae756d5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 32" /></a></p>

<p>The Dawn Patrol 32 is a mid-sized lightweight ski pack that can accommodate either skis or a snowboard and is AvaLung-Ready. The AvaLung Element is a streamlined, modular AvaLung unit that attaches to AvaLung-Ready packs and is a lightweight, affordable avalanche safety technology that significantly increases your fresh air supply in the event of a burial. The <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-avalung-brg/?pid=81">AvaLung</a> almost triples the air supply when you’re in an avalanche and at 100€ it is substantially cheaper than ABS packs et al.</p>

<h2 id="haglfs">Haglöfs</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939316493" title="Haglöfs Hellner Gear by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7407/15939316493_bcfe6cd8b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs Hellner Gear" /></a></p>

<p>The new gear from <a href="http://www.haglofs.com/">Haglöfs</a> was interesting. The skiing gear developed with Marcus Hellner will delight the cross-country readers. Lots of Windstopper garments which keep cold wind out but are highly breathable, with body-mapping constructions and smart details like magnet closures. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373587917" title="Haglöfs Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/16373587917_55fcaed82a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Haglöfs Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Barrier Pro III Belay Jacket won an ISPO Gold Award and is a belaying jacket that’s mighty warm - too hot for me to wear indoors, so I quickly put it off again. Filled with QuadFusion™ Pro that has a windproof and waterproof membrane it keeps in the warm air generated by the body but is breathable enough to not be uncomfortable. The fit is to be worn over a Hardshell/ Softshell which is in my opinion also a great way to wear your insulation jacket during hiking/ skiing breaks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939328973" title="Haglöfs Mountain Pro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7454/15939328973_0e1627983c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Haglöfs Mountain Pro" /></a></p>

<p>The Mountain Pro will only be available for Mountain Guides and SAR Employees - people who work in the mountains. Developed in cooperation with mountain professionals and the Swiss Alpine Rescue the garments are super burly and consists of the ROC Rescue Jacket, BARRIER Rescue Jacket, ROC Rescue Pants and ROC Rescue 40 backpack and are made to be
functional twelve months a year and be adaptable, not just to different weather conditions and temperatures, but also to different types of rescue missions. </p>

<h2 id="montane">Montane</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16080317554" title="Montane Primino Baselayer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8562/16080317554_d85f3c7c29_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Primino Baselayer" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.montane.co.uk">Montane</a>’s big news were the new Primino Baselayers, which combine Primaloft® yarns with Merino wool. These baselayers come 220 g and 140 g weights, with gloves, long johns and boxer shorts accompanying the tops. The idea is that the Merino wool draws vapour sweat away from the body whilst the Primaloft® yarns wick liquid sweat across the outer surface, allowing it to dry quickly. I got one here and will put it to the test so expect an update on them before next winter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16495352457" title="Montane Black Ice 2.0 Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8564/16495352457_026e758e44_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Black Ice 2.0 Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Black Ice 2.0 Jacket is Montane’s warmest down jacket and weighs 679 g in Size M. It is filled with 250 g of Primaloft Gold Insulation Down Blend and has a Freeflow Ultralite 38 g/m2 shell. The torso has a Boxwall construction while the sleeves have a Stitch-through construction. The hood has a wired peak and fits over a helmet. Toasty warm it was!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16701343571" title="Montane Hi-Q Luxe Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16701343571_986c395d26_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Montane Hi-Q Luxe Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>Equally warm was the Hi-Q Luxe Jacket, which is filled with synthetic Primaloft Gold Luxe. Primaloft Gold Luxe is a new twist on the Thermoball technology of The North Face (which also was developed by Primaloft) I feel, which should be just like down but keeps you warm even when wet (unlike normal down, which collapses). The Hi-Q Luxe tips the scale at 575 g in Size M so isn’t too light, but it packs small and would make a good layering piece on cold days - but thanks to the Pertex Quantum shell you also can wear it on its own!</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-23T20:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/ispo-2015/">ISPO 2015</a> gear bonanza continues with sweet new hardware and soft goods for backpackers, climbers, skiers and hikers!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557811671" title="Dynafit Khion Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7367/16557811671_d2d2a49edc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit Khion Carbon" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html">Read Part 1 here</a></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-research">Outdoor Research</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371946330" title="Outdoor Research M&#x27;s Diode Hooded Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16371946330_4138aba056_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research M&#x27;s Diode Hooded Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>At <a href="http://outdoorresearch.com/">Outdoor Research</a> a whole lotta new gear was to be tried on and tested indoors, like the M’s Diode Hooded Jacket up there. A jacket made with Body Mapping technology it uses DWR-treated down and Primaloft Gold. The latter is on the shoulders, hood, top of the sleeves and hips - areas which usually get more wet - while the core is filled with warm down to keep your torso toasty. All that is under a Pertex® Endurance 2L shell where the Primaloft is and the down is protected by Pertex® Quantum. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533381316" title="Outdoor Research by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/16533381316_95ee1e8e2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research" /></a></p>

<p>The Uberlayer Hooded Jacket (the blue on on the left) on the other hand trusts Polartec Alpha insulation completely to keep you warm, but not too hot. It has a stretch mesh lining which wicks sweat quickly away form your baselayer, where it meets on the Polartec Alpha insulation which further transports it to the outside. There’s plenty of pockets on the Uberlayer, a helmet-compatible hood and the shell is also wind and water resistant. The Men’s Uberlayer is 563 g in Size L, the Women’s is 472 in Size M.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558277002" title="Outdoor Research Furio Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8582/16558277002_3d65a62968_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Furio Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Furio Jacket uses the new Gore-Tex® C-Knit fabric in the shoulders, hood and hip, Paclite in the rest of the jacket and is fully seam taped. It has a Standard Fit and is 535 g light and is made for your alpine adventures where it will keep you dry, warm and protected in case the weather turns nasty. I do like OR’s TorsoFlo™ technology which are hem-to-bicep side zips that offer ventilation when the going gets steep. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936813154" title="Outdoor Research Luminary Sensor Glove by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7299/15936813154_921a82e670_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Luminary Sensor Glove" /></a></p>

<p>The Luminary Sensor Glove is an alpine climbing and skiing glove that allows you to take <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> photos without taking the gloves off. The indoor test the glove mastered without difficulties as you can see above. Made from Windstopper the shell gloves are windproof and water-resistant while the warm, removable wool blend liners keep your fingers toasty. The dexterity was good in these and with removable liners you’re able to dry them in your quilt during the night. The pair in L will weigh 236 g. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371894050" title="Outdoor Research Extravert Glove by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16371894050_52555e3dc0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Research Extravert Glove" /></a></p>

<p>The Extravert Gloves have a stretch nylon shell outer, a durable goat leather palm with textured fingertips and a warm wool lining. These ski-touring gloves will keep you warm when you’re skinning up and shed the powder on your turns down. The pair in L will be 165 g light.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559340835" title="Outdoor Research Untold Balaclava by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7427/16559340835_8430a96a97_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Untold Balaclava" /></a></p>

<p>The Untold Balaclava is made from acrylic and weighs 51 g. It’s a convertible balaclava that can be transformed into a cap when you roll the lower part up. It’s probably a very nice piece for winter use when the conditions change from cold and shady to sunny.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533325976" title="Outdoor Research Toasty Beanie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/16533325976_46f3f6dbcb_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Outdoor Research Toasty Beanie" /></a></p>

<p>And then there were literally about a dozen new hats and even more gloves - after all that’s what Outdoor Research does very well. I did like the stylish hats and beanies which would be functional on the trail and stylish at the Aprés Bar after your hike. Lots of nice stuff coming from them, so keep an eye out for them.</p>

<h2 id="vertical-life--zlagboard">Vertical-Life / Zlagboard</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16588486191" title="ZlagBoards! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7336/16588486191_5df67be72b_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="ZlagBoards!" /></a></p>

<p>I’m pretty psyched about the news from <a href="https://www.vertical-life.info">Vertical-Life</a> and especially <a href="https://zlagboard.com">Zlagboard</a>. The latter I tried already at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/outdoor-2014-wrap-up-and-conclusions.html">OutDoor</a> and liked it but was wondering if the price was too high. Well, it seems my ideas were heard and the Zlagboard Team not just dropped the price on the Zlagboard Pro to 250€ but also introduced the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-mini">Zlagboard Mini</a> which will retail for 150€ and also the <a href="https://zlagboard.com/zlagboard-vario">Zlagboard Vario</a> which sells for 190€ and which allows you to attach a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/trainingsboards/">training board</a> you already have (like a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beastmaker-2000-series-trainingsboard/">Beastmaker</a>) to it. That’s not all, though, as the Team also has updated the App and there’s now a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html">Gimme Kraft!</a> training plan available and the option to create your own. I really love this and you can stay tuned for a review of the Zlagboard on these digital pages soon.</p>

<p>Vertical Life is the publishing arm of the business and they do have some <a href="http://guide.vertical-life.info/en/publications/">superb Guidebooks</a> available. Add to that already good line-up are four more guides in 2015: Sportclimbing in Südtirol, Bouldering in Südtirol, Arco Plaisir and Zillertal Multi-Pitch. Besides the dead tree versions they also will be coming as a digital app which you can download to your phone. </p>

<h2 id="salewa">Salewa</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371948468" title="Salewa North X Ice Axe, Speed Ascent shoe &amp; Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8665/16371948468_fbfd3529e8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Salewa North X Ice Axe, Speed Ascent shoe &amp; Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.salewa.com">Salewa</a> had equally interesting hardware and soft good news. Lets start with the hard goods: The North X ice axe is a 52,5 cm long and 540 g light technical ice axe for technical mountaineering. It has a steel head and blade, a 7075 aluminium shaft and a steel spike which makes it both light and durable. The hand rest can be precision-adjusted to the correct height with one hand without tools. The pick is interchangeable and the lower shaft is insulated and it has a integrated belay loop which has a 5kN breaking strength. It’s an ISPO Award Winner, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939441043" title="Salewa Ice screws by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/15939441043_ccedddc1a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Ice screws" /></a></p>

<p>I tried the new Salewa ice screws and did like them. They are an all-in-one solution: The come equipped with a Quickdraw and cap to protect the sharp points and thread, have an integrated crank and they rack very efficiently on your harness. They will be available in three lengths if I remember correctly and will start at 80€. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558505442" title="Salewa Vert Helmet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8636/16558505442_2232827397_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Vert Helmet" /></a></p>

<p>The Vert helmet is certified as both a climbing and skiing helmet, which makes it an ideal choice for ski-mountaineers. It has an heat-dissipating insulation and removable ear pads, the total goggle integration ensures a clear view and works together with anti-fog systems in modern ski eyewear. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533605556" title="Salewa Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/16533605556_0027b98732_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Sesvenna Ski-Touring Jacket is part of the Sesvenna Ski Touring Collection which Gore-Tex, Polartec and Windproof fabrics with Schoeller fabrics and Tyrol and merino wool for garments that combine functionality and traditional looks. They’re made with ski mountaineers in mind and are wind- and water-resistant, warm and breathable. The jacket above also won an ISPO Award and looked pretty good, a fresh design. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939447073" title="Salewa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8647/15939447073_322dfecf19_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salewa" /></a></p>

<p>And then there were several other new things coming from the Italian company. The Speed Ascent shoe won an ISPO Award, the climbing &amp; bouldering line gets some fresh new designs, there’s a line of products which are 100% made in Italy.</p>

<h2 id="garmin">Garmin</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15967528014" title="Garmin fēnix 3 Sapphire by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7357/15967528014_ed75eaba99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Garmin fēnix 3 Sapphire" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.garmin.com/">Garmin</a> presented the <a href="http://fenix3.garmin.com/en-US/">fēnix 3</a> and fēnix 3 Sapphire which had some major updates on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">fēnix</a> I have. The major difference between the two models is that the latter comes with a scratch resistant sapphire lens and a steel wristband (in addition to a normal plastic one) which allows you to wear your outdoor watch to the office. The watch is made for a host of activities, from backpacking to trailrunning to Triathlon. I think it’s a great looking watch, but that ain’t all of course: Under the hood the watch got some major updates: A color display that can be read in the sun (although I had major difficulties getting a good photo under them lamps indoors =), a stainless steel EXO™ antenna with GPS + GLONASS support for fast fix and accuracy, a host of Fitness training features &amp; Outdoor navigation features and Connect IQ™ compatibility for customized apps, widgets, watch faces and data fields. The fēnix 3 should be available in about a month or two, and retails for 500€ to 600€.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16620722281" title="Garmin epix by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8599/16620722281_eb4fc2167b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Garmin epix" /></a></p>

<p>The Garmin epix on the other hand is a GPS watch which comes with a European Freetime Map pre-installed. It also has a Chroma colour display, an EXO Antenna for GPS &amp; GLONASS reception, several sports profiles and connects with several accessories. The  idea is that here you really have a high-resolution, color, touchscreen GPS/GLONASS mapping watch with worldwide, shaded relief basemap and 8 gb memory for further maps. I do like the classic look and the epix will be 500€ and also available in about two months. </p>

<h2 id="mountain-equipment">Mountain Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557871341" title="Mountain Equipment Compressor ¾ Pant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8655/16557871341_a8f03e3708_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Compressor ¾ Pant" /></a></p>

<p>Filled with PrimaLoft® GOLD between a Helium 30 fabric that’s windproof is the Compressor Pant and the Compressor ¾ Pant which I model above. The ¾ Pant version tips the scales at 240 g and the length is chosen so it stays above your skiing boots. It’s easy to put on with a full-length zippers on each side, and it packs into its own seat pocket. The ¾ Compressor will be 160€ will the full length version will set you back a tenner more and you’re able to carry 95 g extra, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373263039" title="Mountain Equipment by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7416/16373263039_e615d2d75a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment" /></a></p>

<p>The Switch Vest is a hybrid garment that combines Polartec® Alpha® in the front and Polartec® Power Dry® 225 Fleece at the sides and back. The idea is that the breathable and warm Alpha® insulation keeps away the headwind while you can lose the sweat and heat via the back when you’re skinning, running or climbing up a mountain. At 240 g and 100€ it’s looks like an interesting piece for the fast &amp; light readership. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373271959" title="Mountain Equipment Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/16373271959_9154aec292_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Equipment Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant" /></a></p>

<p>The Diamir Jacket &amp; Diamir Pant is <a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.co.uk">Mountain Equipments</a> foray into the Ski-touring market. Both garments are made from burly GoreTex Pro 80D. The Super Alpine Hood has been developed further for ski helmets and has an integrated collar, and the Alpine Fit with articulated sleeves ensures you have the freedom of movement you need when you earn your turns. The jacket also has a removable snow-guard while the pants have removable gaiters &amp; suspenders. A pocket on the thigh stores your avalanche beacon. The combo weighs together 1.335 g and will set you back 1100€. </p>

<h2 id="la-sportiva">La Sportiva</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16592940652" title="La Sportiva Ultra Raptor GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7410/16592940652_6b78d41f9e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Ultra Raptor GTX" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.sportiva.com">La Sportiva</a>’s News I’d divided in these Categories: Trailrunning, Mountaineering, High-Altitude News. Lets take a look at them in that order. The Ultra Raptor GTX weighs 410 g per shoe, has a 12 mm drop and a FriXion XF sole with the Trail Bite heel stabilizer which enhances the downhill grip. The shoe isn’t new, but the colour is =) </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16406374858" title="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7365/16406374858_8b978a4691_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX" /></a></p>

<p>The Crossover 2.0 GTX isn’t new either, but at 370 g light per shoe it’s worth a mention. This is the third shoe from La Sportiva in this round-up with an integrated gaiter, and considering this shoe is made for winter trailrunning (and hence is ideal to be “misused” as a backpacking shoe) and Winter being the sorry excuse it currently is I’m sure a few will be interested in it. Beneath the water-repellant gaiter you find a trailrunning shoe with 10 mm drop, a Ortholite Mountain Running Ergonomic footbed and underneath is a FriXion AT sole with Impact Brake System and AT Grip zone. La Sportiva offers a Grip Spike kit which allows you to get even more grip on ice. Good stuff.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15971418784" title="Trango Ice Cube GTX by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7370/15971418784_e2534e7f0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trango Ice Cube GTX" /></a></p>

<p>The Trango Ice Cube GTX is a new boot and carries on the trend of integrated gaiters. Made for up to 4.000 m in terms of its warmth rating the 1.380 g heavy pair of boots comes with a Schoeller fabric gaiter that’s stretchy and water-resistant, a Gore-Tex Insulated Comfort lining, an insulated carbon Honeycomb Tech 3 mm insole and a La Sportiva Cube sole, made by Vibram® with the Impact Brake System lugs on the heel and a climbing zone at the toe. It’s so lightweight because of the seamless construction method on the uppers which use the Thermo Tech Injection™ technology. The boot is obviously fully crampon compatible and can be resoled.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16407729549" title="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7327/16407729549_3a1b2b283c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="La Sportiva Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro" /></a></p>

<p>The G2 SM, which stands for Gasherbrum 2 Simone Moro, is a sexy boot. Oh, its functional too. What I liked about it the most was the sense of adventure it communicates - Gasherbrum 2, Karakoram, 8.035 m, and of course the first winter ascent of Cory Richards, Denis Urubko and Simone Moro in 2011. It’s a very technical boot: Integrated Cordura gaiter, internal shell with BOA® quick lacing System, HoneyComb Tech midsole in carbon fibre, Vibram® Matterhorn sole with Impact Brake System lugs and a removable liner boot. It’s a super warm boot made for expeditions to the high ranges, and the pair will weigh 1.940 g. </p>

<p>Otherwise garments got some colour updates, there were a few rather nice new carbon skis and ski boots. </p>

<h2 id="grivel">Grivel</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16593580955" title="Grivel by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/16593580955_e6acb0d845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Grivel" /></a></p>

<p>I do like what <a href="http://www.grivel.com">Grivel</a> does. Take the A&amp;D above: It’s an Ascender that also allows you to descend. Just thread the rope through the slit in the A&amp;D, clip it into a carabiner, open the Ascender part and you can abseil down. This allows you to use one less piece of kit, and the ascender is also easy to unlock when the teeth have dug deep into your rope. It works with ropes from 8,3 mm to 13 mm in diameter when going up and 7,3 mm to 13 mm when going down and weighs 259 g. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16001900693" title="Grivel Tech Machine Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8642/16001900693_54f2653a73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grivel Tech Machine Carbon" /></a></p>

<p>Then there’s the new Tech Machine which will be available as an aluminium and carbon version. The former is 660 g for the tool, the carbon version saves you 100 g - they work both just as good, as Stevie Haston ensured me - though the carbon one will be warmer. The interesting new development on these is the G Bone Shaft, which should allow for an ergonomic grip along the whole shaft. This technology will also be used in the Air Tech Evo ice axe (which also gets a Hammer Version next winter) and the North Machine ice tool. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15973805963" title="Grivel Mountain Runner Comp backpack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/15973805963_176c1e7bbe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Grivel Mountain Runner Comp backpack" /></a></p>

<p>The Mountain Runner Comp backpack is a 450 g light trailrunning pack with 5 l volume. These packs were designed with experience from the Tor de Geants Race, are one-size-fits-all, have multiple pockets to carry your gear and even allow you to carry your ice axes or poles on it. </p>

<p>Oh, and <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-lambda-twin-lock-hms-karabiner/">Twin Gate carabiners</a> are now in stores. Get one to try them, I do quite like them.</p>

<h2 id="dynafit">Dynafit</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533475316" title="Dynafit by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7431/16533475316_657af5fcd2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit" /></a></p>

<p>If I am at the ISPO a visit to <a href="http://dynafit.com">Dynafit</a> is always in order - gotta know what this company is up to if you like lightweight kit. The Chugach is a free touring ski which will launch for the 2015/ 2016 season and is for free riders who want to conquer new terrain by mountaineering means. Named after Alaska’s Chugach Mountains which represent untouched wilderness and awesome descents, the ski offers an optimal ratio of surface area to weight, which is 1.950 g. It has a double ellipse rocker construction and enables maximum edging on steep, icy terrain without losing the playful lightness when initiating turns. This is going to be a ski to watch if you like to play in big, wild mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373204349" title="Dynafit Khion Carbon by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7339/16373204349_020299b5ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dynafit Khion Carbon" /></a></p>

<p>The Khiôn is a free touring boot which combines the rigidity and support of an alpine downhill boot with the comfort and lightness of a modern ski touring boot on the ascent. The boot will be available as a Khiôn MS model, a stiffer Khiôn Carbon version which adds more performance on the descent and also a Women’s version. The boot will give you performance and precision with direct power transmission and maximal support thanks to the new Precision Lock System which enables the various parts of the boot to work together as a torsionally stiff unit. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557822481" title="Dynafit Radical 2 Binding by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7302/16557822481_ab6d563ebc_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Dynafit Radical 2 Binding" /></a></p>

<p>The Radical 2 Binding takes a step forward in safety and comfort 30 years after the invention of the frameless system. The Radical 2 weighs 599 g and the biggest update is the a pivoting toe piece combined with the Step in Side Towers. This has several advantages: It functions as an additional release mechanism and works to prevent early release from side impacts. It has a a precise release mechanism at the toe and heel piece with a release value between 4 and 10 for the Radical 2 ST version or up to 12 for the Radical FT.</p>

<h2 id="mountain-hardwear">Mountain Hardwear</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937000064" title="Mountain Hardwear HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8650/15937000064_16b2b942f8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Mountain Hardwear HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.com">Mountain Hardwear</a> HyperLamina Flame sleeping bag and it’s sibling Spark are synthetic sleeping bags which employ a central zipper for you to get in and comfortably sit in your bag during your morning coffee. The Spark will be 737 g and the Flame 1106 g with temperature ratings to 0°C and -6°C respectively. The bags are made with MH’s Lamina™ construction which welds the Thermal.Q™ insulation to the shell and lining, eliminating the cold spots caused by traditional stitching. Bodymapping technology was employed throughout the top of the bag to concentrate warmth where you need it most – around your core and feet. The bags will set you back 220 or 240€.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> Then <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ISPO 2015 News I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-17T21:59:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/ispo-2015-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The ISPO is the annual trade fair where outdoor companies present their autumn &amp; winter collections for the coming seasons. I travelled down to München once again to check out what new kit we can expect next winter and here is the first batch of my finds.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371800168" title="VAUDE by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7308/16371800168_23b1e71f13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="VAUDE" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="arcteryx">Arc’teryx</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557800531" title="Arc&#x27;teryx by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8579/16557800531_dab20040d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373187969" title="Arc&#x27;teryx by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7358/16373187969_85d819e367_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx" /></a></p>

<p>The big news at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> is that their glove line has been completely re-designed and like their clothing the gloves now work as a layer system. I tried on the different gloves and really loved them and found them better than the already great <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-alpha-sv-glove-black-xs/?pid=81">Alpha SV Gloves</a> I’m using right now. Most of the new gloves don’t use leather anymore which makes them more flexible and allows for better dexterity, and the liner gloves and shells also can be used completely on their own. For durability the gloves are made from a 3 layer Gore-Tex fabric with TPU laminates on the palm and fingers so that they’re highly abrasion resistant (and waterproof!). The Beta Shell Glove (110 g in M) &amp; Atom Glove Liner (90 g in M) are for the climbers and mountaineers while the Lithic Glove (an ISPO Gold Award Winner) is an insulated glove for backcountry skiers &amp; snowboarders that uses three kinds of PrimaLoft® synthetic insulation in the construction. Also the Mittens I tried on where fantastic and I imagine if you’re a lot out in really cold winter then these gloves will be high on your list.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558836791" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7363/16558836791_9d2067f3a3_b.jpg" width="751" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>The Canadians also will be using the new Gore-Tex® C-Knit™ fabric in their new Zeta LT Jacket which will weigh in at 335 g for a Men’s Medium and the even lighter Norvan Jacket (215 g in M). C-Knit from Gore should be ideal for hikers &amp; backpackers as it combines the durable Gore-Tex Pro membrane with an extremely thin, dense &amp; lightweight circular knit backer on the inside. The result makes the jacket much softer next to the skin and also less noisy and stiff. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15940472133" title="Nuclei AR Jacket by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/15940472133_4b223c94fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="536" alt="Nuclei AR Jacket" /></a></p>

<p>And the new Nuclei AR Jacket (also an ISPO Gold Award Winner) is an all-round belay parka that combines 100 grams/m2 of Coreloft synthetic insulation with a seam taped Windstopper exterior, making it a warm, windproof and water-resistant insulation piece that you can put on when you’re hanging in the middle of a frozen waterfall and are belaying your mate. The Nuclei in Medium will tip the scales at 465 g and set you back 475 €.</p>

<h2 id="primus">Primus</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16557911141" title="Primus Winter Gas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7411/16557911141_182ddf4be5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Winter Gas" /></a></p>

<p>Lots of good stuff coming from <a href="http://www.primus.eu">Primus</a>. <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/primus-winter-gas-254488-braun/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Winter Gas is now available in stores</a> (and expect a spot review from me this week on it, too) which is good news for winter adventurers. It was announced at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor 2014</a> and now helps you to cook, melt snow and boil water in cold temperatures. Seriously good stuff.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559583855" title="Primus Silencer by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7421/16559583855_94195b900f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Primus Silencer" /></a></p>

<p>Have you seen my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/02/primus-omnilite-ti.html">Omnilite Ti with Gas in Winter Video</a>? Do you remember how LOUD the stove was? That’s a thing of the past with the Primus Silencer. The Silencer is mounted in a few seconds by unscrewing the upper part of the OmniLite Ti burner and replacing it with the Silencer and only adds 17 g to the stove weight but doesn’t reduce fuel efficiency or power output. It is not suitable for diesel, kerosene or jet fuel and will set you back 60 €, but the silence it gives you is well worth that in my opinion.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16374728849" title="Primus Stove Paw Ti by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7281/16374728849_9d0556f5f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="941" alt="Primus Stove Paw Ti" /></a></p>

<p>Serious winter backpackers usually take a plate of sort along for their stoves when they’re cooking and melting snow, as stove feet tend to sink into the snow or melt it and two litres of melted snow tipping over in your tent is inconvenient. Enter the Stove Paw Ti, a baseplate that supports stoves when cooking in snow or on other soft, slippery surfaces. The Stove Paw Ti folds super-compact and weighs in at 55 g and is made from Titanium as the name suggests. It fits with the Primus’ OmniFuel, MultiFuel, OmniLite Ti, EasyFuel and Express Spider stoves and the different stove’s feet attach quickly and securely to the slots in the plate, making cooking safer and easier. Again a rather simple yet smart accessory that makes your winter adventure a tiny bit more convenient.</p>

<h2 id="therm-a-rest">Therm-A-Rest</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373717847" title="Therm-A-Rest Voyager Mattress by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7440/16373717847_b3bc02c271_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Therm-A-Rest Voyager Mattress" /></a></p>

<p>There was only one new item at <a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/therm-a-rest/">Therm-A-Rest</a> at the ISPO, and that was their Voyager Mattress. It’s a mattress for the camper as the Regular length model weighs in at 650 g (R-Value 2,2) with a length of 183 cm and a width of 51 cm. The selling argument for the mat is its thickness of 6,3 cm and the WaveCore construction, which will make it a nice, warm camping mat for 3 Season use. </p>

<h2 id="jetboil">Jetboil</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559537985" title="Jetboil by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8563/16559537985_bf898d2a54_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Jetboil" /></a></p>

<p>You’ve likely seen some of the pre-ISPO Press Releases about the new <a href="http://www.jetboil.com">Jetboil</a> Flash Lite and I too got the Press Release well before the fair and so knew what was waiting for me. Like usual at Jetboil I asked for 500 ml of cold water and then made the indoor fair test, in which the Flash Lite boiled that half litre in 2:15 minutes to a rolling boil. The whole stove system weighs 312 g and measures 104 mm x 165 mm, with a suggested Retail Price of 100€. It’s a well-constructed little stove that replaces the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/jetboil-sol-ti.html">Sol Ti</a> and like its predecessor you can fit the stove, legs and a 100 g cartridge inside of the pot. Unlike the Sol Ti it shouldn’t have any problems with the flux ring and bottom of the pot dissolving as everything is made from aluminium. </p>

<h2 id="rjk">Röjk</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15939424333" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7399/15939424333_ac073dca09_b.jpg" width="1024" height="654" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://rojksuperwear.com">Röjk</a> goes Inca Patterns in 2015. The designs are growing on me, from an initial <em>Hmmm, interesting</em> my opinion has matured into a <em>I think they’re onto something there</em> and give it a few more weeks and I’m sure I’ll totally love it. Except those T-Shirts. Those I love already:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558486002" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/16558486002_83f89b2252_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533585186" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8598/16533585186_31807106c9_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p>The Röjk crew partners with different artists each season who develop the designs and I yet have to see a SuperTee I didn’t like. They’re great. As I’m on a hyperbole train already, let me continue with the sweet packaging Jan has designed for the SuperBase baselayers: </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16533597336" title="Röjk Packaging by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/16533597336_8c74017d91_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Röjk Packaging" /></a></p>

<p>As a former sustainability consultant this totally hit home with me. Flat packaging allows you to ship more SuperBase baselayers in one box which minimizes unused space and so brings the efficiency up and the fuel used down. The packaging can be recycled by the end user very easily and it’s pretty, too. Awesome! But back to them garments:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15937025654" title="Röjk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7452/15937025654_b507853293_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Röjk" /></a></p>

<p>Another new garment the Swedish company brought back is their ChillOut Pant. I saw it on the mannequins and Linus and wanted one immediately. It felt very comfortable with laces at the cuffs and waist that keep the pants in place. It looks stylish and I would have no problem heading to a Café in it, but most likely I’d be wearing them when heading to the climbing gym or chilling at home. Because style and comfiness are häftigt =)</p>

<h2 id="inov-8">inov-8</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16559448265" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7409/16559448265_2d0b13a067_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.inov-8.com/">inov-8</a> had several ISPO Winners in their line-up but the best news for the backpacking inov-8 community is that their much-loved X-Talon 212 will come in 2015 besides the good old Regular version also in a Version with a Wide Toebox called Standard Fit. Both have the great close-fitting heel which locks the shoe into position but the wide toebox allows your toes to splay, which probably will make this already popular shoe even more, yeps, popular.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936887794" title="Inov-8 TerraClaw Line-Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7435/15936887794_ec1e7fdff4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8 TerraClaw Line-Up" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16373527077" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7358/16373527077_56bc3bfcef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>New in the inov-8 Line-Up is the TerraClaw family. It comes in 220 and 250 g versions (per shoe) for Men and Women (left &amp; right on the above photo). The TerraClaw 220 is the stripped-down version for super-fast racing, while the TerraClaw 250 adds more protection and comfort and I reckon this could be a good ultralight backpacking shoe. inov-8 sees these shoes as their most versatile yet which should perform well on loose, rocky trails as well as hard-packed paths. It’s an ISPO Award winner and the judges valued the Multi-Directional Lugs which provide traction when climbing, descending and contouring alike. The Dual-C™ Outsole uses two types of sticky rubber - the darker one is more durable and is in areas of high wear while the lighter rubber maximizes grip. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16558347592" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8648/16558347592_f873320966_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Inov-8" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936858314" title="Inov-8 RaceUltra Shell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7325/15936858314_45095e2823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8 RaceUltra Shell" /></a></p>

<p>Then there’s the garments. High on the list for Ultralight backpackers and Ultra Racers alike will be the Race Ultra Shell, a 125 g shell anorak that has a 10.000 mm hydrostatic head (the minimum requirement for many Ultra races nowadays), taped seams, a long venting zipper and the material is also breathable. The fabric is transparent so that race numbers can be seen underneath it and the fabric is stretchy, and best of all: When not needed it packs to the size of an orange. There’s a Race Ultra Pants, too, which tips the scales at 95 g and probably packs down o the size of an apple.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16371756968" title="inov-8 Race Elite Merino LSZ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7361/16371756968_f81da06d79_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="inov-8 Race Elite Merino LSZ" /></a></p>

<p>The Race Elite Merino LSZ (yeps, also an ISPO Award Winner =) is a 263 g Merino wool hoody that uses a lighter fabric in the back and under the arms while at the fron there’s a heavier Merino wool. It has a close fitting hood and built in hand mitts (yes, REAL mitts) that fold into the cuffs when not needed. Add in a long zipper for venting and you got a new Merino hoody on the block which should delight not just trailrunners!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15936852414" title="Inov-8 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8569/15936852414_486098ef3b_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Inov-8" /></a></p>

<p>And finally there was the RaceUltra 10 backpack, an ISPO Gold Award Winner, which also has a little 5 l sibling. I tried this pack on, jumped around like a rubber ball and concluded my indoor test that the zero bounce claim holds true. The pack has several hydration options and ten pockets, which makes it a good choice for 100 miles and longer Ultras where you need to carry more mandatory kit and food. Both packs come with two 500 ml soft flasks with tubes and there’s a compartment for your hydration bladder, too.</p>

<p><strong>Liked this?</strong> The <strong>please share the article</strong> amongst your friends, fans &amp; followers on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>! </p>

<p><em>Check back on Thursday for Batch II!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
