<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-04T00:32:02+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Gear Year]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/01/zero-gear-year.html"/>
    <updated>2016-01-04T23:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/01/zero-gear-year</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Could you buy no outdoor gear for a year?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376799841/in/album-72157644166894052/" title="Camp"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5592/14376799841_388679cf67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Camp" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>This article waits since about four years in my drafts folder. Come November, December, it smiles at me. It says <em>“How about it, Hendrik? Should you take a one year break from getting new outdoor gear?”</em>. And I smile back at it, thinking <em>“You know, I’d love to. But I’m a gear editor at two magazines, so testing the latest and greatest is my job”</em>. And with that I put the thought ad actum, give this draft a new futuristic date, in the hope that the next year could be a <strong>No Gear Year</strong>. </p>

<p>Because honestly, I don’t need anything new. I have enough hardshells and trailrunning shoes, plenty of backpacks and shelters, as well as skis, climbing gear, a packraft and a Fatbike. Now I may be a gear editor at a climbing and at a backpacking magazine, but I’m sure there’s just as many normal outdoor enthusiasts out there who have cupboards full of gear. Much of it only getting used a handfull of times a year, with the owner eyeing the new version already while the one on the shelf is still perfect.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18493538621/in/dateposted/" title="Friday&#x27;s Outdoor Office"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/410/18493538621_e46dd8d195_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Friday&#x27;s Outdoor Office" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And who is to blame? Outdoor shops pretty much have a 20% off sale on a weekly basis, there’s winter, summer and Black Friday sales where shiny new kit is smiling at us at so deep prices - and lets be honest, we really needed that 10 g lighter rain jacket because it will make our skin-out weight significantly lighter. And that new 9.1 mm single rope was needed because it will help me to send my 7c project. That new, inflatable pillow surely will be the last pillow I ever need as I will sleep like at home on it, and those new trailrunners will make me hike faster and be great for training, too. And it was all on sale, too - how could I resist?</p>

<h2 id="money-spent-passionately-on-trips-not-gear">Money spent passionately on trips, not gear</h2>

<p>That lovely headline I copied some four years ago into this draft. As I was pondering last year to buy a new camera and spend a significant amount on it and lenses a friend commented <em>“Why not use what you have, take the money and go on a trip to shoot great photos?”</em>. <em>“Ah well”</em>, I said, <em>“you know, it is not that easy with a house and family”</em>. But the more I thought about it, the more it just seemed like one of those easy excuse phrases. Sure, it is more difficult to travel with a baby and a four-year-old - but it is not impossible as an increasing number of dads &amp; moms show when they go outdoors with their toddlers &amp; kids.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14856100147/in/album-72157645045051650/" title="Hiking in the rain"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5586/14856100147_5784882629_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hiking in the rain" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Spending money on gear is a lot easier than going somewhere, I get it. Browse your favourite outdoor shop, see that there’s something new and it’s for such a good price - click, click, click and another package will be arriving soon. Put it on or up in the garden, maybe snap a photo and you even would have material for a new blog post - if you’re a blogger, that is. But going on a trip? </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Don’t buy more than you need. Because if you do, you are going to consume way more than the resources of the planet can bear. - Rose Marcario, CEO Patagonia</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, that involves planing. Planing a route, the food, gear, getting there, having a look on the weather, etc. You also need to actually go outside, and what if it is -13°C and snowing like here right now? Well, that ain’t particularly pleasant, especially with all that grey sky which makes for less than ideal photo weather. But isn’t that actually what we have all the gear for? Down jackets, softshell pants, warm shoes - they’d be great for this weather, and as they haven’t been used yet (enough), why not take them out for a walk or even a Microadventure?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14847137861/in/album-72157644612250031/" title="Locus Gear Khufu eVent II"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3892/14847137861_5a372ef639_b.jpg" width="1024" height="544" alt="Locus Gear Khufu eVent II" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="join-me-in-a-year-without-new-gear">Join me in a year without new gear</h2>

<p>It’s nothing new. <a href="https://sweepingthegarden.wordpress.com/2012/01/02/no-new-gear-2012/">Craig has done it in 2012</a> and still loves to go outdoors. If a gear nerd like me whose job it is to test &amp; review the latest and greatest outdoor gear can do it, I’m sure you too, my esteemed reader, also can do 12 months without new gear. No new backpacking gear, no new bike, no new climbing gear, no new shoes, no new shelter - <strong>NO NEW GEAR</strong>. Personally I also include used gear in this, but that’s your call really. And twelve months are not that long - I just got used to write 2015 when noting down the date, and now it’s already 2016 - so a year without new gear will be faster over than you think.</p>

<p>And think about all the benefits:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Next year, in 2017, you can splurge on the latest and greatest outdoor gear, which will most certainly be better than in 2016!</li>
  <li>In 2016 you can actually test and use all the gear you have already!</li>
  <li>You can go on more trips, because you’ll save hundreds of €£$ on not buying new equipment and sitting in front of the computer!</li>
</ul>

<p>Exceptions for me will be food and fuel, these I will purchase as needed for my trips - and you should, too. Because hiking &amp; climbing on an empty stomach is no fun!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193489569/in/album-72157644166894052/" title="Dinner in the making"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5568/14193489569_090587cee9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dinner in the making" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="repair-re-use-swap-loan---and-use-what-you-already-have">Repair, re-use, swap, loan - and use what you already have</h2>

<p>In case a piece of equipment fails you - socks can get holes in the heels, shoes get walked through, a shelter starts to leak, the waterproof jacket ain’t waterproof no more - you can just fix it. Bring your shoes to the cobbler to get a new sole on them, wash your waterproofs to make them keep the snow &amp; rain out again, seam-seal your shelter and use the best repair tape of all time to fix everything else: Duct tape! </p>

<p>Still feel the urge to try something new in 2016? You can always loan gear - from friends, companies or websites - to try a new outdoor hobby, from packrafts over a SUP board to a Via ferrata set - there’s no need to own it if you just want to try it. Imagine you don’t like skiing after the first few tries, but you got skiing gear standing there for 2.000€? Loan before you own. </p>

<h2 id="get-out-adventuring">Get out adventuring!</h2>

<p>The bottomline for this move is for me two-fold: I want to Simplify my life further and show that one doesn’t need to chase the latest sale on gear. It’s more fun to go and chase the sunset with a light backpack on, which is what this pastime is all about: Spending time outdoors. Good outdoor gear helps, but we shouldn’t chase it more than spending time outside. So here’s to twelve months of no new gear, and more outdoor adventures!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/judsonhall/4346786079/in/photolist-7C7q4z-cfZCJW-cfZSGh-cfZQN7-cfZNKW-cfZJtQ-cfZwx7-cfZGs1-6kx9Na-5Z3Ybf-4kQtN4-7ukJCb-5TWQPd-9p3NU7-6cLdHP-dSYdk7-4HPnNE-mZEuJF-4Fx5tc-64PeHK-64PeHP-maqCE-d5Atoo-5X9Pr-5X9Ph-6bGLqs-hkSjLj-6Numhm-aLui-obyj7o-8g5TPN-38ZunG-8mjtkq-j8Wz3H-9jcCpW-bUpK8o-r5UoC-m57CJ-7xCm9v-4oGDg3-4KSgum-bUpJmY-dBoEss-dGDFap-7mjPSL-5UU8K9-745gYZ-q6U3x-dEkv1G-4JpHYL" title="Fresh turns"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4070/4346786079_b821dd5c7b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fresh turns" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Perfect Outdoor Gift]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/12/the-perfect-outdoor-gift.html"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T11:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/12/the-perfect-outdoor-gift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Not another Gift Guide”</em>. I hear you. Here is the perfect gift for the hiker, climber, skier, cyclist and packrafter in your life. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8385427873" title="Self Portrait by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8361/8385427873_4c56d5300b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Self Portrait" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>“T’is the season!”</em>. Well, actually <em>“the season”</em> starts nowadays somewhere around September, when chocolate calendars and christmas decorations find their way into the supermarkets and the toys section doubles in size. <em>“Buy. Buy. Buy.”</em> it tells us everywhere. A couple of weeks later blogs and magazines will be full of Articles in the vein of <em>“The ultimate Gift Guide”</em>. </p>

<p>That’s why now is a good moment to reset the brain and engrain: <strong>You are not what you own.</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7728232746" title="Taking in the view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8289/7728232746_bb9a1e666c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Taking in the view" /></a></p>

<p>The hiker, climber, skier, cyclist and packrafter in your life needs just one thing this Christmas:</p>

<p><strong>Time</strong></p>

<p>Time is for our hobbies essential. A weekend away in the hills, a day at the crag, an afternoon ride or paddle - all of them need just one ting: Time. It’s our most precious resource, and it is scarily finite. Our lives are so full of things that it’s difficult for many to follow our passions, because between picking up the kids, grocery shopping, cooking, cleaning the house and other chores there’s often just too little time to pursue what we love to do. It’s the one thing you really can gift (or ask for) this Christmas: Time. It’s relatively cheap - likely free - and you can give the same gift to your partner. </p>

<p>There’s many advantages to this, not least for the environment. How long does happiness last when you get a gift? A few moments? A day? Compare that to a weekend backpacking or climbing, kayaking on the sea, a long cycling ride. That’s adventures, memories, which will last many, many years - maybe a lifetime even. Do you remember what you got last holidays? Might be hard to remember, right? How about the last weekend you were outdoors? </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8701207971" title="Packrafting &amp; Camping by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8257/8701207971_7bdcd68cd4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Packrafting &amp; Camping" /></a></p>

<p>So instead of buying something material, ask for time. You have the gear and it’s just collecting dust in the closet because it so rarely gets used. You don’t need another piece-of-something, you need to have the time to go out and use what you already have. Take your time and go on a long backpacking weekend. Use it for working on your climbing project. Cycle to that hill outside of town which you see each day on your way to work and sleep on top of it that night. </p>

<p>I’ve asked for time the last few years, and it was always a memorable present. I went to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html">Korouoma</a> the first weekend of this year with my time present and climbed Ruskeavirta, Finland’s highest ice waterfall. Last year I went to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a>, skied &amp; ice climbed and saw beautiful Northern Lights. I’m already pondering what to do with my time present this year - go on a Microadventrue? Northwards to Lapland? Or maybe even Scotland? Anticipation is the greatest joy - after being outside, of course!</p>

<p>Get time to go outdoors.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19872954152/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19872954152_05a10af0d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Four Week Winter]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/the-four-week-winter.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-21T15:57:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/the-four-week-winter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An obituary for the winter of 2014.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10983987276/" title="Winter"><img src="https://s2.yimg.com/sk/3789/10983987276_15b9ee5bc9_b.jpg" width="800" height="534" alt="Winter" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Winter,</p>

<p>I haven’t always been fond of you. As I arrived in 2002 in Finland you had the country in your icy grip, and spring couldn’t come early enough for me. Also in the next couple years, when you visited Jyväskylä with -35°C temperatures for weeks at a time, I didn’t find particular pleasure in you. </p>

<p>But I got wiser with age. I slowly started to enjoy your gifts, and took my snowboard and skis down the hills and tracks. I enjoyed walking my dog on frozen lakes, tried Nordic Tour skating, and had many laughs as I was tobogganing down steep hills with my sled. Warming up besides a warm fire with a hot Minttu kakao has become a sacred ritual, one that I carried over into summer after a long day on the trail.</p>

<p>The more time I spent outside between spring and autumn, the more I fell in love with what you had to offer. I realized that there’s no such thing as bad weather as long as one is <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">dressed well</a>. I became aware that you make possible things which spring, summer and autumn can’t: I am able to see the tracks of animals in the snow. On <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">skis</a> the going is fast and fun. I can build <a href="http://youtu.be/HHCZhUZXhZU">snowmens</a> with my son. Go <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/04/snow-wars-ultralighters-strike-back.html">winter hiking</a> with friends and swim in ice holes after a sauna. And lately I enjoy <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html">climbing steep frozen ice</a>. I explored forests and hills on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/video-msr-lightning-ascent-review.html">snowshoes</a>, and built snow caves.</p>

<p>But this year, you decided to not spend much time here. In early January I needed to drive 600 km north to find you. I climbed beautiful ice falls, camped on snow, and enjoyed the silence. Two weeks later you appeared here in the south and covered the land with snowflakes and the sea and lakes with ice. I took pleasure trailrunning on soft, snowy trails, climbing the local icefalls, and building a snowman with my son. It shouldn’t last. And that where I was pondering fatbikes and new <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-tourenski/?pid=81">skis</a>, to bring more fun and excitement to into the cold season.</p>

<p>A mere four weeks after you arrived, you are as good as gone again. I couldn’t even get the skis out for a round on the ice, let alone the local trails. Our snowman is nothing else than a sad little hill of hard-packed snow. Instead of bright, snow-lighted nights, darkness reigns again until the sun will stay up all the time. Your attempts at a comeback are half-hearted, and so I look back on memories of when you visited Finland and gave us lots of fun. May you come back in 2015 like this.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8385427305/" title="Helvetinjärvi NP"><img src="https://v4s.yimg.com/te/8044/8385427305_e65480ec80_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Helvetinjärvi NP" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8386517596/" title="Along the Pirkan Taival"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8093/8386517596_1123ab4863_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Along the Pirkan Taival" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8333513170/" title="Bikepacking in winter is fun"><img src="https://s3.yimg.com/te/8492/8333513170_c45722fc1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Bikepacking in winter is fun" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6962705655/" title="Side wind"><img src="https://s3.yimg.com/so/7038/6962705655_856eb4a2e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="390" alt="Side wind." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6779110164/" title="Madshus Glittertind+"><img src="https://s3.yimg.com/so/7181/6779110164_45847e80a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Madshus Glittertind+" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12561118905/" title="Höstvesi"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7343/12561118905_015d0874cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Höstvesi" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11150128145/" title="Fading Away"><img src="https://s2.yimg.com/sk/3696/11150128145_fb57c7922a_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Fading Away" /></a></p>

<p>As for 2014, I hope that Eastern Tyrol, the Dolomites and the USA know to value your presence. I leave thee behind with the positiv prospect that the packrafting, backpacking, bouldering and rock climbing season this year will start a few months earlier as usually.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
