<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: food | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-03T13:24:41+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ambronite Supermeal Diet]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/01/the-ambronite-supermeal-diet.html"/>
    <updated>2016-01-15T23:54:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/01/the-ambronite-supermeal-diet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Superfoods are since the invention of Soylent all the rage, and I have been fascinated by them since I read about them. When <a href="http://ambronite.com">Ambronite</a> asked me if I’d like to test their all-natural, Vegan Supermeal I said yes and decided to have a wee experiment with it: Living only on Ambronite for a week. This is my journey into the world of superfoods.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24366924076/in/dateposted/" title="Ambronite Supermeal"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1676/24366924076_88ab534832_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ambronite Supermeal" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-perceived-convenience-of-supermeals">The (perceived?) convenience of Supermeals</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.soylent.com">Soylent</a> and it’s copies <a href="https://www.joylent.eu/">Joylent</a>, <a href="https://jakefood.com/">Jake</a>, <a href="http://huel.com">Huel</a> and <a href="http://mymana.eu/">Mana</a> are the <em>Food Revolution</em>. Made for busy office workers who want to work more and not needing to go out to shop, cook, and clean the dishes these meals want to give you more time to pursue the things you like to do - be it working, partying or hiking. The idea did appeal to me since I read about Soylent, so it was easy enough to agree to test <a href="http://ambronite.com">Ambronite</a>. The Start-up from Finland has a Twist on their Supermeal, though: It’s only made from natural ingredients - there’s no chemicals or artificial ingredients in it, only good things from nature. That’s very appealing, but is also represented in their price - they are easily the most expensive option of those named. But as I normally already pay a premium for local &amp; organic food, this would not be a big thing for me - plus I like to support Finnish Start-ups!</p>

<p>My usual diet is 95% Vegetarian (we eat meat &amp; fish once every other week). I usually eat a slice of bread or two with cheese and some veggies for breakfast, together with a cup of coffee and water. At Lunch we eat the leftovers from the previous day, afternoon coffee is the 2nd cup of coffee &amp; some pastry or fruit. Around 17 o’clock I might or might not eat a snack (fruit or bread) and around 19 o’clock we have dinner together. In the evening while watching a series we eat some more fruits. My wife and me cook each two days in a row, then it’s the other’s turn. It’s a system that works well for us, and I normally don’t spend more than an hour in the kitchen in the evenings to prepare food and less than an hour shopping the day before my turn. So all in all I might spend a maximum of 1,5 hours grocery shopping and 3,5 hours cooking in the evenings, with maybe an hour of cleaning the kitchen. Six hours a week - six hours which I now could use for something else. If that is worth it for you to forgo real food - only you yourself can know, and at the end of the article you can order a free pouch of Ambronite and safe time &amp; gain convenince (or lose out on a tasty lunch).</p>

<h2 id="ambronite-outdoors">Ambronite Outdoors</h2>

<p>The Outdoor Aspect of Ambronite comes in when looking at the numbers: A pouch weighs 126 g (120 g powder), has 500 kcal a portion and a massive load of Vitamins and Minerals. It is easy to prepare in the included bottle - add water &amp; powder, shake, drink - and it should be possible to prepare it in a 1l Nalgene. The cheapest option is to subscribe to Ambronite, then a meal will be 7,60€ - a one-off package of ten will make your wallet 89€ lighter (or 8,90€ per meal). I can see it be useful as breakfast or lunch, especially if you have set yourself a long distance to hike and don’t want to stop to eat. Ambronite can be prepared and eaten on the go, and washing the dishes is as easy as rinsing the bottle - all very convenient. Because of the high amount of Vitamins and Minerals it also could help to keep you healthy on a long tour - but normal Vitamin-pills can that too. I would not go outdoors backpacking or ski-touring and eat only Ambronite. The weight to Calorie Ratio isn’t that good, plus it would be very expensive. But one as lunch would be OK. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24310678221/in/dateposted/" title="Ambronite Supermeal"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1693/24310678221_6f5451162f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ambronite Supermeal" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="living-on-1500-kcal-a-day">Living on 1.500 kcal a day</h2>

<p>One pouch of Ambronite has 500 kcal, and the recommended daily intake for a non-active human is 2.000 kcal. The energy value of the orange juice I added is 45 kcal per 100 ml, and the <a href="http://nutritiondata.self.com/facts/beverages/3898/2">kcal value of coffee</a> is 2 per cup - so could say I had an energy intake of ~1.600 kcal a day. I found this interesting because on a normal day it’s hard to quantify the energy intake, and even with a healthy diet like mine the chance of “over-eating” is possible. I wanted to see, in a controlled environment, how it would be to live under the recommended daily intake value. That’s why I also didn’t mix it with any other ingredients - like cocnut or soy milk, bananas oe berries, or spices like honey and cinnamon.</p>

<p>This week I was out cycling, skiing and walking (average of 4,5 km a day), training at home, working and just doing normal daily stuff. During the mornings and afternoons I never felt hungry after a Supermeal Shake, but around 16, 17 o’clock a wee bit of hunger would appear on the first three days. That would get away once the third shake went down, but around 22 o’clock I again got a hungry feeling during the first three days. Well, so much about this - lets jump in to the experiment!</p>

<p><strong>Something to keep in mind: Taste is subjective. What I find OK you might find terrible - or delicious.</strong></p>

<h2 id="day-1">Day 1</h2>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/T8XDzF7zLjw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The first Ambronite Supermeal shake. This first one was with 550 ml water only, and it was OK in taste, grainy, thick and in my opinion very neutral in flavour, possible with a light Black Currant and Spinach after-taste. I expected it to taste much worse after reading <a href="http://hillplodder.com/2015/11/10/can-we-have-gruel-instead/">Matthew’s take on it</a> but was happy that it was for me good enough to get down. It kept the hunger away for the claimed four or five hours and in the afternoon I had my second Ambronite shake - this time mixed with some Orange Juice, which for me improved the taste considerably. In the afternoon I went to the supermarket with the family - to accompany them. I got a bit hungry over there - all the fresh fruits looked very good - but once at home it wasn’t there anymore. I had my third Ambronite sitting at the table while my family ate their delicious dinner, and I drunk the final shake. Later in the evening - I usually eat fruits in the evenings while watching something - I started to get hungry. Once in bed and asleep all was good though.</p>

<h2 id="day-2">Day 2</h2>

<p>I didn’t wake up starving as one might expect, going to bed slightly hungry. The shakes all went down fine today, I was drinking them rather slowly over the matter of an hour or so, but the evening meal I drunk in a matter of minutes. After the kids were sleeping and we were watching a series I again was getting a slightly hungry feeling, but once in bed I was fast asleep. </p>

<h2 id="day-3">Day 3</h2>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DqWh7uQRNsA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>All three meals went down easily without problems, and again there was a light hunger in the evening. </p>

<h2 id="day-4">Day 4</h2>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rt2wIysP-hQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Early breakfast, cycling out to the Baltic to have fun (and shot the above video) and a late Lunch outside - Ambronite didn’t freeze at the -6°C we had, but then I was only two hours outside. Dinner with the family. Surprisingly my body probably must have adjusted to the reduced energy intake, as I didn’t feel hungry at all in the afternoon or evening. </p>

<h2 id="day-5">Day 5</h2>

<p>The last breakfast of this experiment, and it wasn’t easy to get it down. Maybe it was that after having drunk this same-tasting shake now for five days that the taste buds were resenting the same taste, all the time. Not really looking forward to the Lunch and Dinner shakes either - I’ll update this post when they’re down the throat</p>

<h2 id="ingredients--taste">Ingredients &amp; Taste</h2>

<p>You can read the complete list of ingredients <a href="http://ambronite.com/pages/ingredients">here</a>. They are all natural, organic, GMO-free and Vegan, which I find great as it is in line with what I value in my food. The taste thus: It’s really hard to describe this, but neutral, thick (depending on the amount of water you use) and with a light Black Currant and Spinach after-taste would be my take on it. As Ambronite can taste differently between harvests it might be that yours tastes slightly different, too. It is not a taste which I am looking forward to, but more try to get it down as fast as possible - probably an effect of only eating it this week.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24393171225/in/dateposted/" title="Ambronite Supermeal"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1694/24393171225_95e2df0304_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ambronite Supermeal" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24366939346/in/dateposted/" title="Ambronite Supermeal"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1446/24366939346_f9d9a40a19_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ambronite Supermeal" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight-loss-focus-and-tiredness">Weight-loss, Focus and Tiredness</h2>

<p>I’m slim and lean at 63 kg normal weight. I’m certainly underweight (some 15 kg or so) but never gain more weight than 67 kg. It’s always been this way, and I don’t complain. So Ambronite was not a way for me to lose weight, and from what I can guess I didn’t lose any during this week. I have been working at 100% the whole week and was always focussed, and also was not more tired. All in all I would say I feel just as with my usual diet. Also bowel movement was normal, though went down from twice to once a day. I’ll save you further details on this =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23764935714/in/dateposted/" title="Ambronite Supermeal"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1539/23764935714_881ae77d65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ambronite Supermeal" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I am very much looking forward to my first real meal again tomorrow morning. As I say in my video from Day 4, it has shown me that the perceived convenience of these powdery Superfoods is too little for me to give up eating real food. I can see me using it on trips as lunch because of the convenience, but would not use it as a sole source of food - I like my MYOG Müslis and warm evening meals. At home I could see it come in handy on a busy day for lunch, but not just yet =) All in all I was happy to have had the possibility to try this experiment. I thought - reading about Soylent et al. - that this could indeed be the future. </p>

<p>And maybe for some it is. But for me it won’t be - certainly not as something that I eat for breakfast, lunch, dinner and a snack every day. There’s a few reasons for that: It’s prohibitive expensive to only eat Ambronite - the cost for a week (if you drink 4 meals a day) would be 226,95€, which would run up to 907,90€ a month (for 120 meals). That’s for one person, in a family of three that’s a ridiculous amount of money - plus I doubt my four year old son would drink this. As a family we spent between 600 and 800€ a month on high-quality food (lots of veggies and fruits, mostly organic &amp; local if possible), which is quite a bit less than what it would cost to feed one person just on Ambronite. </p>

<p>Another reason is that I do like real food. I like to cook (on trips in a bag), I don’t mind the shopping too much and the dishwasher does most of the cleaning. It’s also the social aspect of sitting together and eating something tasty. Or going to a Café on the weekend to eat some tasty waffles or a piece of cake. Going to a restaurant with friends &amp; family. Even as I was single I was cooking every day, often having friends over for dinner. The idea that everyone is just sitting there with a shake and trying to get it down - well, it feels a bit boring. </p>

<p>That said, there probably will be people who don’t mind the costs or perceived loss of real food. For those Ambronite &amp; its competitors will be an interesting way to experience the future of foods. As for me, I’m having a tasty Brunch in Helsinki tomorrow =)</p>

<p>Finally, you can <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1n39hqCQKCMR34_gtnrPOHOth2n9CMOQzFOg9p_jgH-c/viewform">try Ambronite for free</a> - enter your details and use the code “GETSAMPLE” and you’ll get one free Ambronite pouch sent to your door step. If you like it and want to order more, you can use the Coupon Code “HIKINGINFINLAND” and get 20€ off your order. </p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>Ambronite sent me two boxes for free for this experiment, no strings attached &amp; no money involved. If you want to live only of Superfoods - use Common Sense and consult a specialist doctor first.</em> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Food for Thought IV]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/food-for-thought-iv.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T13:47:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/08/food-for-thought-iv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a while since my last food for though article, so time to look at new foods which I take out when backpacking.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9580009307/" title="Consumables by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3780/9580009307_1c239b39b4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Consumables" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="bullit-meal">Bullit Meal</h2>

<p><a href="http://bullitmeal.com/">Bullit Meal</a> are MREs (Meal, Ready to Eat), made in Finland. They’re complete meals which weigh up to 184 g a bar (incl. plastic, excl. paper wrapper which is 4 g), but pack 400 kcal. I found them an excellent lunch snack which allows you to continue hiking, it’s really easy to eat on-the-go. Nice big chunks of meat, rice and veggies and coated in sesame make them very tasty indeed, even if they might not look that way. There’s no preservatives in there, and the Chilli Beef bar for example has 24,7 g of Protein, 18,9 g of fat and 31,8 g of carbohydrates. In case you rather would eat it while you’re not walking - that is not a problem either. You can heat the bar up - just drop the complete package with plastic into boiling water or heat it up over a (sans plastic!), and you can enjoy it warm. </p>

<p>There’s currently three flavours and a bar costs around 5€. Available at <a href="http://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/">Outdoor Food Shop</a> and these <a href="http://bulletmeal.com/myynti/">Finnish shops</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9574380875/" title="Bullit Meal"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5514/9574380875_e5ee34c2a2_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Bullit Meal" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9580444325/" title="Bullet Meal by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3733/9580444325_dc2e1916c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Bullet Meal" /></a></p>

<h2 id="pronto-caf">Pronto Café</h2>

<p><a href="http://prontocafe.eu/">Pronto Café</a> is a new way to brew a fresh cup of coffee on the trail. I found them at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">OutDoor</a> and it certainly was one of the highlights for me. The “technology”, so the filter, is a South Korean invention and Pronto Café bought the patents and now brings this way to brew coffee to Europe. The coffee they use is roasted in Italy and packed less than 24 hours later in Switzerland. At 8 g a package they’re a bit heavier than Starbucks Via, but taste as good if not better. It’s a super young company and more flavours might come in the future. On short trips for me at the moment my preferred morning cuppa.</p>

<p>Sold in ten or twenty packs they cost between 8€ and 15€, and available at <a href="http://prontocafe.eu/">Pronto Café</a> and <a href="http://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/">Outdoor Food Shop</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9577146958/" title="Pronto coffee by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2883/9577146958_e797354199_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pronto coffee" /></a></p>

<h2 id="lyo-food">LYO FOOD</h2>

<p><a href="http://lyofood.com/">LYO FOOD</a> isn’t very well known yet, which is a shame. Their meals are delicious, light, high in calories and there’s a good variety of different flavours, including the tasty vegetarian Farfalla with Gorgonzola and Spinach Sauce. Packages weigh, depending on the meal, up to 108 g (including the package) and have up to 600 kcal a meal so should even fill up very hungry hikers. All ingredients are 100% natural and there’s no preservatives or artificial flavours in them. At the moment they need to be prepared in your pot (I found the Evernew 600 pot of my Trail Designs Sidewinder a perfect size) which means you’ll need to do the dishes after you’re done, but a “boil in the bag” version is in the works and hopefully will come soon. Given that the LYO Meals are up to half the price of other meals but tasting just as good, these are definitely worth checking out. </p>

<p>LYO also makes dried fruits, which are super tasty as well. I eat them either straight from the bag or drop some into my müsli or dessert. Soups and breakfasts are available, too, and as all soups are vegetarian these are worth trying if you don’t eat meat.</p>

<p>There’s 10 main dinner choices, which cost about 6€ and up. Available at <a href="http://lyofood.com/pl/en/category/main-meals?page=all">LYO FOOD</a> directly and <a href="http://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/">Outdoor Food Shop</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9577124224/" title="LYO Exotic Pleasure by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7385/9577124224_e3f52e3cbb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="LYO Exotic Pleasure" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9574319607/" title="LYO Exotic Pleasure by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5462/9574319607_bd0f847f8a_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="LYO Exotic Pleasure" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9574369139/" title="LYO Penne Bolognese by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7325/9574369139_b4a09a2dfd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="LYO Penne Bolognese" /></a></p>

<h2 id="raw-bite">RAW BITE</h2>

<p>Hailing from Denmark, <a href="http://rawbite.dk/">RAW BITE</a> make some very tasty bars - all made from organic ingredients without added sugar. Bars have ~ 200 kcal on average (some flavours have more, some less). They’re slightly moist but are so tasty that even on a hot day it’s no problem to eat a bar in one go. Perfect as a snack between breakfast and lunch as well as between lunch and dinner, two of these per day keep me going between the meals. </p>

<p>They come in four flavours, cost about 2,50€ a bar and are available at your local Supermarket, Organic Food Store and Health Food Stores.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9580441139/" title="RAW BITE by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3752/9580441139_b37cbcbe75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="RAW BITE" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9574336739/" title="RAW BITE by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5519/9574336739_122a88b306_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="RAW BITE" /></a></p>

<h2 id="myog-meals">MYOG Meals</h2>

<p>And then there’s meals I make myself. I have pretty much since the start made my own breakfasts, Müsli. I tried various commercial ones, but found them expensive and not good tasting. A package of organic Müsli costs me about 3€ and I get four breakfasts out of it, which is a much better price - and it tastes superior, too. 90 g of Müsli, 20 g of milk powder, and 5 g of cacao make for a tasty breakfast which I can eat warm or cold directly from the bag. All in, depending on the Müsli and other ingredients, this costs me about 1,50€ max. If you collect berries of your choice you can pimp your breakfast, too - free of charge!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9584392572/" title="MYOG Müsli by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7320/9584392572_2537fcd0dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MYOG Müsli" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9562508708/" title="Blueberries by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7370/9562508708_54ba234fe6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Blueberries" /></a></p>

<p>I also started to experiment with MYOG meals. I like to keep things simple and easy to prepare, and if possible use organic ingredients, too. The following is a recipe I have adapted from <a href="http://ultraknilch.blogspot.com/">Markus</a>: A package of organic potato mash is three side portions, though if you eat it on your own it is just fine as a filling evening meal. I throw in some fried, dried onions and a sauce of choice - usually some mushroom or pepper sauce. All of it goes in a 1l Ziplock bag and then can be easily rehydrated in the bag. Again, this can be easily pimped with real mushrooms you pick along the trail if it’s the season. If you need extra calories, a bit of olive oil will help with that, and if you need extra taste a soup cube or salt &amp; pepper will serve you well. And if you prefer some meat with it, drop some beef jerky in there and your set!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9574378595/" title="MYOG Potato Mash by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3811/9574378595_fc6123fd22_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MYOG Potato Mash" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9530326570/" title="The forest provides tasty dinner extras - free of charge! by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/9530326570_1e96601ebe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The forest provides tasty dinner extras - free of charge!" /></a></p>

<p>Don’t want to make your own food? Shop for outdoor meals at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/outdoor-lebensmittel/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/nahrung/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1ddm5Ek">CampSaver.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1c4gs7u">Backcountry.com</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thermos Bottle]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html"/>
    <updated>2012-11-15T18:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>It’s cold. 
I wish I’d have a hot drink, to warm me up from the inside. 
But I don’t want to get the stove out in this weather. 
Lets see if there’s still some tea in my Thermos bottle. 
Thank god, there’s still some in there. 
Now just to find a spot outside of the wind, and then to enjoy that hot cup of tea.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8184795376/" title="Thermos Bottle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8478/8184795376_9d1cec45b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Thermos Bottle" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>If you go out in winter, that season where the temperature drops below -10°C outside and there’s snow everywhere, that’s the time where I am very happy to carry a “heavy” container for hot liquids - a Thermos Bottle. I tried “lightweight” alternatives - Nalgenes in Closed Cell Foam containers, Platypus in Cozy-Pouches - but they can, for me, not compare to a real Thermos bottle. The Thermos keeps the liquid inside steaming hot for up to 24 hours in my experience, and with my MYOG Alternatives I never managed to keep the liquid hot anywhere that long (not that it often would stay that long in there!).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8184795628/" title="Thermos Bottle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8209/8184795628_f149edd38e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Thermos Bottle" /></a></p>

<p>I had a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-c-h-vacuum-bottle-075-l-isolierflasche/">Primus Thermos bottle</a> in the past, though somehow it got lost while I was guiding in the north; so I looked for a new one. Ultimately that led me to the classic, whose name defines the whole category of the items - <a href="http://www.thermos.com/product_catalog.aspx?CatCode=BEVG">Thermos</a>. In comparison to the Primus I had, it is lighter and more compact, for the same price. Here are those weights:</p>

<p><strong>Weights for 1 litre Thermos bottle</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Cup: 77 gram</li>
  <li>Stopper: 38 gram</li>
  <li>Bottle: 404 gram</li>
  <li><strong>Total 521 gram</strong></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Weights for 0,7 litres Thermos bottle</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Cup: 81 gram</li>
  <li>Stopper: 38 gram</li>
  <li>Bottle: 360 gram</li>
  <li><strong>Total 480 gram</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>So 41 gram extra get you 0,3 l of extra volume, or two extra cups of tea/ coffee/ hot chocolate (the Thermos Cup holds exactly 1,5 dl). </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8184756037/" title="Thermos Bottle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8488/8184756037_9abd10449b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Thermos Bottle" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8184796698/" title="Thermos Bottle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8070/8184796698_e276c1d085_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Thermos Bottle" /></a></p>

<p>The cup is rather heavy as you will see - a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/10/kupilka-review.html">Kupilka 21</a> is just four gram heavier but offers more volume and has useful handle to hold it from - though as the cup is a protection for the stopper and helps that the bottle isn’t opened by accident in your backpack, possibly spilling its content, I prefer to take the whole bottle with cup when I go out. Especially if you use the Thermos bottle at night in your sleeping bag for some extra heat it’s recommended to not leave the cup at home. The cup tends to get fairly hot when you pour something in it, so use gloves when you lift it up, or wait for a bit till your liquid has cooled down enough to be consumed.</p>

<p>Not only in winter is the Thermos bottle a useful piece of kit, also on day hikes or overnighters in spring, summer and autumn, where you’d rather not carry your stove, a Thermos bottle allows you to have a hot cup of tea and rehydrate a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/07/food-for-thought-iii.html">meal</a> on the go, and much faster than boiling water. It also works the other way around, by the way - keeping your liquids cool - perfect for hikes in hot regions if you crave an ice cold beverage!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8184794688/" title="Thermos Bottle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8210/8184794688_45d68d9559_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Thermos Bottle" /></a></p>

<p>Cleaning the bottle is simple, at home I usually just rinse the bottle and take a brush to the stopper to remove residues from tea or coffee and make sure to also rinse the inside of it; to clean the bottle and cup on the trail is easy, while I clean the stopper thoroughly at home and don’t mind possible “extra” tastes from the stopper (which I haven’t tasted yet, though).</p>

<p>With winter coming any day soon and staying for the next five months, a Thermos bottle will find its way into my packing list on most trips, be it on day trips, overnighters or two week long expeditions. If you go hiking in winter, and rather would have a hot drink immediately instead of waiting till you’ve fired up your stove and it has heated your water, consider a Thermos bottle!</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Buy one at</strong> <a href="http://www.trekki.fi/product/2107/thermos-midnight-blue-1l-termospullo">Trekki</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/product.asp?sua=1&amp;lang=1&amp;s=20695">Partioaitta</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157632006965666/">More photos</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8184756759/" title="Thermos Bottle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8337/8184756759_3b61d2d283_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Thermos Bottle" /></a> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
