<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bikepacking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/bikepacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-03T17:04:56+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[24 = 9]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/24-equals-9.html"/>
    <updated>2012-09-06T17:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/24-equals-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Somtimes trips don’t go according to plan.</em> That’s especially annoying if you don’t get to go on as much trips as you’d like to, and try to make each trip count. While I didn’t put myself under any stress to make this trip a success, outside influences made this 24 trip a lot shorter. <em>A trip report, sort of.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855697732/" title="Onwards by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8445/7855697732_49d53411aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Onwards" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Remember when <strong>24</strong> trips were all the rage? That’d be about two years ago, when Ryan Jordan coined the 24 term for overnighters. He wrote a few superb trip reports and thoughts on 24 trips, and many took up the idea of these short trips, which didn’t need days of planning, but you just grab your kit, food, a map and go to the trail head, hike for a few hours, pitch and spend a fine night outside, before heading back the next morning. The idea is still as great as back then, because just getting away for a few hours, going outdoors, can be enough to recharge your batteries for normal life. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855691676/" title="Lingon berries are ripe by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8428/7855691676_53c81ae7ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lingon berries are ripe" /></a></p>

<p>With an eleven month old baby son and a house renovation which we mightly underestimated, I was delighted as my wife gave me an OK for an overnighter. “<em>Be back before noon on Saturday, so we can get some Raspberries from the market.</em>” was the only condition. Spending eight plus hours working on my house Monday to Friday for four months already is taxing, and going outdoors is for me a good way to recharge and get ready for more of it. </p>

<p>I visited the supermarket after few hours at work to grab some torillas and salami for lunch and snacking, as well as my new favourite trail snack, Honey Roasted Nuts. Back at home I went to pack my <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com/">Porcelain Rocket frame packs</a>, threw a 3 litre reservoir into my <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-raptor-18-hydration-pack-1100cu-in">Osprey Raptor 18</a> and after my son was asleep, taking his afternoon nap, I kissed my wife good bye and went to dress up my bike in its fine garments. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938380460/" title="Bicycle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8457/7938380460_cff51c9186_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bicycle" /></a></p>

<p>Where to go? I decided to visit the island of Köklot, part of the Kvarken Archipelago, Finland’s only UNESCO Natural World Heritage Site. I have visited the area in the past, and decided, that while riding to the main island which I have seen before, this little island on the site would be more interesting. A small beach, around 30 km from Vaasa, was were I planned to spend the night.</p>

<p>As riding on highways isn’t my favourite way to travel, I drove along backroads along the coast. Backroads in Finland are pretty good to cover distance, as you encounter minimum traffic. The scenery is dotted with summer cottages, though some are more like proper houses, and through the trees I glimpsed here and there the Baltic Sea. As I reached the end of the road I took a turn into the forest, where I found a trail which followed the power line. Along the trail, which was only just suited to riding, lingon berries and mushrooms were ripe for the taking. To my surprise, still a lot of mosquitos were around, and I made a happy mental note that it was smart that I took the mosquito headnet. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938444236/"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8310/7938444236_e90a5726ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" /></a></p>

<p>After a bit of bushwacking I finally reached the forest road I aimed for, and soon I was making good speed again. Then it didn’t take long to reach the highway, though fortunately I only needed to share the road a few hundred meters with the moronic car drivers, racing past me, until I made it to a cycle lane next to the street. From here it was smooth riding till the Raippaluoto bridge, Finland’s longest bridge. I drove a bit onto it, for the view, before I turned back. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938459112/" title="Speed limit by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8308/7938459112_b5e427dbe5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Speed limit" /></a></p>

<p>A small break at a rather well-equipped parking lot, where I picked some raspberries, followed. I was less than two hours on the road, and already covered some good distance. That the weather wasn’t very inspiring didn’t bother me too much, these various shades of grey had their own charme, and I was in good hopes that there would be a nice sunset and -rise to enjoy. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7857951104/" title="Raippaluoto bridge by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8447/7857951104_7ab11f7701_b.jpg" width="1024" height="601" alt="Raippaluoto bridge" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938787812/" title="Organic vs. Death by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8042/7938787812_7d9e6fb964_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Organic vs. Death" /></a></p>

<p>I cycled back to the road which would take me to Köklot. To my surprise there was a lot of traffic on it, and it being a side road the drivers seemed to even get more idiotic in terms of how fast they went. I was pondering what would be the most effective way to educate these lunatics in their cars, but ended up wondering if there are mobile EMP weapons which could take out cars in a radius of several hundred meters around me. That’d ensure that none but the oldest cars would go off coming close to me, and I would be safe from racing drivers [If someone needs an Alpha/ Beta Tester for EMP weapons for cyclists, I’m available].</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938768418/" title="Brännved by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8448/7938768418_1d8465731b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Brännved" /></a></p>

<p>While the road was scenic, I was happy to reach the beach I aimed for. It was still plenty early, and it wouldn’t be dark till 22 o’clock. I drove down and was delighted to find such a fine beach all to myself, well, maybe it wasn’t such a surprise as it started to rain. I put on my Rab Pulse and took shelter at one of the dressing cabins, while putting my <a href="http://youtu.be/Pj8sfJ2k7Yo">stove</a> on to boil some water for a hot cup of cappuciono and dinner. The clouds were doing their thing in the sky, while I carved myself a spoon, which I left at home to safe weight. I was happy.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s a good trade-off to take a 42 gram knife instead of a 18 gram spoon -the knife is multi-purpose!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>After dinner I decided to take a look at Köklot, the tiny settlement a few more kilometers down the road; conveniently the rain stopped, too. Also, while the beach was beautiful, it was a tad too close for my taste to the street and was facing south, which meant I might not see that sunrise I hoped for. Back on the street, all drivers finally seemed to have reached the places which they were in such a hurry to reach.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938803200/" title="Road to Köklot by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8180/7938803200_db405b6fe1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Road to Köklot" /></a></p>

<p>I passed a small fishing harbour, and a gorgeous sunset was on display at the horizon. Rain could be seen going north, and it was a pretty sight, with a few sailing boats out on the sea. I continued and drove into Köklot, where warm yellow light came through windows, but no one was to be seen on the street. Riding down a street brought me to an east facing shore, but all possible pitches were on someones land, so off limit. </p>

<p>I continued through the settlement for a bit, in the hope that there’d be some nice place somewhere close to the east-facing shore to pitch my tarp, but no luck. The sun now already set it was time to switch on my <a href="http://www.knog.com.au/gear-lights/boomer-rechargeable.phps">Knog Boomer USB lights</a> just in case one of those drivers decided to go out again for a ride, and cycled the few kilometers back to the beach.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855481330/" title="Pimpin' at the beach by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8429/7855481330_49fdb544f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Pimpin' at the beach" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855623042/" title="Cloudporn by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8298/7855623042_1240cc747c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Cloudporn" /></a></p>

<p>Back at the beach I looked for good spots to camp. Off into the forest I went, though between boulders large and small - these islands being created by the last ice age, they’re all rock - I didn’t find anything. Close to the beach there was a tiny patch of grass, just big enough, but it was at the end of the road, and I like my camps a tad more sheltered. On the sandy beach then I found one good spot. I put on my <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fmountain-hardwear-nitrous-down-jacket-mens">Mountain Hardwear Nitrous Down Jacket</a> and started to unpack, as I heard some hubbub from the street. </p>

<p>Hmmm. I waited, and shortly after a guy with a reindeer skin and some booze appeared. He walked straight to the shore, where he stood still, looking out on the water. Engine noise appeared, and a boat entered the bay, riding up to the shore. Reindeer man jumped in, and off they went. <em>Well, that was lucky</em>, I thought.</p>

<p>Or not. I just got the tarp out of the handlebar pack when a car drove down to the shore. Well, swell. It was ten o’clock by now, I was ready for bed, but not with a bunch of people coming to party where I planned to camp. Somehow that possibility didn’t even cross my mind as I picked this beach as a camping spot, though in hindsight it was obvious that also others might find this Friday evening a good time to go partying at <em>this beach</em>, which was so conveniently close located to the street.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I packed up in the dusk, and headed back up to the street, leaving the party beach behind. I decided to look for a place to camp on the road back to Vaasa, but was not very optimistic.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855660892/" title="Rain by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8439/7855660892_9de34ce63b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rain" /></a></p>

<p>A few turns went of the main street which I drove up just a few hours earlier, but most were leading to summer cottages, which meant they were off limit. Those two that I went down were either un-safe - the noise of heavy forest machinery rang through the forest, explaining the deep tracks I drove through - or so hard and bumpy that even the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Ftherm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm-sleeping-pad">NeoAir XTherm</a> I brought would not be enough to give me a comfortable sleep. An hour and 15 km later I was back at the highway to Vaasa, and another hour and another 15 km later I was just a bit past midnight back at home. My 24 trip was just a bit over nine hours.</p>

<p>While I was a bit disappointed by not sleeping outside - I looked forward to the sound of rain on my tarp and the sunrise - it was a fine ride. I cycled some 70 km, saw some nice places, and was exploring my new surroundings. I also learned to not pick camp places which are too close to a street - something to remember on my next 24 trip, which is just around the corner!</p>

<p><strong>Have you had failed trips? Tell us - what went wrong, and why? What lessons did you learn?</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bikepacking in Pirkanmaa]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/bikepacking-in-pirkanmaa.html"/>
    <updated>2012-06-19T22:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/bikepacking-in-pirkanmaa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;a href=”http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/driving-in-mud-rain.html”target=”_blank”&gt;My bike&lt;/a&gt; has given me the evil eye lately. It’s not that it doesn’t get used - it gets used daily on my commute to our house that I’m renovating, grocery shopping, and some fitness rides - but that it doesn’t get used enough on the singletrack trails and backend roads that it was made for. So when the three family dads of this story finally found a few free days where everyone was exempt from work and family duties, and my bike heard about it, she started to give me less trouble.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7382017036/" title="Le Ride by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7090/7382017036_bf756dbd48_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Le Ride" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>To celebrate the occasion of the first bikepacking trip, I took her to the mechanic who fixed her bent rear derailleur, and as a surprise there was a full set of white XPac &lt;a href=”http://www.porcelainrocket.com/”target=”_blank”&gt;Porcelain Rocket frambags&lt;/a&gt; waiting for her to be dressed up with. After that she was so happy, that the daily commute on asphalt didn’t bother her anymore - soon she’d be joined by two fine bikes on the trails and roads of Pirkanmaa, and she was eager for it.</p>

<p>Toni and Peter life in Turku, while I now hail from Vaasa, so we decided to meet in Pirkanmaa, which is fairly in the middle of us three. Parkano with its railway station close to the Pirkan Taival trail was made the starting point, and after an uneventful trip for me, I was before noon there. Checking Twitter, I had a few messages from Toni and Peter that VR managed to fuck up again (they call it technical problems, I call it running a business very inefficiently) and that they’d be late. Swell. I sat down to make lunch and a hot drink, after which a short phone call with Peter confirmed that they’d be here at around 15.45. Happily there was an electricity outlet to keep the iPhone charged, and I also had &lt;a href=”http://amzn.to/LRcEbu”target=”_blank”&gt;a good book&lt;/a&gt; with me to keep me entertained.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7382012782/" title="Waiting at Parkano Railway station by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7072/7382012782_0d1c9620cc_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Waiting at Parkano Railway station" /></a></p>

<p>VR managed to deliver Toni and Peter with bikes on time to Parkano, and while we had a brief chat about route, tire pressure and general chit chat, our bikes sniffed each others rear wheels, much like dogs do. Toni came, much to my pleasure, with his 9:Zero:7 fatbike, which is something to be seen in Person to understand how awesome these are. I also quickly saw that Toni and I are about the same height, so a test ride on his bike later on should be possible. Peter came on his Salsa Fargo, which looked like a sweet ride, too - but Peter being rather tall, a test ride would be out of the question. But the bikes were happy and ready, and so we set off. </p>

<p>Into a Military Zone. While checking smartphones and maps, a officer drove up, and inquired what we were up to. After taking our social security numbers and names, he led us to the “right” road - the road I wanted to avoid, as I found it boring when I walked it the last time, but well, if it brings us to our goal, so be it.</p>

<p>We rode for one and a half hour before arriving at the &lt;a href=”http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/nationalparks/seitseminen/Pages/Default.aspx”target=”_blank”&gt;Seitseminen Visitor Centre&lt;/a&gt;, which was open for another 30 minutes. Loading up on food and each of us buying a map, we sat there, enjoyed our hamburgers, coffee and cake, and decided how to go forward. A short consultation with the staff of the Visitor Centre confirmed that all trails are open for cyclists in the National Park, and that the especially marked cycling trails are just a bit wider. Swell news - Lets roll.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7399981834/" title="Peter shows how to ride planks. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7215/7399981834_cc9a988a8a_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Peter shows how to ride planks." /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7399997138/" title="Toni on the singletrack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7077/7399997138_992065a3fd_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Toni on the singletrack" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7400017582/" title="More duckboards, more Cottongrass by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8151/7400017582_61ec646d44_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="More duckboards, more Cottongrass" /></a></p>

<p>While I have ridden a bit on trails, it was nothing like this. This was, in the words of Toni &amp; Peter - ‘<i>Awesome singletrack</i>’. While the two raced speedily over the trails and duckboards, yours truly and his steed took a bit slower, to gather up the skills and balls that it takes to ride down steep, rocky singletrack. We made good speed and drove, with plenty of little breaks, onwards to Kovero, the old croft in the National Park, where we rested for a bit. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7400019436/" title="Door handle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7092/7400019436_cdf290bba1_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Door handle" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381904438/" title="Kovero by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7074/7381904438_592d804688_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Kovero" /></a></p>

<p>Then it went forward over forest roads towards our chosen campsite at Löyttöjärvi, with a short stretch of trail as a shortcut. It was a nice stretch, but it was getting late, and I felt my attention wane, and was happy as we reached the forest road. Just another hour and a half till we’d be there; happily my &lt;a href=”http://www.porcelainrocket.com/products/accessory-packs/top-tube-pack/”target=”_blank”&gt;PR Top Tube Pack&lt;/a&gt; held a good amount and variety of chocolate bars - useful for quick energy, I just need to work on how to open them with one hand.</p>

<p>Arriving at camp, a fire needed starting; not because it was cold, but looking at an empty fire pit is just, hmm, not very interesting. Toni &amp; Peter designated me to have the honour to start it, as I’m the ‘<i>professional</i>’ =) A few minutes later, we were sitting on the bench, starring into the Wilderness TV, pondering what to do next. Ah ja, there was this thing with food. Gas stoves were brought up from the depth of frame packs, and quickly water was boiling, meals were hydrated &amp; consumed.</p>

<p>On the Tuesday the same week I went to get a pad &amp; some other kit from my in-laws, where I have my outdoor gear stored. Of course I managed to forget to take the pad among the other stuff I took, so all I had were six segments of a &lt;a href=”http://amzn.to/MsJPk8”target=”_blank”&gt;ZLite&lt;/a&gt;, which was really pushing it (in hindsight I should have brought ten, I had the space and segements) but I managed to find a comfortable spot for my bivy nevertheless. The weather was so good, and the sky clear, that I didn’t bother pitching my &lt;a href=”http://gossamergear.com/shelters/shelters.html”target=”_blank”&gt;shelter&lt;/a&gt;, though the bug free environment which Peter had under his Double Rainbow would have been welcome. The sound of billions of mosquitos soon had me sleeping, though, even if a bit more distance between them and me would have been cool.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7400016170/" title="At camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7234/7400016170_c202f9c3ac_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="At camp" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7382014094/" title="Peter at Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5116/7382014094_a3a7c47f21_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Peter at Camp" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381684016/" title="A bike and a bivy. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8148/7381684016_83a096ac95_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="A bike and a bivy." /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7400016860/" title="Morning glory by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7239/7400016860_cd193e45a8_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Morning glory" /></a></p>

<p>I woke up at 6.30 in the morning, and carefully rising to see if either of my companions were up already, which wasn’t the case, I lay down again and went back to sleep. 90 minutes later I saw Peter up, and despite the army of mosquitos hovering above me, I got out of the bivy and into my &lt;a href=”http://amzn.to/McblXM”target=”_blank”&gt;Arc’teryx Palisade pants&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=”http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/shell/pulse-jacket.html”target=”_blank”&gt;Rab Pulse jacket&lt;/a&gt; to keep them off. A cup of coffee was all we three had for breakfast, as the lack of water at the camping spot hindered us from going very fancy in terms of cooking. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381885298/" title="Toni enjoying himself by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7232/7381885298_82f0781c4e_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Toni enjoying himself" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381908286/" title="On the way to Kuru by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5323/7381908286_d0c06e1782_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="On the way to Kuru" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381648362/" title="My ride on the Pirkan Taival Trail by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7222/7381648362_2ea44868f8_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="My ride on the Pirkan Taival Trail" /></a></p>

<p>Some very fine singletrack brought us to my old school, where we tanked up on water. Peter and Toni found it too late for breakfast now, and so we rode on - until Toni stopped at the Kuru Hardware Store to find some screws for his fenders, which were misbehaving.</p>

<p>After riding out of Kuru on the street we soon took a turn and were on one of the silent backroads which criss-cross the Pirkanmaa. Rolling hills, partly over asphalt, mostly on grit, with less than five cars passing us on some 25 km - fine riding. Up, down, curves, straight, forest, fields, lakes, tiny villages, summer cottages, farms, more forest - this is Finland at its best, experienced in the best way. </p>

<p>We roll down a grit road to a jetty, where we have lunch. As I’m looking for a way to get water from the lake, I spot a nest - with two hatching eggs. Excited we snap a few photos before the parents return, and keep a save distance to not disturb them, or to agitate the parents. Meals are consumed, coffees drunk, dishes cleaned and we continue. The parents return to the nest as we leave, surely happy that these intrudes were more interested in their own food than their offspring.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381903074/" title="Lunch break by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7243/7381903074_0c1ea5f726_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Lunch break" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381910156/" title="Hatching by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5039/7381910156_7f83d47e04_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Hatching" /></a></p>

<p>We continue over the same kind of fine roads for a dozen or so kilometers, and it is here that I try Toni’s fatbike. Wow, how much fun - and so fast! I thought it would be sluggish going on the asphalt, but it is quick and feels even faster than my own bike. We switch bikes again and continue, until we hit the highway. Before we join trucks and cars, we first have a quick stop at the Supermarket: Toni and Peter to have an ice cream, me to restock on chocolate bars and some juice. Then, on the side of the road we cycle onwards, the trucks and cars rushing passed us, but always trying to stay as far away as possible from us. Nevertheless, really comfortable I don’t feel here, and am happy as we turn on the old highway, which sees a lot less traffic - and after some ten kilometers or so even has a cycling path going till Tampere!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381978006/" title="Cycling uphill by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8153/7381978006_143cd7c3ea_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Cycling uphill" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7381972826/" title="Ice cream break by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8011/7381972826_f3c4c9f4ca_c.jpg" width="800" height="531" alt="Ice cream break" /></a></p>

<p>We roll into Tampere at pretty much four o’clock in the afternoon, the sun high in the sky. Peter had some problems with his bike, so I show him &lt;a href=”http://www.rtechsuspension.fi/”target=”_blank”&gt;R-Tech Suspension&lt;/a&gt;, Tampere’s finest bike shop, where his bike was fixed quickly while we sat and ate - first some sandwiches, then some more ice cream. </p>

<p><a href="http://distilleryimage1.s3.amazonaws.com/71ebb95cb6f711e1bf341231380f8a12_7.jpg" imageanchor="1" style=""><img border="0" height="612" width="612" src="http://distilleryimage1.s3.amazonaws.com/71ebb95cb6f711e1bf341231380f8a12_7.jpg" /></a></p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>And so it ends. I head in time to the Railway Station to catch my train back to Vaasa, while Toni and Peter continued to explore the south of Tampere. You definitely should read and see their account of the trip, by the way: &lt;a href=”http://www.yetirides.com/2012/06/bikepacking-in-pirkanmaa.html”target=”_blank”&gt;Peter&lt;/a&gt;</td>
      <td> &lt;a href=”http://tonilund.blogspot.fi/2012/06/pirkanmaa-tour-i.html”target=”_blank”&gt;Toni&lt;/a&gt;</td>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157630149618156/”target=”_blank”&gt;More of my photos&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><b>Lessons learned</b>? It is hard to put into words or photos the immense fun this trip was. We covered 135 km in about 24 hours, 55 km on Thursday, and 80 km on Friday - I didn’t even think I’d be capable of riding that far, and am sure that without Peter &amp; Toni wouldn’t even have tried - it is great if someone pushes you over your boundaries. </p>

<p>Riding singletrack like the one in Seitseminen with a full bikepacking setup also was a first for me, and lots of fun - duck boards seem challenging, but once you realize that you can do it, it is no problem and good, adrenaline-infusing fun. As is going downhill and fast on curvy forest paths. </p>

<p>Ultralight backpacking gives you the gear and skills to try &lt;a href=”http://www.hikinginfinland.com/2011/05/bikepacking-in-finland.html”target=”_blank”&gt;bikepacking&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, you need some additional storage options (and let me tell ya, my &lt;a href=”http://www.porcelainrocket.com/”target=”_blank”&gt;Porcelain Rocket frame packs&lt;/a&gt; are the sexiest pieces of gear I’ve got in a looooong time), and here you can either use what you have and do some MYOG goodies, or go down the custom-made route. Though in terms of camping gear you are very well equipped already, and your small, light and compact kit makes a perfect setup for bikepacking.</p>

<p>Photo wise I think Toni and Peter had an interesting setup - both used a &lt;a href=”http://amzn.to/PlZeqO”target=”_blank”&gt;LowePro Slingshot&lt;/a&gt; which allowed them to have the camera really quickly in their hands, additionally Peter used a point-and-shoot to take photos while riding. I think you can easily see that they have more experience in this discipline than me, and if you want to see some photos of my riding you need to check out their posts =) I on the other hand set on hydration and had a &lt;a href=”http://amzn.to/KKhJqR”target=”_blank”&gt;Osprey Raptor 18&lt;/a&gt; on my back, which also carried my &lt;a href=”http://amzn.to/AcVjjw”target=”_blank”&gt;camera&lt;/a&gt; - but it wasn’t as quick and accessible as Peter &amp; Toni’s setup. I’m pondering if a &lt;a href=”http://amzn.to/MqqSAK”target=”_blank”&gt;small point and shoot&lt;/a&gt; would be useful for taking photos while riding, and using the Sony NEX-5N when I stop.</p>

<p>Anyway. I’m hooked. Negotiations are on-going to broker for more free time for bikepacking trips, possibly with the additional use of something inflatable to be used with a paddle. And a re-run of this trip is in the planning for the autumn. Same cast, other bikes, same fun. Thank you Toni and Peter, looking forward to ride again soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
