<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: alpinism | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/alpinism/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-13T18:51:42+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jon Griffith: Alpine Exposures]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T16:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jon Griffith’s photo book <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/pages/book">Alpine Exposures</a> is the culmination of over ten years photographing in the Alps. Full of breath-taking images that depict some of the best ways to move in the mountains, this is the coffee table book you wanted for those days where you can not head out yourself or need some motivation to get up at 1 am.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16050375500" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/16050375500_2694d126ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I have been following Jonathan Griffith’s photography since many years via his <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/blogs/chamonix-conditions">blog</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Alpine-Exposures-Jon-Griffith-Photography/120793041299250">Facebook</a> so when word came out that he was working on a photo book I knew it would be superb. Jon regularly kept readers and Fans up to date about the process of producing and publishing this book, and just in time for the holidays the alpine exposures came out last November. </p>

<p>Alpine Exposures starts off with a Foreword by Ueli Steck which is one of the best forewords I have read in a while. Honest and appraising, highlighting why Jon takes such good photos (because he’s a mountaineer first, photographer second) Ueli sets the tone for the book and gets you excited to turn the pages. Jon follows that up with an equally touching Introduction before you meet some of Jon’s rope partners and then you can start to enjoy the photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16211793956" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/16211793956_541519cb26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<p>The book is written in three languages: English, French and German. This lingual trinity is well executed with a good layout that’s easy to read and follow throughout the book. It’s high-quality paper that depicts the superb images very well, and it’s a pleasure to read the book. The photos all are from real situations, so no fake “Lets go to the Aiguille Du Midi and do some shoots on the Cosmiques” kind of photos. The seven distinct chapters in the book show Jon’s favourite photos from Alpinism, Skiing, Climbing, Landscape, Ice Climbing, Flight (BASE and Paragliding) and Work. In between the photos are here and there short anecdotes from climbs and work trips, and some climbs are highlighted in longer photo essays which not just give you an idea of the route if you’re planning to climb it yourself, it also adds variation to the book and makes it very interesting for alpinists that want to attempt some of these routes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16050174968" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7517/16050174968_925b8dd4f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<p>This is the coffee table book you wished you would have gotten as a present from Santa last Christmas. Cover to cover it features breathtaking photos from the mountains and people having fun in them, and will inspire you to make a trip to Chamonix as soon as possible so you can experience the beauty yourself. It’s a book for alpinists, climbers and photographers and you’ll have a hard time putting it down once you start to read it. <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/kx49us95qxbuj0f/Alpine_Exposures_Sample.pdf?dl=0">View a 60 page sample online</a>, if you’re convinced (and you will be!) you can buy your copy of <em>alpine exposures</em> directly from Jon at <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/products/alpine-exposures-photo-book-10-years-of-photography-by-jon-griffith">Alpine Exposures</a>, your local book shop or order it online from <a href="http://amzn.to/1I10mLL">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1xYMvBb">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1APW8EE">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T12:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ve probably seen a trend in my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">book reviews</a> in the last years: They’ve been more and more about mountaineering and climbing. Why that is so I’ll explain at another time, but now I want to take you along and tell you about the latest book I have read, <em>8000 Metres - Climbing the World’s Highest Mountains by Alan Hinkes</em>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15985413000" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8658/15985413000_e521caa7ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There’s 14 8.000 m peaks on this planet and Alan Hinkes is the first British Mountaineer to have successfully summited all fourteen of them. In his splendid coffee table book “<a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/tab/detail/iid/1/show/description#.VKZk6cbvR_0">8000 Meters - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</a>” he tells the stories and shares his fantastic photos with the reader. Its a chronological layout and after a Foreword, Preface and Introduction we start at Alan’s first 8.000 m summit, Shisha Pangma, which he climbed in 1987. </p>

<p>From that year one Alan has been almost every season in the Himalayas and Karakoram on a quest to climb 8.000 m peaks, even if climbing all 14 of them wasn’t something that he set out to from the start. His writing style is very enjoyable: Honest, down-to-earth and lacking hyperboles which easily could sneak itself in when writing about climbing the highest peaks on the planet. The thoughtful texts describe the experiences of climbing the high mountains, what kind of mental and physical difficulties one can face, from the waiting game in base camp while sitting out bad weather and passing frozen corpses high on the mountains to climbing difficulties and getting up and down these peaks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15986690559" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7463/15986690559_90c9064a27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World &#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<p>Alan’s climbing Motto is <em>“No mountain is worth a life, coming back is a success and the summit is only a bonus”</em> and throughout the book he also highlights the importance to have enough power reserves for the descent. What happens if you don’t have these Alan has seen in his friends on some expeditions, which burned themselves out on the ascent and then had no energy left for the descent, which often is even more dangerous than going up. </p>

<p>In between chapers there are small anecdotes from Alan’s encounters with fellow mountaineers like Reinhold Messner and Jerzy Kukuczka or the Trek-Ins to base camps and local cuisine. These loosen up the already enjoyable peak stories. A real highlight for me are the fantastic photos Alan has shot during his ascents and from his travels to these two mountain ranges. The photos were shot before the rise of automatic digital cameras and so one needed to know how to adjust ISO, Aperture and Shutter Speed to get great results, and the photos in this book are proof that Alan knows his trade. I have spent a lot of time just browsing the photos, tracing the lines described in the texts to the summit, and enjoy the vast views which you can have when standing on the top of the world. </p>

<p><em>8000 Metres - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</em> is a highly enjoyable book that shouldn’t be missing on your bookshelf if you like mountaineering, alpinism and are dreaming of the highest peaks of the planet. The honest &amp; evocative writing is on par with the superb images in the book, and if you ever hope to stand on top of a 8.000 m peak you will do well to read Alan’s book and follow his Motto!</p>

<p>Get the book at your local bookshop, directly from <a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/title/8000-metres#.VKZejsbvR_0">Cicerone</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/1wIIMnr">Amazon.de</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1xzM7fy">Amazon.com</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1yehuvP">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard Interview]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T11:11:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An interview with Barry Blanchard, one of Canada’s most famous Alpinists, in which we chat about music, fear and his book “<a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">The Calling</a>”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15606594195" title="Barry Blanchard by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5608/15606594195_52bea0a1b6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Barry Blanchard" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Barry, thanks for taking the time to answer a few questions from an aspiring Alpinist in Finland. First things first: What song are you right now listening too?</strong></p>

<p><em>Snake Farm by Ray Wylie Hubbard. I’ve listen his music since I was teenager and had the pleasure of meeting the man, and his wife, Judy, yesterday at a concert in the park. Very, very cool.</em></p>

<p><strong>What’s your favourite medium: MP3, Vinyl or Cassettes?</strong></p>

<p><em>I listen to most music on my computer these days so I guess its MP3, although I still listen to CDs in my truck.</em></p>

<p><strong>If you would make a mixtape for a road trip, which songs would definitely be on there?</strong></p>

<p><em>On my road tripping mix there would definitely be: King of the Road by Roger Miller, Six Days on the Road by Dave Dudley and a cover by Steve Earle, Hurtin Albertan by Corb Lund and by Tim Hus, Running on Empty by Jackson Browne, Continental Trailways Blues by Steve Earle, Brand New Cadillac by the Clash, Cadillac Ranch by Bruce Springsteen, Born to Run by Bruce Springsteen … and the list goes on.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15421002960" title="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/15421002960_d3178af41a_b.jpg" width="678" height="1024" alt="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p><strong>I really enjoyed reading your book, by the way. It was raw, to the point and I had a few good laughs. It also had a Quentin Tarantino-esque feel to it at times: Good music, story lines that interweave and come together at the end. Did you plan it like that?</strong></p>

<p><em>My friend, Mark Twight, told me that my book would not end up being what I thought it would be, and that it would be more work than I thought it would be. He was right on both counts. I wanted to write a full 360 degree view of my life and climbing as I believe that much of the value in my writing is that which is common to all people: love, loss, desire, fear, hurt, joy. I believe I share the most that way and that is what writing is for me, a hope to share a little something about life with people.</em></p>

<p><strong>The weather this summer in Chamonix seems to have been much the same as you first visited the crucible of European Alpinism. Any idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer?</strong></p>

<p><em>I have no idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer. Mark Twight and I were pleased to see that our route, The Richard Cranium Memorial, had several repeats in the last couple years and that the ascensionists seemed to enjoy it.</em></p>

<p><strong>Reinhold Messner, another of your idols judging from your book, just got 70 in September. Did you send him a card or where even invited?</strong></p>

<p><em>Reinhold didn’t invite me to his birthday, but he might have invited my guiding mentor, Rudi Kranibitter, who took Reinhold out climbing in Reinhold’s early days and taught him some stuff. Rudi once told me “Ya, that guy was a fast learner!”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14985858864" title="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/14985858864_8c1c2399df_b.jpg" width="710" height="1024" alt="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You are well-read and have devoured a lot of books - from Heinrich Harrer’s “The White Spider” to Lionel Terray’s “Conquistadors of the Useless”. If you could recommend just three books to aspiring alpinists, which ones would that be?</strong></p>

<p><em>I would recommend: <a href="http://amzn.to/1xc7z5m">The Great Days</a> by Walter Bonatti, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vRe3bB">The Seventh Grade</a> by Reinhold Messner and <a href="http://amzn.to/12gRwtY">Feeding the Rat</a> by Al Alvarez.</em></p>

<p><strong>One of your colleagues, Andy Kirkpatrick from the UK, made in his essay “How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche” his first point to not have kids. You’re a father of two - do you feel you climbed harder pre-fatherhood or that you stayed on the same level?</strong></p>

<p><em>I definitely climbed harder before the birth of my daughters but I became a father at 45 and I was, by then, far past my physical prime that was, for me, between 25 and 35. I just can’t climb as hard now, especially at 55! as I could when I was younger. But! the inner journey up the easier mountain is still as challenging and rewarding, maybe more so on both counts.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15582918726" title="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3951/15582918726_29591133dd_b.jpg" width="672" height="1024" alt="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee" /></a></p>

<p><strong>As someone who likes to climb mountains myself it feels like the majority of climbers nowadays are rather enjoying themselves in gyms or bouldering. How would you try to get these people outside?</strong></p>

<p><em>I think that once gym climbers and boulders experience the added challenges of traditional climbing, especially dealing with risk, some of them will be called to the richness of alpinism, but it is a dangerous game so it is not for everyone.</em></p>

<p><strong>Is there a chapter of your climbing life that you wished would have made it in the book still?</strong></p>

<p><em>When I sat down to write The Calling I thought that it would cover my whole climbing life, but I’ve been cursed with a long memory and seemed to have a lot to write. I’d like to write a second book to cover the rest of my climbing life beyond 1988.</em></p>

<p><strong>Well Barry, many thanks again and have fun on the book tour!</strong></p>

<p><em>You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">read my Review of Barry’s book “The Calling” here</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard - The Calling]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T06:23:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What do Joy Division, The Rolling Stones, Les Droites, Nanga Parbet and the Cassin Ridge have in common?</em> They play a part in Barry Blanchard’s life, which is aptly re-told in his memoirs, “The Calling”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15451426995" title="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15451426995_53b9507d6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="675" alt="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge.of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Tune in to the soundtrack of Barry’s life with this Playlist, dutifully reconstructed from Chapter 2:</p>

<iframe src="https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify:user:skullmonkey:playlist:7qy8hUL8yIyABU8JFRfj3z" width="300" height="380" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true"></iframe>

<p>Alpinism and mountaineering books tend to often be of interest only to pursuers of these activities. But Barry manages to write his memoirs in such a compelling edge-of-your-seat style that also non-climbers will be eagerly turning each page to read how the stories unfold. And unfold they do. And if you haven’t heard of Barry before, that’s easily fixed: He is <em>one of North America’s top alpinists, noted for pushing the standards of highly technical, high-risk alpine climbing in the Canadian Rockies and the Himalayas.</em> But nobody is born an alpinist, even if it is their calling.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264859557" title="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15264859557_249539e96d_b.jpg" width="660" height="1024" alt="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the.exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never.been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p>In 20 chapters <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">The Calling</a> stops at important stations in Barry’s life, but does not take a linear approach. It’s more a Tarantino style, weaving stories together, jumping between different stations, different countries, different mountains, different climbing partners. It starts off with an Avalanche and only later on you learn more about how the four rope partners ended up in that situation on a high Himalaya peak. It’s followed two chapters on how Barry grew up and how he got into climbing (via the Canadian equivalent of the Boy Scouts), and that especially will be of interest to aspiring alpinists and climbers around the globe. From how he loaned books at the library on how to climb to saving up to buy his first climbing shoes, it shows that Barry is from a pre-Internet era where you couldn’t just order the latest gear and books online - but often head to search in shops across town to find what you wear looking for.</p>

<p>Really interesting are the personal stories and how Barry manages to illustrate his climbing partners: Kevin and Ward, Gregg and David, Mark and Phil and many more. If you climb, especially in the mountains, you know how important it is to be able to totally trust the person at the other end of the rope, and Barry is able to communicate that trust between climbing partners wonderfully. The story accompanies Barry and his partners as they learn to climb - from Trad at the Wasootch Slabs with Phil to alpine climbing the Calgary Route on Mt Yamnuska with Gray, all told in such a fun way that I couldn’t help but chuckle a few times. After a stop in Chamonix and taking Rebuffat’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1pECtyN">The Hundred Finest Routes</a> as a tick-list Barry travels a bit through Europe (and manages to lose his wallet and passport) before heading back to Canada and onwards to Yosemite. We see how Barry makes the decision to quit his salesman job to go more climbing and becoming a guide, all while repeating hard routes in Canada and the USA.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15448265551" title="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3929/15448265551_a50450ccbc_b.jpg" width="676" height="1024" alt="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p>And as the walls and routes keep getting bigger &amp; more committing we accompany Barry to the Karakoram &amp; Himalaya, to Peru and the Cassin Ridge and read captivating accounts of daring alpine ascents. Always interweaved are anecdotes from his time - be it books (I got away with a whole list of books to read) to music (see above) to relationships and how climbing gear has evolved. The writing is lively &amp; outspoken and I often was laughing out loud, and it was able to keep me on reading until I finished the book in a week, often reading in my lunch breaks and late till night. It were the personal connections with his rope partners that I found very fascinating and that kept me on reading past bedtime, how they pushed themselves on to become better climbers, train together, climb together, party together and go on expeditions together, all while trying to figure out how to be able to get out more to the mountains. If you have a longing for the mountains but can’t be in them as much as you like (and don’t want to quit your job just yet for them), I can warmly recommend you this fine book for your mountain fix. It’s captivating style with adventures from near &amp; far will keep you entertained for many days, and after you’re done you’ll go through the book again - to search out some of the books Barry mentioned, look up a song and re-read about the daring ascents.</p>

<p>Get your paper or digital copy today from <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">Patagonia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1rTGvIH">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vDx8O1">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1nTA8oO">Amazon.de</a> or your local book store.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264720600" title="The Calling Cover by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15264720600_920b3f8714_b.jpg" width="674" height="1024" alt="The Calling Cover" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-08T11:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What if <a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a> would go and build an alpine climbing pack that is minimalistic, comfortable, highly water-resistant and durable? Would it work also for backpacking?</em> These and other questions I answer in this review.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193953927" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/14193953927_5201bcbb49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l-505024.html">Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L</a> landed here in March 2014 and has been used various times at the local crag and in Chamonix, a week backpacking in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/lake-district/">Lake District</a> and a week climbing &amp; hiking in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/poland/">Polish Tatras</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193760149" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2916/14193760149_8ba4f829a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>This is a streamlined alpine climbing backpack with more space than it’s litte brothers (there’s a <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-25-l-505021.html?farbe=tailored%20grey">25 l</a> and <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-505022.html?farbe=electric%20orange">35 l</a> version available), made to carry more climbing gear for big ascents and/ or an overnight kit. It carries very well thanks to the Aluminium frame and easily can be used for week-long ultralight backpacking strips.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14378961872" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2926/14378961872_aeec0f6d90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>This is what Patagonia says about their pack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Light and durable nylon ripstop with excellent tear and abrasion resistance </li>
  <li>The spindrift collar opens wide for easy packing; drawcord simultaneously cinches collar and closes lid for a secure seal; additional spindrift collar deploys to protect your gear when you have overstuffed your pack</li>
  <li>Aluminium stay frame with tensioned mesh center gives the pack structure and helps to support heavy loads and can be removed for Fast &amp; Light adventures</li>
  <li>Padded hip belt can be removed to create a simple webbing hip belt</li>
  <li>Center sheath ice axe carry system accommodates a wide assortment of axes</li>
  <li>Daisy chains on front and side panels provide lashing options; compression straps on sides help manage different size loads; zippered pocket on lid provides easy access to small items</li>
</ul>

<p>What they fail to mention is that this pack is the brain-child of Steve House, one of the world’s top alpinists. This pack won’t make you climb like him, but at least you can carry your gear like him =)</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/FnWap_pZ3YU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Something I haven’t seen before is the internal frame system that Patagonia uses in this pack. It’s an aluminium frame that’s covered by mesh and that’s super flexible - you can twist it 180° so it gives the pack great freedom of movement. The DWR on the material is also very good and kept my gear inside dry during hikes in sustained, heavy rain from all angles. Also the inside rain-cover is a nice way to not need an external one when you carry more gear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624434903" title="Patagonia Ascensionist internal frame by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5530/14624434903_5969025411_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist internal frame" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After over two weeks of backpacking, climbing and scrambling with it it still shows no tears or signs of weakness. The DWR also still holds up very well, and all seams - despite some heavier loads and being fully packed - are still perfect like on day one. I think this pack will be with me for many hikes and climbs to come.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624459203" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3918/14624459203_a9bd18b0f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Patagonia Ascensionist is available in two lengths and I have the S/ M length of the pack. </p>

<p>Stripped Pack: 847
Frame: 151 g
Hipbelt: 140 g</p>

<p>TOTAL: 1138g</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417796848" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3838/14417796848_c8389e3d6c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="770" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>It’s Patagonia who made this pack so you know it has top-notch environmental credentials. ‘Nuff said!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602382524" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2939/14602382524_dd6979ab34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a wide variety of <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/kletterrucksack.html">climbing backpacks</a>, very good ones are the <a href="http://bit.ly/1qR0yaH">Crux AK-47</a> and the <a href="http://www.campsaver.com/speed-22-pack">Black Diamond Speed</a> packs. <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/">Cilogear</a> also makes top-notch climbing packs, as does <a href="http://www.mchalepacks.com/ultralight/index.htm">McHale</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14581386756" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3904/14581386756_39bdddd491_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The closure of the pack is really nice. It is easy to open and close, even if it seems like an old-fashioned closure it is a smart system in my opinion. You can close it with one hand, opening with both. You pull the cord to close it, and then put the aluminium hook through the webbing loop. Even when fully packed it’s easy to open and close and most important - it stays closed. The front aluminium hook can be moved up if it’s really fully loaded. </p>

<p>The elastic loops to tie down straps are a very nice detail. This way webbing does not dangle around when the straps are pulled tight - if you’re anal-retentive about straps and stuff dangling around on your pack and like things to be orderly you will really like this small addition to all the straps.</p>

<p>Your ice axes or <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools.html">ice tools</a> are connected to the pack via a small and durable ice axe pocket with a buckle at the front pocket and the shafts are held in place by the side compression straps. It’s a safe, good system for transport to the mountain and when you really won’t need it. For in between sections where you won’t need the tools you can store the ice axe He-Man style between your shoulder blade and strap.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14581388176" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2903/14581388176_f817a9ed5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<p>The top pocket is surprisingly spacious and I can fit a large amount of stuff in there. Map, compass, sunscreen, lip balm, snacks, shades, extra camera lens - and still room to spare. It’s fairly weatherproof too, so in case you forgot your phone’s rain cover it’s safe in there (but even safer inside the pack!).</p>

<p>For a 45 l pack the Ascensionist is super spacious. Food and UL kit for six days + 2 l water were no problem for it, and there would have been even more space - that large opening + inside rainflap makes it a very large backpack. But also a full trad kit, helmet, harness, crampons and rope + UL sleeping gear and snacks fit in there with some room left. I really like the form of the pack with the narrow bottom and the wider top - it makes for easy packing. Food or climbing gear go in the bottom, followed by down garments and rain clothes, kitchen, quilt, bivy, shelter and helmet. Water bottles I store on the top of everything for easy access.</p>

<p>So is the Ascensionist better with the frame or without? That’s a difficult question to answer. In the Lake District I had the frame in the pack and found it worked superb. In the Polish Tatras I left the frame at home and also found it excellent. Subjectively I feel with the frame it carries slightly better and transfers weight more effectively to the hipbelt. The pack has what feels like a closed cell foam pad in the back which does a good job of keeping the shape of the pack when the frame is removed and also gives a bit of extra cushioning against your back. </p>

<p>Moving with it - climbing, hiking, scrambling - is wonderful. It rides high on the waist and does not limit movement at all. As it is a streamlined pack it you also have no stuff at the sides in your way, and low chances of the pack snagging something along the route or trail. As the pack is narrow and not very deep it’s close to the body so you can squeeze through tight passages, and your centre of gravity is close to where it’s supposed to be. The thickly cushioned shoulder straps are comfy also on long days, as is the hip belt. The gear loops on the hip belt are solid and a welcome addition to rack gear on long routes.</p>

<p>Oh, and you also can attach the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Designs Capture PRO</a> wonderfully to the shoulder straps!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417878278" title="Hiking in the Polish Tatras by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5507/14417878278_ff97606b7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking in the Polish Tatras" /></a></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>When climbing with the frame in the pack I often would hit my head on it when looking up, which is not good. Removing the frame solves this, but it’s better with the frame inside for carrying heavier loads. If it’s possible I’d imagine making the internal frame shorter would solve this, as would a gap for the helmet when climbing/ looking up. </p>

<p>You can remove the padded hipbelt (and save 140 gram weight) but it’s too complicated - mainly because the wide webbing belt is sewn to the pack and can’t be removed. So you need to thread the webbing through the padding loops to take it off. I’d wish that everything could have been removed easily - I don’t see much sense in using the webbing as a hipbelt.</p>

<p>Water Management is not as straight forward as I’d like it to be. There’s no hydration system exit and no side pockets, so you need to take the pack off to drink. When climbing this is fine as you likely take the pack off at the belay and then can drink, but when hiking it’s not convenient to stop every 30 minutes to take the pack off to access your water bottle. You could attach your water bottle with a carabiner to the gear loop on the hipbelt, though I think that would be annoying if you have a bottle dangling in front of your legs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417828779" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3924/14417828779_643901874a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>At the moment the Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L is my favourite backpack. It carries very well, is large enough for week-long trips - be it climbing or backpacking - and can take a lot of abuse. It’s weatherproof, easy to pack, the big haul loop makes it easy to grab the pack &amp; put on, and the cushioned shoulder straps and hip belt make it comfortable to carry also on 30 km days with 2000+ m of ascent. Most importantly it does not bother me when climbing or scrambling and gives me freedom of movement to go to those high places I enjoy so much! If you’re in the market for a large-volume alpine climbing backpack I can really recommend the Ascensionist 45L from <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia.html">Patagonia</a>.</p>

<p>Oh, in orange it also looks great - Hup Holland Hup!</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Get your Ascensionist pack at <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l-505024.html">Unterwegs.biz</a> if you are in Europe, from <a href="http://bit.ly/1qG5cXo">CampSaver</a> if you’re in the USA or directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1lPYO9Z">Patagonia</a> everywhere else. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602411384" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3917/14602411384_f4f4f02911_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
