<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: alpinism | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/alpinism/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-01T21:12:05+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Top of the World - Herausforderung 8000er]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/on-top-of-the-world-herausforderung-8000er.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-30T14:56:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/on-top-of-the-world-herausforderung-8000er</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you like to know more about the history of the highest peaks on this planet, then <em>On Top of the World. The New Millennium</em> as <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/list?back=9db5a3e1b607eeefc414b4266862f7c2&amp;xid=11345923">Herausforderung 8000er</a> is called in English, should be on your bookshelf. Packed with detailed information and chronics from the first ascents to the newest route attempts, Herausforderung 8000er is required reading if you want to climb one of the highest mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16213778198" title="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7355/16213778198_ccd2dbe9e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="765" alt="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>After reading <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters.html">8000 Metres</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html">Alpine Exposures</a> Herausforderung 8000er from the <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/">Tyrolia Verlag</a> is the third book in the mountaineering corner on my bookshelf which is about the highest of peaks. Besides detailed topographic photos and lists of the first ascents on the different routes it are the captivating stories from the ascents and expeditions which are worth getting this book. </p>

<p>The book has 17 chapter - after an introduction each 8.000 m peak has its own chapter where stories about the first ascents, the different expeditions, tragic accidents and solo ascents are given, with lists on the first ascents on the many routes on the peaks. It gets interesting in the “The New Millennium” sections, where stories about more current ascents are told. So the book goes from Annapurna to Shisha Pangma and then finishes with an outlook on the next decade and all relevant statistics.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16399669221" title="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/16399669221_1d67e65f4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="796" alt="Herausforderung 8000er - On Top of the World" /></a></p>

<p>Not just the stories are captivating, also the superb photos from the mountains &amp; expeditions will let you forget the time when you’re reading this book. It highlights how some 8.000 m mountains nowadays can be attempted by normal people while at the same time alpinists on the cutting edge still find new routes up these same peaks. If you dream about standing on the top of the world on one of these mountains, then you should get Herausforderung 8000er - <em>On Top of the World. The New Millennium</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/leseproben/9783702232948/leseprobe.pdf">View the sample</a> and then get the book in German directly from <a href="http://www.tyroliaverlag.at/list?back=9db5a3e1b607eeefc414b4266862f7c2&amp;xid=11345923">Tyrolia</a>, your local bookshop or <a href="http://amzn.to/1uIeFNA">Amazon.de</a> or buy the English Edition at <a href="http://amzn.to/1uIf6ay">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1CiQkpf">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jon Griffith: Alpine Exposures]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T16:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/jon-griffith-alpine-exposures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jon Griffith’s photo book <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/pages/book">Alpine Exposures</a> is the culmination of over ten years photographing in the Alps. Full of breath-taking images that depict some of the best ways to move in the mountains, this is the coffee table book you wanted for those days where you can not head out yourself or need some motivation to get up at 1 am.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16050375500" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/16050375500_2694d126ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I have been following Jonathan Griffith’s photography since many years via his <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/blogs/chamonix-conditions">blog</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Alpine-Exposures-Jon-Griffith-Photography/120793041299250">Facebook</a> so when word came out that he was working on a photo book I knew it would be superb. Jon regularly kept readers and Fans up to date about the process of producing and publishing this book, and just in time for the holidays the alpine exposures came out last November. </p>

<p>Alpine Exposures starts off with a Foreword by Ueli Steck which is one of the best forewords I have read in a while. Honest and appraising, highlighting why Jon takes such good photos (because he’s a mountaineer first, photographer second) Ueli sets the tone for the book and gets you excited to turn the pages. Jon follows that up with an equally touching Introduction before you meet some of Jon’s rope partners and then you can start to enjoy the photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16211793956" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/16211793956_541519cb26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<p>The book is written in three languages: English, French and German. This lingual trinity is well executed with a good layout that’s easy to read and follow throughout the book. It’s high-quality paper that depicts the superb images very well, and it’s a pleasure to read the book. The photos all are from real situations, so no fake “Lets go to the Aiguille Du Midi and do some shoots on the Cosmiques” kind of photos. The seven distinct chapters in the book show Jon’s favourite photos from Alpinism, Skiing, Climbing, Landscape, Ice Climbing, Flight (BASE and Paragliding) and Work. In between the photos are here and there short anecdotes from climbs and work trips, and some climbs are highlighted in longer photo essays which not just give you an idea of the route if you’re planning to climb it yourself, it also adds variation to the book and makes it very interesting for alpinists that want to attempt some of these routes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16050174968" title="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7517/16050174968_925b8dd4f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="alpine exposures - Jon Griffith" /></a></p>

<p>This is the coffee table book you wished you would have gotten as a present from Santa last Christmas. Cover to cover it features breathtaking photos from the mountains and people having fun in them, and will inspire you to make a trip to Chamonix as soon as possible so you can experience the beauty yourself. It’s a book for alpinists, climbers and photographers and you’ll have a hard time putting it down once you start to read it. <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/kx49us95qxbuj0f/Alpine_Exposures_Sample.pdf?dl=0">View a 60 page sample online</a>, if you’re convinced (and you will be!) you can buy your copy of <em>alpine exposures</em> directly from Jon at <a href="http://www.alpineexposures.com/products/alpine-exposures-photo-book-10-years-of-photography-by-jon-griffith">Alpine Exposures</a>, your local book shop or order it online from <a href="http://amzn.to/1I10mLL">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1xYMvBb">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1APW8EE">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T12:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/alan-hinkes-8000-meters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ve probably seen a trend in my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">book reviews</a> in the last years: They’ve been more and more about mountaineering and climbing. Why that is so I’ll explain at another time, but now I want to take you along and tell you about the latest book I have read, <em>8000 Metres - Climbing the World’s Highest Mountains by Alan Hinkes</em>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15985413000" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8658/15985413000_e521caa7ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There’s 14 8.000 m peaks on this planet and Alan Hinkes is the first British Mountaineer to have successfully summited all fourteen of them. In his splendid coffee table book “<a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/tab/detail/iid/1/show/description#.VKZk6cbvR_0">8000 Meters - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</a>” he tells the stories and shares his fantastic photos with the reader. Its a chronological layout and after a Foreword, Preface and Introduction we start at Alan’s first 8.000 m summit, Shisha Pangma, which he climbed in 1987. </p>

<p>From that year one Alan has been almost every season in the Himalayas and Karakoram on a quest to climb 8.000 m peaks, even if climbing all 14 of them wasn’t something that he set out to from the start. His writing style is very enjoyable: Honest, down-to-earth and lacking hyperboles which easily could sneak itself in when writing about climbing the highest peaks on the planet. The thoughtful texts describe the experiences of climbing the high mountains, what kind of mental and physical difficulties one can face, from the waiting game in base camp while sitting out bad weather and passing frozen corpses high on the mountains to climbing difficulties and getting up and down these peaks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15986690559" title="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World&#x27;s highest Mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7463/15986690559_90c9064a27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Alan Hinkes: 8000 Metres - Climbing the World &#x27;s highest Mountains" /></a></p>

<p>Alan’s climbing Motto is <em>“No mountain is worth a life, coming back is a success and the summit is only a bonus”</em> and throughout the book he also highlights the importance to have enough power reserves for the descent. What happens if you don’t have these Alan has seen in his friends on some expeditions, which burned themselves out on the ascent and then had no energy left for the descent, which often is even more dangerous than going up. </p>

<p>In between chapers there are small anecdotes from Alan’s encounters with fellow mountaineers like Reinhold Messner and Jerzy Kukuczka or the Trek-Ins to base camps and local cuisine. These loosen up the already enjoyable peak stories. A real highlight for me are the fantastic photos Alan has shot during his ascents and from his travels to these two mountain ranges. The photos were shot before the rise of automatic digital cameras and so one needed to know how to adjust ISO, Aperture and Shutter Speed to get great results, and the photos in this book are proof that Alan knows his trade. I have spent a lot of time just browsing the photos, tracing the lines described in the texts to the summit, and enjoy the vast views which you can have when standing on the top of the world. </p>

<p><em>8000 Metres - Climbing the World’s highest Mountains</em> is a highly enjoyable book that shouldn’t be missing on your bookshelf if you like mountaineering, alpinism and are dreaming of the highest peaks of the planet. The honest &amp; evocative writing is on par with the superb images in the book, and if you ever hope to stand on top of a 8.000 m peak you will do well to read Alan’s book and follow his Motto!</p>

<p>Get the book at your local bookshop, directly from <a href="http://www.cicerone.co.uk/product/detail.cfm/book/548/title/8000-metres#.VKZejsbvR_0">Cicerone</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/1wIIMnr">Amazon.de</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1xzM7fy">Amazon.com</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1yehuvP">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard Interview]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T11:11:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An interview with Barry Blanchard, one of Canada’s most famous Alpinists, in which we chat about music, fear and his book “<a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">The Calling</a>”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15606594195" title="Barry Blanchard by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5608/15606594195_52bea0a1b6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Barry Blanchard" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Barry, thanks for taking the time to answer a few questions from an aspiring Alpinist in Finland. First things first: What song are you right now listening too?</strong></p>

<p><em>Snake Farm by Ray Wylie Hubbard. I’ve listen his music since I was teenager and had the pleasure of meeting the man, and his wife, Judy, yesterday at a concert in the park. Very, very cool.</em></p>

<p><strong>What’s your favourite medium: MP3, Vinyl or Cassettes?</strong></p>

<p><em>I listen to most music on my computer these days so I guess its MP3, although I still listen to CDs in my truck.</em></p>

<p><strong>If you would make a mixtape for a road trip, which songs would definitely be on there?</strong></p>

<p><em>On my road tripping mix there would definitely be: King of the Road by Roger Miller, Six Days on the Road by Dave Dudley and a cover by Steve Earle, Hurtin Albertan by Corb Lund and by Tim Hus, Running on Empty by Jackson Browne, Continental Trailways Blues by Steve Earle, Brand New Cadillac by the Clash, Cadillac Ranch by Bruce Springsteen, Born to Run by Bruce Springsteen … and the list goes on.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15421002960" title="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/15421002960_d3178af41a_b.jpg" width="678" height="1024" alt="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p><strong>I really enjoyed reading your book, by the way. It was raw, to the point and I had a few good laughs. It also had a Quentin Tarantino-esque feel to it at times: Good music, story lines that interweave and come together at the end. Did you plan it like that?</strong></p>

<p><em>My friend, Mark Twight, told me that my book would not end up being what I thought it would be, and that it would be more work than I thought it would be. He was right on both counts. I wanted to write a full 360 degree view of my life and climbing as I believe that much of the value in my writing is that which is common to all people: love, loss, desire, fear, hurt, joy. I believe I share the most that way and that is what writing is for me, a hope to share a little something about life with people.</em></p>

<p><strong>The weather this summer in Chamonix seems to have been much the same as you first visited the crucible of European Alpinism. Any idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer?</strong></p>

<p><em>I have no idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer. Mark Twight and I were pleased to see that our route, The Richard Cranium Memorial, had several repeats in the last couple years and that the ascensionists seemed to enjoy it.</em></p>

<p><strong>Reinhold Messner, another of your idols judging from your book, just got 70 in September. Did you send him a card or where even invited?</strong></p>

<p><em>Reinhold didn’t invite me to his birthday, but he might have invited my guiding mentor, Rudi Kranibitter, who took Reinhold out climbing in Reinhold’s early days and taught him some stuff. Rudi once told me “Ya, that guy was a fast learner!”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14985858864" title="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/14985858864_8c1c2399df_b.jpg" width="710" height="1024" alt="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You are well-read and have devoured a lot of books - from Heinrich Harrer’s “The White Spider” to Lionel Terray’s “Conquistadors of the Useless”. If you could recommend just three books to aspiring alpinists, which ones would that be?</strong></p>

<p><em>I would recommend: <a href="http://amzn.to/1xc7z5m">The Great Days</a> by Walter Bonatti, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vRe3bB">The Seventh Grade</a> by Reinhold Messner and <a href="http://amzn.to/12gRwtY">Feeding the Rat</a> by Al Alvarez.</em></p>

<p><strong>One of your colleagues, Andy Kirkpatrick from the UK, made in his essay “How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche” his first point to not have kids. You’re a father of two - do you feel you climbed harder pre-fatherhood or that you stayed on the same level?</strong></p>

<p><em>I definitely climbed harder before the birth of my daughters but I became a father at 45 and I was, by then, far past my physical prime that was, for me, between 25 and 35. I just can’t climb as hard now, especially at 55! as I could when I was younger. But! the inner journey up the easier mountain is still as challenging and rewarding, maybe more so on both counts.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15582918726" title="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3951/15582918726_29591133dd_b.jpg" width="672" height="1024" alt="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee" /></a></p>

<p><strong>As someone who likes to climb mountains myself it feels like the majority of climbers nowadays are rather enjoying themselves in gyms or bouldering. How would you try to get these people outside?</strong></p>

<p><em>I think that once gym climbers and boulders experience the added challenges of traditional climbing, especially dealing with risk, some of them will be called to the richness of alpinism, but it is a dangerous game so it is not for everyone.</em></p>

<p><strong>Is there a chapter of your climbing life that you wished would have made it in the book still?</strong></p>

<p><em>When I sat down to write The Calling I thought that it would cover my whole climbing life, but I’ve been cursed with a long memory and seemed to have a lot to write. I’d like to write a second book to cover the rest of my climbing life beyond 1988.</em></p>

<p><strong>Well Barry, many thanks again and have fun on the book tour!</strong></p>

<p><em>You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">read my Review of Barry’s book “The Calling” here</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard - The Calling]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T06:23:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What do Joy Division, The Rolling Stones, Les Droites, Nanga Parbet and the Cassin Ridge have in common?</em> They play a part in Barry Blanchard’s life, which is aptly re-told in his memoirs, “The Calling”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15451426995" title="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15451426995_53b9507d6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="675" alt="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge.of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Tune in to the soundtrack of Barry’s life with this Playlist, dutifully reconstructed from Chapter 2:</p>

<iframe src="https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify:user:skullmonkey:playlist:7qy8hUL8yIyABU8JFRfj3z" width="300" height="380" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true"></iframe>

<p>Alpinism and mountaineering books tend to often be of interest only to pursuers of these activities. But Barry manages to write his memoirs in such a compelling edge-of-your-seat style that also non-climbers will be eagerly turning each page to read how the stories unfold. And unfold they do. And if you haven’t heard of Barry before, that’s easily fixed: He is <em>one of North America’s top alpinists, noted for pushing the standards of highly technical, high-risk alpine climbing in the Canadian Rockies and the Himalayas.</em> But nobody is born an alpinist, even if it is their calling.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264859557" title="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15264859557_249539e96d_b.jpg" width="660" height="1024" alt="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the.exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never.been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p>In 20 chapters <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">The Calling</a> stops at important stations in Barry’s life, but does not take a linear approach. It’s more a Tarantino style, weaving stories together, jumping between different stations, different countries, different mountains, different climbing partners. It starts off with an Avalanche and only later on you learn more about how the four rope partners ended up in that situation on a high Himalaya peak. It’s followed two chapters on how Barry grew up and how he got into climbing (via the Canadian equivalent of the Boy Scouts), and that especially will be of interest to aspiring alpinists and climbers around the globe. From how he loaned books at the library on how to climb to saving up to buy his first climbing shoes, it shows that Barry is from a pre-Internet era where you couldn’t just order the latest gear and books online - but often head to search in shops across town to find what you wear looking for.</p>

<p>Really interesting are the personal stories and how Barry manages to illustrate his climbing partners: Kevin and Ward, Gregg and David, Mark and Phil and many more. If you climb, especially in the mountains, you know how important it is to be able to totally trust the person at the other end of the rope, and Barry is able to communicate that trust between climbing partners wonderfully. The story accompanies Barry and his partners as they learn to climb - from Trad at the Wasootch Slabs with Phil to alpine climbing the Calgary Route on Mt Yamnuska with Gray, all told in such a fun way that I couldn’t help but chuckle a few times. After a stop in Chamonix and taking Rebuffat’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1pECtyN">The Hundred Finest Routes</a> as a tick-list Barry travels a bit through Europe (and manages to lose his wallet and passport) before heading back to Canada and onwards to Yosemite. We see how Barry makes the decision to quit his salesman job to go more climbing and becoming a guide, all while repeating hard routes in Canada and the USA.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15448265551" title="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3929/15448265551_a50450ccbc_b.jpg" width="676" height="1024" alt="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p>And as the walls and routes keep getting bigger &amp; more committing we accompany Barry to the Karakoram &amp; Himalaya, to Peru and the Cassin Ridge and read captivating accounts of daring alpine ascents. Always interweaved are anecdotes from his time - be it books (I got away with a whole list of books to read) to music (see above) to relationships and how climbing gear has evolved. The writing is lively &amp; outspoken and I often was laughing out loud, and it was able to keep me on reading until I finished the book in a week, often reading in my lunch breaks and late till night. It were the personal connections with his rope partners that I found very fascinating and that kept me on reading past bedtime, how they pushed themselves on to become better climbers, train together, climb together, party together and go on expeditions together, all while trying to figure out how to be able to get out more to the mountains. If you have a longing for the mountains but can’t be in them as much as you like (and don’t want to quit your job just yet for them), I can warmly recommend you this fine book for your mountain fix. It’s captivating style with adventures from near &amp; far will keep you entertained for many days, and after you’re done you’ll go through the book again - to search out some of the books Barry mentioned, look up a song and re-read about the daring ascents.</p>

<p>Get your paper or digital copy today from <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">Patagonia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1rTGvIH">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vDx8O1">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1nTA8oO">Amazon.de</a> or your local book store.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264720600" title="The Calling Cover by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15264720600_920b3f8714_b.jpg" width="674" height="1024" alt="The Calling Cover" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
