<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Reader Survey | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/reader-survey/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-04T13:32:46+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reader Survey]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/reader-survey.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-26T11:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/reader-survey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first HiF Reader Survey lets you decide how to improve Hiking in Finland in the future!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9370758910" title="Thoughts, high as mountains by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5530/9370758910_76bc9d7fb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Thoughts, high as mountains" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-goal">The Goal</h2>

<p>Hiking in Finland will be six years old this year and it has been going from strength to strength. It is the most-read outdoor blog in Scandinavia and loved for its <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/destinations/">trip reports</a>, detailed <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">gear reviews</a>, interesting <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/interviews/">interviews</a> and the classic <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">TWIR</a> which brings you the best finds from the digital outdoors.</p>

<p>But standing still and resting on my laurels is something I have never been good at. I switched to a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/07/welcome-to-the-new-hikinginfinland-dot-com.html">new platform</a> almost three years ago, have created new <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mountain-people/">content</a> <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gear-outtakes/">ideas</a>, have been working on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/writing/">writing</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/photography/">photography</a>, looking over the borders for inspiration so that I can continue to entertain you with interesting and varied outdoor content from the north and elsewhere. Best of all, Hiking in Finland is probably the only outdoor blog that’s also a proud <a href="https://onepercentfortheplanet.org/">One Percent for the Planet</a> member since 2012 and helps protect the outdoors we enjoy so much.</p>

<p>To further enhance the experience of Hiking in Finland for you, I’d love to know what topics, categories and posts you are most interested in. Tell me via the underneath questionnaire if I’m still on the right trail, where my navigation is off, and what else you’d like to see. Your time and effort shall not go unrewarded, either. </p>

<h2 id="the-prizes">The Prizes</h2>

<p>Of course I am very thankful that you complete my questionnaire, and that’s why you have the chance to win a few nice prizes for your time and effort. If you’d like to be entered into the raffle you just need to enter a valid email address at the end of the questionnaire before you push <em>Submit</em> and you’ll be entered into the raffle to win one of these prizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A <a href="http://www.haglofs.com">Haglöfs</a> Type 16 backpack &amp; Twice Beanie</li>
  <li>A one year subscription to <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com">trekking Magazin</a></li>
  <li>2 x 50€ Gift Card from <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/?pid=81">Bergzeit.co.uk</a></li>
  <li>4 x 25€ Gift Cards from <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/?refID=hif">trekking-lite-store.com</a></li>
  <li>2 x 25€ Gift Card from <a href="http://bit.ly/1yc4iWV">Bergfreunde.de</a></li>
  <li>A <a href="http://nikwax.co.uk/en-us/productselector/cleaning.php">Nikwax Hardshell DuoPack</a></li>
</ul>

<p><em>Your answers have Zero influence on winning so be honest!</em></p>

<h2 id="the-questionnaire">The Questionnaire</h2>

<p>You can access the Questionnaire here if you read Hiking in Finland via a RSS Reader or just answer the questions via the underneath embedded form. It is built with Typeform which lets you use your Keyboard and/ or Trackpad to answer and also works great on tablets and phones. The survey is open till midnight 1st of February so you got almost a week to answer.</p>

<p><strong>Thanks for answering the survey. It closed now and winners will be contacted via Email shortly.</strong></p>

<p><br /><strong>If you like to read more news and trip reports</strong> please follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, and <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> where I often post current photos and stuff which don’t make it to the blog. And to not miss any future articles you should subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
