<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Black Diamond | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/black-diamond/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-22T20:44:10+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles.html"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T14:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles are made for fast packers, trailrunners and anyone who needs ultralight poles on the trail. If that sounds like the the perfect backpacking trekking pole for ultralighters to you, read on!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7753090722" title="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Z-Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8444/7753090722_305dc0cd69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="557" alt="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Z-Poles" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>Puh, I’ve had the <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en/trekking-poles/ultra-distance-trekking-pole-BD112135_cfg.html">Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles</a> for a long time. They arrived in early 2012 and have since been used on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/ultralight-summit-daytrippin.html">UL Summit in Slovenia</a>, in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho Kekkonen National Park</a>, on approaches and camping on ice climbing trips and several <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/untold-trip-reports.html">untold trip reports</a>. They have seen well over 50 days in the outdoors on trips.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7783259222" title="Open Doors by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8307/7783259222_fbc46ab400_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Open Doors" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>A trekking pole has several advantages on the trail:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Helps you to keep your balance on difficult terrain</li>
  <li>Useful in fording rivers</li>
  <li>Can be transformed into a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html">tripod</a> or used with a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/03/interview-rod-java-from-thestickpic-com.html">StickPic</a> for photography</li>
  <li>It pitches your tarp or shelter</li>
  <li>It trains your upper body muscles when hiking</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14098484266" title="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5543/14098484266_124624b994_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The Z-Poles have quite a list of features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>100% carbon fiber shafts</li>
  <li>3-section Z-Pole folding design with speed cone deployment</li>
  <li>Lightweight EVA foam grip and breathable, moisture-wicking, Velcro® adjustable strap</li>
  <li>Non-slip foam mini grip extension for secure choke ups</li>
  <li>Interchangeable, non-marking Z-Pole Rubber Tips or Z-pole Carbide Tips</li>
  <li>Stopper basket with shaft catcher secures folded sections</li>
  <li>The Z-Poles do not accept, or have fittings for snow or powder baskets</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14121649845" title="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2907/14121649845_eb867c75e1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>As the Z-Poles came out in 2012 there were already quite a few carbon poles available, but none were as light as the Z-Poles. They fold well, are easy to deploy, and are super durable. The folding mechanism is probably the innovation in these poles, as they are very well made and robust - even after hundreds of times folding and unfolding them they still work perfect, a witness to the engineering and thinking that went into them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763991746" title="Dry feet technique by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7316/9763991746_bd9a340f48_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Dry feet technique" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>As you can guess from above, the Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles are high-quality trekking poles. They work even after months of use flawlessly, and while there are some scratches from use they still are in tip-top shape. Unless you get them stuck between boulders and put too much pressure on them so that they break I think these poles will be very durable and long-lasting.</p>

<iframe src="http://hikinginfinland.com//player.vimeo.com/video/35529643?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" width="1280" height="720" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>142 gram with strap (one pole), 132 gram without strap (one pole), both cases this weight is for the 130 cm Z-Pole. Might be off by a gram or two because of the duct tape I have on them, too =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14121989584" title="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7458/14121989584_23f06d68f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Black Diamond has a <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en/sustainability.html">sustainability page</a> in which they highlight their commitment to environmental matters. “<em>“To champion the preservation of, and access to, mountain, crag and canyon environments while minimizing our own environmental footprint.</em>” is one of the Black Diamond founding commitments. Their page goes into much details about what BD does to be a environmentally friendly company, and it certainly is very impressive what they do: From car pooling to efficient warehousing &amp; transportation and the support of well over two dozens of environmental groups, BD does good things for the environment. As for the recyclability of the Z-Poles themselves, as they’re made of various different materials - carbon, foam, kevlar, plastic - it is probably not that easy to recycle them. I am not aware of a take-back programme either, so you better treat them well and keep them as long as they’re good =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14141720353" title="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2906/14141720353_e2b81929cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I always carry a pair of trekking poles, but rarely use them for hiking. They’re more along for pitching my shelters and in case the going gets so though that I decide to get them out. I think my trip in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho Kekkonen NP</a> was the last time I really used poles all the time, and also in Slovenia they were used a fair bit. So for me it is important that poles are light and compact, and you can’t beat the Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles in that respect.</p>

<p>I love the rapid, no-fuss deployment of the poles. BD transferred their expertise from building avalanche probes to trekking poles, so that thanks to the concealed inner Kevlar cord and the speed cones the collapsible Z-Poles snap into place and lock with a single pull. Sweet, fast and no need to fuss around with telescope mechanisms, which seem to give up their proper function after some time. The single push button release makes folding the poles up just as easy; Push the button, slide the handle down, pull the three segments gently apart, pack away. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14121660905" title="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7444/14121660905_72190b191f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles" /></a></p>

<p>Now the fixed length is something one could worry about. What if I need a shorter pole for ascent, and a long pole for descents? How does it pitch with a shelter? For that purpose I chose the longest model available - 130 cm in length - because I want to use it with my two Locus Gear Khufus. With 130 cm I can pitch the Khufu with one pole in the middle, or use the DPTE with both poles to have a lot of free space in the shelter. 130 cm is ideal for that. As for hiking, because the Z-Poles have a long foam handle it is easy to take the grip lower or higher, just as you need it. The grips itself are comfortable for walking long days, although I found the straps a bit too tight for me - happily they are easy to remove if you prefer strap-less hiking (which also saves weight!). </p>

<p>One of the biggest plusses for me with these poles is their compact size, which makes travelling in a plane very easy. I can pack the Z-Poles in my backpack or a tube which is the same height than my pack and stuff backpack and tube into a large drysack for transport. With some poles the collapsed length is pretty long which makes it more difficult to get them save from A to B, but with the Z-Poles travelling has never been easier. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14121995354" title="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5313/14121995354_c37976d335_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles" /></a></p>

<p>Now as for hiking with them, I think they do a very good job too. The tips give good grip on rock, dirt and trails, its easy &amp; fast to switch hands lower or higher on the handles, and on sketchy terrain they do help with keeping in balance. As they are so light you don’t get tired using them and you can hike 8 or more hours with them in hand without problems. I also always keep some duct tape wrapped around both poles for fixing gear - its a convenient place to store the tape out of the way, and easy to get it off when you need it. </p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>Black Diamond makes themselves various <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en/trekking-poles">Poles</a> which compete with the Z-Poles. If we look at lightweight carbon poles the <a href="http://rutalocura.com/trekking_poles.html">Ruta Locura Yana poles</a> (also available as a <a href="http://rutalocura.com/trekking_poles3.html">three-piece pole</a>) are certainly a contender, and I do love mine a lot (as they’re excellent to use with the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">HMG UltaMid</a>). Komperdell makes with the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/komperdell-carbon-ultralite-vario-4-wanderstoecke/">Carbon Ultralite Vario 4</a> a light carbon telescope pole, and Leki’s <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/leki-mico-vario-carbon-teleskopstock/">Micro Vario Carbon</a> is another telescope pole from carbon - both not as light as the Z-Pole, though.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13935008479" title="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5502/13935008479_0f08c8fc4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>While I am not a big trekking pole user I always carry a pair. For the last few years on the big trips abroad this has always been the Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles. They fold up small &amp; compact, are easy and safe to transport in my backpack when flying, a pleasure to use when hiking, fording rivers and walking in difficult terrain, and work extremely well with various ultralight shelters like the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review.html">Locus Gear Khufu</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mpv4kAtN_DQ">MLD TrailStar</a>. I can transform them into a tripod with the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html">TrailPix</a>, too, and as they fold small and are so light they easily pack in my backpack when I don’t need them. I have several big trip coming up this year, and one thing is pretty sure: The Black Diamond Ultra Distance Trekking Poles will be along on many of them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157644528292461">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>You can get your pair at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-ultra-distance-wanderstoecke-gr-110cm/">Bergzeit</a> (currently on offer!), <a href="http://bit.ly/1ilUu0v">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/19d20q2">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekkingstoecke/">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1g4Dz2v">REI</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7807416278" title="HMG Porter &amp; BD Z-Poles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8432/7807416278_d55bc283b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="HMG Porter &amp; BD Z-Poles" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody.html"/>
    <updated>2014-05-05T07:47:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody is a very interesting jacket: Made from Schoeller softshell material with a NanoSphere finish, it is light, breathable, windproof and water-resistant. Could this be the wind jacket to rule them all?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14132042473" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5486/14132042473_b49994e399_b.jpg" width="510" height="1024" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I’ve had the Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody since <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/photos/pb.499777346719269.-2207520000.1399265441./675801809116821/?type=3&amp;theater">November 2013</a> in constant use. It has been ice climbing in Korouoma, backpacking in the Lake District as well as cycling, walking and bouldering in Vaasa. It has seen well over 90 days of use in all kind of activities, and likely will see many more days in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14108904862" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7059/14108904862_29b52003e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a> </p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>It’s a softshell jacket. It’s a windjacket. It’s the one jacket you take if you need something that is light, windproof and breathable. Black Diamond has the <a href="http://eu.blackdiamondequipment.com/en/jackets-shells/alpine-start-hoody-APNG0X001MED1.html">Alpine Start Hoody</a> on their Jackets and Shells page and says it’s “<em>Built for days that start long before the sun comes up, the Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody is an ultralight, softshell windshirt that offers minimalist-minded protection against stiff ridgeline breezes and light, unexpected precip.</em>” I can sign that.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14108898502" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2931/14108898502_6938c15807_b.jpg" width="1024" height="759" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The minimalistic feature set of the Alpine Start Hoody includes</p>

<ul>
  <li>An adjustable, helmet-compatible hood</li>
  <li>It stows in its zippered chest pocket with a carabiner clip loop</li>
  <li>Climbing-specific gusseted underarm panels</li>
  <li>Elastic cuffs</li>
  <li>Drawcord hem</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13925359560" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5557/13925359560_1bf8ae969e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The innovation in this garment is the use of the Schoeller® stretch-woven fabric that has a NanoSphere® Technology coating. It’s a 80 g/m2 fabric made from 93% nylon and 7% elastane and is very stretchy. The special <a href="http://www.schoeller-textiles.com/en/technologies/nanosphere.html">Schoeller NanoSphere®</a> is a “<em>nanotech-based finishing technology that allows dirt and water to simply run off the surface of the textiles</em>”. It “<em>is transferred to the surface of textiles by means of nano technology</em>” and which improves their water, dirt and oil repelling properties and makes it easier to clean in the washing machine. Additionally NanoSphere® is free from PFOA and PFOS and bluesign® approved. It certainly is a superb fabric with an equally impressive finish that we will see a lot more in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14112346724" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7337/14112346724_f7bbe187db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After six months of use, rubbing it against rock and ice, hanging <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools.html">ice tools</a> over my shoulders on it and carrying backpacks the garment looks still like new. Sure, it could need a wash, but it pretty much still has the same bright blue colour it had when it arrived, and dirt has a hard time sticking to it. I will thank the NanoSphere® coating for that =) All seams hold up just fine and the zippers also work flawless. And in case something goes broken, Black Diamond has a Full Commitment Guarantee which will repair, replace or refund you if you’re not satisfied with it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14108714181" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7385/14108714181_d2ebba73ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>204 g in Size M. Heavier than much of the competition if looking at windshirt, but the lightest softshell I own. </p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>I’ve met with Schoeller at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/ispo-news-2014.html">ISPO</a> and know that they’re a environmentally conscious company. Sadly I didn’t find any information on their sustainability and recycling efforts for the softshells; although you likely could get an old jacket repaired via the Black Diamond Full Commitment Guarantee. </p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>There’s one problem I have with this jacket: It’s not my size. I’m a Size S and this is a Size Medium, which makes it just a tad too long in the torso for my taste. Sure, I still use it almost every day and it’s currently my go-to windjacket, but I think I’d like it even more if it’d be my size. This short video I did on sizing illustrates the fit on me well (and garment sizing in general) and why I think it’s better to get garments in the size you need them.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/_FYuB9j_9A4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Now apart from that I really have no major complaints about the jacket. Well, maybe the brim of the hood could be better, but that really is already it. It’s a helmet compatible hood, and while it does fit over a helmet I have always worn it underneath it - in that case I can also wear a tubeshawl or beanie under the hood and still fit the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">helmet</a> comfortably over it. You can adjust the hood via a drawstring with cinches on the right &amp; left. These are inside, which I didn’t find to troublesome: Usually I adjust the hood once and that’s it. When I don’t need it it hangs down in the back, while when needed I can easily pull it over my head even with the front zipper fully closed. It’s a good, close fit and certainly offers a bit more protection than for example on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/rab-cirrus-wind-top.html">Rab Cirrus windjacket</a>. The hood turns well with your head when cinched down, both to the sides and up &amp; down.</p>

<p>The Alpine Start Hoody has a straight hem with one drawcord cinch which you can operate via the inside pocket. The inside pocket is big enough to hold a Nalgene water bottle or your map and compass. A folded map and compass also fit into the chest pocket, as does the jacket itself. Packing the jacket into the pocket is straight forward and easy, and it makes for a soft, small package that you can either hang via the carabiner clip to your harness or can stuff into your backpack. </p>

<p>The sleeves have elastic cuffs which are a bit wide, though if you wear gloves they make a tight fit over the gloves and will not let any cold air in (or hot air out). The wind protection of the jacket is very good, though in seriously strong wind at low temperatures I prefer a real hardshell as it is warmer. For activities in warm &amp; windy weather - summer backpacking &amp; hiking, alpine climbing, spring mountaineering adventures - the Alpine Start Hoody is a superb choice. It’s fairly water-resistant and as I was ice climbing in the jacket in January at -4°C on a very wet ice fall the jacket held me nicely dry. At some point the fabric got a bit saturated in one spot, but no water came inside. Even better, it dried very fast afterwards in the cold weather.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14108808991" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2910/14108808991_cdacbfb475_b.jpg" width="1024" height="164" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<p>As I was sent a Size Medium layering underneath is no problem. I can have up to three layers (Baselayer, Midlayer, Synthetic Puffy layer) on and still the jacket fits comfortable over it. I reckon if I’d have a Size Small I would need to leave the Syntethic Puffy layer away, but I could life with that. I find the breathability of the jacket very good. On cool &amp; sunny days I didn’t overheat in the jacket, but those hot, sunny days in the Lake District when I was hiking up I needed to pull the sleeves up and open the zipper to not overheat. Where the backpack was I had perspiration accumulating and wetting the fabric, but a few minutes in the wind and sun and it was dry again. The breathability is better than other wind jackets I own, and really is much better as any hardshell material - as it should be, as this is a softshell fabric after all.</p>

<p>The freedom of movement is superb as you’d expect from a garment that’s made for climbing. If you leave the hem loose and don’t cinch it tight (as I like to do) then you can comfortably move your hands far up without that the jacket moves. If you’re gone stretch then the hem will move, and even more so when cinched tight to not let any drafts in. It’s nice to wear the Alpine Start Hoody just over a T-shirt as the inside is soft and comfy on the skin. All seams are flat so there’s no chaffing or pressure points under backpack straps or your climbing harness.</p>

<p>Finally, the garment has a seriously high level of abrasion resistance. I have bouldered now a handfull of times in it, rubbing it across sharp edges, dragging it over the granite and also have ice climbed in it, and there’s not a single spot on the fabric which looks worn. Also carrying a backpack with it - be it backpacking, approaching or grocery shopping - has not produced any pilling or damage to the shoulder area. Absolutey fantastic. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14112349274" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7070/14112349274_5fbf55b108_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>At the moment there’s no Schoeller NanoSphere® wind jacket I’m aware of, but of course there are several other <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/wind-jackets/">wind jackets</a> and light softshells on the market which compete with this garment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13925314237" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7405/13925314237_0a9f7f3cd7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody is comfortable on the skin, very durable, lightweight, breathable and keeps the wind at bay. It’s also very water and dirt repellant and easy to clean with cold water. It has great freedom of movement and an acceptable hood. Even if my jacket is not my size, I am still using it daily for many activities - and that’s a very good indicator of how good this jacket is. Looking at what it is made for, and what it does, I think this is fabric-wise one of the best wind jackets currently on the market.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157644511415381">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Get your Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody at <a href="http://bit.ly/OcTdRJ">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody-mosaic-gr-s/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody-softshelljacke/">Bergfreunde</a> (currently on offer!), <a href="http://bit.ly/1hztiz1">Backcountry.com</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/1fJttJz">REI</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14112337924" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7456/14112337924_7b04c0e430_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assorted Ice Climbing Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/assorted-ice-climbing-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-19T21:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/assorted-ice-climbing-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Besides boots, crampons, ice axes and a backpack there’s a few more pieces of gear an ice climber needs - ice screws, belay devices, slings, quick draws, and and and. In this article I highlight some of the assorted ice climbing gear which I have used during this years ice climbing exploits.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661762203/" title="Assorted climbing gear by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8250/8661762203_070d206c29_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Assorted climbing gear" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="black-diamond-express-ice-screws">Black Diamond Express Ice Screws</h2>
<p>The Gold Standard in ice screws, the Black Diamond Express have the best price/ quality ratio and perform superbly on the ice. Easy to screw into the ice with one hand thanks to the crank and with to two carabiner holes to clip in, the Express ice screw helps you to secure yourself quickly when the going gets tough. Petzl will bring out a similar design next winter which performs very well, and Grivel’s <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-ice-screw-360-kurbeleisschraube/">360 ice screws</a> too is great. However, at the moment Black Diamond makes the lightest screws and they’re very well priced, thus these excellent ice screws shouldn’t be missing on any ice climbers rack.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-express-ice-screw-eisschraube/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-express-ice-screw.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15pvcgK">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115SnGQ">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJ4OcT">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587935487/" title="Secured by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8241/8587935487_cc1e3ed8d0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Secured" /></a></p>

<h2 id="slings">Slings</h2>
<p>Slings are an important piece of gear when climbing ice whenever you don’t toprope. A 120 cm sling is essential to build a belay station together with two ice screws, and a daisychain or another 120 cm sling are needed to secure yourself at a belay station. They also can be very useful when setting screws and taking care that the rope isn’t making a wide curve (Imagine it a bit like this sign <strong>&lt;</strong> where the three points are ice screws and the line is the rope. With a sling and two ‘biners in the middle point you can make the rope run in a more straight line). Also when rappeling down slings come in handy, and they of course also can be used in rock climbing. A piece of gear that definitely needs to come along.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schlingen-reepschnur/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/schlinge-reepschnur.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15ptb3X">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/Zv14fB">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115RtdF">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662799740/" title="Slings &amp; Daisychain by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8245/8662799740_908fe80d94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Slings &amp; Daisychain" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quick-draws">Quick draws</h2>
<p>When you’re leading a climb you’ll need quick draws (Read Tomás superb article on <a href="http://www.scandinavian-hiking.com/2011/08/relatively-ultralight-quickdraws-petzl.html">Ultralight Quick Draws</a>). As so often, lighter quick draws means you either can take more or then safe a substantial amount of weight for the same performance. Some clip in easier and are better handled with gloves, so keep that in mind when building your rack.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/express-sets/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/express-sets.html?priceMin=&amp;priceMax=&amp;query=&amp;sort=&amp;_artperpage=">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15puIat">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176mNNe">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176mZw0">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662796740/" title="Quick draws by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8259/8662796740_9938e7249a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Quick draws" /></a></p>

<h2 id="carabiners">Carabiners</h2>
<p>I thought I’d be set with my two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-phantom-schraubkarabiner/">DMM Phantom</a> locking ‘biners, though I was wrong. And so I bought a few more locking carabiners, in slightly bigger sizes, because they’re easier to operate with gloves on. If you’re not toproping then a about five locking carabiners are good to have along: Three to set up a belay, one to clip yourself in with a sling, and one if you’re belaying someone else. A spare or two in these situations can’t hurt, either.</p>

<p>As for non-locking carabiners, I have been using the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-phantom-schnappkarabiner/">DMM Phantom gate ‘biner</a> and still think they’re superb. The gate opens easy, they’re light yet strong - a great biner to have along to rack gear.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schraubkarabiner/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/karabiner.html?Limit%5B%5D=Schraubkarabiner&amp;Limit%5B%5D=HMS-Karabiner&amp;priceMin=&amp;priceMax=&amp;query=&amp;sort=&amp;_artperpage=&amp;f=1">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZAAOxi">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJ9vn8">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115W5QI">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662797582/" title="Carabiners by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8251/8662797582_9b811ef47f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Carabiners" /></a></p>

<h2 id="camp-speed-helmet">CAMP Speed helmet</h2>
<p>I used the CAMP Speed helmet during all climbing, and really like the comfort of this helmet - light and protective, easy to adjust the size when I wear a beanie or not, not to hot nor too cold. I can wear shades or my googles underneath them, a Headlamp like the Petzl Nao fits easily on it, and it also fits under all my jacket’s hoods. However, with the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-vapor-hybridhelm/">Black Diamond Vapor</a> and Petzl Siricco helmets available, the Speed is no longer the lightest option, something too keep in mind when you’re buying a helmet (I used the Petzl Siricco and really like it, especially the magnetic closure that’s easy to operate with one hand is very good).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-speed-kletterhelm/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/camp-brg-5.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176wpYi">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661816397/" title="CAMP Speed Helmet by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8258/8661816397_2b4e3ce0b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="CAMP Speed Helmet" /></a></p>

<h2 id="poc-iris-3p-googles">POC Iris 3P Googles</h2>

<p>Because my helmet doesn’t have a visor to keep ice and water from flying in my face, I was wearing the comfortable <a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">POC Iris 3P Googles</a>. They have a superb view and while they on occasion were fogging up, the fog cleared up quickly. I can wear them with my Speed Helmet without problems, but had problems to get a comfortable fit with the new Petzl Helmet. The googles’ lens are antiscratch and have a oleophobic &amp; hydrophobic treatment which means it keeps fat and water off your lens very easily - a very welcome function when climbing ice where you sweat and ice is coming at you. A great pair of googles that I can recommend if you climb ice or ski.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">JK-Shop</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176xmjq">Backcountry</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662911976/" title="POC Iris 3P Googles by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8266/8662911976_1d5db327e1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="POC Iris 3P Googles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="petzl-reverso-4">Petzl Reverso 4</h2>
<p>I usually use a Petzl Verso, though enlightenment struck as I tried the Reverso 4. It’s only a tad heavier than the Verso but offers so much more functions: You can secure two climbers that are climbing after you, and connect it to your belay with the ring. As with the Verso, you can belay and rappel. When not toproping then definitely a piece of gear to take along. </p>

<p>There’s plenty of belaying devices around, though one to consider is the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/s/Mammut--Smart----Alpine/kategorie--klettern/">Mammut Smart Alpine</a> which offers similar functionality as the Reverso though has the added benefit of breaking the rope dynamically in the case of a fall. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-reverso-4-sicherungsgeraet/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-reverso-4-belay-device.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZABoLu">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/11m0gIL">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13qZm2O">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577735844/" title="Petzl Reverso 4 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8234/8577735844_86d4c770cb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Reverso 4" /></a></p>

<h2 id="tendon-master-97-rope">Tendon Master 9.7 rope</h2>
<p>A superb rope for toproping, also on ice. It’s my rock-climbing rope which I diverted from its intended use to toproping on ice. Super smooth handling, light, great knot-ability, and with a middle marking, this is a great piece of kit which does the job very well.</p>

<p>For lead climbing on ice a twin or half rope is needed, though, and also there the market offers plenty of great ropes for us ice climbers. I used a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beal-ice-twin-golden-dry-77-mm-zwillingsseil/">BEAL rope</a> which were very great to handle and didn’t soak out, and if you’re serious about ice climbing then you won’t get around getting a twin or half rope (<a href="http://www.highinfatuation.com/blog/straight-from-the-mammoths-mouth-half-ropes-are-not-twins/">Here’s an explanation on the difference</a>!).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/tendon-master-97-mm-einfachseil/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/tendon-master-9-4-complete-shield-kletterseil.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r7uA8">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r6YCt">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/17sOoX6">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8486287141/" title="Tendon Rope by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8372/8486287141_7f341247e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Tendon Rope" /></a></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-r320-harness">Arc’teryx R320 harness</h2>
<p>The Arc’teryx R320 has been my harness of choice and I like the racking capacity it has - plenty of gear fits on the four gear loops. For ice climbing a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-caritool.html">Petzl Caritool</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-ice-clipper.html">Black Diamond Ice Clipper</a> would have been useful, though I made work without this season. It’s comfortable, the leg loops are big enough to step through in case you put on your crampons before your harness (happens!) and with it’s good design it feels well over pants and jacket. If one is serious about ice climbing, the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-i340a-klettergurt/">Arc’teryx I340A</a> of course would be a nice harness to have, though for the time being the R320 is very good for my needs and can be used all year around.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-r-320-hueftgurt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-r-320a-klettergurt.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJanYJ">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/Z1PB8H">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/11m0I9Q">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="black-diamond-ice-box">Black Diamond Ice Box</h2>
<p>A backpack is the best way to get your gear from home to the ice fall. But what when between the ice fall and home there’s a airplane? Backpacks with the sharp tools outside aren’t great for travelling - enter the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633281180152/">Black Diamond Ice Box</a>. It fits four tools, one pair of crampons, up to ten ice screws, a mesh compartment for drying gear and still has plenty of space left for small stuff. For me very important too, is that its perfect to store the ice climbing gear safely and using minimal space at home, out of the reach of an exploring toddler. A great piece of kit for ice climbers that travel a lot and want to store their gear safely when not in use.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ice-box/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/17sM0zG">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r3DTL">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662893104/" title="Black Diamond Ice Box by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8248/8662893104_f8e2087b75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond Ice Box" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661794319/" title="Black Diamond Ice Box by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8260/8661794319_4c98c70443_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ice Box" /></a></p>

<p><em>Most of the ice-climbing related gear has been used for a week of ice climbing this season. These short reviews thus should be considered as an initial review, which will be updated during the next winter season when I have used the gear more. If you have questions, please use the comments to ask!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576458309/" title="Abisko Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8392/8576458309_581552ba62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abisko Canyon" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaiming the Disclaimer</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
