<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Marmot | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/marmot/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-31T23:57:28+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/marmot-space-walk-jacket-and-edge-insulated-pants-review.html"/>
    <updated>2016-03-29T23:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/marmot-space-walk-jacket-and-edge-insulated-pants-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Skiing, sledding, hiking and building an igloo: Winter is a great time for kids to be outside &amp; enjoy the snow. So that he does not get cold, our son wore the Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants - which we review here.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108799805/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1583/26108799805_df4fb92f57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Winter, also known to parents as the time where you need to get ready 15 minutes before you plan to leave - because your little ones need help dressing up in the multitude of layers we make them wear so they do not get cold. Because only when they’re not cold they actually enjoy being outdoors (much like adults, really). We tested the <a href="https://marmot.com/products/details/boys-space-walk-jacket">Marmot Space Walk Jacket</a> and <a href="https://marmot.com/products/details/boys-edge-insulated-pant">Edge Insulated Pants</a> during the last four months outside while alpine skiing, sledding, building snowmen and XC skiing, and here are our thoughts about them.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484248574/in/dateposted/" title="Sledding at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1538/25484248574_b0fe932edf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sledding at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25835958970/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1488/25835958970_4ab4a4766b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25506181673/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1536/25506181673_6ef459c4a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="space-walk-jacket">Space Walk Jacket</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.marmot.de/content/de/collection_26&amp;c=643&amp;show=5778">Space Walk Jacket</a> in Size XS equals size 110 and weighs 512 g. Our son loved the colour combination of orange and reds, and we too really liked it. Outside a waterproof &amp; breathable Marmot MemBrain® Fabric keeps snow and moisture at bay, while on the inside a Thermal R 100 g insulation ensures generated warmth stays inside. The hood is removable, and a really good fit, even over a bobble hat. The Powder Skirt keeps the snow out and is extremely useful for little skiers and playing in the snow. It has a silicone band on the inside which keeps it in place and has two levels of tightness. In the back, chin and neck a fleece lining makes it comfortable against the skin and likely helps with breathability, too. What we found overkill were the six pockets, we could have done easily with only the one large mesh pocket on the inside (which is great to store beanie, neck warmer and gloves!) and one of the outside pockets. Our son never used the Velcro hand pockets nor the other two pockets on the outside. The hem is adjustable, though with the toggles in the pockets it is difficult to do so - happily we never needed it. The sleeves have Velcro closures and also can be adjusted, and most importantly are wide enough so gloves can be worn underneath the sleeves to keep the snow out. The jacket closes high and our son found the area in the front of the face constricting, something we solved by leaving the zipper always a couple of centimetre open.</p>

<p>In terms of warmth, we feel the jacket (and pants for that matter) are warm till -10°C with a thin midlayer on (plus normal clothes), probably more with a thicker midlayer. The jacket has plenty of space underneath for layering, and our son never was cold in a variety of activities and weather conditions. It gives little skiers and climbers great freedom of movement, and the Powder Skirt ensures no cold and wet snow comes inside. After four months of use and a couple of washes the jacket also still looks like new, also at high-stress areas like the cuffs and back. Overall our son really liked his Space Walk Jacket - it is warm, has nice colours and is easy for him to put on and off on his own. </p>

<p>Get the Marmot Space Walk Jacket right now with great discounts at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/marmot-boys-space-walk-jacket-ski-jacket/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1Uq4bDm">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1Sh9qz1">Campsaver</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1ogTV1S">evo</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1Uq5jqD">REI.com</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108801235/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1637/26108801235_cfc707f7e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25506181033/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1478/25506181033_1c7630e710_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25504057124/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1685/25504057124_34e4c202fc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="edge-insulated-pants">Edge Insulated Pants</h2>

<p>In size XS the <a href="http://www.marmot.de/content/de/collection_26&amp;c=647&amp;show=5792">Edge Insulated Pants</a> weighs 444 g. They are, as the name suggests, insulated pants, made of the proprietary Marmot MemBrain® fabric on the outside which makes the pants water-resistant, while on the inside a Thermal R™ insulation keeps little winter lovers warm. We found the internal flex boot gaiters great to keep shoes &amp; socks dry from the inside, and the reinforced inside leg is useful for skiing as well as scrambling on rocks. The waist is adjustable via Velcros on the inside, but sadly the adjustment is only minimal - we feel a bit more adjustment in width or a stretchy waist could have been better and would possibly make it possible to use the pants two winter seasons. The removable suspenders are great, and the soft inside lining makes it easy to put the pants on over other pants. We never used the three pockets on the pants, so maybe it’d make sense to get rid of at least the two zippered pockets. </p>

<p>Putting the pants on is easy thanks to the smooth lining and it stays well in place with the adjustable suspenders and button closure. After four months of daily use outside the Edge Insulated Pants still looks like new after a couple of washes. The Marmot MemBrain® fabric kept the snow &amp; wetness always reliable outside and it was easy to brush dirt off the pants. They allow for great freedom of movement, be it scrambling up the snow hills along the streets, climbing on the playground or Alpine and XC skiing. The sizing is good for kids between 108 and 112 cm, though if your child is wearing more than one baselayer the waist might get tight (we just left the button open). Asides from these little things from us parents our son simply liked his Edge Insulated Pants a lot: They were toasty, allowed him to go sledding on his pants down steep snow hills and also looked cool!</p>

<p>Buy the Marmot Edge Insulated Pants at <a href="http://bit.ly/1URthuB">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/marmot-boys-edge-insulated-pant-ski-pant/">Bergfreunde.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1RnGIAh">Campsaver</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/1UxaV2z">evo</a> - all of them have great offers on the pants thanks to their winter sales!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26108802745/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1705/26108802745_6e2c8c20c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26016281992/in/dateposted/" title="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1582/26016281992_7a9bd6e1ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marmot Space Walk Jacket and Edge Insulated Pants" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The jacket and pants have been provided by Marmot for review. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marmot Speed Light Jacket]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/marmot-speed-light-jacket.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-22T09:04:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/marmot-speed-light-jacket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A Gore-Tex® Pro jacket which is light, durable and has an excellent hood - that’s the <a href="http://marmot.com/products/speed_light_jacket">Marmot Speed Light Jacket</a>. I’ve put it to the test for the past year, so here’s my insights into this hardshell jacket!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416921593/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3748/10416921593_e9007c8bba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>It arrived in October 2012 and has been on backpacking and skiing trips since. It has seen a fairly decent amount of day hikes and pram strolls, too. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416697306/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3786/10416697306_8b6c285bce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>As a hardshell its purpose is to sit lightly in your pack until it starts to pour down, the wind picks up, and you’re climbing a snowy mountain. In those situations, and others which include inclement weather, the hardshell comes out of the pack and on, with the aim to keep you dry, warm and comfy while the weather tries to make you turn around and go inside. But as you’re wearing the Marmot Speed Light Jacket, you hike/ climb/ paddle happily on, until the weather understands that you’re not going home.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416893513/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket Gore-Tex Pro by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5518/10416893513_2a75c7717e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket Gore-Tex Pro" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>What I liked about the Speed Light Jacket is the clear focus on the essentials. It has a pretty low-key feature set, but that’s exactly what I appreciate about it:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Made of the durable GORE-TEX® Pro Fabric</li>
  <li>Excellent Gale-Force Hood with a laminated Wire Brim, which is helmet compatible, too!</li>
  <li>One chest pocket, two harness/ hipbelt compatible hand pockets</li>
  <li>Elastic drawcord hem and Velcro cuffs</li>
  <li>Angel-Wing Movement™ design for pretty great freedom of movement</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416717185/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket Pit Zips by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5516/10416717185_23945cbfe2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket Pit Zips" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>Quality of this hardshell is superb. Clean seams, good design, this is a top-notch jacket which will satisfy your hardshell needs very well.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416753666/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5523/10416753666_7b8626e607_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Marmot Speed Light Jacket in Size Medium weighs in at 405 gram. That’s not the lightest hatdshell available, but good for such a durable hardshell.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416834063/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5536/10416834063_94d495d24d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Marmot Europe has a <a href="http://2013.marmot.de/content/en/company.responsibility/">Responsibility</a> website in which they detail their philosophy and how they think about social and ecological things, which is great. They’re a member of the European Outdoor Conservation Association, which tries to protect the wild areas we enjoy so much. They have a code of ethics which you can read on their website, and support social initiatives across the globe. </p>

<p>In some of their products they us recycled polyester, these are labelled UpCycle® as the bottle has e.g. become a fleece jacket. They also try to use sustainable fabrics whenever they can and use organic cotton in some products. This hardshell is made of Gore-Tex, which back in the day (1993 onwards till it stopped) you could recycle in the GORE™ BALANCE PROJECT™. However, that isn’t possible nowadays any more, so this is what <a href="http://www.gore-tex.com/remote/Satellite/content/customer-service/faq/5">Gore suggest</a> you do with the jacket at the end of its life-cycle:</p>

<p><em>Garments or footwear made from GORE® fabrics can be safely disposed of just like any other apparel product.</em></p>

<p>[…]</p>

<p><em>Finding ways to extend the useful life of a product has always been the environmentally preferred option over product disposal. One might wish to consider donating footwear or garments to charities or repurposing the product for other applications.</em></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The Speed Light Jacket has been used for hiking, backpacking and skiing, but sadly not for any alpine activities. Nevertheless, for these activities it performed admiringly. It ticked all the right things for me: The drawstring hem with the cut of the jacket made it stay in place and not ride up, the cuffs were large enough to vent but could be closed with the Velcros, the pockets were large and the hood was perfect.</p>

<p>Yes, the hood and its brim are superb, this is the kind of hood &amp; brim any hardshell that wants to call itself a hardshell should have. The very wide brim keeps snow and rain off your face, can be bend and adjusted thanks to the wire to your needs and the hood closes nice and tight around the face. Sure, the hood adjustment strings could be on the outside - now they’re on the inside - but you still can get a very great fit. From the back you can adjust it further, too, and it fits a helmet so mountaineers and alpinists will really like this jacket.</p>

<p>Size-wise this Medium was a bit too large for me, though as it was the only Size Marmot had available for test I made it work. There’s plenty of space for layering underneath the trim fit of it, and as I loaned the jacket to my brother to see how it’d works for him, it was perfect (he’s a tad taller than me) and still offered plenty of space for layering a puffy jacket underneath it.</p>

<p>I’m pretty much neutral nowadays if it comes to WPB materials, Gore-Tex, eVent, NeoShell and Co. all seem to work equally well for me. Gore-Tex Pro is a pretty nice material, though - very durable, breathable and the DWR on it is superb - even after months of use the rain would still roll off nicely from it. Carrying backpacks, be it light packs on day hikes or heavy backpacks full of groceries had no negative effect on it, and I’m sure that even a large rucksack loaded with two weeks food wouldn’t trouble this jacket.</p>

<p>A subjective like is the colour, although because of the green - blue mix I’m often remembered of a <a href="http://open.spotify.com/track/64KxqiGLYHkyxdiLKXDVAR">sketch</a> by Badesalz. Nevertheless, the blue is a good colour and the green details make it pop nicely. I’m also happy with the weight, it’s light enough to carry it in the pack on good days, and it also feels light when wearing. The fabric is pretty stretchy and allows for some great freedom of movement, so for (ice) climbing this is a very good choice.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416783466/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2849/10416783466_2c18984105_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416928913/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3781/10416928913_e51dfe9c73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416752296/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7443/10416752296_7e0b8278d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>Plenty of competition, though if we just look at hardshells made of the new Gore-Tex Pro then we have the <a href="http://bit.ly/16sZ9Je">Arc’teryx Alpha SV</a>, <a href="http://www.adidas.com/us/product/mens-outdoor-terrex-advanced-jacket/G72286X">Adidas Terrex Advance</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1h5mRTe">Mammut Meron</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/17GGfil">Patagonia Powslayer</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1cbMmmd">The North Face Kichatna</a> and the <a href="http://bit.ly/16q9VFg">Norrøna lofoten Gore-Tex Pro Jacket</a>. However, all of these are more expensive than the Marmot Speed Light Jacket and also are more geared towards skiers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416761235/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3776/10416761235_4a6d39391d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="759" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p><a href="http://blessedoutdoors.blogspot.fi/2012/11/marmot-speed-light-first-impressions.html">James</a> likes his a lot and <a href="http://www.trektechblog.com/2013/03/marmot-speed-light-jacket-review.html">Tyler</a> loves his, even if it has a ketchup and mustard colour.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416760005/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2880/10416760005_625b592cbb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>It’s a great, durable jacket that you can take backpacking, mountaineering &amp; ice-climbing and you don’t need to be afraid that contact with rock &amp; ice would harm it. Personally I could have done without the Pit Zips, which would have made the jacket even lighter, but they’re there even if I don’t use them. If you’re in the market for a new hardshell which keeps you dry in the rest of autumn, winter and spring, then this could be it!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157636822996153/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/marmot-speed-light-jacke-dark-azure/">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marmot-womens-speed-light-jacket-hardshelljacke/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176AJZP">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176B8eQ">CampSaver.com</a> <em>Best Deal! Just $255</em></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/19XZbJd">REI.com</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/Marmot_Speed_Light_Jacket">Partioaitta</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10416898253/" title="Marmot Speed Light Jacket by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2856/10416898253_47721804df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Marmot Speed Light Jacket" /></a> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
