<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sleeping | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/sleeping/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-15T18:48:15+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHD Minix Sleeping Bag]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/phd-minix-sleeping-bag.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-02T23:19:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/phd-minix-sleeping-bag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/minix-down-primaloft-sleeping-bag">PHD Minix Sleeping Bag</a> is interesting: Down on top and Primaloft in the bottom with a water-resistant shell, which makes it a warm and very lightweight sleeping bag. If it’s a good choice for your 3-season backpacking trips you read in my review.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18387083991" title="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8879/18387083991_18fcbe74b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/minix-down-primaloft-sleeping-bag">PHD Minix Sleeping Bag</a> arrived last year May and has been used on several trips since, like my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/bouldering-on-aland.html">climbing roadtrip in Finland</a> and backpacking on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">Högakustenleden</a>.</p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The Minix is a sleeping bag, and so it’s function is to keep you warm while you sleep outdoors. </p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>PHD has this to say about the Minix:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Water-resistant Ultrashell outer (40 g/ m²)</li>
  <li>Primaloft Gold insulation on the base to handle damp &amp; maximise insulation under compression</li>
  <li>Box wall construction on top to maximise down loft</li>
  <li>900 fillpower European goose down</li>
  <li>Superlight MX inner (32 g/ m²)</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18199309079" title="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag bottom &amp; top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/289/18199309079_157412966a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag bottom &amp; top" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>PHD uses high-quality fabrics - a water-resistant outer, a box-wall construction for the 900 cuin down and Primaloft Gold - to create a ultralight sleeping bag. There’s also not many sleeping bags available that have a synthetic bottom and down on top - a smart way to use these two insulation materials.</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>I own a few garments and the Minix from PHD and they are really of a superb quality. All of them are hand made in the UK, from the best and most functional materials. That quality has its price, but you’ll get many years of use out of them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18197780400" title="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag Bottom by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7750/18197780400_0e075a9a30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Sleeping Bag Bottom" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Minix I have - it’s the 2014 model which has a different colour than the 2015 one, otherwise they’re the same - weighs 575 g in Standard length, with the stuff sack tipping the scales at 25 g.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I really like using the Minix. While it needed some time to get used to the restricted movement that a sleeping bag offers, and that you only can get in via the top, once inside it was warm and comfy to sleep in. PHD gives the Minix a Comfort rating of 0°C and I can confirm that. With a T-shirt on the Minix kept me warm till 0°C, but once there was just some light minus degrees I immediately was cold in the sleeping bag. So for early spring and autumn trips you might want to take an extra baselayer along to sleep warm in the Minix, for all other times when the temperatures stay warm you can sleep just in your shirt and underwear in the Minix.</p>

<p>If it gets too warm - for me that’s +10°C and over - the Minix was very hot and I would start to perspire. This meant I would either pull the sleeping bag down to my waist to cool off or get completely out of the bag and just use it as a blanket over me, which allowed me to also leave a leg out to cool down. The Minix is very wide above so using it as a blanket worked well for me when laying on my back. I think the sleeping bag is ideal for temperatures between +1°C and +9°C, if it goes under 0°C you want to wear something in it, and if it goes over 10°C I do run to warm in it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18387090991" title="PHD Minix Hood Open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/540/18387090991_edecbec72d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Hood Open" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18381395682" title="PHD Minix Hood Closed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/438/18381395682_1677d102c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Hood Closed" /></a></p>

<p>The freedom of movement inside of the sleeping bag is good, too. Because the Minix does not have a collar and just one drawstring to close the hole there’s not anything in the way on top, which makes turning around inside of the bag easy. The foot box was big enough for my size 42 feet and I also could lay in comfort on my side inside of the bag. </p>

<p>The Minix comes with a mesh storage bag and a 2 l stuff sack, the latter is great and well-suited for the bag but for the mesh bag I would prefer something larger from organic cotton. I have used the Minix with and without a bivy and with a bivy you have the added benefit of a mosquito protection and a few degrees more warmth. The Minix packs nice and small and lofts very quickly at camp. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17764852993" title="PHD Minix Footbox by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/277/17764852993_dd73e687ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Footbox" /></a></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>A small pocket for the drawstring on top would be great, I hate straps flying around my head and a pocket where I can stuff the drawstring in would take it out of the way and add just a couple of gram of weight. I’m also wondering if a light zipper down one side would be of benefit, while this would add quite a bit of weight it would make it easier to get in to the sleeping bag and also venting would be improved. </p>

<p>Finally, I wonder if the concept of the Minix - synthetic bottom and down top - would not be a great idea for a quilt. It would lose the hood most likely, but freedom of movement and venting would be improved a lot, and it even should be able to be lighter.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>If I just think about sleeping bags then the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mountain-hardwear-hyperlamina-spark-kunstfaserschlafsack/">Mountain Hardwear Hyperlamina Spark</a>, the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/montane-featherlite-5-schlafsack-reg-links/">Montane Featherlite 5</a>, the <a href="http://bit.ly/1AInDmz">Rab Ascent 300</a> and the <a href="http://bit.ly/1cvmt1X">Western Mountaineering MegaLite</a> sleeping bags come to mind. The first is a synthetic sleeping bag while the other three are very good down sleeping bags, but none of these have two insulation materials in combination.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If the idea of quilts is alien to you, then the Minix sleeping bag will be great for you. An ultralight sleeping bag that has a water-resistant shell you can use it without a bivy from spring to autumn as long as the thermometer stays above 0°C. The Primaloft bottom allows you to use a lighter, less insulated <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/sleeping-pads/">sleeping pad</a> as it is warm, even when compressed, and also is less sensitive to dew and moisture than down. The warm layer of 900 cuin down in box-wall construction on top keeps you toasty on fresh nights, and if it gets too warm you can even improvise the Minix into a narrow blanket. The water-resistant Ultrashell withstands dew and a light drizzle, protects the down and lets it loft nicely. If you want one sleeping bag for your 3-season trips that’s water-resistant, light, has a small pack size and is toasty warm, consider the Minix from PHD!</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk/minix-down-primaloft-sleeping-bag">Minix</a> is part of the PHD <a href="http://stories.phdesigns.co.uk/summer-lightning-2015">Summer Lightning Collection</a> that is only available in May &amp; June from PHD directly - so hurry if you want this sleeping bag!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18387085671" title="PHD Minix Packed Size by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/420/18387085671_180a8b2f5c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PHD Minix Packed Size" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/jacks-r-better-high-sierra-sniveller.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-06T21:03:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/jacks-r-better-high-sierra-sniveller</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller</a> is the Multi-Tool amongst the winter quilts, as it not just is a toasty quilt for your autumn to spring backpacking trips but also works as a Poncho/ Serape and can be used with your hammock. Toasty times!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17375828181" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Reading/ chilling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5464/17375828181_01ce55ee52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Reading/ chilling" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller</a> arrived in December 2013 at HiF HQ and has seen several outings since, amongst others to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html">Lake District</a> in England.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376802441" title="Bed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5515/14376802441_7b2115dea3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller is not just a quilt. It is</p>

<ul>
  <li>A quilt</li>
  <li>A serape/ poncho</li>
  <li>A top quilt for your hammock</li>
  <li>Almost a sleeping bag</li>
</ul>

<p>Made for cold temperatures the High Sierra Sniveller is a winter quilt which should keep you toasty to around -5°C to -10°C, maybe even colder temperatures if you’re a warm sleeper.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17350199956" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Inside open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7785/17350199956_125178e9ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Inside open" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The High Sierra Sniveller can be used as a flat blanket, a sleeping bag/ quilt and a serape. A serape is like a poncho, and for that it has a Velcro head hole in the middle which you can open and put your head through. You then can tie it closed around your waist to minimize drafts. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376162885" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Closed in the back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8698/17376162885_dbf25b1de9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Closed in the back" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The JRB Sierra Sniveller Quilt is very well constructed, with clean seams, durable and high-quality materials. It uses a 1.1 oz., 30 denier ripstop nylon and 800 cuin fill power goose down. The shell &amp; lining material is soft and comfortable on the skin and the high-quality down keeps you toasty warm.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17375828531" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Tags by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7795/17375828531_440530fdf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Tags" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>679 g High Sierra Sniveller Quilt, Regular length</p>

<p>38 g Compression stuff sack</p>

<p><strong>717 g Total</strong></p>

<p>That’s a very good weight for a winter quilt, especially when set in relation to the price. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376164525" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Down under by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5450/17376164525_c009b7de26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Down under" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/quilt-comparison-chart/">Quilt Comparison Chart</a> is ideal in my opinion for anyone considering a JRB quilt. These kind of tables should be standard for any company offering many similar products within the same category, as it makes choosing the right product for a customer much easier. </p>

<p>The High Sierra Sniveller is unassuming. A green, stealthy shell blends in in forest environments, and the black inside helps with drying the quilt in the sun in the morning. The construction is clean and sturdy, and while being lightweight I didn’t have the feeling that I need to treat it with silk gloves. The cord locks and cords as well as the Velcro closures radiate sturdiness, too. </p>

<p>I have used the High Sierra Sniveller mostly as a quilt/ sleeping bag and a flat blanket, in both configurations I was very happy with it. The footbox is long enough for me and it is easy to take one leg out of it to <em>“cool down”</em>. The Regular length has a small taper, it’s 132 cm wide at the top and goes down to 96 cm at the foot end. It was a good size for my thin self and drafts where no problem, also when sleeping on my side. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17376164655" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Chilling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8715/17376164655_8c5f7da7c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Chilling" /></a></p>

<p>I have used the JRB High Sierra Sniveller on autumn and spring trips where temperatures went down to around -2°C and it was too warm for me in those conditions, so I think it’s easily good to -5°C to -10°C as claimed by JRB. If you like to strap the quilt to your mat then there’s three pairs of webbing loops to allow you to do that. </p>

<p>Using it as a serape is only something for morning and evening use in Camp, I wouldn’t want to wear it while moving throughout the day - it’s not very ergonomic. If you’re out on a winter trip and want to minimize the puffy, space-consuming down jacket for camp and breaks, the High Sierra Sniveller will be a good solution for you. The draw-back is that you need to be more careful around campfires when wearing your High Sierra Sniveller, as you don’t want any holes from sparks or such in it. If saving weight &amp; space is a high importance, then the multiple use aspect of this quilt will be high. If not needed the head hole closes tightly and almost can’t be seen, and also has not been a source of drafts or similar. This is a good feature for people who want it, and if you don’t need it it’s easy enough to ignore that it’s there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17168694907" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole closed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8782/17168694907_cb451e5ed1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole closed" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188369558" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7774/17188369558_f630c2f75a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Head hole open" /></a></p>

<p>I didn’t like the compression bag a lot - it does tend to get into a strange shape, and the biggest problem I have with that is that packing it in a backpack creates some unusable, empty space. Also the pull strap you can hold on to feels, while being sturdily sewn, that it could break. I much prefer super basic roll-top closure stuff sacks that are light. The storage <em>“sack”</em> is a plastic square bag with a zipper, which I also felt isn’t the best place to store a down bag. Here I prefer large (organic) cotton bags or at least a fabric that’s breathable. Organic cotton bags also would be more environmentally friendly, and look nicer if stored in plain sight. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17189931059" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Size comparison by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8728/17189931059_3b7cb85afd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Size comparison" /></a></p>

<p>With the sleeping bag I have no serious complaints. I saw that the head end got a push button in 2014 which allows you to close the quilt around your neck so it stays in place, this is a nice feature especially on more breezy, cold nights as it keeps drafts out and the warm air in. JRB also is now using a hydrophobic down, which is good for a quilt which is likely used in wet &amp; cold environments. The cord locks and cords are very durable and big, I imagine JRB could easily use smaller &amp; lighter versions of these without making them more difficult to use but saving a bit of weight. I also would put the top loops for attaching the quilt to a mat further down, though in use the two pairs in the middle should be enough if you use that feature.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193694557" title="Camp II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2898/14193694557_4fe213486b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Camp II" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>The quilt maker market has seen some influx in the last years, and also some big brands have started to make quilts. Directly competing with the JRB High Sierra Sniveller are for me, given it’s unique feature set, only the <a href="http://astucas.com/en/products/sestrals-poncho">As Tucas Sestrals Poncho</a> and the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=42&amp;products_id=133">MLD Spirit Quilt</a>, though both are synthetic insulation quilts. These have the option to wear it as a poncho. A warm winter quilt is also the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/01/katabatic-gear-sawatch-quilt.html">Katabatic Gear Sawatch Quilt</a>, and then there’s several other quilts &amp; sleeping bags which are fit for winter use.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188583110" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Top View by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7664/17188583110_59c95bb036_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Top View" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Ultralight-Sleeping-Bag-Reviews/Jacks-R-Better-Sierra-Sniveller">Outdoor Gear Lab</a> gave it 4 Stars and <a href="http://treadoutdoors.blogspot.fi/2014/11/love-sniveller-jack-r-better-sierra.html">T.R.E.A.D. Outdoors</a> rates it high, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188369208" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - A look from beneath by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8732/17188369208_47fa87f620_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - A look from beneath" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I like the Jacks ‘R’ Better High Sierra Sniveller. The Multiple-use aspect of it is great: You can use it as an open blanket, a quilt, a poncho and also as a top quilt in your hammock, which is superb value for your money - if you need these options. If you don’t plan to use the High Sierra Sniveller as a serape you might be able to save some weight by getting a quilt without the head hole, though it probably is useful to have in an emergency - and does not add a substantial amount of weight. As a quilt it performs just as it should: Unpack, let it loft and then have a comfortable, un-restricted night’s sleep underneath it. It’s easy to vent when you run warm, and if you plan to use it as a serape it will save you money that you’d spent on a dedicated down jacket. If you’re looking for a multiple-use, lightweight, warm and affordable autumn to spring quilt, take a good look at the High Sierra Sniveller from Jacks ‘R’ Better - you won’t be disappointed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157652366367951">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>You can buy the <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/shop/high-sierra-sniveller/">High Sierra Sniveller</a> at <a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/">Jacks ‘R’ Better</a>. Right now it is on Sale and starts at $310 (regular price starts at $410).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17188368038" title="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Sleeping by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7708/17188368038_aac28bc259_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="JRB High Sierra Sniveller - Sleeping" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Klymit Pillow X]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/klymit-x-pillow.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-15T23:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/klymit-x-pillow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not only a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/sleeping-pads/">sleeping pad</a> is needed for a good night’s sleep on the trail, also a pillow is what many of us want for sweet dreams under the stars. After trying several pillows and fussing around with spare clothes I found the Klymit Pillow X and don’t go backpacking without it anymore.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732148989" title="75% of the sleep system deployed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5554/14732148989_77b4b1a3af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="75% of the sleep system deployed" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Another 56 g that’s added to the sleep system. If it looks like there’s a gear-increase, that well may be possible. But after years of fussing around with rolled-up clothing or stuff sacks to act as a pillow, trying some other <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kissen/">backpacking pillows</a> and trying to learn to sleep without one I pulled the trigger on the <a href="http://bit.ly/1BiBQ6m">Klymit Pillow X</a> as I saw it over at <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=42&amp;products_id=207">Mountain Laurel Designs</a>. I didn’t bother reading reviews (there were none) but felt this would be a winning purchase just by a look at the design.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14923923062" title="Klymit Pillow X Packed Size by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3854/14923923062_c4b0718a72_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Klymit Pillow X Packed Size" /></a></p>

<p>That X is where the magic happens, design-wise. It centres your head in the middle, cradles it a bit, and works great for side and back sleepers. I turn a lot in my sleep, from side to belly to side to back and onwards, and the Pillow X is comfortable in any of these positions. I even can prop my arm up underneath it, almost as home. I have used it on all long hikes this year, from winter camping in the north to hillwalking in the Lake District and backpacking on the Eisleck Trail and the result is: It’s a winner. It gets packed always, because I value good sleep on the trail. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918461392" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5579/14918461392_fca784d892_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow" /></a></p>

<p>Two puffs to inflate. It takes longer to deflate and roll up the Pillow X, around a minute or two, as the X construction likes to trap air here and there. But hey, that’s OK, there’s usually no hurry in the mornings. When the vlave looks big: It is. But it ain’t in the way for me, in a pinch you can even turn the pillow around and don’t have the valve on top. Maybe Klymit will at some point use a smaller vlave which would save some weight and not stand out that much, but even like this it works well.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918807565" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5574/14918807565_ee3f52704a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow" /></a></p>

<p>The bottomline is pretty straight forward: When I pack along with the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html">XLite</a> or <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">Xtherm</a> the Pillow X always comes along. It are 56 g that I’m happy to carry for a comfy pillow that works. If you feel the same and want to get a good night’s sleep order your Pillow X from <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=42&amp;products_id=207">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> or directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1BiBQ6m">Klymit</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732204528" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5564/14732204528_9318db644b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite &amp; Klymit X Pillow" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-14T12:37:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/ie/therm-a-rest/mattresses/fast-and-light/neoair-xlite/product">Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite</a> lets you sleep comfortable &amp; warm all night long and won’t slow you down or take up a lot of space in your pack while you’re hiking. After over a year of use on different trails the verdict is out: This is one of the best 3-Season sleeping pads on the market. <em>Read all about it in my in-depth review.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376802441" title="Bed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5515/14376802441_7b2115dea3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bed" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I’m sleeping on the NeoAir XLite Regular since August 2013 when it’s the season. It was along in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho-Kekkonen National Park</a>, on the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/koli-national-park.html">2013 UL Summit</a> and every hike of 2014. I slept over 50 nights on this mat and it still works superb.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14915727601" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3883/14915727601_8491b07928_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>Like the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">NeoAir XTherm</a> the XLite’s function is to provide you with a warm and comfortable bed at camp while being small &amp; light when being carried in your pack. The mattress is insulating you towards the ground so you can sleep warm.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732150280" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, inflated by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5552/14732150280_caed27a91e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, inflated" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>My Regular length XLite has the following specs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>R-Value 3,2</li>
  <li>183 cm long, 6 cm thick, tapers from 49 cm to 38 cm (that’s the real inflated width)</li>
  <li>Reflective ThermaCapture™ technology traps radiant heat </li>
  <li>Triangular Core Matrix™ construction minimizes convective heat loss</li>
  <li>Made in Ireland</li>
</ul>

<p>The XLite is available in three sizes (S = 119 cm long, 230 g/ Regular = 183 cm long, 353 g/ L = 196 cm, 460 g) and a Women’s Version (168 cm, 340 g) which has a higher R-Value.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732146959" title="Sleep &amp; shelter system by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/14732146959_1ed65c71de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sleep &amp; shelter system" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The Reflective ThermaCapture™ technology is an innovation. It are reflective layers inside the NeoAir mattress that reflect radiant heat back to your body, and so amplifys the warmth without the bulk, weight or durability issues of down and synthetic fills. Also the Triangular Core Matrix™ construction is an innovation, this construction combines two layers of triangular baffles to create over a hundred insulating cells in the mattress and so slowing down convective heat loss as well as delivering very good stability for maximum comfort.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918803885" title="75% of the sleep system deployed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5563/14918803885_16ef248408_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="75% of the sleep system deployed" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After over 50 nights on thee mattress it still works and looks great and shows no signs of weaknesses. It’s a durable mat and can take the abuse of what you encounter when you’re backpacking.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Regular length XLite is 353 g.</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>The XLite is made in Ireland of oil based materials and has a coating on the inside, so shouldn’t be thrown in the garbage like ordinary rubbish. You could try to either recycle it via your local outdoor shop or inquire from Therm-A-Rest how to recycle the mat at the end of its life cycle.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14918814195" title="Valve by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3906/14918814195_4dd814de57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Valve" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>15 large breaths, that’s how often a non-smoker will need to inhale and exhale to make out of the small, rolled up package a fully inflated, comfy mat. If you like it softer, maybe 13 or 14 are enough, and if you have a small lunge volume it might be more, but 15 breaths is what it takes me to inflate this mat. If that seems too much for you then Therm-A-Rest has a a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-neoair-mini-pump/">Mini Pump</a> for you which will add 65 g to your pack or an <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-neo-air-pumpsack/">Pump Sack</a> that adds 77 g to your packed weight and make life on the trail slightly easier. Of course then you just also could take a self-inflating mat or a closed cell foam mat and be done and never inflate a mattress again. </p>

<p>But those mats are quite a bit larger in packed size and often also quite a bit more heavy. So with a mat like the XLite you get a light mat that packs up small - about 1 l rolled up is what it will take of the space in you pack. Speaking of the rolled up mat, deflating is just as easy as inflating. Open the valve and it will largely empty itself, but to speed things up you can kneel on it. When it’s fully deflated I lay it out flat, fold it twice into the middle and then roll it up, that way I get an approximately 23 cm long package that’s about 9 cm in diameter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732244997" title="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, folded by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3904/14732244997_e1fbff813e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite, folded" /></a></p>

<p>One of the reasons you will consider the XLite is Comfort. At six cm thick the XLite is fully inflated a very comfy mattress, and if you like more cushy/ soft mattresses just open the valve to adjust it to your liking. It also makes camping fairly flexible as you’re less dependent on 100% even surfaces - if theres a root protruding from the spot you want to camp the XLite is able to comfortably lay on top of it and you’d have never known. Similarly it’s great for camping on the rocks, for example if you want to bivy on a summit. While it’s a durable mat I do carry a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/exped-doublemat-evazote-sleeping-mat.html">very thin Exped CCF pad</a> along which I lay underneath the XLite to protect it a bit from sharp, small rocks or stuff I might have not seen. It’s also a good back-up and adds a bit of extra warmth.</p>

<p>Warmth is one of the other things where the XLite shines. It’s a warm mattress - I had it down to around -5°C and was toasty on it and never knew I’m on a 3-Season pad. Which means you’re good to go till late autumn with this mattress, and if you like to use a CCF pad in winter as a back-up either way you even might be able to use the XLite in mild winters. For serious cold winters I’d still use the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html">XTherm</a>, though.</p>

<p>Finally, the XLite fits well into my different bivys. While in SUL bivys which are not very high you might run into trouble, my tyvek, Pertx and Cuben bivys are all wide and spacious enough to accommodate this inflated mattress. If you use a thin mattress right now and your bivy is a bit tight already it might be useful to get a more spacious bivy at the same time that you’re getting the XLite. If you don’t use a bivy this obviously will be of no concern =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13982574636" title="Good night! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7203/13982574636_c7f96370bb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Good night!" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a few mattresses that fill the same niche as the XLite: There’s the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/exped-synmat-7-isolierte-isomatte-kunstfaserfuellung/">Exped SynMat 7</a>, the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-light-pump-mat-ul-isomatte/">Mammut Light Pump Mat UL</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/vaude-norrsken-primaloft-isomatte/">Vaude Norrsken</a> and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/trangoworld-micro-air-isomatte/">Trangoworld Micro Air</a> which all have a similar pack size and warmth rating but most of these are heavier. </p>

<h2 id="what-could-be-better">What Could Be Better</h2>

<p>I have no complains about the XLite. Sure, at some point in time it’d be nice to get the same warmth &amp; comfort for less weight, but for now I’m happy. Those that always thought the XLite and XTherm were to loud, Therm-A-Rest has heard you and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html">from 2015 on the mats will be more silent</a>. And those that would like to not have to inflate their XLite but still want a 5 cm thick pad should get the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html">EvoLite</a> in 2015.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>After many years of backpacking and sleeping outside it’s pretty straight forward for me when I pack the sleep system: Spring till autumn it’s the XLite, winter and high-altitude it’s the XTherm. The XLite packs small in my pack when on the trail and is lightweight with just 353 g for the 183 cm long mattress. After 15 puffs of air at camp I have a comfy mat to chill and sleep on that keeps me well insulated against the ground. It makes finding a 100% perfect camp spots less of a hassle as I can lay comfortable above roots and round rocks on this 6 cm thick pad. Most important, I get a great nights sleep on it every time and am ready for another good day on the trail, where the small packed mattress again disappears in my pack. If you want comfort &amp; warmth paired with a light weight and small pack size, look no further than the Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XLite.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Buy your XLite at <a href="http://bit.ly/Vpj8J3">Backcountry</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-neo-air-xlite-small-isomatte/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite-isomatte/">Bergfreunde</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/1bcnz0i">Campsaver</a>, <a href="http://tinyurl.com/pacvgwc">Cotswold</a>, <a href="https://www.globetrotter.de/shop/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite-200118/?utm_source=PTID13002584">Globetrotter</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/VmUMQt">REI</a> or the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Isomatten/Therm-A-Rest-NeoAir-XLite::458.html?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14732238277" title="Day-Dreaming by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3867/14732238277_8e75eeaf30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Day-Dreaming" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Therm-A-Rest NeoAir XTherm]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-11T16:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While the UL scene rejoiced when the original NeoAir came on the market, I never have been a big fan of it. It was just too cold for me, even on a warm summer night with a CCF pad underneath it. I quickly got rid of it, and have been using CCF pads and self-inflatable mats pretty much exclusively since then. But then Therm-A-Rest presented us the <a href="http://cascadedesigns.com/therm-a-rest/mattresses/fast-and-light/neoair-xtherm/product">NeoAir XTherm</a>, with a R-Value of 5,7, and they got my attention for that. Now that I have been using this mat since over a year, it is time to take a good, close look at it.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8594192687/" title="Inflated top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8594192687_811819c147_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Inflated top" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>
<p>The NeoAir XTherm arrived in 2011 and I have been using it a lot since, even on trips where I was wondering if it is smart to take such a mat with me. The mat has been holding up very well and shows no signs of usage after over 30 nights on it. It’s stored at the moment deflated &amp; rolled up to safe space, though once I’m moving I will store it unrolled &amp; inflated as it is recommended.</p>

<p>It got used on the UL Summit in Slovenia, Bikepacking, Autumn hikes on the Pirkan Taival and winter hikes in the Helvetinjärvi National Park, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html">Korouoma</a> and overnighters. </p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>
<p>The XTherm’s function is to provide you with a warm and comfortable bed at camp while being small &amp; light when being carried in your pack. In both aspects, camp-use and during hiking, it performs superbly. It has a small enough pack size, inflates fully with 15 to 20 puffs, and is warm and very comfortable in use. </p>

<p>What this means in practice is that when you’re hiking the XTherm won’t take a lot of space in your pack, and when you arrive at camp it isn’t too strenuous to inflate the mat - you could even use the pack sack as an inflation bag if you’re out of breath. The mat is a superb padding on hard and uneven undergrounds, and insulates you against the cold that creeps up from the ground, even in the depth of winter. It works very well together with <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/11/quilt-101.html">quilts</a> but sleeping bag users will like it just as much.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8594211097/" title="Size by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8231/8594211097_96530624a7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Size" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<p>The XTherm has horizontal, over 6 cm thick baffles and is tapered at the ends, and has a friction surface which stops you from sliding around. The pack sack functions as a inflation bag though I never have bothered with that, although the idea is that it helps to avoid getting moisture inside which could possibly freeze and damage the internals of the mat. That hasn’t been a problem for me yet, even if the XTherm has been outdoors a lot in cold temperatures. It comes with a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-fast-and-lite-repair-kit.html">repair kit</a>, too.</p>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>
<p>The XTherm comes in four lengths, and I decided to get the Regular length. I have had a Short NeoAir in the past which was not comfortable for me, as the drop-off was at my knees. I tried putting thicker equipment under my legs to make the height difference bearable, but in the end wasn’t happy with the solutions. The Regular length XTherm, 183 cm long, is superb for me (175 cm tall, 63 kg light). I can sleep comfortably on the mat, be it on my side, back or stomach. I also never compress the mat enough to touch the ground with my hips or elbows when on the mat, which sometimes can happen for side sleepers on thin mats. Its tapered at the ends, but is still wide enough so that head and feet stay on the mat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8638950503/" title="Sleeping by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8522/8638950503_b06042fdd4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sleeping" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>
<p>The <em>Reflective Barriers</em> used in the XTherm are a new technology which Therm-A-Rest is using in this mattress, which help to save weight and bulk. Four layers of this reflective material recycle body heat and create air pockets that reduce convective heat loss. Additionally Therm-A-Rest developed a <em>Triangular Core Matrix</em> construction which provides stability and comfort. In practice these have been working for me indeed as claimed, the pad is very warm and stable to sleep on, be it on my back, side or belly.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595308334/" title="Deflated by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8509/8595308334_f7cc248b58_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Deflated" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>
<p>I need to say that thus far (30+ nights) I am amazed about the quality of the XTherm. I know that e.g. <a href="http://tramplite.com/">Colin</a> has had less luck with other NeoAir models, which have developed a “pillow” after 60 nights on them, but so far I have not had any problems with my XTherm. It’s also surprisingly durable, in that it has been laid down on rough mountain floors and hard, ice covered snow &amp; ice and has withstood that without problems. If it doesn’t develop the <em>pillow</em> then I am sure that I will get many years use out of this mat.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8594196409/" title="Inflated top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8369/8594196409_2f0fc1af78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Inflated top" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>
<p>My XTherm in Regular length (183 cm long) is 427 gram. It is a lot warmer than my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-ridgerest-solar-matte.html">RidgeRest Solar</a>, packs A LOT smaller and is lighter, too. Overall I rate this a the go-to mat for weight conscious backpackers who sleep outdoors in real cold weather.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8639086145/" title="XTherm vs. RidgeRest Solar by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8532/8639086145_0480bcbb35_b.jpg" width="1024" height="574" alt="XTherm vs. RidgeRest Solar" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>
<p>It’s made of oil based materials and has a coating on the inside, so shouldn’t be thrown in the garbage like ordinary rubbish. You could try to either recycle it via your local outdoor shop or inquire from Therm-A-Rest how to recycle the mat at the end of its life cycle.</p>

<p><em>More coming later.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595294416/" title="Inflated top by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8101/8595294416_f1f611b950_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Inflated top" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>
<p>I have used the XTherm pretty much always with a CCF pad, mostly the superb <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/exped-doublemat-evazote-sleeping-mat.html">Exped Doublemat</a> which I have cut in half for 3 Season use, or a <a href="http://www.multimat.uk.com/store/products/summit-xl">Multimat Summit XL</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-ridgerest-solar-matte.html">RidgeRest Solar</a> in winter. In winter it’s to get a little bit of extra warmth, in summer to protect the pad slightly better from sharp rocks or sticks. Inflating it is easy even after a 30 km day, and it takes me less than 2 minutes to get the mat fully inflated. Before I go to sleep I add a few extra puffs - I like to sleep on a hard mat - and that is it. </p>

<p>In the mornings the deflating and rolling up is similarly easy, I fold the pad a couple of times and then knee on it, and then just roll it up. I don’t use the pack sack (heavy!) and just pack it fairly in the middle of my pack with the shelter and bivy. The noise the internal baffles make is not a problem for me, though if you camp with other people in the same shelter and move a lot in your sleep, it might be something that could bother. It will not impact your sleep in any way, though. </p>

<p>I have slept down to -12°C only with the NeoAir XTherm on the ground and down to -17°C with a CCF pad underneath it. In both setups I was comfortably warm and didn’t feel any cold coming up from the ground through the mat. I feel confident to take the mat out in up to -30°C nights together with a CCF pad in winter.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7783259222/" title="Open Doors by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8307/7783259222_fbc46ab400_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Open Doors" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re now under the impression that the XTherm is only a winter mat, let me correct that view right away! While it certainly shines in cold temperatures, it is also great in summer. So have I used it for example for one week on the Ultralight Summit in Slovenia last year, where we were in August. During the day we had temps of over 35°C but at night high up in the mountains it quickly got cold once the sun set, and during the night temperatures were as low as 5°C. In these situations I was happy that I had the XTherm with me, as the rocks on the high plateau were not warm! Also here in the north, especially above the Arctic Circle, temperatures in the summer can sometimes drop down to 0°C and in those situations a mat like the XTherm comes in very useful, guaranteeing you a comfortable night.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>
<p>The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/exped-synmat-ul-7-isolierte-isomatte-kunstfaserfuellung/">Exped Synmat UL 7</a> and the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/exped-downmat-7-daunengefuellte-isomatte/">Exped Downmat 7</a> both are similarly warm, yet sadly Exped’s quality control lets quite a few faulty mats end up in customer hands so reviews are mixed. The <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/mammut-softskin-mat-aufblasbare-isomatte/">Mammut SoftSkin Mat</a> too has a good R-Value, as does the <a href="https://www.bigagnes.com/Products/Detail/Pad/qcoresl">Big Agnes Q-Core SL</a>. </p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>
<p><a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/sleeping-mats-hyalite-peak-elite-ac-and-thermarest-neoair-xtherm">Michael likes the XTherm</a> and compares it to two other mats. <a href="http://www.outdoorgearlab.com/Sleeping-Pad-Reviews/Therm-a-Rest-NeoAir-Xtherm">Max from the Outdoor Gear Lab</a> gives the XTherm five stars. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595275160/" title="At Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8365/8595275160_8c6acc852b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="At Camp" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>
<p>Quite easily the best all-season mat I have slept on to date. Lightweight, small pack size, warm and comfortable, the NeoAir XTherm ticks a lot of boxes that are important for backpackers that value a good nights sleep while not carrying heavy, bulky mats. If I know that I want a good nights sleep then I bring along the XTherm, which lately has been pretty much always. </p>

<p>If you only want one inflatable mattress for all your trips, be they in winter or summer, for an overnighter in the nearby forest or for an high alpine adventure in the Alps, then the NeoAir XTherm is your mat of choice.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633104057740/">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-neoair-xtherm">Where to buy the NeoAir XTherm</h2>
<p>Buy it at <a href="http://bit.ly/128XiGA">Backcountry</a> $190 | <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm-isomatte/">Bergfreunde</a> 140€ | <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-neo-air-xtherm-isomatte.html">Bergzeit</a> 170€ | <a href="http://bit.ly/TVCVNY">CampSaver</a> $190 | <a href="http://bit.ly/128YMAG">REI</a> $180 </p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>
<ul>
  <li>More on Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Disclaimer</em><br />
Therm-A-Rest provided me the XTherm free of charge for testing, and paid me 1 million € to review it.*</p>

<p><sub><sup><sub><sup>* One of these statements is not true.</sup></sub></sup></sub></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8595282884/" title="At Camp by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8102/8595282884_af20f61bcf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="At Camp" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
