<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: EOG | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/eog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-04T13:01:02+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get Out into Nature because #ItsGreatOutThere]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/get-out-into-nature-because-itsgreatoutthere.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-08T23:44:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/get-out-into-nature-because-itsgreatoutthere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Its Great Out There</em> has been my thinking since I started to regularly go outdoors and climb, hike, packraft, cycle or camp. Why I thinks that way you find out in this post!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27700551721/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Sunrise on the Kanisfluh"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7180/27700551721_12abb83624_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise on the Kanisfluh" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>This article is part of an <a href="http://en.outdoor-blogger-network.com/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Network</a> campaign &amp; I got paid to write it. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site.</em></p>

<p>In last years #MyWeek #BeActive Challenge you got a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/take-part-in-the-myweek-beactive-challenge.html">permit to get outdoors</a>, and following up on that initiative this year the European Outdoor Group wants you to realize once more that <a href="http://www.itsgreatoutthere.com">#ItsGreatOutThere</a>. If you <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">follow me on Instagram</a> you probably have seen that hashtag quite a bit, because I honestly prefer being outside instead of standing in front of my desk. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26965430150/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Paddling at Matka Canyon 01"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7138/26965430150_1868afd7c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Paddling at Matka Canyon 01" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The #ItsGreatOutThere campaign’s believe - which I fully support - is that outdoor activites have an positive impact on individuals and society as a whole. Fitness, self-confidence, life skills, fun, health, unforgettable memories &amp; a sustainable connection with nature – that is the power of outdoor sports. Add in friends &amp; your family and you will create lasting memories &amp; bonds which you will fondly look back to in old age! I much prefer to spend my time in nature with the family &amp; friends instead of being in a busy city or working at the office. When the latter gets too much I jump on my bike and head out for a ride, coming back feeling much more satisfied and happy.</p>

<p>To help you realize that its better outside (just in case you have forgeotten ;) the European Outdoor Group has partnered with a lot of cool events &amp; companies to offer you some great prizes in their competitions this autumn. First off is the <a href="http://www.itsgreatoutthere.com/competition01-timeout/">timeout</a> competition where you can win two tickets for the The North Face Mountain Festival as well as some cool outdoor kit which makes autumn adventures warmer &amp; drier. Click that link if you feel like chilling with like-minded folks in Switzerland in the middle of September!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23380978901/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Hello Beach!"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/1/720/23380978901_4d30838bf6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hello Beach!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But even if you don’t have the desire to go to Switzerland for hiking, camping, climbing and good campfire vibes, you always can use the #ItsGreatOutThere and #beactive hashtags when you’re outside. Be it your cycle commute to the office, an after-work run in the forest, a packrafting Microadventure at the weekend or going for a dayhike with the kids. Need some ideas how you can #BeActive? Here you go:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Explore a Nature trail near where you life</li>
  <li>Go geocaching</li>
  <li>Build a den in the forest with your kids</li>
  <li>Go bouldering</li>
</ul>

<p>And after that, share your outdoor fun with your friends &amp; followers on Social Media. Don’t forget to add the #ItsGreatOutThere and #BeActive hashtags - That’s it =) You now have a great permission to get outdoors and a superb excuse, too - in case you need one! Have fun and feel free to share your adventures with us in the comments underneath!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27976948552/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Hiking towards the sunset"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7417/27976948552_cefcfdeaf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking towards the sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>This article is part of an <a href="http://en.outdoor-blogger-network.com/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Network</a> campaign &amp; I got paid to write it.This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
