<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-01T16:38:36+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker's Gear Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/andrew-skurka-the-ultimate-hikers-gear-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2015-09-04T23:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/andrew-skurka-the-ultimate-hikers-gear-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>New to (ultralight) backpacking, hiking and camping? Then read Andrew Skurka’s book “The Ultimate Hiker’s Gear Guide” before you spend a lot of money on your outdoor gear and avoid a lot of mistakes!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20944339600/in/dateposted-public/" title="Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker&#x27;s Gear Guide"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5806/20944339600_aab8b5cb74_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker&#x27;s Gear Guide" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Andrew Skurka is an Outside “Adventurer of the Year” and has hiked over 30.000 miles on long-distance trails and off the beaten path - to say he knows a thing or two about hiking &amp; backpacking is a small understatement. I bought Andrew’s Manuscript for this book in 2011 and as the book hit the shelves in 2012 I also ordered a copy. That’s one thing to keep in mind, as the book is from 2012 some gear recommendations will be outdated by now - GoLite for example is bankrupt and doesn’t trade anymore - but you’ll still find similar recommended kit that is likely even lighter! Plus there are several classics in there that are still available, from <a href="http://bit.ly/1PPeQS5">ULA Equipment</a> to <a href="http://bit.ly/1JGgXpL">Granite Gear</a>. The gear recommendations are solid &amp; lightweight, and you’ll not find heavy, traditional recommendations in this book - which is great.</p>

<p>Besides gear recommendations the best reason to get this book are the skills and knowledge articles. From tips on pitching a tarp, how to make a fancy feast alcohol stove to minimizing drafts when you sleep under a quilt, there’s hundreds of tried &amp; tested tricks in the book which will help you to pick up knowledge and skills without making the mistakes to learn them. For me these were the most interesting sections of the book, and it’s easy to pick up some new idea to try out on a future hike.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21106252506/in/dateposted-public/" title="Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker&#x27;s Gear Guide"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/704/21106252506_582d709224_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker&#x27;s Gear Guide" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As someone who likes logic I found it disappointing that the illogical imperial units where used in the book and not the Metric system. The gear lists in the end are all focussed on the United States of America which can be adapted to European, Asian and Australian needs in a pinch. Also, as mentioned before, some gear has evolved since Andrew wrote the book, and so it makes sense to check out for example breathable insulation garments and consider hydrophobic down when buying a quilt or jacket.</p>

<p>The book proclaims that this book is for novices, occasional backpackers and seasoned hikers alike, and I have to concur with that statement. The book packs a ton of knowledge into its 224 pages and is very much worth the ~ $20 it costs - because the result will be that you will save money on future (lightweight) gear purchases and have more fun &amp; comfort right from the start of your hiking career. The book has a good layout, is easy to read &amp; understand and has great photos of Andrew’s adventures in it which will get you in the mood to go outdoors. The book is a smaller size so it even could come along on a weekend trip or on your commute - a great way to learn about ultralight backpacking on the way to the office!</p>

<p>You can order a <a href="http://andrewskurka.com/product/ultimate-hikers-gear-guide/">signed copy from Andrew</a> or buy it online at <a href="http://amzn.to/1UqVZTS">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1JSjr5y">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1NedN0d">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kilian Jornet: Run Or Die]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/kilian-jornet-run-or-die.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-28T23:42:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/kilian-jornet-run-or-die</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you don’t know who Kilian Jornet is you have a great opportunity to get to know him in this personal look at what motivates him, why he runs and why he enjoys being outdoors.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20959699761/in/dateposted/" title="Run Or Die"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5748/20959699761_61679e92f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Run Or Die" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In nine chapters and 181 pages you get to know Kilian rather well. From his cycling adventures with his mom and sister, training for races and what goes on in his mind when he runs and competes. I don’t really like competitions, especially in the outdoors, but still found it interesting to read &amp; understand what drives him to go stand in a line and compete. I could very well relate to the difficulty at times to overcome one’s inner swine which just wants to stay in bed or chill on the sofa instead of going out for training, but Kilian trains (or competes) 360 days per year so I think many of use can learn in that department something from him!</p>

<p>The book is written in a pleasant way which is easy to read. Kilian takes you on a journey from his days as a child over his youth to a love story and onwards to the Western States Endurance and a run up &amp; down Kilimanjaro. You learn about his preparation for races, his music taste, where he loves to run and what goes on in his head when he runs the UTMB and other competitions. And in the end you learn that he, like you &amp; me, also really just enjoys to be outside and be active.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20959700571/in/dateposted/" title="Run Or Die"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5622/20959700571_6f982521e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Run Or Die" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The desire I feel is the same as I felt in the United States: I want to challenge myself, give the best of myself, and try to discover what my thresholds are, to know myself better.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So for whom is this book? I think it’s a good read for anyone who is interested in being outside and ponders what others think &amp; feel when being in nature. Trailrunners, ski mountaineers and fans of Kilian definitely should pick up his book, too, and learn what drives the most dominating endurance athlete of our time to push the envelope.</p>

<p>Buy Run Or Die at your local bookstore or ordered it online at <a href="http://amzn.to/1VhXcKh">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Ip3nTz">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1JBIsSv">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Wide Open]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Wide Open</em> has the byline <em>New Outdoor and Landscape Photography</em>. If it is really new and if you should get a copy, you read in my review.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968932345/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/319/19968932345_8fc222df65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gestalten-verlag/">Gestalten Verlag</a>. They make cool coffee table books with great photos and texts, so when <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">The Great Wide Open</a> appeared on my radar I was eager to check it out. An email and a few days later the heavy book slammed on my porch, ready to be browsed. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19780862558/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3665/19780862558_72b216d413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>However, opening the book the euphoria quickly ended. Sure, there are very fine images in there, but just as much of them look like they’re shot on an iPhone for Instagram and not for a large coffee table book. It feels like every other photo is a grainy mess that looked great on your Instagram feed when seen on a smartphone but shouldn’t have been printed in such a large format. Speaking of Instagram, if you’re on it and follow some landscape photographers then you’ll have seen the vast majority of these images in one form or another already. Another disappointment was that you could clearly see in many images that they have been taken not far away from a road or civilization - given that the Prologue of the book refers to <a href="http://amzn.to/1SFXAis">Ansel Adams</a> and how he would set off on long expeditions to capture expansive, wild landscapes that feels a bit wrong. Oh, and if you don’t like Chris Burkard - don’t get the book. Half the images are from him, and while they’re technically very good I personally find them a bit boring. On ther other hand, if you love him - get the book!</p>

<p>But for all that there’s also some very great &amp; inspiring photos in the book. The pictures from Anki Grøthe, Kilian Schönberger, Jimmy Chin, Logan Watts and a few others are crisp, sharp and with a fresh perspective on the outdoors. Add in the small stories and anecdotes from the photographers, athletes and outdoor folks and you get a book that will inspire you at least for one afternoon. Well, maybe a couple more. And if you like Instagram photos and would love to see them in a big book, you’ll probably read it every day! So if you feel like you want to give The Great Wide Open a chance and browse it yourself then order it directly at <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">Gestalten</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1RXDe9B">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJyEz">Amazon.co.uk</a> &amp; <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJFzT">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968931705/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/374/19968931705_29152e803e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kelly Cordes: The Tower]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/kelly-cordes-the-tower.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-26T23:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/kelly-cordes-the-tower</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bit.ly/1BQVH0i">Kelly Cordes - The Tower</a> is a gripping book about the history of climbing on Cerro Torre. If you’re in love with Patagonia, it’s mountaineering history, and the Chalten massiv, read on to hear my verdict on this book.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19165133102" title="Kelly Cordes - The Tower by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/302/19165133102_bd1146bf09_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kelly Cordes - The Tower" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Oh Patagonia, how I long to see thee!</em> As <a href="http://bit.ly/1BR9bcu">Patagonia Books</a> asked me if I’d like to read Kelly Cordes new book about Cerro Torre, my answer was of course <em>Yes!</em> How would one who likes to climb and loves the mountains not read the book about one of the most beautiful mountains on this planet? Also history enthusiasts will enjoy this fine book, which is written in such a way that also non-climbers will find it fascinating and read chapter after chapter.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Climbing is not a democracy. It never has been. That’s one of the things we love about it. Climbing is about freedom, and just as Maestri scarred Cerro Torre when he put in all those bolt ladders, Jason and I removed about 120 of his bolts on our descent.”</em> - Hayden Kennedy</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In a nutshell the book chronicles the history of climbing on Cerro Torre and the controversy surrounding the claimed first ascent in 1959 and the 1970 Compressor Route of Cesare Maestri, an Italian climber who became world-famous because of these two routes. The book has four distinct parts, divided into 35 chapters on 400 pages. Cordes tries on these pages to uncover the truth about the claimed First Ascent in 1959 &amp; the death of Toni Egger, who died under unknown circumstances on the claimed descent. Cordes interviews supporters and opponents of Maestri, talks with Reinhold Messner, and many of the Alpinists which have climbed new routes on Cerro Torre. In the end he draws logical conclusions, but lets you, the reader, come to your own results. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19170902365" title="Kelly Cordes - The Tower by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/318/19170902365_ed1f2005d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kelly Cordes - The Tower" /></a></p>

<p>On the side he also looks at how modern technology and tourism has changed the landscape in El Chalten, the removal of 120 of Maestri’s bolts and the ensuing discussion, and then gives you in three Appendixes a Timeline of Cerro Torre Ascents, the people mentioned and a climbing glossary, as well as maps and a selected bibliography. It’s a well rounded book with gorgeous photos and will inspire many to climb in Patagonia, or at least visit the area and hike underneath these stunning peaks. If you’re an Alpinist, climber, mountaineer or just barely interested in mountains and Cerro Torre then you should read this book. It’s an enthralling read and you’ll fly through the chapters, eager to learn more about the history and climbing on this beautiful mountain &amp; it’s difficult history. You can order the book directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1BQVH0i">Patagonia</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1GBoCAZ">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Jngv26">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1Cy6NlF">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Christopher McDougall: Born To Run]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/christopher-mcdougall-born-to-run.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-22T22:48:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/05/christopher-mcdougall-born-to-run</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s rare that I read a science/ novel/ diet/ adventure book which with each turn of the page has me think just one thing: I wanna go out for a run. Barefoot. <em><a href="http://amzn.to/1EnnrUf">Born to Run</a></em> is that book, and it is fortunate that the sun doesn’t set until 23 o’clock, leaving plenty of time for a quick run after reading in the evening.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17966167111" title="Born To Run by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7728/17966167111_9cc4bcb40f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Born To Run" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Born to Run sat for a while on my book shelf, and finally a couple of weeks ago I started reading it. Like many <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">books</a> it was difficult to put down and but as the clock was going towards midnight I resistantly put the book down and went to sleep, just to read a couple more pages in the morning. As an ultralight backpacker and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a> enthusiast I have been since a long time an advocate of minimalist footwear, this book serves you with a great story why modern running (and hiking) shoes are bad for you &amp; great reasons why you should go for a run if you feel stressed. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Suffering is humbling. It pays to know how to get your butt kicked.</em> -Caballo Blanco</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But from the start. Christopher McDougall, the author, is a running enthusiast - but after plenty of problems with achilles tendons, knees and back pain he’s about to put his running shoes on the hook. After seeing a photo of a Tarahumara runner in a magazine while being on assignment in Mexico McDougall starts the search for these runners, which takes him deep down into the Copper Canyons in search of them and the mystical Caballo Blanco. What evolves is part adventure novel, part science &amp; nutrition journal and part sports history, in which you find out how McDougall went from almost stopping to run to running an Ultra in the Copper Canyon, meeting Scott Jurek and running with the elusive Tarahumara indians. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17777626938" title="Born To Run by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5321/17777626938_555fa11535_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Born To Run" /></a></p>

<p>Born to Run is mandatory reading for runners, and also backpackers - because the latter are just endurance runners that go a tad slower. It’s a gripping read that will have you forget the time while you turn each page in anticipation, ditch your running shoes, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Aju8Ms">try new foods</a>, ponder your first Ultra and having the itch to go out for a run. Pick Born To Run up at your local bookshop or order it from <a href="http://amzn.to/1EnnrUf">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1FHztyZ">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1K8Ebns">Amazon.de</a> - and be prepared to wanna go running after reading a couple of pages!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
