<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-02T14:39:21+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard - The Calling]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T06:23:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What do Joy Division, The Rolling Stones, Les Droites, Nanga Parbet and the Cassin Ridge have in common?</em> They play a part in Barry Blanchard’s life, which is aptly re-told in his memoirs, “The Calling”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15451426995" title="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15451426995_53b9507d6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="675" alt="Traversing the Tent Arête on the Cassin Ridge.of Mount McKinley, Alaska, 1982. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Tune in to the soundtrack of Barry’s life with this Playlist, dutifully reconstructed from Chapter 2:</p>

<iframe src="https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify:user:skullmonkey:playlist:7qy8hUL8yIyABU8JFRfj3z" width="300" height="380" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true"></iframe>

<p>Alpinism and mountaineering books tend to often be of interest only to pursuers of these activities. But Barry manages to write his memoirs in such a compelling edge-of-your-seat style that also non-climbers will be eagerly turning each page to read how the stories unfold. And unfold they do. And if you haven’t heard of Barry before, that’s easily fixed: He is <em>one of North America’s top alpinists, noted for pushing the standards of highly technical, high-risk alpine climbing in the Canadian Rockies and the Himalayas.</em> But nobody is born an alpinist, even if it is their calling.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264859557" title="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15264859557_249539e96d_b.jpg" width="660" height="1024" alt="T. P. Friesen planting ice picks and crampons into the.exit bulge of the Andromeda Strain—ice that had never.been touched by man. Canadian Rockies. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p>In 20 chapters <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">The Calling</a> stops at important stations in Barry’s life, but does not take a linear approach. It’s more a Tarantino style, weaving stories together, jumping between different stations, different countries, different mountains, different climbing partners. It starts off with an Avalanche and only later on you learn more about how the four rope partners ended up in that situation on a high Himalaya peak. It’s followed two chapters on how Barry grew up and how he got into climbing (via the Canadian equivalent of the Boy Scouts), and that especially will be of interest to aspiring alpinists and climbers around the globe. From how he loaned books at the library on how to climb to saving up to buy his first climbing shoes, it shows that Barry is from a pre-Internet era where you couldn’t just order the latest gear and books online - but often head to search in shops across town to find what you wear looking for.</p>

<p>Really interesting are the personal stories and how Barry manages to illustrate his climbing partners: Kevin and Ward, Gregg and David, Mark and Phil and many more. If you climb, especially in the mountains, you know how important it is to be able to totally trust the person at the other end of the rope, and Barry is able to communicate that trust between climbing partners wonderfully. The story accompanies Barry and his partners as they learn to climb - from Trad at the Wasootch Slabs with Phil to alpine climbing the Calgary Route on Mt Yamnuska with Gray, all told in such a fun way that I couldn’t help but chuckle a few times. After a stop in Chamonix and taking Rebuffat’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1pECtyN">The Hundred Finest Routes</a> as a tick-list Barry travels a bit through Europe (and manages to lose his wallet and passport) before heading back to Canada and onwards to Yosemite. We see how Barry makes the decision to quit his salesman job to go more climbing and becoming a guide, all while repeating hard routes in Canada and the USA.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15448265551" title="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3929/15448265551_a50450ccbc_b.jpg" width="676" height="1024" alt="Barry leading the crux pitch of the Wild Thing on the northeast face of Mount Chephren. Twenty feet higher, Wally took over the belay from James Blench, and Barry took a thirty-foot leader fall coming to rest just opposite them. Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p>And as the walls and routes keep getting bigger &amp; more committing we accompany Barry to the Karakoram &amp; Himalaya, to Peru and the Cassin Ridge and read captivating accounts of daring alpine ascents. Always interweaved are anecdotes from his time - be it books (I got away with a whole list of books to read) to music (see above) to relationships and how climbing gear has evolved. The writing is lively &amp; outspoken and I often was laughing out loud, and it was able to keep me on reading until I finished the book in a week, often reading in my lunch breaks and late till night. It were the personal connections with his rope partners that I found very fascinating and that kept me on reading past bedtime, how they pushed themselves on to become better climbers, train together, climb together, party together and go on expeditions together, all while trying to figure out how to be able to get out more to the mountains. If you have a longing for the mountains but can’t be in them as much as you like (and don’t want to quit your job just yet for them), I can warmly recommend you this fine book for your mountain fix. It’s captivating style with adventures from near &amp; far will keep you entertained for many days, and after you’re done you’ll go through the book again - to search out some of the books Barry mentioned, look up a song and re-read about the daring ascents.</p>

<p>Get your paper or digital copy today from <a href="http://bit.ly/10ptnQO">Patagonia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1rTGvIH">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vDx8O1">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1nTA8oO">Amazon.de</a> or your local book store.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15264720600" title="The Calling Cover by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15264720600_920b3f8714_b.jpg" width="674" height="1024" alt="The Calling Cover" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Karwendel by Heinz Zak]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/karwendel-by-heinz-zak.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-22T16:36:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/karwendel-by-heinz-zak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.tyrolia.at/list?back=de0e51d6a2668c2896f6ca67e63d39c1&amp;xid=3626313">Karwendel</a> is a beautiful mountain range in the Alps between Munich and Innsbruck. In his book Heinz Zak shows his home mountains and its inhabitants in all seasons, and gives tips on hiking, mountaineering, climbing, canyoning and paddling. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14975984496" title="Karwendel by Heinz Zak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3908/14975984496_0f5a1d1a39_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Karwendel by Heinz Zak" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>750 km² large is the Karwendel and with that the largest nature park in Austria. It’s home to Chamois, Ibex, Eagles, and more, and also you can find the pretty Edelweiss and Gentian growing on the alpine pastures of this beautiful region. But not only nature is highlightesd in this book, also the people of this unique area are portrayed and the mountains themselves.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14812270409" title="Karwendel by Heinz Zak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5557/14812270409_1d674db674_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Karwendel by Heinz Zak" /></a></p>

<p>The over 200 photos in this 284 page thick coffee-table book will make you fall in love with the region and will have you plan your next holiday to this part of the Alps. The photos from all seasons are accompanied by stories and anecdotes of the author, but he also gives tips for your own ski-touring trips and hikes. Small stories with local people, from Mountainbikers to Mountaineers, loosen up the book and give other viewpoints on this range. </p>

<p>At close to 2 kg it’s not really a book you want to carry into the Karwendel (unless you’re training) but it makes a fine coffee-table book to read while you’re stuck at home. It’s a gorgeous book and <em>the</em> photo book about the Karwendel. You can get your copy from your local bookstore, <a href="http://www.tyrolia.at/list?back=de0e51d6a2668c2896f6ca67e63d39c1&amp;xid=3626313">Tyrolia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1llioS9">Amazon.de</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1tsdWRy">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1llixFb">Amazon.com</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canyons and Ice - The Wilderness Travels of Dick Griffith]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/canyons-and-ice-the-wilderness-travels-of-dick-griffith.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-01T14:53:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/canyons-and-ice-the-wilderness-travels-of-dick-griffith</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have to agree with Craig Medred: Many of today’s cardboard-cutout adventurers only dream of adventure. Dick Griffith, on the other hand, has traversed unexplored canyons in a packraft and has skied solo across thousands of kilometres of the Arctic. All of it without sponsors. All vividly documented in his journals. And now for you and me to read about in this fine book.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14614504160" title="Canyons and Ice by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3847/14614504160_d1e910e7b4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Canyons and Ice" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Canyons and Ice: The Wilderness Travels of Dick Griffith</strong> is written by Kaylene Johnson and is based on the journals Dick and his wife Isabelle have written on their trips, while several of their contemporaries &amp; their children also have contributed to the book. It is very captivating, written in the third person and contains 17 of his adventures. If you’re by now wondering who that Dick Griffith is: The pioneer of packrafting who has done the first descend of the Barranca del Cobre canyon in Mexico (without topographic maps!), a 17 times participant of the Alaska Wilderness Classic and a man who has walked &amp; skied over 6000 miles (that’s over 9.650 km) across the Canadian and Alaskan Arctic. All of it paid out of his own pocket and not looking for recognition. Inspiring stuff.</p>

<p>The first story in the book takes place in 1946 and we accompany a 19 year old Dick on a walk in Colorado along the White River, which started out on a home-made wooden raft that sunk on the first day. But already two years later we stand with Dick at the shore of the San Juan River and accompany him on a rafting trip down it. The following five chapters contain stories from various river exploits and we learn how packrafts got used for the first time on large rivers &amp; in tight canyons. We meet Dick’s wife Isabelle, encounter Tarahumara Indians and make a few first descents down deep canyons over hard wild water.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14614508550" title="Canyons and Ice by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3869/14614508550_c48854e64e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Canyons and Ice" /></a></p>

<p>After so much water the stories turn north and we accompany Dick on his first Arctic skiing expedition. On which he almost dies - lets say frostbite on your buttocks and legs is no fun. The photos documenting this mishap I will remember for a long time, as well as the lesson that you always should have a windproof pants on when venturing in the cold Arctic and there’s a stiff breeze blowing. After a few operations we accompany Dick on several more Arctic expeditions, where we encounter ice bears, rabid foxes, hospitable locals who can’t believe to encounter a white-haired man skiing alone through the frozen north. The photos are pre-digital and fit the stories very well and depict the people Dick met and travelled with, as well as the landscapes he travelled through.</p>

<p>The untamed wilderness is what drove Dick to explore. Being with his own thoughts. Recharging the batteries. Much of the same reasons many of us go out. If you’re in need for a book to keep you entertained - and you will be, it’s a gripping book that’s hard to put down - before your next trip, you should read this book. You can get it at <a href="http://amzn.to/1zCEVMS">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1zCF1US">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1zCFgix">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mont Blanc - The Finest Routes]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/07/mont-blanc-the-finest-routes.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-04T09:29:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/07/mont-blanc-the-finest-routes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Mont Blanc massive is a mountaineering paradise - once you arrive in Chamonix you will quickly realize that. But where to start? Which route should you definitely do? Philippe Batoux has written a modern version of the Rébuffat classic and helps you to find the finest routes to climb!</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2913/14590314533_473cc7c842_b.jpg#tl-541506463084838914;1043138249" class="alwaysThinglink" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Going to the Mont Blanc massive and planning to climb can be overwhelming. There’s just so many options and on busy days at least as much people! Philippe Batoux is a mountain guide, instructor at the <em>École nationale de ski et d’alpinisme</em> and has done all of the 100 tours in his book - many of which are fairly new and were only opened in the last years. But besides these new routes there’s also several classics in this book which makes it a worthy successor to the Gaston Rébuffat book <em>Les 100 plus belles</em>.</p>

<p>After a brief introduction the book has a short legend, explaining important points like time &amp; gear needed, difficulty ratings (with a useful comparison chart of UIAA, French, Australian, UK and US ratings) and maps before you dive into the 100 routes. These are varying in difficulty, from easy entry routes like the Pointes Lachenal traverse to the Voyage selon Gulliver on the Grand Capucin. The described routes vary between rock climbing, mixed, ice or all three. Each route is accompanied by a topo map and beautiful photos which capture your imagination and make you excited about the route. </p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2912/14383550730_1146425ae4_b.jpg#tl-541506463470714882;1043138249" class="alwaysThinglink" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<p>I got the book before I went to Chamonix last month and it was an inspiration. I looked up different routes, was talking with my friend which routes we should do and the superb photos made us eager to go to the Alps! And after the trip is before the trip and so I still skim through the book, read up on the routes and am pondering which ones to climb the next time I am in Chamonix =)</p>

<p>If you plan a trip to the Mont Blanc massive and don’t know where to start with narrowing down which tour to do, get this book. In my opinion it’s a required addition to an alpinist’s bookshelf and will lighten up the imagination for future routes to climb in the capital of alpine climbing. Get your copy at <a href="http://amzn.to/1q1QMPc">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1zcc3f8">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1t4GUcU">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alpine Climbing: Techniques to take you Higher]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/alpine-climbing-techniques-to-take-you-higher.html"/>
    <updated>2014-06-12T14:04:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/alpine-climbing-techniques-to-take-you-higher</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Living at the coast and loving to climb I sadly don’t get to go to the mountains that much. Practice makes an expert, but to build up the theoretical skills and knowledge I decided to get a book to help with the latter. <em>Alpine Climbing: Techniques to take you Higher</em> is a superb read which helps you to take the first steps in becoming an alpinist.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2909/14170822738_b5f5d6dfeb_b.jpg#tl-533237944639553538;1043138249" class="alwaysThinglink" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>As with other books about climbing, they’re there to read up on skills &amp; knowledge and help you to avoid making mistakes. However, the best way to learn is to be in the mountains - go with a Guide at the beginning, visit courses to build up the practical skills and take the first solo excursions on easy objectives.</em></p>

<p>Alpine Climbing: Techniques to take you Higher was the first book that popped up in Amazon search when looking for alpine climbing books. The authors, Mark Houston and Kathy Cosley are both certified UIAGM mountain guides, have been climbing on all big ranges of the world and have a lot of experience, which they share in this 330 page book. It’s not a book that you will read in one sitting and then pass on, but more likely it will sit on your bookshelf for a long time while you’re referring back to it to look something up. As a novice alpinist (if we don’t count the childhood ascents with mom. dad and siblings) I found the book a superb read, never boring and always informative.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5570/14357462545_c4dcb5b447_b.jpg#tl-533239189488009218;1043138249" class="alwaysThinglink" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<p>The book is divided in seven chapters and starts out with “The Making of an Alpinist”. After having established what an alpinist is, the authors move on to talk about The Alpine Environment, Preparation and Equipment and Routefinding and Navigation before giving loads of practical examples of how to belay on rock, snow and ice, help you plan a white-out strategy and give tips on glacier travel. Very enlightening I found the little stories of their experiences in the mountains which are interweaved into the text via grey boxes, these personal accounts make for amusing &amp; interesting reading.</p>

<p>Alpine Climbing is easy to read from cover to cover, however, with so much information in it there’s a lot to digest, so it will be a book which I will continue to refer to while I make excursions to the mountains - I’m just unlikely to remember it all from reading it just once. As it is well structured with a good index to look things up that won’t be a problem, either, and it’s nice and compact so it also fits well in my pack and can be taken along in a pinch. If you’re looking to take the next step with your hiking and climbing then Alpine Climbing: Techniques to take you Higher is a very good book to get you started. </p>

<p>You can get the book at your local book store or climbing shop and online at <a href="http://amzn.to/107Cz5P">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/SMPYmi">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1kOrdS0">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
