<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-31T23:57:28+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/bikepacking-on-the-wild-trails-of-britain.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/bikepacking-on-the-wild-trails-of-britain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html">Ireland</a> to Britain: Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain takes you &amp; your bike on the most beautiful multi-day rides in Wales, Scotland and England. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101282/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7252/27183101282_48e647f3ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Bikepacking is a big trend these days (check the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html">The Bikepacking Framebag Manufacturer List</a> to see how to transform your bike into a bikepacking rig) so it was a nice surprise as I was contacted by Wild Things Publishing and a question if they could use one of my photos in the book. Sure they could! As a wee thank you they sent me a copy of the book, and as I love alternative travel guide books <em>Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain</em> was right up my alley.</p>

<p>It is another beautiful book that will inspire you to pack up your bike and head to Britain in order to ride one (<em>or more!</em>) of the presented trips. From Epic Wilderness Rides over Family Rides to Technical &amp; Coastal Trails, the book presents 30 trips which range from a night to a week or riding in the countryside of Britain. The book starts off with an introduction to bikepacking and some history, some stories to get you in the mood, tips on gear - including a cool short chapter on tarps! - and how to plan a ride. In short: All you need to get on your bike and head out for a night or more in the wild. After the introduction it takes you on the different rides, which make up the majority of the book. These are sorted by regions in the UK - from the South East to the South West of England to the Midlands, Scotland and Wales. A map of the UK in the beginning highlights where these trips are to be found (good for planning) and a table on the next page gives  quick overview of relevant data about the rides - including distance, ascent and how many percent of the ride are off-road. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101142/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7326/27183101142_3113691725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I loved the very well designed info boxes which had all needed information ready with one look, a small map which gave a good idea of the ride (though you’ll need a real map for your adventure) and the beautiful photos. The trip descriptions are entertaining little trip reports in their own which will make you anticipate your own ride even more. All in all a unique book that is beautifully designed &amp; presented. If you’re into bikepacking and want to go to Britain for a wee adventure or more, this book is a recommended read!</p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://www.wildthingspublishing.com/product/bikepacking-book/">Wild Things Publishing</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i3Sr">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUYI3">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5hJmE">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Ireland's Wild Atlantic Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T22:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is the Wild Atlantic Way on your bucket list? Then you want to grab this travel guide to Ireland’s wild west coast!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183102302/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Cover"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7074/27183102302_ee6f87d84a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Cover" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last year I was lucky enough to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">explore Ireland</a>, hike the IAT and go sea stack climbing. What caught my interest and brought me to the Green Isle, however, was the Wild Atlantic Way: The world’s longest coastal touring route which goes from south to north along the west coast and is over 2.500 km long. There’s all kind of adventures to be had along the WAW, from visits in picturesque Irish villages and their pubs to bigger towns and their cultural offerings. However, <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</a> helps you find the off-the-beaten-track gems and takes you outdoors into the fresh, Irish air (and occasional rain shower!). </p>

<p>On 224 pages <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> takes you from the south in Kinsale to the far north of Malin Head along the coast. In seven chapters - divided by county - you can start to explore the Wild Atlantic Way. Do you fancy surfing, sea stack climbing and lots of remote wilderness? Then head to Donegal in the north. Do you prefer a cable car ride to an island, trying your luck fishing or going cycling? Then Cork in the south is a good place to start your adventures! Wherever you decide to go, <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> will have an insider tip ready for you. The seven county chapters are further divided into sections, each coming with their own little overview map to give you a feel of the land. Hundreds of gorgeous photos will get you in the mood to explore, while the detailed introduction chapter gives tips on when to come, what to bring and any other question you may have.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101542/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Inside"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7529/27183101542_ffe5d299bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Ireland is beautiful, and <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> helps you discover the green isle beyond the hustle and bustle of Dublin and the other big towns. Jam-packed with beautiful photos that inspire to visit the described places on Ireland’s west coast this book helps you plan your ultimate outdoor adventure itinerary. Three Rocks Books has created another stunning book which showcases some of the best scenery, sights and places in Ireland, and no matter if you plan to explore the Wild Atlantic Way on a roadtrip, by bike or public transportation, it will make sure you will see the true Wild Atlantic Way. <em>My tip: Book a flight to Ireland the same time you order this book!</em></p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Three Rocks Books</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/25pjt1d">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i48S">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUK3G">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yosemite in the Fifties]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/yosemite-in-the-fifties.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T20:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/yosemite-in-the-fifties</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Big walls, inspiring stories, epic climbing photos - that’s <a href="http://bit.ly/1RvKL98">Yosemite in the Fifties</a> in a nutshell.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101812/in/dateposted/" title="Yosemite in the Fifties Cover"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7095/27183101812_79dc07e245_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yosemite in the Fifties Cover" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>“Show me a climber who doesn’t know Yosemite and I show you someone who doesn’t climb.”</em> OK, I made that up, but there’s a hint of truth in that: Climbers from across the globe know the view down the valley on El Cap, heard about the epic Dawn Wall climb of Tommy Caldwell and Kevin Jorgeson in 2015, and just long to stand underneath the towering granite walls of El Capitain before also they will start to scale it. Yosemite in the Fifties transportes you back in time to the iron age of climbing history in the valley, when climbers where pushing the envelope of what had been thought possible and established the routes we still climb today.</p>

<p>The book is a collection of beautiful photos of the valley, the protagonists and their climbs, all taken with cameras that relied on the skill &amp; knowledge of the operator. In between these inspiring photos are four chapters with over a dozen essays. These essays are from original source material - first-person narratives and anecdotes of the climbers and their friends, interspersed with archive photos and shots of memorabilia from back in the day. Stories range from a history of climbing tools over portraits to historic climbing routes. With over 200 pages and twenty essays <em>Yosemite in the Fifties</em> is captivating for a long time and a book one can go back to time &amp; again to let the imagination wander off once more while looking at the old photos or reading one of the adventurous stories.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183102042/in/dateposted/" title="Yosemite in the Fifties Inside"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7301/27183102042_88924e20aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yosemite in the Fifties Inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Climbing in Yosemite is high on my bucket list so <em>Yosemite in the Fifties</em> is a book I enjoyed immensely. It’s a tasteful combination of visuals and stories, many written by John Long, one of climbing’s best writers. If climbing in Yosemite is something you also aspire to, I think you should pick up this beautiful coffee table book and immerse yourself into the history of the Iron Age of climbing in the valley. The stories and little anecdotes will surely be something that will make your wish to go to Yosemite even stronger, and once you’re standing on a ledge on El Cap Tower you will remember this book, it stories, and smile - because now you are there, and become part of its history! </p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1RvKL98">Patagonia</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/25pkA0R">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5ilsg">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUhP2">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laufen. Essen. Schlafen.]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/laufen-essen-schlafen.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-06T09:22:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/laufen-essen-schlafen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Planning on hiking the PCT, CDT or AT? Then you can’t get around not reading German Tourist’s book <em>“Laufen. Essen. Schlafen.”</em>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26846528165/in/dateposted/" title="Laufen. Essen. Schlafen."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7688/26846528165_87e238d3c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Laufen. Essen. Schlafen." /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I met <a href="http://www.christine-on-big-trip.blogspot.fi">Christine</a> two years ago as she was cycling through Finland, and we spent a nice afternoon eating cake and sushi in Vaasa. Of course I knew her much longer digitally, but it was really nice to finally met her and hear more about her stories from hiking, paddling and cycling around the globe. If you’re not so lucky to meet German Tourist (her Trailname) then you should pick up a copy of her book <em>Laufen. Essen. Schlafen.</em> which was published just a month ago. It’s in German, though, so I hope your Deutsch skills are up to scratch. The book chronicles GT’s decision from first hiking one long-distance trail in the US to all three and abandoning a <em>normal</em> 9-to-5 life. </p>

<p>The book starts out with Christine as a successful business women who is on holiday in the US, to losing her job and a good friend which in turn make her decide to go hiking the Pacific Crest Trail. The hiking story reminded me in parts of Keith’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1XbLlQl">The Last Englishman</a>, a book about Keith’s PCT hike. It’s a mix of trail description, <em>trail talk</em> (gossip) and Chrisitine’s experiences on the PCT. The PCT chapter is also the longest of the 288 page long book, with each subsequent chapter getting shorter. </p>

<p>The CDT chapter then starts again with Christine the successful business woman, a romance that’s doomed from the start, and the hard hiking life on the CDT. No rest days for three and a half months! During the CDT chapter German Tourist meets friends from the PCT again, loses her job while hiking the CDT and subsequently decides to quite the 9-to-5 rat race life. The AT chapter, which is a mere fifty something pages, then feels hurried. There’s the misery at the start, the realization that she does not need to hurry anymore, more meetings with old friends from the PCT and pretty autumn hiking through the green jungle. </p>

<p>I read the book in a day and overall found it an enjoyable read. There were a few sections that made me thoughtful, sad, laugh and anticipate what would happen next. The book is entertaining, but I felt that in the CDT and AT chapter Christine was just in a hurry to finish the book and get outdoors again - I would have wished for similar insights &amp; details from her about these two trails, too. Despite this I think it is a great read for anyone who is interested in hiking and long-distance backpacking, as Christine writes eloquently about the life on the trail and what it entails. The sections about her conversations with fellow thru-hikers and trail angels where my favourites by far, and made me want to pack my backpack and fly over to the USA! Get your copy from <a href="https://www.piper.de/buecher/laufen-essen-schlafen-isbn-978-3-89029-471-1">Piper</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1rwC7BW">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1rwCgp9">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Off The Road]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/off-the-road.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-08T23:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/off-the-road</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You like to go outdoors and love a tricked out van or off-road vehicle to get there? Then <em>Off the Road</em> is the book for you - but careful, you might want to sell your house and move into a van!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26210796662/in/dateposted/" title="Off the Road Cover"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1665/26210796662_6361a93f26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Off the Road Cover" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I don’t have a driving license. We don’t own a car. And yet I like the idea of living in a van or tricked-out off-road vehicle. Hence <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/off-the-road.html">Off the Road</a> is such an appealing book. On over 250 pages and even more photos you get inspiration for your own #VanLife. Are you an BMW Enduro kind of guy, or an VW T4 aficionado? Does your heart beat for adventure off the beaten track in a Toyota Land Cruiser or do you prefer to have an adventure-ready trailer behind your car? This book illuminates people from all these roads &amp; more, with inspiring stories of people who rode from the most southern point in Florida to the most northerly point in Alaska or who crossed Russia from the west to the east. </p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/144480827?byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>But it has not only such adventurous expeditions in it, also more achievable #VanLife stories are in the book - things you can realize at the weekend or during your summer holidays. Like going to the beach with your trailer for a lonely weekend at the sea, or taking your van with the surfboards on top for a trip to search the best waves. There’s a bunch of vans, cars, trailers, motorcycles and off-road vehicle depicted in the book, complete with technical information and how to make them even more off-road worthy for your next big (or small) trip. Inspiration for how to renovate the interior of your van, why an Unimog still is one of the greatest All-terrain vehicles, and how you can transform your van into a mobile office which allows you from anywhere. </p>

<p>And the appeal also comes through to me, who is generally opposed to motorized outdoor activities. I could imagine trading the house for a small van, drive around the world and have a new view to wake up to each morning. Where I can sit in front of the car and drink a coffee, sit by the camp fire and watch the stars before going laying down on a comfortable bed, and which would allow me to just put on the skis in the morning and skin up a mountain. Of course I’d first need to get a driving license to do that =) But if you have one, and it sounds like a good life to you, pick up this book and be inspired by what is possible. Great photos and stories most likely will make you think if you really need a house, or if a nice off-road vehicle or van wouldn’t suffice for a life off the road!</p>

<p>You can support me and buy this book at one of the following affiliate links - at no extra costs for you. <a href="http://amzn.to/1qbfFgW">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1S6UkSB">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1S6WEZL">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26210796292/in/dateposted/" title="Off the Road Inside"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1708/26210796292_ac7aee5ac8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Off the Road Inside" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Gestalten sent me the book for review. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
