<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-03T15:07:20+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Karwendel by Heinz Zak]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/karwendel-by-heinz-zak.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-22T16:36:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/08/karwendel-by-heinz-zak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.tyrolia.at/list?back=de0e51d6a2668c2896f6ca67e63d39c1&amp;xid=3626313">Karwendel</a> is a beautiful mountain range in the Alps between Munich and Innsbruck. In his book Heinz Zak shows his home mountains and its inhabitants in all seasons, and gives tips on hiking, mountaineering, climbing, canyoning and paddling. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14975984496" title="Karwendel by Heinz Zak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3908/14975984496_0f5a1d1a39_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Karwendel by Heinz Zak" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>750 km² large is the Karwendel and with that the largest nature park in Austria. It’s home to Chamois, Ibex, Eagles, and more, and also you can find the pretty Edelweiss and Gentian growing on the alpine pastures of this beautiful region. But not only nature is highlightesd in this book, also the people of this unique area are portrayed and the mountains themselves.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14812270409" title="Karwendel by Heinz Zak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5557/14812270409_1d674db674_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Karwendel by Heinz Zak" /></a></p>

<p>The over 200 photos in this 284 page thick coffee-table book will make you fall in love with the region and will have you plan your next holiday to this part of the Alps. The photos from all seasons are accompanied by stories and anecdotes of the author, but he also gives tips for your own ski-touring trips and hikes. Small stories with local people, from Mountainbikers to Mountaineers, loosen up the book and give other viewpoints on this range. </p>

<p>At close to 2 kg it’s not really a book you want to carry into the Karwendel (unless you’re training) but it makes a fine coffee-table book to read while you’re stuck at home. It’s a gorgeous book and <em>the</em> photo book about the Karwendel. You can get your copy from your local bookstore, <a href="http://www.tyrolia.at/list?back=de0e51d6a2668c2896f6ca67e63d39c1&amp;xid=3626313">Tyrolia</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1llioS9">Amazon.de</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1tsdWRy">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1llixFb">Amazon.com</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gimme Kraft!]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft.html"/>
    <updated>2014-06-10T10:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/gimme-kraft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lacking <em>Kraft</em> to do your project or carry your UH pack? Then <a href="http://gimmekraft.com/">Gimme Kraft</a> is the book that helps you develop the power you need to send your next problem.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3890/14385371581_1329c62e2d_b.jpg#tl-532816872920317954;1043138249" class="alwaysThinglink" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Kraft, die [kraft]: Vermögen, Fähigkeit zu wirken; [körperliche oder geistige] Stärke</em> / <em>Kraft is German for power, force, strength</em></p>

<p><strong>It’s not about power, it’s about technique</strong> was my bouldering teachers opening line to our group of eager students. And seeing him - a thin and tall guy - climb several rounds upside down in our boulder cave, it’s easy to agree. We went on to learn proper boulder technique, first indoors, then took it to the rocks of Vaasa. But of course some Kraft does help, especially if you already have a good technique. However, Kraft does not magically appear from going climbing - that much I have learned in the three odd years since I have rekindled my passion for the art. Kraft comes from training. Being dedicated in developing a training routine, sticking to it and mixing it up as needed, that’s what this fine book from one of Germany’s best climbing gyms, <a href="http://cafekraft.de/">Café Kraft</a> helps you do. </p>

<p>When you pick up the book you realize that here people were writing who know what they’re talking about. The authors have worked with athletes like Alex Megos, Mayan Smith-Gobat, Stefan Glowacz, Sasha DiGiulian and many more, and have sat down to write this fine training book. It’s bi-lingual in English and Deutsch and comes with a DVD where the exercises can be viewed, as well as extra footage of Wolfgang Güllich training. The book starts out with an introduction to effective climbing training - you get a password to download the full 16 page introduction pdf online - and then sets out with dozens of exercises. The exercises are divided into different categories, like the Bouldering Wall, Pull-Ups, Rings, Floor &amp; Minibars, amongst others.</p>

<p><img style="max-width:100%" src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2908/14202091729_e331c948dd_b.jpg#tl-532816872635105282;1043138249" class="alwaysThinglink" /><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//cdn.thinglink.me/jse/embed.js"></script></p>

<p>This really being the first time I set out to train (apart from many years of Kenjutsu) I adhered to the books tips to do most of my training as climbing. In the Bouldering Wall chapter there’s several good exercises which not just train you, but also help you to improve your technique. At home I do the floor exercises and train on the two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/metolius-rock-rings-3d-trainingsgriffe/">Metolius Rock Rings</a>, though I will need to switch the exercises up soon (the book recommends you change up your training routine at the latest every six weeks as otherwise you’re stagnating). I definitely have seen an increase in power, stamina and also feel like I climb better since I started to work out, and as the book is small and light I also usually carry it along to the boulders to see if there’s a new exercise I could try. </p>

<p>One critic I have about the book it’s that they put the video instructions on a DVD. Living in a household without TV (and DVD Player) and also all our computers being without DVD Drives, I have no opportunity to watch the videos. I’d rather would have seen the videos being available online to stream or download, which makes a lot more sense than a DVD. </p>

<p>Other than that this book really is great, and not just for climbers - though they obviously will benefit the most from reading it and doing the exercises. If you’d like to get more Kraft, get this book, make a personal training plan, stick to it, and see how your climbing and power will improve. Then take it out to the rocks and send your project!</p>

<p>You can order the book online at <a href="http://cafekraft.de/laden/produkte/GK">Café Kraft</a> and <a href="http://shop.boulderkeskus.com/fi/kauppa/muut/kirjallisuus/gimmekraft.html">Boulderkeskus</a> and with some luck buy it at your local climbing gym. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outsiders]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/04/the-outsiders.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-25T13:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/04/the-outsiders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Going <em>Outdoors</em> is a big trend right now. So Gestalten Verlag went outdoors to meet <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/outsiders.html">The Outsiders</a>, a group of successful outdoor and lifestyle entrepreneurs, bloggers, writers, hikers, surfers, skiers - in short: People who love to be outside. The result is a book which portrays in a gorgeous way the growing outdoor trend - from hiking over cycling to paddling &amp; surfing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13981714206" title="The Outsiders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/13981714206_6177d493ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Outsiders" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There come quite a few coffee <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">books</a> across my desk, but The Outsiders was different. While many have captivating photos, I felt that each page of the The Outsiders was crafted with love &amp; attention to detail. Everything fits: Beautiful fonts, captivating photos, interesting interviews, short bios of outdoor folks and highlighting some cool products. Did I mention the inspiring photos? Oh. OK. Good.</p>

<p>What I liked a lot about the 272 page thick book was that there were a lot of familiar names and faces featured in it. There was Cass from <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/blog">While Out Riding</a> and Joe from <a href="http://joecruz.wordpress.com/">Pedaling in Place</a>, <a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/">Wanderlust Equipment</a> gear and <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> was seen on a few pages, and a couple more people &amp; brands that you have heard about if you’re interested in the outdoor scene. Overall there was a very good balance of the known &amp; trendy and the unknown and cool in all categories.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14024833953" title="The Outsiders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2898/14024833953_cdffce8fbd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Outsiders" /></a></p>

<p>There’s six “chapters” in the book: Hiking, Surfing, Cycling, On The Road, Snow and Water. All that comes after an Intro from Jeffrey Bowman, one of the authors of the book, and Erling Kagge, the first human to reach the South Pole, North Pole and stand on the summit of Mt. Everest. Add in interviews with Vincent Stanley from Patagonia, the Hoepner brothers who cycled from Berlin to Shanghai, designer Geoff McFetridge, amongst others, and you will have a hard time to put this book down. And even after you have read it back-to-back you will pick it up again, browse through the different sections to be inspired, or look up one of the cool kit pieces or blogs on the internet. And then you’ll want to go outside.</p>

<p>It’s a beautiful book for rainy days at home. You can get it directly from <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/outsiders.html">Gestalten</a> or order it from your favourite taste of Amazon: <a href="http://amzn.to/1faj21y">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1ikFiQV">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1rralzY">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Justin Lichter: Trail Tested]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/justin-lichter-trail-tested.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T15:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/justin-lichter-trail-tested</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you looking for a book which helps you choose trail tested gear and has a gear list for any occasion? Then Trail Tested by Justin Lichter is for you!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7801519412" title="Trail Tested: A Thru-Hiker&#x27;s Insights Into Hiking and Backpacking by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8431/7801519412_3ea1547a14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Trail Tested: A Thru-Hiker&#x27;s Insights Into Hiking and Backpacking" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://www.justinlichter.com/sample-page/shop/trail-tested-revised-ed/">Trail Tested: A Thru-Hiker’s Insights Into Hiking and Backpacking</a> is a useful book for every backpacker who has set his sights on thru-hiking a long-distance trail - although also hikers and backpackers who go out for only “short” trips will benefit from the accumulated experience of the author. Justin has hiked over 35.000 miles - he is a Triple Crowner, has hiked in Nepal, Africa, and many other countries, and over the duration of that time in the outdoors he has learned a lot, and helps us to not make some costly mistakes.</p>

<p>The book has three distinct sections: </p>

<ul>
  <li><em>For Starters</em>, which looks at gear</li>
  <li><em>Getting The Grove</em>, which gives useful tips for the trail</li>
  <li><em>Stepping It Up</em>, which gives advanced tips</li>
</ul>

<p>All three sections will help you to make smart decisions - first at home and at the gear shop, then on the trail. Justin is a lightweight backpacking proponent and lists several reasons to go for lightweight gear - and if someone who puts thousands of kilometers on a shelter, sleeping bag and backpack thinks it’s durable &amp; smart, be ensured that it is! He runs you through the details when choosing the Big Three, gives tips on footwear and socks, stoves, clothes and everything else. Always along are small anecdotes and tips, which highlight the item in question. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7880235432" title="Trail Tested by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8429/7880235432_bdfdfca6ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Trail Tested" /></a></p>

<p>After the gear is sorted, Justin takes us out on the trail, and again small anecdotes and tips give insightful advice on the topic. As Justin often hikes with his dog, there’s several pages of useful infos on taking your best friend into the outdoors, choosing a backpack for him, and how to ensure he stays healthy and fit. If you’re planning to hike abroad, especially in less developed countries, he has some useful tips on making it a beautiful trip, and also if you’re setting out to thru-hike a long trail the book has a few good tips for you. </p>

<p>This book might feel like it is aimed at hiking and backpacking beginners, but even seasoned backpackers will find a few nuggets of wisdom and tips in it. Every page is accompanied by beautiful photos from across the globe which alone will make you want to hit the trail, and with the extensive knowledge dispersed over 217 pages this book really is for everyone who likes to spend time hiking &amp; backpacking in the outdoors.</p>

<p>Get the book <a href="http://www.justinlichter.com/sample-page/shop/trail-tested-revised-ed/">directly from the author</a> (autographed versions available!) or from <a href="http://amzn.to/1g72bpY">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1dzHM26">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1g72jWz">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rock The Shack]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/rock-the-shack.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T07:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/03/rock-the-shack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Want to leave the city behind? Then <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/rock-the-shack.html">Rock the Shack</a> will give you the inspiration you need to build your own beautiful cabin in the mountains, by the sea or in the forest!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13290864674/" title="Rock The Shack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7315/13290864674_6172e5b767_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock The Shack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Most of us outdoor folks dream about a cabin in the middle of nowhere. A place where we can go for a walk right from the door sill. Where the only noise is the wind blowing through the trees and the birds singing. Where you chop wood to fire your stove. A sauna by the lake. Wide views across mountains and forests.</p>

<p><a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/rock-the-shack.html">Rock The Shack</a> is a dangerous book for those who long to be closer to nature, living in their own cabin. Showcasing on 240 pages <em>“shacks”</em>, which range from self-sufficient sheds in the hills to luxurious hide-outs at the coast. There are wooden constructions, packed clay huts to combinations of brick, steel and glass. The forms range from organic leaf-like structures and cocoons to rather futuristic expressions of a shed. </p>

<p>The book takes you on a journey across the globe and shows the most inspiring cabins, from Japan over Chile and the USA to Sweden, Finland and Norway. As diverse the locations and cabins are, so similar are they in what they portrait: A place for people to be away from the city and in nature. A place where you can relax, meditate, be with your family and friends or just by yourself. Where the next hike, climb or swim is just a few steps away.</p>

<p>Not just architects and designers will find this book superb, also outdoor folks that are looking for ideas for their own shed. It has given me plenty of ideas for our garden shed, and further inflamed the desire to have a cabin out in the forest by a lake. It’s a beautiful book that helps you dream of your own little space, and is perfect to escape to when you need to relax for a few moments. Have it next to you on your work desk for those long office days. It definitely will be a conversation starter, but I’m not sure if it will get you a raise - although, who knows, maybe your boss dreams about a shed in the mountains, too?</p>

<p>You can <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/rock-the-shack.html">order it directly from Gestalten</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/OF8fzT">Amazon.de</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/1duc68Y">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13290862584/" title="Rock The Shack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3828/13290862584_fe094d8f1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rock The Shack" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
