<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gear of the Year | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gear-of-the-year/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-09T13:57:49+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear of the Year 2016: DPS Wailer Tour1 Skis]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/gear-of-the-year-dps-wailer-tour1-skis.html"/>
    <updated>2016-10-31T23:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/gear-of-the-year-dps-wailer-tour1-skis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Winter is coming</em>. And that means I’ll again step into the bindings of my DPS Wailer Tour1 Skis, skin up a fine mountain, put down my heel and flow through the pow!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148754403/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="At the summit"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/2/1681/26148754403_5dff0ce1e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the summit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Picking my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gear-of-the-year/">Gear of the Year</a> isn’t easy: There’s a lot of equipment that comes over my table (happily a lot <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/01/zero-gear-year.html">less this year</a>) and while that alone isn’t what makes it hard, it’s those favourites which I have used for many years which make it difficult, as these favourites are always strong contenders for my Gear of the Year Award. But while I really love my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a> it is my <a href="http://www.dpsskis.com/en/skis/browse-skis-by-shape/all-mountain-mixed-snow/wailer-430.html">DPS Wailer Tour1 Skis</a> which I chose this year, because of two reasons: 1. They allow me to be more in the mountains and 2. They’re some of the lightest ski-touring skis on the market. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25738443973/in/album-72157664672954972/" title="Tools of joy!"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/2/1598/25738443973_d7b1af966a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tools of joy!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>These skis (as well as the <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/g3-ion-12-tourenbindung-16-17/?pid=81">bindings</a>, <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/contour-hybrid-free-split-skins-skifell-s/?pid=81">skins</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/la-sportiva-spectre.html">boots</a>) have accompanied me to Canada, South Tyrol, Austria, Finnish Lapland, Switzerland and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/lyngen.html">Norway</a> and I have stood almost 30 days on them. Thirty days in the wintery mountains, that’s pretty sweet in my book. Simply because in my book a day spent in the mountains is a day well spent. And if I can be active, skin up a mountain with good friends, smile together at the summit and then put down my heel to carve a fine line into the fresh powder, well, I can imagine few things which would be better in winter &amp; which make me so happy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25105375706/in/album-72157664672954972/" title="I like crust, but I only like it on Crème brûlée"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1676/25105375706_0f539523c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I like crust, but I only like it on Crème brûlée" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I was skiing with my brother in South Tyrol and we went on a ski-tour while it was dumping snow. We were the only ones out that day, and as we reached that cabin down there, sat down in it and drunk some hot tea, we didn’t care that the summit would be some other 20 minutes of skining further up the mountain. We sat there, sweaty, smiling, munching a chocolate bar, and looking forward to ski down through that fresh powder. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24460363514/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="I love me a nice cabin!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1466/24460363514_7edaab5590_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I love me a nice cabin!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I Switzerland Anselm, Willi and me wanted to complete the <a href="http://www.hauteroute-graubuenden.ch">Graubünden Haute Route</a> but conditions conspired against us. While this winter wasn’t particularly good the week we were in Switzerland the Avalanche Danger was so high that we weren’t able to do the complete Haute Route. That didn’t hinder us from having a grand time in the Swiss Mountains, staying with some fantastic hut wardens, skiing some great lines and feeling happy while standing on our skis. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26436513541/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Boot-packing up"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/2/1490/26436513541_8e1264ac4b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Boot-packing up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/2eUHSEx">DPS Wailer Tour1 Skis</a> are award winning skis which are Made in Utah, USA. They’re ultralight at 1.410 g per ski and 184 cm length, which is great when you’re having days with lots of ascent - the low weight is very energy saving. You’ll float through powder with a smile on your face and will be happy on spring crust - through stay off-piste as that’s the one thing they don’t really like (and weren’t made for). But powder, well, you’ll surf through it, make ace turns and throw up some cold smoke that you wish will never end. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25816133670/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Backcountry fun on Jyppyrä, Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1675/25816133670_564e5094cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Backcountry fun on Jyppyrä, Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So, that possibility - to surf through a meter of fresh snow and then skin back up to take a 2nd run - that’s why I love my <strong>DPS Wailer Tour1 Skis</strong> and that’s why they are my <strong>Gear of the Year</strong>. I’m sure they will allow me to collect a lot more of fine winter mountain skiing memories, and for that I am grateful. </p>

<p>If you want to experience the mountains in winter and float through the powder, buy a pair at <a href="http://bit.ly/2fnPt2K">evo</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2eUHSEx">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2f645Qd">REI</a> or <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/dps-wailer-106-tour1-tourenski-16-17-168cm/?pid=81">Bergzeit</a>.</p>

<script src="http://hikinginfinland.com//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-pricecompare.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1371" type="text/javascript" id="outtrapricecomparewdgt" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapcwdgt="1371"></script>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26458154986/in/album-72157666711089840/" title="Packing for a ski-tour"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1512/26458154986_a0a9acf22a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packing for a ski-tour" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The skis were sent to me for free and DPS asked me to have fun with them. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear of the Year 2015: Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html"/>
    <updated>2015-10-19T23:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is reasonably light, connects to any of my backpacks and is the #1 tool I have along on every trip? It’s the Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip - my Gear of the Year 2015.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22265356552/in/photostream/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/740/22265356552_51b9767b0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I own a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> since over two years and it has been on every trip I have been on in that time, from day packrafting in the Kvarken Archipelago over mountaineering in Chamonix to backpacking in Bosnia and Herzegovina - the Capture PRO has seen it all. When I pack my backpack for a trip, attaching the camera clip to my left shoulder strap is always the first thing I do, and it does not matter if that’s a big <a href="http://bit.ly/1W1xPjI">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Porter</a> or a small <a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/packs/packsack-plus/">LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack Plus</a>, the clip fits on any shoulder strap and allows me to have my camera always at the ready. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22089327210/in/photostream/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/733/22089327210_8b0d8808d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/capturepro/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Capture PRO</a> Clip weighs 113 g and the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/microplate?acc=97">Micro Plate</a> weighs 21 g and is a perfect match for any of my smaller cameras, from the compact &amp; ultralight <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html">Sony RX 100 III</a> to the slightly bigger Olympus OM-D E-M5. For even bigger cameras I use the standard ARCAplate Quick Release Plate which tips the scales at a reasonable 29 g and which works great with e.g. the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Sony A7R</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963271736/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2847/11963271736_fa16b81885_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the trail, in the city and at trade fairs like the OutDoor and ISPO alike my Capture PRO always arouses the interest of fellow outdoor enthusiasts who look for a better way to carry their camera. After two plus years of use &amp; dozens of long trips for me it is clear: It’s the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/capturepro/?acc=97">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a>. Because being able to have my camera in my hand in a second or two to not miss a photo opportunity is very important - it can be the difference between a good photo and an outstanding photo. If you’re a photography professional or a hobby enthusiast - give this system a try, there is no better way to carry your camera always at the ready. And that’s why I chose the Capture PRO Camera Clip from Peak Design to be my Gear of the Year 2015!</p>

<p><strong>Get 10% off your Peak Design Order!</strong> I partnered with Peak Design and am happy to offer you 10% off their products. Simply enter the <strong>Coupon Code “hikingfin”</strong> at checkout and you get ten percent off your order!</p>

<p><em>For more thoughts and information on it, please read my detailed <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Capture PRO Camera Clip Review</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
