<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gear of the Year | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gear-of-the-year/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-09T22:21:09+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear of the Year 2015: Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html"/>
    <updated>2015-10-19T23:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is reasonably light, connects to any of my backpacks and is the #1 tool I have along on every trip? It’s the Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip - my Gear of the Year 2015.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22265356552/in/photostream/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/740/22265356552_51b9767b0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I own a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> since over two years and it has been on every trip I have been on in that time, from day packrafting in the Kvarken Archipelago over mountaineering in Chamonix to backpacking in Bosnia and Herzegovina - the Capture PRO has seen it all. When I pack my backpack for a trip, attaching the camera clip to my left shoulder strap is always the first thing I do, and it does not matter if that’s a big <a href="http://bit.ly/1W1xPjI">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Porter</a> or a small <a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/packs/packsack-plus/">LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack Plus</a>, the clip fits on any shoulder strap and allows me to have my camera always at the ready. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22089327210/in/photostream/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/733/22089327210_8b0d8808d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/capturepro/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Capture PRO</a> Clip weighs 113 g and the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/microplate?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Micro Plate</a> weighs 21 g and is a perfect match for any of my smaller cameras, from the compact &amp; ultralight <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html">Sony RX 100 III</a> to the slightly bigger Olympus OM-D E-M5. For even bigger cameras I use the standard ARCAplate Quick Release Plate which tips the scales at a reasonable 29 g and which works great with e.g. the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Sony A7R</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963271736/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2847/11963271736_fa16b81885_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the trail, in the city and at trade fairs like the OutDoor and ISPO alike my Capture PRO always arouses the interest of fellow outdoor enthusiasts who look for a better way to carry their camera. After two plus years of use &amp; dozens of long trips for me it is clear: It’s the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/capturepro/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a>. Because being able to have my camera in my hand in a second or two to not miss a photo opportunity is very important - it can be the difference between a good photo and an outstanding photo. If you’re a photography professional or a hobby enthusiast - give this system a try, there is no better way to carry your camera always at the ready. And that’s why I chose the Capture PRO Camera Clip from Peak Design to be my Gear of the Year 2015!</p>

<p><strong>Get 10% off your Peak Design Order!</strong> I partnered with Peak Design and am happy to offer you 10% off their products. Simply enter the <strong>Coupon Code “hikeinfin”</strong> at checkout and you get ten percent off your order!</p>

<p><em>For more thoughts and information on it, please read my detailed <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Capture PRO Camera Clip Review</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
