<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: backpacking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/backpacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-08T11:44:45+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Gear from the Cottages 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T22:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What new gear can you expect to see from the ultralight cottages in 2015? We have talked with our sources and deliver you the lightest and finest new gear for 2015!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16240736587" title="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7455/16240736587_ee1a0957b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="685" alt="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Remember your roots,</strong> they say. Our roots are in ultralight backpacking. We have spread the gospel about ultralight backpacking since a long time, have <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/interviews/">interviewed cottage manufacturers</a> and used a lot of ultralight kit on our hikes and treks. And even when I nowadays am attending the big outdoor trade fairs like <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/ispo-news-2014.html">ISPO</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor</a>, it’s the new gear from the cottages that I am most excited about. And so <a href="http://hrxxlight.com">Benjamin</a> and me again set out to ask Cottage Manufacturers about the new gear they have been developing, prototyping and testing in the last months and are now ready to release to you. So here we are, and we wish you a lot of fun checking out the <strong>New Gear from the Cottages 2015</strong>!</p>

<p><em>You have a cottage and should be on this list with your new gear? <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Email me</a> and I’ll add you!</em> </p>

<h2 id="locus-gear">Locus Gear</h2>

<p>Jotaro and the team at <a href="http://locusgear.com">Locus Gear</a> have been dreaming big. Big in two ways: A ultralight, breathable dome tent for the winter mountains and a massive 8 Person shelter. The Djedi eVent Dome Shelter sleeps 2 persons, is 2,3 m long and 1,3 m wide with a height of 1 m and will tip the scales at 1,2 kg with the poles included. It looks like a spacious mountain shelter and being made from eVent you know it will be breathable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425702462" title="Locus Gear Djedi eVent Dome by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7321/16425702462_abcb9f94df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Locus Gear Djedi eVent Dome" /></a></p>

<p>I dubbed it the “Party Tent” as I saw the Prototype Photos on the Locus Gear Instagram stream and I still think that the Soris Sil Shelter could be that. Or a great group tent for scouts, a family with kids, or a a handful of hiking buddies. It can sleep six to eight persons and is pitched with two poles - and it is huge: 6 m long, 3 m wide and 1,8 m high. But it only weighs in at 1,7 kg (without poles, stakes and extra guylines) which, if broken down on the number of people it can sleep, is very light (283 g per person if there’s six in it!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239236370" title="Locus Gear Soris Sil Shelter 149 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7458/16239236370_73bae29845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Soris Sil Shelter 149" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hanchor">Hanchor</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.hanchor.com/">Hanchor</a> releases two new backpacks in 2015 which are currently in the prototyping stage. The Marble is a 65 l roll-top closure pack that will weigh around 918 g (or 1032 g with aluminum stays). Made from XPac vx07 it has a backpanel that allows for some ventilation. Horizontal seams of the Marble are folded to the upper side to make it more waterproof though they are not seam taped, while the seam between bottom panel and the body are seam taped with wide webbing from the outside to prevent water coming in. It can carry a lot of gear, too: It has one large Kangaroo pocket, 2 side pockets, 2 hip pockets and 2 daisy chains for attaching shock cord, accessories and gear. The two aluminum stays are removable, as is the padded hip belt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15804131964" title="Hanchor Marble by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8651/15804131964_ca206f9d87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hanchor Marble" /></a></p>

<p>The Chert on the other hand is a 51 l pack that will be made from XPac wx20 and has a removable frame pad and stays which will weigh in at 847 g or 961 g with the aluminum stays. It also comes with a lot of features: A roll top closure, 2 daisy chains for shock cord, accessories and gear, 2 removable aluminum stays, a removable, padded hip belt, 4 gear loops and straps and buckles for attaching ice axes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238994458" title="Hanchor Chert by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/16238994458_9a3d5dfa5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hanchor Chert" /></a></p>

<p>The guys at Hanchor are also working on a new version of their patents-pending, built-in chock sock chalk bag. The opening of the built in chalk sock is constructed with a circular plastic ring that makes it super easy to fill in the chalk and the amount of chalk coming out is enhanced. If you can’t wait for it to come out, have a look at their <a href="http://www.hanchor.com/products/SUL%20Series/Steam_drawstring_backpack?locale=en">STEAM Cuben drawstring pack</a> which came out last December.</p>

<h2 id="porcelain-rocket">Porcelain Rocket</h2>

<p>The big news from <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com">Porcelain Rocket</a> is that they just opened a Workshop in the USA which will be manufacturing their most popular items in the most popular colours, decreasing lead times and making shipping within the States easier. There’s still the option for the custom gear you can dream up, with the usual lead times =)</p>

<p>New this years is the MCA Handlebar System which replaces the PR Mission Control as their sole handlebar offering. It is easier to use, accepts any commercial drybag in the 5 - 15 l range, is lighter and works with drop bars. It consists of a simple series of nylon webbing straps mounted to a rubberized fabric plate which will keep everything organized and tidy. The drybag loads hassle-free from the front and comes with the accessory pouch which is easy to attach &amp; detach. The whole set sans drybag weighs in at 284 g and is made from 500D Cordura and now available.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/53243955@N05/16327109566" title="Porcelain Rocket &quot;MCA&quot; by Sim Works, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7287/16327109566_29bd105424_b.jpg" width="900" height="900" alt="Porcelain Rocket &quot;MCA&quot;" /></a>
© Sim Works, used with Permission</p>

<p>You might have seen the custom-made PR Panniers in the past, which where probably what has led to the development of the Micro Panniers. They’re intended as an auxiliary to the other gear systems for more volume on longer tours and allow you to get rid of your Ortlieb panniers and invest into a pair of these. They attach to most popular racks on the market including fatbike-specific racks, and are made from 500D &amp; 1000D Cordura with a weight of 340 g per pannier. You don’t need to wait to get these, either, as they’re available now and cost $250 CAD for a set of two.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/53243955@N05/16350764831" title="Porcelain Rocket &quot;Micro Panniers&quot; by Sim Works, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7349/16350764831_46d48677a9_b.jpg" width="900" height="900" alt="Porcelain Rocket &quot;Micro Panniers&quot;" /></a>
© Sim Works, used with Permission</p>

<h2 id="mountain-laurel-designs">Mountain Laurel Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> has updated the Burn, Prophet, Exodus and Ark. They now come with hybrid solid/ mesh outside pockets which was done after research on the areas where mesh pockets wear or snag in brush - those parts are now solid Dyneema X. Also the side pocket’s front edges are solid and the bottom of the large rear pocket is solid, while the large mesh holes allows faster drying times. The 2015 packs also come with improved hardware and webbing: The 10 mm and 15 mm buckles MLD now uses are twice as strong as the 25/ 30 mm buckles of the past and the narrower webbing is a lot lighter without being thin and fragile. </p>

<p>MLD continues to uses their tried &amp; tested Dyneema X fabric, which has the highest strength and is much better than the weaker Robic fabric and regular ripstop nylons that some other manufacturers use. The reason for cheaper fabrics like Robic is obvious: It’s just $3 a yard - versus $25 a yard for DXG! I imagine you’re a gear freak if your following this blog, so you’ll appreciate this little nugget Ron shared: </p>

<p><em>Interestingly, the white Dyneema ripstop threads that makes the Dyneema X so recognizable and known for the highest quality has lead to some pack makers now using regular nylon woven with a plain white nylon thread ripstop pattern (no Dyneema in the weave at all) to look like it is Dyneema X ripstop!</em></p>

<p>So the next time you’re shopping for a pack, make sure to read the material descriptions well! Right, onwards to the new gear.  MLD has replaced the Newt with a small and ultra clean and simple pack code named Core, and all backpacks will be available in the new Wasabi Green and the signature MLD Stealth Gray colours, with a shipping date of Mid-February.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426661665" title="MLD Corepack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7400/16426661665_d61f16733b_b.jpg" width="720" height="918" alt="MLD Corepack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806623933" title="MLD Wasabi Exodus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/15806623933_065e5e7684_b.jpg" width="720" height="907" alt="MLD Wasabi Exodus" /></a></p>

<p>Also coming from MLD in 2015 is an Apex Balaclavas in three sizes, <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?products_id=222">Cuben Packing Cubes</a> for the lightweight traveller and Size Small eVENT Rain Mitts, while all 2015 Mids now use the stronger 10 mm buckles &amp; the SuperLight bivys use the new Mountain 10d fabric and nicer nickel zip pulls. The Superlight Bivy Duo is already available and additional sizes of the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=47&amp;products_id=127">PyraMid InnerNets</a> are on the website.</p>

<h2 id="nature-base">Nature-Base</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.naturebase.de/">Nature-Base</a> from Germany has several products on offer which are interesting for the ultralight winter backpacker. Their <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/pulka">Folding Pulka</a> has been improved and now can be ordered with a few options like skids, a stiffening rail and a pack sack. It’s a great option for lightweight ski and snow-shoe hikes where you might want to pull your kit instead of carrying it most of the time.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16424876091" title="Nature-Base UL Pulka by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8627/16424876091_61b77fc790_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nature-Base UL Pulka" /></a></p>

<p>Great looking is the EtaProof 110g/m² <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/ul_weste">Vest</a> which tips the scales at 130 g in Size L! The material is windproof and water-resistant which makes it ideal for your skiing adventures on the fjells, while it has a hood that also protects your head. EtaProof is a material with great environmental credentials, and all Nature-Base garments can be fully customized.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238993008" title="Nature-Base UL Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16238993008_43813e7247_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Nature-Base UL Vest" /></a></p>

<h2 id="waldschneider">Waldschneider</h2>

<p><a href="">Waldschneider</a> is a new cottage in stealth mode that will launch in the summer 2015. Based in Germany they have been working since a couple of years on different shelter designs, from Tarps to Pyramids and Inners, as well as bivy bags and bathtub floors. You can check out some of their work here: <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/1643-solo-pyramide/page-2#entry28601">Trollhaus 1</a>, <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/2296-und-noch-ein-lavvu/">Laavu</a> and <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/983-nur-ein-tarp/page-2#entry30186">Sägewerk 2</a>. When they have launched their webshop you’ll hear it here first =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/16078382599" title="014 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8643/16078382599_0970a80c30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="014" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/16263679582" title="010 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7538/16263679582_169cfda566_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="010" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/14463223102" title="001 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2902/14463223102_c7eb32716c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="001" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hyperlite-mountain-gear">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> has a lot of news coming in 2015 - though keeps its card close to their chest. Coming soon is their 100% Woven Dyneema Canyoneering Pack which you might already have spotted on their Social Media outlets. There are also inserts for the Ultamid 2 and Ultamid 4 coming, Chalk Bags for climbing, Throw Bags for packrafting and several other items. Right now <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-of-hyperlite-mountain-gear-two-years-on.html">Mike</a> and his team are working on getting inventory to be built up, so expect some of these items to be available soon!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16400660386" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Canyoneering Pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8619/16400660386_9b7eaf759e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Canyoneering Pack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="packrafting-store">Packrafting Store</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de">Packrafting Store</a> helps in 2015 even more people to enjoy packrafting. They will start to offer some alternative Packrafts in the familiar shape, from a reasonable material (TPU), a good construction, slightly heavier, less varied (= less colors etc.) and <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Packrafts/Nortik-Trekraft-no-deck::598.html">more affordable</a>. There will be also superlight and high performance packrafts available later this spring, but the Classic Alpacka Rafts will remain their prime product. </p>

<p>You’ll also be able to shop for a new paddle from them this year or build your own. There’s four options:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Anfibio Ultimate, a full Carbon Packraft Paddle, 730 g, 5 pieces, fully adjustable (length/angle), stiff and tough at 335€</li>
  <li>Anfibio Smash is the Whitewater Packraft Paddle, 1025 g, 4 pieces, rigid carbon shaft, full size blades, a real “smasher” 209€</li>
  <li>Anfibio Vertex is their well-loved combi paddle (Vertex multi) in a classic version (double blade), fine shaft and very reasonable specs (920 g/ 129€)</li>
  <li>Or make your own webbed paddle with the Shearwater DIY kits. Webbs, rods &amp; clamp shell are provide. Find your shaft (in the garage or in the forest) and follow the instructions (300 g/ 69€)</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425701182" title="Packrafting Store Paddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16425701182_e436981b4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packrafting Store Paddle" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806595653" title="Anfibio Shearwater Paddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8612/15806595653_19b14b066b_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Shearwater Paddle" /></a></p>

<p>The Anfibio Multibag come snow in 60 l and in black, selling for 39€. Also the Anfibio Buoy Boy grows up in Size and now will be available in XL (in black), gets pockets and secured inflation tubes for 89€. The Anfibio Packsuit gets enhanced materials and will be lighter (~100 g per suit), more breathable (25.000 g/m2/24h), softer (better packing) but retains its robustness and price! The fabric also now is Bluesign certificated (environmentally friendly). And as usually each suit can be tailored - That’s cottage style! Also new neoprene gloves, a lightweight whitewater PFD and other accessories as well as courses on the river Soca in Slovenia are coming, and most of this sweet gear will be launched on their 3rd anniversary on February 15th. Check their website then or subscribe to the <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/newsletter.php?language=en">Newsletter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426633735" title="Anfibio Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/16426633735_23a6f0bd9c_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Vest" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16240402769" title="Anfibio Multibag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8668/16240402769_bbd00aea0b_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Multibag" /></a></p>

<h2 id="as-tucas">As Tucas</h2>

<p><a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a> introduces the new schoeller®-ftc fabric with ecorepel® finish this year to their offerings. It’s not just a lighter fabric at 28 g/m2, it is also stronger, more breathable and softer to the skin than any other fabric they have seen so far. Their quilts, insulated &amp; windproof garments are being upgraded to this new fabric, which I find rather exciting. </p>

<p>Their collection of quilts just was expanded with a wearable quilt: the Sestrals 2 Poncho. It features an insulated collar, which they think is more efficient and elegant than the simpler slit designs. Marco expects it will become the cornerstone of those who are looking for a truly versatile sleeping system that also doubles as a insulation garment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806594903" title="As Tucas Sestrals 2 Poncho by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7377/15806594903_e65805e35a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Sestrals 2 Poncho" /></a></p>

<p>As Tucas enters in 2015 the waterproofs market with two new ultralight pants: the Otal Pants made with a 2,5 layer WPB fabric and the Acher Pants made with WPB Cuben fiber. Starting at 120 &amp; 85 grams respectively they are really light but don’t skimp on essential features like an elasticated waist and adjustable cuffs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238993098" title="As Tucas Otal Acher Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/16238993098_f1c454c4e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Otal Acher Pants" /></a></p>

<p>Marco is very busy designing and testing new products, too: The Zilindro 2 collection of base layers made from a new grid fabric by Eschler is almost ready, a Sestrals 2 insulated bivy is under development, and their down quilts are coming soon, too! </p>

<h2 id="tarptent">Tarptent</h2>

<p>Henry has been busy at <a href="http://www.tarptent.com/">Tarptent</a>, redesigning the popular Contrail which is available from February onwards as the ProTrail. It includes all the feedback Tarptent has received over the years since they introduced the Contrail in 2006.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426661605" title="Tarprent Proshelter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8674/16426661605_09c54b282d_o.jpg" width="640" height="360" alt="Tarprent Proshelter" /></a></p>

<p>Here’s a short statement from Henry on Cuben Fibre: <em>We receive our share of requests for cuben fiber products from the die-hards but have opted not to go that route due to the extreme cost. I have always prided myself on producing lightweight shelters that are also affordable and unfortunately cuben just isn’t. I understand that there are people who are willing to pay but if we’re going to do a product it has to pass the “would Henry buy it?” test and at the price of cuben (and the labor involved in hand seam-taping all the seams) the answer is no. I would very much love to move to lighter fabrics but is has to make cost/ benefit sense.</em> So for a Cuben Tarptent to become a reality CubicTech would need to drop their prices, which they as a Monopolist probably aren’t likely to do just yet. </p>

<h2 id="yama-mountain-gear">YAMA Mountain Gear</h2>

<p>Do you like the opener pic at the far top of this article? Because I do. It says freedom and ultralight to me. I think <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/interview-gen-shimizu-from-alpinlite-gear.html">Gen</a> from <a href="http://www.yamamountaingear.com">YAMA Mountain Gear</a> hopefully thinks the same, and maybe it even where some of the ideas he had in mind when he designed the <a href="http://www.yamamountaingear.com/swiftline-2P/">Swiftline Tent</a>, a sub 1 kilo, 2-person, side-entry tent. The versatile new design lets users roll up the walls in nice weather to enjoy bug-free views, while two unobstructed entrances make entry &amp; exit a breeze with a large vestibule that keeps your gear protected and out of the way.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806594923" title="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/15806594923_3267baebdd_o.jpg" width="1200" height="803" alt="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P" /></a></p>

<p>What I also like about YAMA is that they help thru-hikers. In 2015 they welcome five aspiring Pacific Crest Trail thru-hikers to the second year of their <a href="http://mYAMAdventure.com">mYAMAdventure program</a>. The program’s team of mentors is currently helping the 2015 hikers prepare for their upcoming hikes, which will also benefit the Pacific Crest Trail Association. It’s definitely something worth checking out if you plan to hike the PCT!</p>

<h2 id="katabatic-gear">Katabatic Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://katabaticgear.com">Katabatic Gear</a> has released three <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/category/backpacks/">backpacks</a> in 2014 will appeal to both the lightweight and traditional crowds, because they do not sacrifice function, comfort or design while shedding weight from your shoulders. All packs are Made in Colorado, and here’s a quick look at the three packs: </p>

<p>The Artemis is a lightweight, durable pack with 55 l Volume. It’s made from durable 420D nylon fabrics throughout with a Dual Density, Ventilated Framesheet with a removable Aluminum Stay. The ribbed and perforated backpanel provides airflow while the stretch side pockets expand to accommodate loads while keeping pockets low profile when empty. The large zippered front pocket allows for easy access and the stretch woven hipbelt pockets with have an inner key clip. Finally, dual hydration ports ensure you can keep hydrated on the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16400660046" title="Katabatic Gear Artemis 55 Quarter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7336/16400660046_eb5f583b1e_o.jpg" width="475" height="606" alt="Katabatic Gear Artemis 55 Quarter" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/helios-40-backpack/">Helios</a> is similar in design to the Artemis, but focuses more on saving weight. It is made from a lightweight Cuben Fiber laminate which delivers exceptional strength for it’s weight. The woven polyester face fabric gives it additional abrasion resistance and seam strength. The Helios features all of the same design elements as the Artemis, above except that the front pocket is zipper free and uses durable stretch panels. It is currently available in 40 and 55 liter volumes, with the 40 l version tipping the scales at around 850 g in Size Medium.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16424876241" title="Katabatic Gear Helios 55 Quarter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8635/16424876241_4b8ef522a3_o.jpg" width="470" height="594" alt="Katabatic Gear Helios 55 Quarter" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, the Eos is their 30 l lightweight, durable alpine climbing pack. Made from the same durable and water resistant fabric as the Artemis it is designed with climbing and ski-mountaineering in mind. The compression straps allow for carrying skis while the front daisy chain and bungee securely carry ice tools and crampons. The webbing waist belt, compression straps, ice tool bungee, and aluminum stay can be removed when not needed - saving weight when you wanna go really fast &amp; light, but the padded bottom adds durability while carrying a climbing rack. The extension collar expands capacity to 39 l and the zippered inner security pocket with key hook stores your wallet and keys while you’re climbing your Dawn Wall. Finally, major seams are sewn with Dyneema thread for maximum seam strength. Expect this pack to last!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425700432" title="Katabatic Gear Eos 30 Tool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7403/16425700432_3234424f01_o.jpg" width="466" height="554" alt="Katabatic Gear Eos 30 Tool" /></a></p>

<h2 id="yamatomichi">YAMATOMICHI</h2>

<p><a href="http://yamatomichi.com">YAMATOMICHI</a> is also one of the fine Japanese cottages which add style to the ultralight + functionality equation. Right now in the prototyping stage are their YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap, the U.L.Backpack No.3 and their 5-Pockets Long pants. Here’s a couple of photos to get you curious, with the gear coming out in March.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239235120" title="YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7365/16239235120_a5f60764ca_o.jpg" width="640" height="640" alt="YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239235200" title="YAMATOMICHI U.L.Backpack No.3 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7300/16239235200_e90cae49b8_o.jpg" width="640" height="640" alt="YAMATOMICHI U.L.Backpack No.3" /></a></p>

<h2 id="terra-rosa-gear">Terra Rosa Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.terrarosagear.com">Terra Rosa Gear</a> is teaming up with Australian DIY supplier and hammock maker <a href="http://www.tiergear.com.au">Tier Gear</a> for a hammock tarp. It will be available as a package with the Tier Gear hammock shortly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15812036024" title="TRG Tarp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7404/15812036024_7300e9bf2e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="TRG Tarp" /></a></p>

<h2 id="underground-quilts">Underground Quilts</h2>

<p><a href="http://undergroundquilts.com/">Underground Quilts</a> has several new items coming in 2015. Just a month ago they released their <a href="http://undergroundquilts.com/renegade/default.html">RENEGADE TQ</a>. The cold weather quilt uses a combination of vertical and horizontal chambers and can be made with your choice of HyperDRY 800/ 850 fillpower down. The quilt is fully customizable so you can get the quilt of your dreams. Underground Quilts also now offers a 10d fabric option for the inner shell on their top and bottom quilts and 20d fabrics for their our tarps - going lighter!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16429141215" title="RENEGADE TQ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8659/16429141215_4733bfa2f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="RENEGADE TQ" /></a></p>

<h2 id="flat-cat-gear">Flat Cat Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flatcatgear.com">Flat Cat Gear</a> has a new website! Besides that they offer a trio of DIY titanium Stove kits which should be interesting for the MYOG girls and guys out there: </p>

<ul>
  <li>The Epicurean Titanium UL 15 is designed for use with Esbit and will burn up to 50-60 minutes</li>
  <li>The Focus Fire 14 in Titanium is designed to burn Esbit efficiently, one 14 gram tablet can bring 4 cups of 70F water up to 200F</li>
  <li>The new TiLight stove is a tea light replacement stove and weighs 2,84 g</li>
</ul>

<p>They are pre-assembled and you do the final sanding and folding, and cost $10 in the USA and $15 Internationally.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16243283067" title="Flat Cat Gear Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/16243283067_4a53feef8e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="617" alt="Flat Cat Gear Website" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15804132074" title="Flat Cat Gear  Flight by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8584/15804132074_ab3b89bcfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="Flat Cat Gear  Flight" /></a></p>

<h2 id="zpacks">ZPacks</h2>

<p><a href="http://zpacks.com">ZPacks</a> has a few things coming soon, like a synthetic insulated jacket. It will be similar to their <a href="http://zpacks.com/accessories/wind_shell.shtml">wind shell</a> but with Climashield insulation. ZPacks has the insulation in stock and have a prototype which right now is out on the trail, but it needs some work on the patterns. Joe and his team also just got Dyneema X Gridstop fabric in stock and a prototyp Arc Blast and Arc Zip backpacks are being tested right now - expect some photos later this week. Finally Joe is working in a Dyneema pack that can handle 35-40 lbs. There will be some changes to their frame system and more padding on the belt and straps . again, a prototyp is being tested as I write this, so expect some news on it later on. What’s available already since last November is their <a href="http://zpacks.com/shelter/altaplex.shtml">Altaplex shelter</a>. The whole system weighs in at 479 g and is very versatile in use.</p>

<h2 id="warbonnet-outdoors">Warbonnet Outdoors</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.warbonnetoutdoors.com">Warbonnet Outdoors</a> is working on a new Camo pattern specifically designed for larger items like tarps and hopes to have it available later this spring. This should be pretty interesting for the hunters and Bushcrafters out there, so keep your eyes on the Warbonnet website this spring.</p>

<h2 id="more">More</h2>

<p>Cottage Manufacturers are busy people - some are just now out hiking, other’s are finishing up your gear. That’s why not every cottage is on this list. It’s a living document, though, and likely will be updated a couple of times during the next few days while more companies are added. Either check back at the end of the week or follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> where I will announce updates.</p>

<p>And if you liked this article, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> =)</p>

<p><strong>Want more gear news?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> &amp; <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a> for gear reviews and previews!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Högakustenleden - The High Coast Trail]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-13T18:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Högakustenleden - or High Coast Trail in English - is a new trail that passes through the UNESCO World Heritage site of the same name. The scenic trail passes through villages &amp; towns, along the coast, through the forest and a beautiful National Park and if you have a free week makes for a great walk along the Swedish coastal hills.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034082038" title="Jon Nils Berget is the highest point on the trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7571/16034082038_6e226a048a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jon Nils Berget is the highest point on the trail" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>November marks usually the last month of the year where I go out on a Press Trip to do research for <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/magazines/">magazine</a> articles. It’s far from the perfect backpacking month in the North and I had planned to hike the High Coast Trail in August, but changes in schedules meant it’d be the final backpacking trip of the year. Happily my good friend Martin agreed to accompany me, and so we met up late on a Sunday night in a <a href="http://umea.kfum.se">Hostel in Umeå</a>, him after flying in, me after taking the <a href="http://www.wasaline.com">ferry from Vaasa</a>. The next morning we enjoyed the breakfast at the Hostel and walked to the bus station from where we had a comfortable and fast bus ride to the bus stop at Hornöberget just before the High Coast Bridge, the start point of the trail. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221689035" title="Start at the High Coast Bridge in Hornöberget by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7551/16221689035_e5fb4a7ab7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start at the High Coast Bridge in Hornöberget" /></a></p>

<p>We followed the street for a bit, took to a forest road and soon saw our first Högakustenleden trail marker and were on a proper trail. It was a short one, though, because the next several kilometres took us along on village roads, along the street, across bridges until we finally walked along the Baltic Sea and came upon a proper trail into the forest. It wasn’t all pleasurable forest trails, though, we also passed a few deforested areas until we finally reached Sör-Lövvik, the end of section 1. The <a href="http://lovvikbedandbreakfast.se">Lövvik B&amp;B</a> looked inviting just along the trail, and while it was still early in the day we somehow wouldn’t have minded to stop there or at the free cottage in the village, but as it was closed for the winter we just continued until Fjärdbotten.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601850203" title="Fishing Nets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7503/15601850203_bcabd0086a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fishing Nets" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035884247" title="On streets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7487/16035884247_65a120cd5d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On streets" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195855506" title="And trail markers to keep us on course by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7542/16195855506_1793df18c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And trail markers to keep us on course" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219888711" title="A B&amp;B in Lövvik by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16219888711_bd1004d1a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A B&amp;B in Lövvik" /></a></p>

<p>We hiked for a while along the road and then took a turn onto a forest path. We found a stream to refill our water bottles and continued until the Laavu at Halsviken Bay. The place looked nice, and with dusk upon us we yet again were tempted to put the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">HMG UltaMid</a> up for the night. We resisted the early finish and continued on the trail, which then went through a boulder field along the shore. Sleet from the sky, strong winds and spray from the sea make walking on boulders a pleasurable past time, which only can be improved by onsetting darkness. We somehow managed to no break any feet or legs and were rather happy as we reached the forest road and road to Fjärdbotten. It was dark and raining as we arrived there, not knowing what to expect. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035659269" title="Boulder-hoping in the dark and rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7546/16035659269_bb0576bfb7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boulder-hoping in the dark and rain" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034258558" title="Night Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8603/16034258558_8d5ccdb6a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night Selfie" /></a></p>

<p>Fjärdbotten was a great camping place. Around six wooden cottages with tables, benches, beds and some with a stove in them were too good a chance to pass up. Martin quickly put a clothes line up, we hang our wet gear up to dry, got a fire started and then the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/primus-eta-lite-gaskocher/">Primus Lite+</a> came out and boiled us hot water for dinners and Minttu Kakaos! Well fed we soon dived into our sleeping bags and had a good night’s sleep. </p>

<p>The next morning was drizzly but looked like it might clear up. After we explored the Fjärdbotten summer farm and checked out the other cottages and got water from the well we had a warm breakfast &amp; coffee, boiled water for our <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos</a> and then soon were out on the trail again. The decision to stay at Fjärdbotten was a good one, and it was a very nice place.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035560289" title="Breakfast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16035560289_94649b7d5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Breakfast" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601808053" title="Inside our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/15601808053_901c543d1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inside our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034318520" title="Our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/16034318520_918a454e5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601795673" title="Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15601795673_efdbc0fec3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a></p>

<p>The next section took us on the highest point along the trail, Jon Nils Berget. We were lucky as the drizzle from the morning stopped after a few kilometres of hiking and we were treated by one of those fine, sunny days which you get after a night of rain. The trail was a mix of nice forest roads (they’re great to walk and talk on with a party of two!) where abandoned caravans were every few kilometres. As we reached Jon Nils Berget the sun came out and we really enjoyed this beautiful moment. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195729126" title="Supertramp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16195729126_3621a39362_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Supertramp" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237534596" title="Martin taking in the view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16237534596_140c3a9356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Martin taking in the view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219705131" title="Viewing the view stop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7514/16219705131_dd6c0e5321_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the view stop" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035459759" title="And looking outta the window by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7523/16035459759_b39d89a0c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And looking outta the window" /></a></p>

<p>We had a quick tea and cookies break at the Nipstugan on Lidenipan, and the sun just continued to treat us with warmth and light on the way to Gavik, the end of the 3rd Section. Behind Gavik we hiked on a forest road along summer cottages which had been closed up for winter, and had a very late lunch as the sun was just setting somewhere in the West. Soon the headlamps came on as we hiked on dark and wet forest trails and snowy forest roads.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034049618" title="Well, lets get moving by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16034049618_5c2d180b64_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Well, lets get moving" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601684713" title="Back on asphalt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7521/15601684713_a62f3aef77_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back on asphalt" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033999978" title="Where the road stops by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7495/16033999978_94444f9be6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Where the road stops" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601652373" title="Views without trees by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8576/15601652373_c0ddf9bf12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views without trees" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220694082" title="Headlamp illuminated views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7490/16220694082_cb669dd0de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Headlamp illuminated views" /></a></p>

<p>The goal of Section 4 was Lappuden, which was hailed as <em>the</em> camping spot along the Högakustenleden. Well, it was not. As it was closed. Closed up for winter. After the luxury of the Fjärdbotten hut we were going to sleep outside, and as the lake and grass fields already were covered with thin ice we knew we’d be in for a cold night. Alas, not even a fire we were able to lighten up, for a lack of wood and a fire place. We still had a good night, even if my <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk">PHD Minix Sleeping Bag</a> was a tad too less insulation for these temperatures. The next morning the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">fēnix</a> said -3°C and we packed up while the Lite+ boiled water for breakfast &amp; coffee. We were early on the trail again, and we were happy to leave the disappointment of Lappuden behind.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601643623" title="Lappuden by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/15601643623_59636ae21f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lappuden" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035648837" title="Reindeer moss by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/16035648837_9c8c2cea2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reindeer moss" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15599059654" title="Quartz veins by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7525/15599059654_c6e420dee6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Quartz veins" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035354489" title="Erikskojan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7547/16035354489_03b5cf6996_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Erikskojan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221453515" title="Inside Erikskojan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7582/16221453515_d0cda2ee6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inside Erikskojan" /></a></p>

<p>The trail was again a mix of enjoyable forest trails, OK forest roads and less enjoyable asphalt streets, but happily the trails made up the majority os Section 5 to Ullånger. The highlight for Martin and me was the beautiful Erikskojan hut high up in the middle of the forest. It stood lonely there, and if I hadn’t pulled like someone who really wants to sit inside with his tea we probably would have drunk our hot tea on its steps as the door was very tightly closed =) Of all the huts we passed this was the one we both really would have loved to stay in for the night, as it was cozy and comfortable. Alas, we needed to continue onwards.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195558186" title="Lovely deforestation views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7568/16195558186_41f1ab48d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lovely deforestation views" /></a></p>

<p>As we hiked into Ullånger it was still lunch time, and we didn’t need long to decide on the Värdshuset Restaurang Snäckan to get our business. A Lunch Buffet is a Hiker’s dream, and tasty Swedish food was consumed in large amounts, topped off with coffee and cookies. It was fortunate that we didn’t need to hike a long distance to our next camping place, the Gårdberget Stugan just above Ullånger. We didn’t really know what to expect, but were delighted by the hut, which was decorated in a 70s style and had a big stove inside. A fire was roaring quickly while night fell, and we enjoyed the evening by talking and drinking a good Whisky.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263362435" title="Gårdberget Stugan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7529/16263362435_bf07675705_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gårdberget Stugan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262537602" title="Mäjasjön Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16262537602_c7326acd44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mäjasjön Summer Farm" /></a></p>

<p>The night over a powdery coat of snow covered the land and we enjoyed the walk in the morning through the silent forest. That silence was interrupted the closer we got to Sjöland and Skoved as the trail went along the highway. It was an interesting experience to hike with trucks and cars passing by at high speeds, and I do hope that the trail finds a different route in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262738312" title="Church door by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7555/16262738312_90e05236cb_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Church door" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16075793398" title="Truck by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7559/16075793398_dc2885d33f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Truck" /></a></p>

<p>We flew through Section 7 from Skoved to Skuleberget and the <a href="http://www.naturumhogakusten.se/">Naturum Höga Kusten</a> Centre. Sadly the Museum also was closed, and as we still had well over 15 km before us we also didn’t take the detour over the top of the Skuleberget. The hill was impressive, though, and it’s nice to see that local entrepreneurs have installed Via Ferratas on it. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15643755233" title="Naturum Höga Kusten by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7561/15643755233_c0fd06d8dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Naturum Höga Kusten" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076092610" title="Skuleberget National Park South Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7537/16076092610_7e0d2a9016_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park South Entry" /></a></p>

<p>Section 8 from Skuleberget to the Skuleberget National Park South Entry must have been one of the most frustrating ones on the trail. After the Naturum Höga Kusten Centre we had another quick lunch break outside and then followed the nice Kids Adventure/ Robber Trail, passed an Open Air Theatre and then crossed the highway once more to hike on trails and forest roads to the South Entry of the National Park. Some sections of the trail were flooded and it was impossible to keep your feet dry, which usually doesn’t bother me at all, but somehow that day it really annoyed me a lot. The trail wasn’t fun in the wet dirt &amp; mud, but happily I recovered as soon as the trail became dry again. As we came closer and closer to the Skuleberget National Park the better our moods got, and the view from the South Entry was indeed well worth coming there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263434465" title="View at Skuleberget National Park South Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8609/16263434465_9a283ba21d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View at Skuleberget National Park South Entry" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263398085" title="Skuleberget National Park Signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16263398085_8e31435fc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park Signs" /></a></p>

<p>As frustrating as that wet part of the trail previously was, so wonderful was the <a href="http://www.sverigesnationalparker.se/skuleskogen#.VLUOe8bJhJc">Skuleskogen National Park</a>. The National Park probably was the highlight of our trip, and we were a bit sad that we spend only such a short time in day light in it. We hiked on duck boards for kilometres, passed waterfalls and then hiked up to the impressive Slåttdalsskrevan, a 200 m long, 40 m deep and 7 m wide crevice. We explored it in the shine of our headlamps and then made us on the way down to the Tärnättvattnen Stuga in the middle of the National Park. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237633986" title="Checking out the small waterfall, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7481/16237633986_fdcba0d04b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Checking out the small waterfall, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238289906" title="Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7464/16238289906_fa3b941b49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237741036" title="Frozen, slippery, smooth granite at night by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7478/16237741036_d5b335e1dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Frozen, slippery, smooth granite at night" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16261636721" title="Frozen lake at Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7578/16261636721_4058a06423_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Frozen lake at Skuleberget National Park" /></a></p>

<p>The hut was gorgeous from the inside and outside, though as it often happens with such huts, they seem to accumulate rubbish and trinkets which previous visitors <em>left for others to enjoy</em> or simply <em>forgot</em>. We cleaned up, got a fire started and enjoyed the evening with the a <em>Feierabendbier</em> which we carried all the way from the Supermarket in Docksta till here to enjoy in this rustic hut. The next morning grey clouds still hung thickly in the sky and the sun wasn’t to be seen. We brought some more wood for the next visitors to the hut, cleaned up and packed and where on our way again.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076128100" title="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16076128100_74c11ae583_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076804860" title="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/16076804860_db7f85d833_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15641095154" title="Signs in Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7528/15641095154_3e564daab1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signs in Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076115510" title="Looking back towards Slåttdalsskrevan, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7572/16076115510_c722693948_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Looking back towards Slåttdalsskrevan, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077690687" title="Dot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8619/16077690687_48928e6a0a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dot" /></a></p>

<p>The way out of the National Park was again very beautiful, along frozen lakes, via Duckboards over swamps, over small streams and soft forest trails until the North Entry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15643662733" title="Stream crossing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8643/15643662733_6e3a184cbc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Stream crossing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077649527" title="The sea, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8636/16077649527_664f582c49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The sea, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262745482" title="Skuleberget National Park North Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7469/16262745482_6731323942_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park North Entry" /></a></p>

<p>It was noon as we arrived in Köpmanholmen, and as every good tourist hiker does we immediately located the local Pizzeria and ordered their lunch Pizza. 60 SEK for a Pizza, salad, drink and coffee is a real bargain, especially considering that the Pizzas were about 40 cm (!) in diameter. We were stuffed as we walked out of the village and walked on a sandy road until the where we would enter the Balesudden Nature Reserve. It was a very beautiful reserve and not even a kilometre from the start of the forest trail we passed the prettiest Laavu on the whole Högakustenleden, up on the hill overlooking the Baltic Sea. Again we regretted that we needed to push on and couldn’t stay here, as the view and atmosphere was gorgeous.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15640967264" title="Party time by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15640967264_7ba6d83d27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Party time" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076221740" title="Sweden! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8676/16076221740_3f181081cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sweden!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077751717" title="Högakustenleden Signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16077751717_bc80426d93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Högakustenleden Signs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262764232" title="Laavu with a view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7521/16262764232_d025afbe1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Laavu with a view" /></a></p>

<p>Instead we pushed on through on and up through the Balesudden Nature Reserve, though with dusk coming upon us and a light drizzle we had our eyes mostly on the slippery trail in front of us. We passed a nice fireplace and camping spot near a bay until we happened upon the Bodviken Stugan, our hut for the night. The drizzle had become rain and I was happy as Martin offered to go chop the wood. I started the fire and rolled out my sleeping bag and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html">mattress</a> and again fired up the Primus Lite+. Soon we were well fed and had a whisky in our cups, which ensured we had another good, relaxed and warm night.</p>

<p>In winter you can sleep long and still catch the sunrise. So after we had breakfast I took a little stroll around the hut to photograph the sunrise. It was just a brief moment where one could spot the sun, as it passed up from the sea to hide again behind the clouds. It was our last day on the trail, and we only had 21 km till Örnsköldsvik, with the last part in civilization, so that we took it easy. We passed a few more Laavus in the morning, hiked on forest roads and streets, up hills and had a quick break in the Småtjärnstugan, and then were very quickly in Svedje, the end of Section 12. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238233526" title="Sunrise by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7565/16238233526_786eec69cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15672818967" title="Natur Reservat by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/15672818967_bc83905b3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Natur Reservat" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16261709811" title="Bodviken Stugan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/16261709811_108f7dfe02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodviken Stugan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076028498" title="Along the frozen lake by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7503/16076028498_a1176918ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Along the frozen lake" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16078073489" title="That way! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7494/16078073489_fed4a67d95_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="That way!" /></a></p>

<p>From here we passed through the town and climbed the local recreation area. As it was windy, 0°C and grey we just marched on towards Örnsköldsvik, the end of Section 13 of the Högakustenleden. Early in the afternoon we reached town. Done.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076823010" title="Örnskoldvik by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7566/16076823010_6ce886089b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Örnskoldvik" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076101788" title="Örnköldsvik! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8616/16076101788_c758bc15da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Örnköldsvik!" /></a></p>

<p>While standing on the square in the centre a young Swede came talking to us, who recognized me as <em>the writer of Hiking in Finland</em>. It was a fun coincidence as he said he saw that we’d be hiking the trail that week and he met us just as we finished! Very cool! After inquiring about a good place to eat in the evening we walked to our hostel, <a href="http://www.vindarnashus.se">Vindarnas Hus</a>. It was a nice &amp; quiet hostel with Wifi, hot showers and good beds, and we chilled there in the evening until we headed out to eat at <a href="http://www.bishopsarms.com/Ornskoldsvik">The Bishops Arms</a> which not only had superb food but also impeccable service and great beers. It was a worthy finish to a great Högakustenleden thru-hike!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221464365" title="Still plenty of signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7539/16221464365_a08cce908d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Still plenty of signs" /></a></p>

<h2 id="planning-your-high-coast-trail-hike">Planning your High Coast Trail hike</h2>

<p>To see about 150 more photos check out the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157648982512379/">Höga Kusten Trail Album</a> on Flickr.</p>

<p>The funniest thing about the Högakustenleden was for Martin and me how the distances were way off from what the signs and the guide booklet said. It makes me wonder if the trail is actually hiked by the people who planned it and if they made the effort to check the distance, or if these were just made via some mapping tool. Because the Högakustenleden is supposed to be 128,6 km from Hornöberget to Örnsköldsvik, but I tracked with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">Garmin fēnix</a> 141,8 km in the six days we hiked it. This isn’t uncommon and I regularly hike trails and sections which are longer/ shorter than they’re claimed to be, but still is something to keep in mind when you plan to hike the trail. </p>

<p>Also important to know is that the trail goes quite a bit along forest roads and streets. It does feel like at least 50% of the trail makes use of such infrastructure, and while it can make for fast hiking (5 km an hour and easy to chat while walking next to each other) it isn’t really very inspiring. Happily there are enough of nice forest trails, too, and the section through the Skuleskogen National Park was gorgeous. If you have time I’d recommend planning a day to just explore the National Park and then hike on.</p>

<p>Plan the travel there and back via <a href="http://reseplanerare.resrobot.se/bin/help.exe/sn?L=vs_resrobot&amp;tpl=webapp">Resrobot</a>, one of the best travel apps I have used. It helps you to find the best Bus/ Train/ Flight connections from e.g. Stockholm to Hornöberget and Örnsköldsvik and also lets you book the tickets right away. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.visitsweden.com/sweden/">Visit Sweden</a> and the <a href="http://www.hogakustenleden.com">Högakustenleden</a> + <a href="http://hogakusten.com/en/hk/high-coast-trail.html">High Coast Trail</a> websites offer a host of information about Sweden and the trail, especially the last page has a great overview map and a description of each section. You can order from there also the useful <a href="http://hogakusten.com/information/en/brochures.html">Trail Guide</a>, though don’t bother with the (free) map as it’s too large a scale to be useful for hiking. Speaking of maps, you really can hike it just with the maps in the Trail Guide. The trail is exceptionally well marked and so very beginner-friendly, sometimes every third tree has an orange dot or stripe. </p>

<p>We slept every night in one of the free huts or Laavus and were completely alone on the trail, we once encountered day hikers. But then we were hiking in November, so in the spring, summer and autumn that could look very differently. I recommend you take a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">shelter</a> along when hiking in those months, or make use of the various accommodation options along the trail. Basic ultralight gear choices would suit the trail well, you can practice pitching tarps and sleeping with a quilt here very well as you could always head to one of the Laavus or Huts. From Ullånger on you almost daily would pass a village with a supermarket, Café and Restaurant, so you could easily resupply along the trail (or buy a Swedish Beer for the evening each day =).</p>

<p>Along the trail you also could easily go packrafting, sea kayaking, climbing and Via Ferrata. While you could do some of these activities just besides the trail you’d need to plan an extra day for some others. Because of the good infrastructure (huts &amp; Laavus, Restaurants and Shops along the way) the trail could be a good choice for families who want to try backpacking with their kids. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lake District Traverse: Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/a-lake-district-traverse-part-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T16:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/06/a-lake-district-traverse-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As it’s almost a month ago that I published <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html">Part I</a> of my Lakeland Traverse and there have been several more trips since then, it’s time to hike on and bring it to a finish =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057561889" title="Sca Fell camp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5117/14057561889_18ae743375_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sca Fell camp" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>After a calm night I wake up, have breakfast and smile because the sun is shining as I head up towards Sca Fell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14112337924" title="Breakfast on Sca Fell"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7456/14112337924_7b04c0e430_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Breakfast on Sca Fell" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14278964730" title="Up to Sca Fell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3884/14278964730_540e217c3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Up to Sca Fell" /></a></p>

<p>I continue to smile, even as it gets more and more cloudy the nearer I get to the summit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14100737371" title="Sca Fell in the mist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7209/14100737371_aca59cc552_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sca Fell in the mist" /></a></p>

<p>Once there, the summit is indeed dressed in clouds as, accompanied with a stiff breeze. Hardshell top and bottom come on, down I go.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14464228632" title="Foxes Tarn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3851/14464228632_af387f9179_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Foxes Tarn" /></a></p>

<p>The descent to Foxes Tarn is nice though you should be sure-footed. The place itself looked clean and inviting for a camp, but I continued.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14464435354" title="Whaddyalookingat? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2926/14464435354_ebe953770b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Whaddyalookingat?" /></a></p>

<p>Down a scrambly bit to the path up Scafell Pike. Good fun that section! Up on England’s highest hill I snap a Selfie and walk on. Views are good, people few.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14442477696" title="Scafell Pike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5564/14442477696_133ca1fd87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scafell Pike" /></a></p>

<p>But it are the views from Bowfell that I enjoy most.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14278945979" title="Sca Fell &amp; Scafell Pike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2921/14278945979_f9aeefc6de_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Sca Fell &amp; Scafell Pike" /></a></p>

<p>I descend via the Flat Slabs and head onwards to the Old Dungeon Ghyll Climber’s Bar.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14465578885" title="Flat Slabs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3885/14465578885_812eb60118_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Flat Slabs" /></a></p>

<p>A fine Ale, soup and a roll are consumed, and with not much enthusiasm I leave the fine establishment behind. My route takes me up to Stickle Tarn, where I count four other tents around the lake!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14485734013" title="Stickle Tarn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3884/14485734013_8bbd3a8927_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Stickle Tarn" /></a></p>

<p>It’s windy and I’m soon in my quilt after a hot meal. It is a fiercely windy night and past midnight a couple descends to the valley past me under my TrailStar. Rain sets in occasionally. I drift in and out of sleep, and with dawn I’m up. The Coleman gas canister is empty (after just 3 l of water boiled!) and so I can’t have my morning coffee. Up I go, forgoing the scramble I came for.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14378696112" title="Above Stickle Tarn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5040/14378696112_6157530f5f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Above Stickle Tarn" /></a></p>

<p>Drizzle and wind accompany me on my way to High Raise and onwards to Calf Crag, Gibson Knott and Helm Crag, before I descend to the village of Grasmere.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193578570" title="Cloudy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2938/14193578570_7f313cd441_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Cloudy" /></a></p>

<p>I buy a new gas canister and fruits, have a coffee and soup and head up Grisedale Tarn. The weather improves and the sun breaks through.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14465582995" title="Arriba by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5474/14465582995_f52759df3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arriba" /></a></p>

<p>My plan to go on to Helvellyn and walk its Ridges is dropped in favour of a low camp. But the valleys are private land and I don’t feel like sneaking into one of the woods to pitch my TrailStar and so end up in the Youth Hostel in Patterdale. A hot shower is enjoyed, and a good sleep is had.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193489749" title="Looking up to Grisedale by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2939/14193489749_047e97d4e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Looking up to Grisedale" /></a></p>

<p>Breakfast on the sofa, packing with plenty of space, wall to wall sunshine awaiting me. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13948223152" title="That way by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2938/13948223152_b31fb818c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="That way" /></a></p>

<p>Up to Angletarn Pikes. A lovely hill with fine views all the way.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13948221232" title="Upwards by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7121/13948221232_2b2bbe2598_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Upwards" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14380144815" title="Lovely view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2915/14380144815_d36e8bc42c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lovely view" /></a></p>

<p>Angle Tarn is a wonderful place and would make a fine camping spot. Birds are swimming on its clear blue water, while the sun reflects in ripples as a slight breeze sweeps across it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193530658" title="Angle Tarn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3856/14193530658_46c3c33068_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Angle Tarn" /></a></p>

<p>The views from up here are magnificent, further enhenced by the superb weather. I walk with an open wind jacket and cuffs up, but soon decide it’s time to hike in my T-Shirt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193699467" title="Gate by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3837/14193699467_022eb5b942_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Gate" /></a></p>

<p>I take the faint path up Rest Dodd before heading down and up to The Knott. Time for coffee and Vitamin C in the sun, there’s no hurry anywhere.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14379174464" title="Coffee on The Knott by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2902/14379174464_06571c2c53_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Coffee on The Knott" /></a></p>

<p>I stroll onwards to the High Street where plenty of day hikers enjoy the great weather. I shortly ponder a stroll up and down the Riggindale Crag, but decide to head onwards to the Thornthwaite Crag. A large cairn marker (more a tower, really) spends shade that is welcomed in this hot weather.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193497129" title="Blue by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5231/14193497129_9eeb9496af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Blue" /></a></p>

<p>The impending ridge walk of Froswick, Ill Bell and Yoke has me smiling ear to ear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14379175414" title="Spikey by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5191/14379175414_3f63597556_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Spikey" /></a></p>

<p>Then water runs low and so I am looking out for water. Close to the Garburn Pass I find a gurgling stream and the Playtypuses are filled up and emptied right away. Tasty. So why not stay?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14380141145" title="Camp III by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2928/14380141145_b69ab58d1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Camp III" /></a></p>

<p>I do. It’s beautiful and I love the views - Windermere to the south, the high hills to the west, crags, grass and sheep to the north and east. I have a mighty fine evening up on the hill, and fall asleep under the stars.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13912268942" title="MLD TrailStar in the English Lake District. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2900/13912268942_8066e0cef6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MLD TrailStar in the English Lake District." /></a></p>

<p>The next morning the weather is again on repeat: Blue sky and sunshine. I take it slow, enjoy the last bit outside, but am soon enough on the trail. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14380137475" title="Troutbeck Tongue by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3918/14380137475_5f5a6dc457_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Troutbeck Tongue" /></a></p>

<p>Then I arrive at Orrest Head, Tourists being delighted by the view to be had from here. And also I smile, even as know that this will be the last time I will lay my eyes on the hills of the Lake District, those fine small mountains whom I just traversed. And so I walk down to the railway station, happy to return in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14379173934" title="Orrest Head by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5496/14379173934_b7daa145f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Orrest Head" /></a></p>

<p>More photos on <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157644166894052/">Flickr</a>. <em>Follow along on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/">Google+</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lake District Traverse: Part I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html"/>
    <updated>2014-05-22T12:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Lake District is one of England’s most scenic National Parks, with steep hills, lush green valleys, glittering lakes and inviting Pubs. I traversed this beautiful area from Ravenglass to Windermere in a 125 km route and hiked up some of the most well-known mountains and camped at some beautiful sites.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057613217" title="On the hills by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2916/14057613217_6cf64400c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="On the hills" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>It’s funny to think that on the birthday of the website I started my Lake District hike. Funny, as English blogs were one of the inspirations to start this site, and on it’s fifth birthday I was setting off to backpack in one of the most popular National Parks in the UK.</em></p>

<p>The Lake District has long appealed to me, and with the help of <a href="http://www.visitengland.com/">Visit England</a> I was able to realize this trip. As I had six days for backpacking I early on decided that a traverse would be best to see as much as possible, and my list of things I’d like to see was long, as I explained in my “<a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/planning-a-trip-in-the-lake-district.html">Planning a Trip in the Lake District</a>” article. </p>

<p>So on Monday morning I left Manchester by train and arrived punctual at 10:55 o’clock in Ravenglass, where I meet <a href="http://stevenhorner.com/">Steven</a> and Traci who would join me for the first day. We had a quick lunch at the Café in the Railway Station and then set off towards the hills. Steven explained to me the system of paths in the UK - I still am baffled by it! - and soon we were hiking past cows to the Muncaster Castle. We passed it, eager to get to the hills, but before that a short stroll on the street was necessary. As someone from the continent the left side traffic was something to be well aware of, as you do everything just the other way around as you’d at home. The walk on the street was quickly done, and then it was off into the wild - or the swamp. For quite a bit we were searching for the path, which was marked on our maps, to Devoke Water, but in the end we just gave up, took an aim and just kept on walking. Surely enough, close to the lake we then happened upon a trail which we followed for a bit before a short break. I refilled my water bottles and we enjoyed the fine views over the lake. As we had still some bit to go we continued, following the path to Woodend and then up to Great Worm Crag. The mandatory first summit photo was taken, I made a few quick bolder moves and onwards to White How and Green Crag we continued.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057537858" title="Clouds and sheep by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2920/14057537858_705a68c7a4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Clouds and sheep" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057583230" title="Muncaster Castle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2915/14057583230_e73a1c193a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Muncaster Castle" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057607037" title="The English Road by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5541/14057607037_60f2fd8aa0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The English Road" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14240888771" title="Landscape I by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5073/14240888771_10db0ed9a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="561" alt="Landscape I" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14264374953" title="Here&#x27;s the path! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5192/14264374953_aa82ca27d9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="567" alt="Here&#x27;s the path!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14244197675" title="Devoke Water by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2919/14244197675_1b8b2bff86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Devoke Water" /></a></p>

<p>While there was a path marked down on my map, the reality looked different. Through a swamp, which has claimed the life of a sheep or two, we made it with even wetter feet to the foot of Harter Fell. The sun was shining, the full water bottles added a couple of kilograms of weight and so we started our ascent. Grazing sheep were gazing as we passed them by in what must have seemed like snail speed to them, but then, finally, we made it to a large “plateau” which lays a dozen of meters under the summit. We walked the last bit up to the Summit Marker and enjoyed the wide views: To the West lay the sea and the Isle of Man, a bit further to the north the southern tip of Scotland came into view, and to the north Sca Fell and Scafell Pike dominated the view and demanded attention. Further to the east Brown Pike, Dow Crag and the Old Man of Coniston could be seen. It was a magnificent place to be.</p>

<p>With plenty of space to pitch the TrailStars Traci and Steven pitched theirs on the plateau, while I went a bit further up between two large boulders. As the wind picked up we ate dinner together, enjoyed the sunset and rising moon, and had a Finnish dessert before hitting the hay. During the night the wind turned and was blowing well into my shelter. Not being amused I just took out a peg which practically closed the TrailStar, and a more calm nicht could be enjoyed. I was up with the sunrise (the sun still rising <em>“late”</em> back then) though the high wind demanded that I wear all my layers. We packed up and said our good byes, Steven &amp; Traci heading back to Eskdale while I set off to the west. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221053606" title="Up there? Really? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2899/14221053606_d48e1939b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Up there? Really?" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14243892084" title="Harter Fell view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5506/14243892084_3c6bda84c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Harter Fell view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057561029" title="Dinner by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5577/14057561029_d94d9303c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dinner" /></a></p>

<p>Through the re-forested Hardknott Forest I made my way down as the sun was rising and promised a fine day. Down at the river I happened upon a Parking place with benches, which made for the perfect breakfast spot. I enjoyed the bird song and purl of the river, only once or twice interrupted by a passing car. Refilled with water I walked down the street, passing by the gorgeous houses in the valley. A mother who was carrying her daughter walked a horse to the meadow and greeted me with a smile, and it is easy to imagine how good life must be far off the beaten track between the hills. I hiked on, finding the sign and path which brought me on line with my first summit of the day. </p>

<p>After some backtracking and climbing fences I made it on the road to Walna Scar Road. This path is so wide that you three to four people could hike next to each other - but right now I was alone, just far off in the distance I could make out a few couples slowly making their way to the top. Along the Long House Gill stream the path climbed continuously up, and at the crossroad I sat down to have a zip of water and some nuts. A father and son couple was now following behind me. I packed up and continued, the summit of Brown Pike getting closer and closer. </p>

<p>As I reached the crossroad underneath the summit, the wind welcomed me. I said a <em>“Hiya”</em> greeting to the couple who arrived with me at the crossroad from the other side, and while the husband was looking into his Wainwright the wife set off towards Brown Pike. I had a quick look across the valley and could see dozens of people on the Old Man and this side, so I continued. As I hiked from Buck Pike to Dow Crag two dayhikers and their dog emerged from the south rake, a scramble I had intended to do but as it would have meant walking down and then scrambling up again, I decided to leave it for the time being. However, seeing those two emerge, elated, I was a bit disappointed that I did not have the time to do this fine scramble. </p>

<p>Dow Crag was busy with families eating a summit lunch (in T-shirts and shorts in the blazing wind, nonetheless), and so I continued. The Old Man of Consiton was still so busy, with plenty of people arriving and leaving. I took in the view from the summit cairn, and then decided it’s time to go on. After Swirl How it got eerily devoid of people, and I strolled on my own onwards to the Grey Friar. A fine summit with views on Crinkle Crags, Bow Fell, Sca Fell and Scafell Pike I sat down for some water, figs and dates, trying to make out the path to the valley. As I took off I followed a faint path, but soon I was walking on sheep trails down. I arrived in a muddy field amongst cows, between me and the street an insurmountable lake of wet cow dung. The cows looked on as I tried to avoid to step in their excrements, hoping from stone to a small green island of grass, but to no avail: As I reached the gate my shoes were covered in wet cow poop. At the road in Cockley Beck I sat down at the stream, tried to rinse and dry my socks, but the smell &amp; colour of cow poop was intending to stay. Barefoot, eating nuts, I observed an old couple who happily arrived back at their car. After they packed up they came over to offer me a ride up the pass - they must have seen that I intended to go that way - but I kindly said “No, thank you” and explained that I’d mess up their car with my wet &amp; dirty shoes. <em>“That’s no problem”</em> came the reply - an answer I least expected! I smiled and explained I prefer to walk, and thanked them again.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14244195805" title="Walna Scar Road by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5479/14244195805_ba9aa709dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Walna Scar Road" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221050576" title="Dow Crag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5319/14221050576_a2d817d37d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dow Crag" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221050166" title="The Old Man of Coniston by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5489/14221050166_7c850e257d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Old Man of Coniston" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14241982842" title="View from Grey Friar by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2897/14241982842_63f5179ca8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="View from Grey Friar" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221048576" title="Cockley Beck by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2918/14221048576_28bc655047_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Cockley Beck" /></a></p>

<p>After allowing my socks and shoes to dry a bit I slipped them back on and started the hike up Hardknott Pass road. Cars passing me smiled, and with some satisfaction I reached the top of the pass, from where I had a fine view on the Eskdale valley. I absolutely adore these views: Lush green fields speckled with white and black sheep, green forests, a blue river which meanders through the valley and lovely houses. I passed by the Roman Fort and walked on the road till I saw the sign up to Sca Fell. A family just arrived from the top, and with the clock being almost 17 they looked curiously as I hiked on. Now my plan was ambitious and I hoped to camp up on Sca Fell or at the Fox Tarn, though after almost 28 km hiked I decided to camp lower, in the vicinity of water, at a lovely camp spot. </p>

<p>I pitched the TrailStar, boiled water for food, tea &amp; dessert, and looked as a big, yellow moon was slowly rising at Hardknott Pass while the last cars of the day made their way up the street. </p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14243890524" title="Grazing sheep II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2905/14243890524_ab1a31f65a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Grazing sheep II" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13982573296" title="Sign up Sca Fell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7383/13982573296_379bef8909_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sign up Sca Fell" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14243892344" title="Sca Fell camp at dusk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2908/14243892344_c9ae90606b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sca Fell camp at dusk" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untold Trip Reports]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/untold-trip-reports.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T11:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/untold-trip-reports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Unsung heroes, untold stories. So much time outdoors, so little time to write about them.</em> <strong>These are the Untold Trip Reports.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9537611324/" title="Dusk by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7312/9537611324_1787dd85ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dusk" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="packrafting-in-ruunaa">Packrafting in Ruunaa</h2>

<p>I was just back from the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">OutDoor Fair</a> when I saddled two packs with packrafts on my shoulders to travel to Ruunaa, where I was teaching a packrafting course. It was a very wet weekend, though we laughed, paddled and hiked a lot. One more packrafting aficionado joined the tribe, eagerly waiting to acquire his own, taking it on future adventures on rivers and lakes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715313/" title="Wet by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/9559715313_228cbc97ab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wet" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9562508942/" title="Time to pick some berries by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/9562508942_5af0666233_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Time to pick some berries" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715473/" title="Water by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5532/9559715473_6d6f4ee7e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Water" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715389/" title="Fire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7314/9559715389_6c714de875_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="backpacking-in-seitseminen">Backpacking in Seitseminen</h2>

<p>Another course with three superb clients, we were backpacking for three days in the beautiful Seitseminen National Park and learned about ultralight skills and gear. Gathered mushrooms, swam in the lake, sat around the fire and slept warm in hammocks and quilts, while the sun shone down on our trail. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9519459009/" title="Ultralight camping by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3793/9519459009_f7441f5148_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ultralight camping" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9537712134/" title="Mirror II by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/9537712134_1c135a66d0_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Mirror II" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9534948843/" title="UL Tenkara fly fishing setup by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2821/9534948843_b9483f1f44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Tenkara fly fishing setup" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9534922329/" title="Ramaria flava by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5471/9534922329_a1b6a2e21f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Ramaria flava" /></a></p>

<h2 id="kungsleden">Kungsleden</h2>

<p>A failed trip is also a trip. After the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> I had an ambitious plan to ski a loop on the Kundgsleden, though as I took a fall while ice climbing where I injured my knee the skiing was just too painful, and so I returned after having skied 20 km on brand-new skis which I would have loved to take up some fjells. Alas, it was not meant to be, though I will return soon enough for a re-match.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571269176/" title="Dynafit Broad Peak by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7348/10571269176_24320b56c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dynafit Broad Peak" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571517553/" title="Shadowboxing I by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5485/10571517553_1cf154a314_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Shadowboxing I" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9129268734/" title="Khufu on the Kungsleden"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2850/9129268734_56263af54b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Kungsleden" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571514423/" title="Dusk by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7335/10571514423_5fbb1fcc56_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dusk" /></a></p>

<h2 id="dayhikes--overnighters">Dayhikes &amp; Overnighters</h2>

<p>The largest amount of untold stories are the dozens of <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/WorldHeritageSites/kvarkenarchipelago/activities/Pages/Default.aspx">dayhikes</a> and overnighters here in the region. Plenty of great outdoor destinations around Vaasa, not only the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/a-family-hike-on-the-bodvattnet-runt.html">Kvarken Archipelago</a> which it counts to explore - by bike, packraft, on foot, and soon again on skis and snowshoes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410128705/" title="Dawn by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/10410128705_2ce65c655f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Dawn" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410103134/" title="Skis, carried. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3704/10410103134_a0acf19995_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Skis, carried." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9982464505/" title="Reflection. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2813/9982464505_bbbbcd925d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="909" alt="Reflection." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8839376917/" title="052113_1264 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7307/8839376917_73a7be00b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="052113_1264" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632582072/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8389/8632582072_9c86a0a5ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p><em>These are the Untold Trip Reports, and there will be more of them in the future.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
