<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: backpacking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/backpacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-04T12:59:47+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lake District Traverse: Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/a-lake-district-traverse-part-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T16:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/06/a-lake-district-traverse-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As it’s almost a month ago that I published <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html">Part I</a> of my Lakeland Traverse and there have been several more trips since then, it’s time to hike on and bring it to a finish =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057561889" title="Sca Fell camp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5117/14057561889_18ae743375_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sca Fell camp" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>After a calm night I wake up, have breakfast and smile because the sun is shining as I head up towards Sca Fell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14112337924" title="Breakfast on Sca Fell"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7456/14112337924_7b04c0e430_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Breakfast on Sca Fell" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14278964730" title="Up to Sca Fell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3884/14278964730_540e217c3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Up to Sca Fell" /></a></p>

<p>I continue to smile, even as it gets more and more cloudy the nearer I get to the summit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14100737371" title="Sca Fell in the mist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7209/14100737371_aca59cc552_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sca Fell in the mist" /></a></p>

<p>Once there, the summit is indeed dressed in clouds as, accompanied with a stiff breeze. Hardshell top and bottom come on, down I go.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14464228632" title="Foxes Tarn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3851/14464228632_af387f9179_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Foxes Tarn" /></a></p>

<p>The descent to Foxes Tarn is nice though you should be sure-footed. The place itself looked clean and inviting for a camp, but I continued.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14464435354" title="Whaddyalookingat? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2926/14464435354_ebe953770b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Whaddyalookingat?" /></a></p>

<p>Down a scrambly bit to the path up Scafell Pike. Good fun that section! Up on England’s highest hill I snap a Selfie and walk on. Views are good, people few.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14442477696" title="Scafell Pike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5564/14442477696_133ca1fd87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scafell Pike" /></a></p>

<p>But it are the views from Bowfell that I enjoy most.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14278945979" title="Sca Fell &amp; Scafell Pike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2921/14278945979_f9aeefc6de_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Sca Fell &amp; Scafell Pike" /></a></p>

<p>I descend via the Flat Slabs and head onwards to the Old Dungeon Ghyll Climber’s Bar.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14465578885" title="Flat Slabs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3885/14465578885_812eb60118_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Flat Slabs" /></a></p>

<p>A fine Ale, soup and a roll are consumed, and with not much enthusiasm I leave the fine establishment behind. My route takes me up to Stickle Tarn, where I count four other tents around the lake!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14485734013" title="Stickle Tarn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3884/14485734013_8bbd3a8927_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Stickle Tarn" /></a></p>

<p>It’s windy and I’m soon in my quilt after a hot meal. It is a fiercely windy night and past midnight a couple descends to the valley past me under my TrailStar. Rain sets in occasionally. I drift in and out of sleep, and with dawn I’m up. The Coleman gas canister is empty (after just 3 l of water boiled!) and so I can’t have my morning coffee. Up I go, forgoing the scramble I came for.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14378696112" title="Above Stickle Tarn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5040/14378696112_6157530f5f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Above Stickle Tarn" /></a></p>

<p>Drizzle and wind accompany me on my way to High Raise and onwards to Calf Crag, Gibson Knott and Helm Crag, before I descend to the village of Grasmere.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193578570" title="Cloudy by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2938/14193578570_7f313cd441_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Cloudy" /></a></p>

<p>I buy a new gas canister and fruits, have a coffee and soup and head up Grisedale Tarn. The weather improves and the sun breaks through.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14465582995" title="Arriba by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5474/14465582995_f52759df3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arriba" /></a></p>

<p>My plan to go on to Helvellyn and walk its Ridges is dropped in favour of a low camp. But the valleys are private land and I don’t feel like sneaking into one of the woods to pitch my TrailStar and so end up in the Youth Hostel in Patterdale. A hot shower is enjoyed, and a good sleep is had.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193489749" title="Looking up to Grisedale by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2939/14193489749_047e97d4e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Looking up to Grisedale" /></a></p>

<p>Breakfast on the sofa, packing with plenty of space, wall to wall sunshine awaiting me. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13948223152" title="That way by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2938/13948223152_b31fb818c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="That way" /></a></p>

<p>Up to Angletarn Pikes. A lovely hill with fine views all the way.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13948221232" title="Upwards by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7121/13948221232_2b2bbe2598_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Upwards" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14380144815" title="Lovely view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2915/14380144815_d36e8bc42c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lovely view" /></a></p>

<p>Angle Tarn is a wonderful place and would make a fine camping spot. Birds are swimming on its clear blue water, while the sun reflects in ripples as a slight breeze sweeps across it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193530658" title="Angle Tarn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3856/14193530658_46c3c33068_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Angle Tarn" /></a></p>

<p>The views from up here are magnificent, further enhenced by the superb weather. I walk with an open wind jacket and cuffs up, but soon decide it’s time to hike in my T-Shirt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193699467" title="Gate by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3837/14193699467_022eb5b942_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Gate" /></a></p>

<p>I take the faint path up Rest Dodd before heading down and up to The Knott. Time for coffee and Vitamin C in the sun, there’s no hurry anywhere.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14379174464" title="Coffee on The Knott by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2902/14379174464_06571c2c53_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Coffee on The Knott" /></a></p>

<p>I stroll onwards to the High Street where plenty of day hikers enjoy the great weather. I shortly ponder a stroll up and down the Riggindale Crag, but decide to head onwards to the Thornthwaite Crag. A large cairn marker (more a tower, really) spends shade that is welcomed in this hot weather.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193497129" title="Blue by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5231/14193497129_9eeb9496af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Blue" /></a></p>

<p>The impending ridge walk of Froswick, Ill Bell and Yoke has me smiling ear to ear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14379175414" title="Spikey by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5191/14379175414_3f63597556_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Spikey" /></a></p>

<p>Then water runs low and so I am looking out for water. Close to the Garburn Pass I find a gurgling stream and the Playtypuses are filled up and emptied right away. Tasty. So why not stay?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14380141145" title="Camp III by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2928/14380141145_b69ab58d1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Camp III" /></a></p>

<p>I do. It’s beautiful and I love the views - Windermere to the south, the high hills to the west, crags, grass and sheep to the north and east. I have a mighty fine evening up on the hill, and fall asleep under the stars.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13912268942" title="MLD TrailStar in the English Lake District. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2900/13912268942_8066e0cef6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="MLD TrailStar in the English Lake District." /></a></p>

<p>The next morning the weather is again on repeat: Blue sky and sunshine. I take it slow, enjoy the last bit outside, but am soon enough on the trail. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14380137475" title="Troutbeck Tongue by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3918/14380137475_5f5a6dc457_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Troutbeck Tongue" /></a></p>

<p>Then I arrive at Orrest Head, Tourists being delighted by the view to be had from here. And also I smile, even as know that this will be the last time I will lay my eyes on the hills of the Lake District, those fine small mountains whom I just traversed. And so I walk down to the railway station, happy to return in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14379173934" title="Orrest Head by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5496/14379173934_b7daa145f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Orrest Head" /></a></p>

<p>More photos on <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157644166894052/">Flickr</a>. <em>Follow along on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/">Google+</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lake District Traverse: Part I]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html"/>
    <updated>2014-05-22T12:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Lake District is one of England’s most scenic National Parks, with steep hills, lush green valleys, glittering lakes and inviting Pubs. I traversed this beautiful area from Ravenglass to Windermere in a 125 km route and hiked up some of the most well-known mountains and camped at some beautiful sites.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057613217" title="On the hills by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2916/14057613217_6cf64400c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="On the hills" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>It’s funny to think that on the birthday of the website I started my Lake District hike. Funny, as English blogs were one of the inspirations to start this site, and on it’s fifth birthday I was setting off to backpack in one of the most popular National Parks in the UK.</em></p>

<p>The Lake District has long appealed to me, and with the help of <a href="http://www.visitengland.com/">Visit England</a> I was able to realize this trip. As I had six days for backpacking I early on decided that a traverse would be best to see as much as possible, and my list of things I’d like to see was long, as I explained in my “<a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/planning-a-trip-in-the-lake-district.html">Planning a Trip in the Lake District</a>” article. </p>

<p>So on Monday morning I left Manchester by train and arrived punctual at 10:55 o’clock in Ravenglass, where I meet <a href="http://stevenhorner.com/">Steven</a> and Traci who would join me for the first day. We had a quick lunch at the Café in the Railway Station and then set off towards the hills. Steven explained to me the system of paths in the UK - I still am baffled by it! - and soon we were hiking past cows to the Muncaster Castle. We passed it, eager to get to the hills, but before that a short stroll on the street was necessary. As someone from the continent the left side traffic was something to be well aware of, as you do everything just the other way around as you’d at home. The walk on the street was quickly done, and then it was off into the wild - or the swamp. For quite a bit we were searching for the path, which was marked on our maps, to Devoke Water, but in the end we just gave up, took an aim and just kept on walking. Surely enough, close to the lake we then happened upon a trail which we followed for a bit before a short break. I refilled my water bottles and we enjoyed the fine views over the lake. As we had still some bit to go we continued, following the path to Woodend and then up to Great Worm Crag. The mandatory first summit photo was taken, I made a few quick bolder moves and onwards to White How and Green Crag we continued.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057537858" title="Clouds and sheep by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2920/14057537858_705a68c7a4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Clouds and sheep" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057583230" title="Muncaster Castle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2915/14057583230_e73a1c193a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Muncaster Castle" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057607037" title="The English Road by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5541/14057607037_60f2fd8aa0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The English Road" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14240888771" title="Landscape I by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5073/14240888771_10db0ed9a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="561" alt="Landscape I" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14264374953" title="Here&#x27;s the path! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5192/14264374953_aa82ca27d9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="567" alt="Here&#x27;s the path!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14244197675" title="Devoke Water by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2919/14244197675_1b8b2bff86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Devoke Water" /></a></p>

<p>While there was a path marked down on my map, the reality looked different. Through a swamp, which has claimed the life of a sheep or two, we made it with even wetter feet to the foot of Harter Fell. The sun was shining, the full water bottles added a couple of kilograms of weight and so we started our ascent. Grazing sheep were gazing as we passed them by in what must have seemed like snail speed to them, but then, finally, we made it to a large “plateau” which lays a dozen of meters under the summit. We walked the last bit up to the Summit Marker and enjoyed the wide views: To the West lay the sea and the Isle of Man, a bit further to the north the southern tip of Scotland came into view, and to the north Sca Fell and Scafell Pike dominated the view and demanded attention. Further to the east Brown Pike, Dow Crag and the Old Man of Coniston could be seen. It was a magnificent place to be.</p>

<p>With plenty of space to pitch the TrailStars Traci and Steven pitched theirs on the plateau, while I went a bit further up between two large boulders. As the wind picked up we ate dinner together, enjoyed the sunset and rising moon, and had a Finnish dessert before hitting the hay. During the night the wind turned and was blowing well into my shelter. Not being amused I just took out a peg which practically closed the TrailStar, and a more calm nicht could be enjoyed. I was up with the sunrise (the sun still rising <em>“late”</em> back then) though the high wind demanded that I wear all my layers. We packed up and said our good byes, Steven &amp; Traci heading back to Eskdale while I set off to the west. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221053606" title="Up there? Really? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2899/14221053606_d48e1939b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Up there? Really?" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14243892084" title="Harter Fell view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5506/14243892084_3c6bda84c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Harter Fell view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14057561029" title="Dinner by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5577/14057561029_d94d9303c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dinner" /></a></p>

<p>Through the re-forested Hardknott Forest I made my way down as the sun was rising and promised a fine day. Down at the river I happened upon a Parking place with benches, which made for the perfect breakfast spot. I enjoyed the bird song and purl of the river, only once or twice interrupted by a passing car. Refilled with water I walked down the street, passing by the gorgeous houses in the valley. A mother who was carrying her daughter walked a horse to the meadow and greeted me with a smile, and it is easy to imagine how good life must be far off the beaten track between the hills. I hiked on, finding the sign and path which brought me on line with my first summit of the day. </p>

<p>After some backtracking and climbing fences I made it on the road to Walna Scar Road. This path is so wide that you three to four people could hike next to each other - but right now I was alone, just far off in the distance I could make out a few couples slowly making their way to the top. Along the Long House Gill stream the path climbed continuously up, and at the crossroad I sat down to have a zip of water and some nuts. A father and son couple was now following behind me. I packed up and continued, the summit of Brown Pike getting closer and closer. </p>

<p>As I reached the crossroad underneath the summit, the wind welcomed me. I said a <em>“Hiya”</em> greeting to the couple who arrived with me at the crossroad from the other side, and while the husband was looking into his Wainwright the wife set off towards Brown Pike. I had a quick look across the valley and could see dozens of people on the Old Man and this side, so I continued. As I hiked from Buck Pike to Dow Crag two dayhikers and their dog emerged from the south rake, a scramble I had intended to do but as it would have meant walking down and then scrambling up again, I decided to leave it for the time being. However, seeing those two emerge, elated, I was a bit disappointed that I did not have the time to do this fine scramble. </p>

<p>Dow Crag was busy with families eating a summit lunch (in T-shirts and shorts in the blazing wind, nonetheless), and so I continued. The Old Man of Consiton was still so busy, with plenty of people arriving and leaving. I took in the view from the summit cairn, and then decided it’s time to go on. After Swirl How it got eerily devoid of people, and I strolled on my own onwards to the Grey Friar. A fine summit with views on Crinkle Crags, Bow Fell, Sca Fell and Scafell Pike I sat down for some water, figs and dates, trying to make out the path to the valley. As I took off I followed a faint path, but soon I was walking on sheep trails down. I arrived in a muddy field amongst cows, between me and the street an insurmountable lake of wet cow dung. The cows looked on as I tried to avoid to step in their excrements, hoping from stone to a small green island of grass, but to no avail: As I reached the gate my shoes were covered in wet cow poop. At the road in Cockley Beck I sat down at the stream, tried to rinse and dry my socks, but the smell &amp; colour of cow poop was intending to stay. Barefoot, eating nuts, I observed an old couple who happily arrived back at their car. After they packed up they came over to offer me a ride up the pass - they must have seen that I intended to go that way - but I kindly said “No, thank you” and explained that I’d mess up their car with my wet &amp; dirty shoes. <em>“That’s no problem”</em> came the reply - an answer I least expected! I smiled and explained I prefer to walk, and thanked them again.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14244195805" title="Walna Scar Road by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5479/14244195805_ba9aa709dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Walna Scar Road" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221050576" title="Dow Crag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5319/14221050576_a2d817d37d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dow Crag" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221050166" title="The Old Man of Coniston by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5489/14221050166_7c850e257d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Old Man of Coniston" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14241982842" title="View from Grey Friar by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2897/14241982842_63f5179ca8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="View from Grey Friar" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221048576" title="Cockley Beck by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2918/14221048576_28bc655047_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Cockley Beck" /></a></p>

<p>After allowing my socks and shoes to dry a bit I slipped them back on and started the hike up Hardknott Pass road. Cars passing me smiled, and with some satisfaction I reached the top of the pass, from where I had a fine view on the Eskdale valley. I absolutely adore these views: Lush green fields speckled with white and black sheep, green forests, a blue river which meanders through the valley and lovely houses. I passed by the Roman Fort and walked on the road till I saw the sign up to Sca Fell. A family just arrived from the top, and with the clock being almost 17 they looked curiously as I hiked on. Now my plan was ambitious and I hoped to camp up on Sca Fell or at the Fox Tarn, though after almost 28 km hiked I decided to camp lower, in the vicinity of water, at a lovely camp spot. </p>

<p>I pitched the TrailStar, boiled water for food, tea &amp; dessert, and looked as a big, yellow moon was slowly rising at Hardknott Pass while the last cars of the day made their way up the street. </p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14243890524" title="Grazing sheep II by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2905/14243890524_ab1a31f65a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Grazing sheep II" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13982573296" title="Sign up Sca Fell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7383/13982573296_379bef8909_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sign up Sca Fell" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14243892344" title="Sca Fell camp at dusk by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2908/14243892344_c9ae90606b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sca Fell camp at dusk" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untold Trip Reports]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/untold-trip-reports.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T11:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/untold-trip-reports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Unsung heroes, untold stories. So much time outdoors, so little time to write about them.</em> <strong>These are the Untold Trip Reports.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9537611324/" title="Dusk by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7312/9537611324_1787dd85ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dusk" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="packrafting-in-ruunaa">Packrafting in Ruunaa</h2>

<p>I was just back from the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">OutDoor Fair</a> when I saddled two packs with packrafts on my shoulders to travel to Ruunaa, where I was teaching a packrafting course. It was a very wet weekend, though we laughed, paddled and hiked a lot. One more packrafting aficionado joined the tribe, eagerly waiting to acquire his own, taking it on future adventures on rivers and lakes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715313/" title="Wet by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/9559715313_228cbc97ab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wet" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9562508942/" title="Time to pick some berries by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/9562508942_5af0666233_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Time to pick some berries" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715473/" title="Water by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5532/9559715473_6d6f4ee7e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Water" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9559715389/" title="Fire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7314/9559715389_6c714de875_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="backpacking-in-seitseminen">Backpacking in Seitseminen</h2>

<p>Another course with three superb clients, we were backpacking for three days in the beautiful Seitseminen National Park and learned about ultralight skills and gear. Gathered mushrooms, swam in the lake, sat around the fire and slept warm in hammocks and quilts, while the sun shone down on our trail. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9519459009/" title="Ultralight camping by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3793/9519459009_f7441f5148_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Ultralight camping" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9537712134/" title="Mirror II by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/9537712134_1c135a66d0_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Mirror II" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9534948843/" title="UL Tenkara fly fishing setup by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2821/9534948843_b9483f1f44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="UL Tenkara fly fishing setup" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9534922329/" title="Ramaria flava by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5471/9534922329_a1b6a2e21f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Ramaria flava" /></a></p>

<h2 id="kungsleden">Kungsleden</h2>

<p>A failed trip is also a trip. After the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> I had an ambitious plan to ski a loop on the Kundgsleden, though as I took a fall while ice climbing where I injured my knee the skiing was just too painful, and so I returned after having skied 20 km on brand-new skis which I would have loved to take up some fjells. Alas, it was not meant to be, though I will return soon enough for a re-match.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571269176/" title="Dynafit Broad Peak by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7348/10571269176_24320b56c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dynafit Broad Peak" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571517553/" title="Shadowboxing I by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5485/10571517553_1cf154a314_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Shadowboxing I" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9129268734/" title="Khufu on the Kungsleden"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2850/9129268734_56263af54b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Kungsleden" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10571514423/" title="Dusk by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7335/10571514423_5fbb1fcc56_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dusk" /></a></p>

<h2 id="dayhikes--overnighters">Dayhikes &amp; Overnighters</h2>

<p>The largest amount of untold stories are the dozens of <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/destinations/WorldHeritageSites/kvarkenarchipelago/activities/Pages/Default.aspx">dayhikes</a> and overnighters here in the region. Plenty of great outdoor destinations around Vaasa, not only the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/a-family-hike-on-the-bodvattnet-runt.html">Kvarken Archipelago</a> which it counts to explore - by bike, packraft, on foot, and soon again on skis and snowshoes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410128705/" title="Dawn by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/10410128705_2ce65c655f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Dawn" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410103134/" title="Skis, carried. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3704/10410103134_a0acf19995_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Skis, carried." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9982464505/" title="Reflection. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2813/9982464505_bbbbcd925d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="909" alt="Reflection." /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8839376917/" title="052113_1264 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7307/8839376917_73a7be00b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="052113_1264" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632582072/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8389/8632582072_9c86a0a5ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p><em>These are the Untold Trip Reports, and there will be more of them in the future.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
