<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Vaasa | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/vaasa/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-06T15:58:33+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pack-Sail-Rafting in the Kvarken Archipelago]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/pack-sail-rafting-in-the-kvarken-archipelago.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T18:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/pack-sail-rafting-in-the-kvarken-archipelago</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pack-Sail-Rafting is the next evolutionary step for packrafting. <a href="http://valppaus.com/">Joni</a> and <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/m3t/sets/72157644771350449/">Marko</a> have been having fun packsailing (as it is also know) already since the spring and with Joni being currently in Pohjanmaa I took the opportunity to it try out when he asked me to join him on a packrafting trip in the Kvarken Archipelago.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/14786363612" title="Heading out with the wind by Joni Palomäki, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2923/14786363612_615c4308be_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Heading out with the wind" /></a>
© Photo Joni Palomäki</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Svedjehamn harbour is a 45 minute ride from Vaasa and was quickly picked as a starting point for our little Pack-Sail-Rafting trip. I’ve been here <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/kvarken-archipelago/">before</a> a few times, while it was the first time for Joni to be at this most distant point on the archipelago which can be reached by car. We paid for the parking ticket (2€ for 4h, though I doubt anyone checks) and headed off to the harbour. <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/">Packrafts</a> were inflated, gear stored, <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Safety/Anfibio-Buoy-Boy::499.html">Anfibio Buoy Boy Vests</a> put on and then we boarded our vessels.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14600378168" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3840/14600378168_0cd20936e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14600505917" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3899/14600505917_cb934ed46a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="789" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14787014975" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3857/14787014975_b4d6f8a28b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a></p>

<p>Joni had the <a href="http://www.windpaddle.com/cruiser_sail.htm">WindPaddle Cruiser Sail</a> attached to his Llama and we quickly saw that the <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Safety/Anfibio-Throwbag::415.html">Anfibio Throwbag</a> is a great multi-use item as it worked well as a towing-rope. There were two White-tailed Eagles making their rounds above us while the wind transported us in no time across the water. We stopped at one of the rocks protruding from the sea - which is very shallow in the Archipelago - and attached the <a href="http://www.welhonpesa.fi/tuote/2301/windpaddle-scout-malli-yksikoille">WindPaddle Sail</a> to my Yak. I got some quick instructions on its use and then I was off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14806861073" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2935/14806861073_8888452ae9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a></p>

<p>It was superb. I’ve never been that fast in my packraft without needing to do anything. Balancing the sail behind my head and keeping it in the wind while steering with the paddle I quickly reached the outer limits of the moraines that criss-cross the archipelago here. I stopped and waited for Joni, we had a look at the map &amp; clock to decide what to do next.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14783874171" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3883/14783874171_2bb78d94c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14783864891" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2940/14783864891_b70e651921_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/14806573763" title="Relaxed paddling while spotting White-tailes Eagles by Joni Palomäki, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5584/14806573763_8b589068a1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Relaxed paddling while spotting White-tailes Eagles" /></a>
© Photo Joni Palomäki</p>

<p>We switched the sail again to Joni’s Llama and took a bearing to the West, as much as the wind allowed. But as the wind did blow more to the north, Joni stashed the sail away after a while and we paddled onwards, west-wards. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14600497307" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5580/14600497307_c7690fe772_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/14600027780" title="Shallow waters is where packrafts excel in places like this - up close and personal by Joni Palomäki, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3922/14600027780_404d0540be_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Shallow waters is where packrafts excel in places like this - up close and personal" /></a>
© Photo Joni Palomäki</p>

<p>We crossed loads of shallow bays where the water wasn’t much deeper than 50 cm - often less. But with packrafts this wasn’t much of a problem - if you got stuck on a rock you just pushed yourself loose with some momentum &amp; were free again. We paddled until we were in a dead end &amp; then had the option to paddle around the ridge or cross it. We decided for the latter - that’s after all the beauty of packrafting, that you can just land at shore, shoulder your raft and walk onwards. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/14600027980" title="Crossing of one of the ridges ended up as a muddy wade through a bed of reeds and what not, while being chased by a flight of hungry horse flies - part of the game :) by Joni Palomäki, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3881/14600027980_0567d7110c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Crossing of one of the ridges ended up as a muddy wade through a bed of reeds and what not, while being chased by a flight of hungry horse flies - part of the game :)" /></a>
© Photo Joni Palomäki</p>

<p>It was a short hike along the beach and through very high reed with a high amount of horse flies, so we were happy as we reached the water again and could continue paddling, leaving the biting insects behind as fast as possible. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/14600074089" title="Untitled by Joni Palomäki, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2901/14600074089_2a00c670f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Untitled" /></a>
© Photo Joni Palomäki
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14600361029" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5563/14600361029_040fa6290d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a></p>

<p>We paddled between the moraines which made for nice, calm paddling. Just the final bit was in strong head wind, but thanks to the new design of the Alpacka packrafts which run so smooth and straight it wasn’t much of a problem. We arrived back in Svedjehamn after having paddled and sailed six kilometre which felt like just two - funny how distances on the water can be so deceiving. Back on terra firma we packed up as the sky was darkening and the thunderstorms which were forecast started to make themselves known. We packed the car, snapped some more photos and then were off back to Vaasa, where thick rain drops welcomed us. </p>

<p>It was a fun day out and a <a href="http://www.welhonpesa.fi/tuote/2301/windpaddle-scout-malli-yksikoille">WindPaddle Sail</a> is now high on my list. I’ve had it since last year on the radar as three Spaniards crossed Scotland by packraft with the WindPaddle Sails but dismissed it then, but trying one I think it’s an excellent way to efficiently travel by packraft - if the wind goes your way. Thanks Joni for letting me try it!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14600502357" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2939/14600502357_11c81be91c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14600371018" title="Pack-Sail-Rafting by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3902/14600371018_cd4202c791_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Pack-Sail-Rafting" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Last Day of Winter]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/last-day-of-winter.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-01T22:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/last-day-of-winter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The venerable overnighter has been modernised a few times in the last years: Two, three years ago they were called <a href="http://ryanjordan.com/blog/">24</a> adventures by Ryan, about two years ago Alastair started to call them <a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com/microadventures-3/">Microadventures</a>, and Aaron called them <a href="http://aaronteasdale.blogspot.com/">S24O</a> (Sub-24 hour Overnighter) somewhere in between. I went on one of these S24O-Microadventure-Overnighters on one of the last cold days in April.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631516475/" title="Sunset by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8262/8631516475_c299f19e4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sunset" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I kissed my wife and son Good Night, grabbed my ready-packed <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/packs/3400-porter-pack.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Porter</a>, skis attached to it, and walked the two kilometres to the nearby recreation area, Pilvilampi. The sun was just disappearing behind the trees as I arrived on skis at the frozen lake. I wanted to ski for some three to four kilometres to the other end of the lake, and pitch my shelter over there. </p>

<p>There are tracks on the lake, but we already had a wonderfully warm March and so much of the ice was in less-than-perfect skiing conditions. But my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">Madshus Glittertind MGV+</a> had good grip, and after a quick decision I just left the rubbish tracks behind and made my own ones. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632582072/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8389/8632582072_9c86a0a5ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p>It didn’t take me long to arrive at the place I wanted to pitch, and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hilleberg-brg.html">Hilleberg Anjan 2</a> I loaned from a friend came out. I practiced pitching it a few times before, so it was quickly up and ready. The thermometer was wandering in the direction of -10°C, and I enjoyed the evening, with the stars coming out, the sun fading away far in the west, and some Whopper Swans arriving from their winter quarters with their loud calls.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631552987/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8265/8631552987_36fa0a9212_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p>I took a few fun photos, and then heated up some water with the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Kueche/MSR-Reactor-1-0-L::601.html?refID=hif">MSR Reactor 1.0 l</a> for a late night hot chocolate. Even at -11°C it had the half litre of water boiling in less than three minutes, and inner warmth soon returned. Donning the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/rab-infinity-endurance-jacket/">Rab Infinity Endurance</a> down jacket I enjoyed the gorgeous night sky a bit more, knowing that soon the stars won’t be seen for the lack of darkness that we have here during the summer in the far north. Even if I planned to go to sleep early, it was past 23 o’clock as I crept into my quilt. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632700218/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8388/8632700218_9b72195ced_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Sonic Boom</strong>. Well, not quite. But minutes after I was tucked in, the ice decided to start it’s concert of booms and creaks. The mind plays funny things at those moments, and so I was wondering if I’ll be able to get out of the tent in case the ice under me should collapse and I’m engulfed by freezing cold water. Then the other side of the brain told me that I need not worry, as I’m either way camped close to a small island and hence the water couldn’t be deep under me. And either way, the ice is still over 20cm thick. So the concert continued throughout the night, and I drifted in and out of sleep. A loud <strong>boom</strong> had me sitting almost upright in the tent, and I welcomed the first rays of sunlight close to 7 o’clock.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631779593/" title="Cold morning by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8105/8631779593_b240668ae3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cold morning" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631612299/" title="Morning by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8544/8631612299_ca3d6a0c76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Morning" /></a></p>

<p>There was a bit of hoarfrost on my gear.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631603519/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8253/8631603519_e6a2ab33d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632731688/" title="Guyline by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8540/8632731688_8e40fcf26a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Guyline" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632720204/" title="Hoarfrost by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8540/8632720204_afc82f4d32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hoarfrost" /></a></p>

<p>I melted a bit of snow, put on my <a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/176-westcomb-switch-lt-hoody.html">NeoShell Westcomb Switch LT Hoody</a> and enjoyed the scenery with a cup of coffee in hand. A man who was well in is sixties skied past by me at 7.30 o’clock, at a speed which would have me made him guess 40 years younger. He looked surprised, as did I. <em>A quick lap before work, to stay healthy.</em> That’s the Nordic way.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631665847/" title="Breakfast by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8119/8631665847_1f4c43f5ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Breakfast" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631656205/" title="Hilleberg Anjan 2 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8112/8631656205_a3694af548_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Hilleberg Anjan 2" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631642589/" title="Toughstake by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8545/8631642589_c914f7ba42_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Toughstake" /></a></p>

<p>Then it was time to pack. The tent was rolled up and put back in its stuff sack, gear found it’s way into the HMG Porter, I switched from my wonderful <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/mukluk">Mukluks</a> into the skiing boots, stepped into the bindings and skied off towards civilization. The improvised skiing poles I left at the trail head, and was in time for a second coffee at home, having enjoyed the last cold night of winter before the snow and ice melted away just days later.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631464645/" title="Snow by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8125/8631464645_fc905e9739_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Snow" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8632601812/" title="Skiing Poles, improvised by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8109/8632601812_db099cf5e9_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Skiing Poles, improvised" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8631589275/" title="Way home by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8102/8631589275_72963e0640_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Way home" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[24 = 9]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/24-equals-9.html"/>
    <updated>2012-09-06T17:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/24-equals-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Somtimes trips don’t go according to plan.</em> That’s especially annoying if you don’t get to go on as much trips as you’d like to, and try to make each trip count. While I didn’t put myself under any stress to make this trip a success, outside influences made this 24 trip a lot shorter. <em>A trip report, sort of.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855697732/" title="Onwards by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8445/7855697732_49d53411aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Onwards" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Remember when <strong>24</strong> trips were all the rage? That’d be about two years ago, when Ryan Jordan coined the 24 term for overnighters. He wrote a few superb trip reports and thoughts on 24 trips, and many took up the idea of these short trips, which didn’t need days of planning, but you just grab your kit, food, a map and go to the trail head, hike for a few hours, pitch and spend a fine night outside, before heading back the next morning. The idea is still as great as back then, because just getting away for a few hours, going outdoors, can be enough to recharge your batteries for normal life. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855691676/" title="Lingon berries are ripe by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8428/7855691676_53c81ae7ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lingon berries are ripe" /></a></p>

<p>With an eleven month old baby son and a house renovation which we mightly underestimated, I was delighted as my wife gave me an OK for an overnighter. “<em>Be back before noon on Saturday, so we can get some Raspberries from the market.</em>” was the only condition. Spending eight plus hours working on my house Monday to Friday for four months already is taxing, and going outdoors is for me a good way to recharge and get ready for more of it. </p>

<p>I visited the supermarket after few hours at work to grab some torillas and salami for lunch and snacking, as well as my new favourite trail snack, Honey Roasted Nuts. Back at home I went to pack my <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com/">Porcelain Rocket frame packs</a>, threw a 3 litre reservoir into my <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-raptor-18-hydration-pack-1100cu-in">Osprey Raptor 18</a> and after my son was asleep, taking his afternoon nap, I kissed my wife good bye and went to dress up my bike in its fine garments. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938380460/" title="Bicycle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8457/7938380460_cff51c9186_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bicycle" /></a></p>

<p>Where to go? I decided to visit the island of Köklot, part of the Kvarken Archipelago, Finland’s only UNESCO Natural World Heritage Site. I have visited the area in the past, and decided, that while riding to the main island which I have seen before, this little island on the site would be more interesting. A small beach, around 30 km from Vaasa, was were I planned to spend the night.</p>

<p>As riding on highways isn’t my favourite way to travel, I drove along backroads along the coast. Backroads in Finland are pretty good to cover distance, as you encounter minimum traffic. The scenery is dotted with summer cottages, though some are more like proper houses, and through the trees I glimpsed here and there the Baltic Sea. As I reached the end of the road I took a turn into the forest, where I found a trail which followed the power line. Along the trail, which was only just suited to riding, lingon berries and mushrooms were ripe for the taking. To my surprise, still a lot of mosquitos were around, and I made a happy mental note that it was smart that I took the mosquito headnet. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938444236/"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8310/7938444236_e90a5726ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" /></a></p>

<p>After a bit of bushwacking I finally reached the forest road I aimed for, and soon I was making good speed again. Then it didn’t take long to reach the highway, though fortunately I only needed to share the road a few hundred meters with the moronic car drivers, racing past me, until I made it to a cycle lane next to the street. From here it was smooth riding till the Raippaluoto bridge, Finland’s longest bridge. I drove a bit onto it, for the view, before I turned back. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938459112/" title="Speed limit by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8308/7938459112_b5e427dbe5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Speed limit" /></a></p>

<p>A small break at a rather well-equipped parking lot, where I picked some raspberries, followed. I was less than two hours on the road, and already covered some good distance. That the weather wasn’t very inspiring didn’t bother me too much, these various shades of grey had their own charme, and I was in good hopes that there would be a nice sunset and -rise to enjoy. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7857951104/" title="Raippaluoto bridge by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8447/7857951104_7ab11f7701_b.jpg" width="1024" height="601" alt="Raippaluoto bridge" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938787812/" title="Organic vs. Death by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8042/7938787812_7d9e6fb964_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Organic vs. Death" /></a></p>

<p>I cycled back to the road which would take me to Köklot. To my surprise there was a lot of traffic on it, and it being a side road the drivers seemed to even get more idiotic in terms of how fast they went. I was pondering what would be the most effective way to educate these lunatics in their cars, but ended up wondering if there are mobile EMP weapons which could take out cars in a radius of several hundred meters around me. That’d ensure that none but the oldest cars would go off coming close to me, and I would be safe from racing drivers [If someone needs an Alpha/ Beta Tester for EMP weapons for cyclists, I’m available].</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938768418/" title="Brännved by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8448/7938768418_1d8465731b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Brännved" /></a></p>

<p>While the road was scenic, I was happy to reach the beach I aimed for. It was still plenty early, and it wouldn’t be dark till 22 o’clock. I drove down and was delighted to find such a fine beach all to myself, well, maybe it wasn’t such a surprise as it started to rain. I put on my Rab Pulse and took shelter at one of the dressing cabins, while putting my <a href="http://youtu.be/Pj8sfJ2k7Yo">stove</a> on to boil some water for a hot cup of cappuciono and dinner. The clouds were doing their thing in the sky, while I carved myself a spoon, which I left at home to safe weight. I was happy.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s a good trade-off to take a 42 gram knife instead of a 18 gram spoon -the knife is multi-purpose!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>After dinner I decided to take a look at Köklot, the tiny settlement a few more kilometers down the road; conveniently the rain stopped, too. Also, while the beach was beautiful, it was a tad too close for my taste to the street and was facing south, which meant I might not see that sunrise I hoped for. Back on the street, all drivers finally seemed to have reached the places which they were in such a hurry to reach.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7938803200/" title="Road to Köklot by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8180/7938803200_db405b6fe1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Road to Köklot" /></a></p>

<p>I passed a small fishing harbour, and a gorgeous sunset was on display at the horizon. Rain could be seen going north, and it was a pretty sight, with a few sailing boats out on the sea. I continued and drove into Köklot, where warm yellow light came through windows, but no one was to be seen on the street. Riding down a street brought me to an east facing shore, but all possible pitches were on someones land, so off limit. </p>

<p>I continued through the settlement for a bit, in the hope that there’d be some nice place somewhere close to the east-facing shore to pitch my tarp, but no luck. The sun now already set it was time to switch on my <a href="http://www.knog.com.au/gear-lights/boomer-rechargeable.phps">Knog Boomer USB lights</a> just in case one of those drivers decided to go out again for a ride, and cycled the few kilometers back to the beach.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855481330/" title="Pimpin' at the beach by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8429/7855481330_49fdb544f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Pimpin' at the beach" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855623042/" title="Cloudporn by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8298/7855623042_1240cc747c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Cloudporn" /></a></p>

<p>Back at the beach I looked for good spots to camp. Off into the forest I went, though between boulders large and small - these islands being created by the last ice age, they’re all rock - I didn’t find anything. Close to the beach there was a tiny patch of grass, just big enough, but it was at the end of the road, and I like my camps a tad more sheltered. On the sandy beach then I found one good spot. I put on my <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fmountain-hardwear-nitrous-down-jacket-mens">Mountain Hardwear Nitrous Down Jacket</a> and started to unpack, as I heard some hubbub from the street. </p>

<p>Hmmm. I waited, and shortly after a guy with a reindeer skin and some booze appeared. He walked straight to the shore, where he stood still, looking out on the water. Engine noise appeared, and a boat entered the bay, riding up to the shore. Reindeer man jumped in, and off they went. <em>Well, that was lucky</em>, I thought.</p>

<p>Or not. I just got the tarp out of the handlebar pack when a car drove down to the shore. Well, swell. It was ten o’clock by now, I was ready for bed, but not with a bunch of people coming to party where I planned to camp. Somehow that possibility didn’t even cross my mind as I picked this beach as a camping spot, though in hindsight it was obvious that also others might find this Friday evening a good time to go partying at <em>this beach</em>, which was so conveniently close located to the street.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I packed up in the dusk, and headed back up to the street, leaving the party beach behind. I decided to look for a place to camp on the road back to Vaasa, but was not very optimistic.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855660892/" title="Rain by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8439/7855660892_9de34ce63b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rain" /></a></p>

<p>A few turns went of the main street which I drove up just a few hours earlier, but most were leading to summer cottages, which meant they were off limit. Those two that I went down were either un-safe - the noise of heavy forest machinery rang through the forest, explaining the deep tracks I drove through - or so hard and bumpy that even the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Ftherm-a-rest-neoair-xtherm-sleeping-pad">NeoAir XTherm</a> I brought would not be enough to give me a comfortable sleep. An hour and 15 km later I was back at the highway to Vaasa, and another hour and another 15 km later I was just a bit past midnight back at home. My 24 trip was just a bit over nine hours.</p>

<p>While I was a bit disappointed by not sleeping outside - I looked forward to the sound of rain on my tarp and the sunrise - it was a fine ride. I cycled some 70 km, saw some nice places, and was exploring my new surroundings. I also learned to not pick camp places which are too close to a street - something to remember on my next 24 trip, which is just around the corner!</p>

<p><strong>Have you had failed trips? Tell us - what went wrong, and why? What lessons did you learn?</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
