<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cottage manufacturers | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/cottage-manufacturers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-27T13:15:01+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Gear from the Cottages 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T22:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What new gear can you expect to see from the ultralight cottages in 2015? We have talked with our sources and deliver you the lightest and finest new gear for 2015!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16240736587" title="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7455/16240736587_ee1a0957b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="685" alt="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Remember your roots,</strong> they say. Our roots are in ultralight backpacking. We have spread the gospel about ultralight backpacking since a long time, have <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/interviews/">interviewed cottage manufacturers</a> and used a lot of ultralight kit on our hikes and treks. And even when I nowadays am attending the big outdoor trade fairs like <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/ispo-news-2014.html">ISPO</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor</a>, it’s the new gear from the cottages that I am most excited about. And so <a href="http://hrxxlight.com">Benjamin</a> and me again set out to ask Cottage Manufacturers about the new gear they have been developing, prototyping and testing in the last months and are now ready to release to you. So here we are, and we wish you a lot of fun checking out the <strong>New Gear from the Cottages 2015</strong>!</p>

<p><em>You have a cottage and should be on this list with your new gear? <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Email me</a> and I’ll add you!</em> </p>

<h2 id="locus-gear">Locus Gear</h2>

<p>Jotaro and the team at <a href="http://locusgear.com">Locus Gear</a> have been dreaming big. Big in two ways: A ultralight, breathable dome tent for the winter mountains and a massive 8 Person shelter. The Djedi eVent Dome Shelter sleeps 2 persons, is 2,3 m long and 1,3 m wide with a height of 1 m and will tip the scales at 1,2 kg with the poles included. It looks like a spacious mountain shelter and being made from eVent you know it will be breathable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425702462" title="Locus Gear Djedi eVent Dome by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7321/16425702462_abcb9f94df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Locus Gear Djedi eVent Dome" /></a></p>

<p>I dubbed it the “Party Tent” as I saw the Prototype Photos on the Locus Gear Instagram stream and I still think that the Soris Sil Shelter could be that. Or a great group tent for scouts, a family with kids, or a a handful of hiking buddies. It can sleep six to eight persons and is pitched with two poles - and it is huge: 6 m long, 3 m wide and 1,8 m high. But it only weighs in at 1,7 kg (without poles, stakes and extra guylines) which, if broken down on the number of people it can sleep, is very light (283 g per person if there’s six in it!).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239236370" title="Locus Gear Soris Sil Shelter 149 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7458/16239236370_73bae29845_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Soris Sil Shelter 149" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hanchor">Hanchor</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.hanchor.com/">Hanchor</a> releases two new backpacks in 2015 which are currently in the prototyping stage. The Marble is a 65 l roll-top closure pack that will weigh around 918 g (or 1032 g with aluminum stays). Made from XPac vx07 it has a backpanel that allows for some ventilation. Horizontal seams of the Marble are folded to the upper side to make it more waterproof though they are not seam taped, while the seam between bottom panel and the body are seam taped with wide webbing from the outside to prevent water coming in. It can carry a lot of gear, too: It has one large Kangaroo pocket, 2 side pockets, 2 hip pockets and 2 daisy chains for attaching shock cord, accessories and gear. The two aluminum stays are removable, as is the padded hip belt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15804131964" title="Hanchor Marble by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8651/15804131964_ca206f9d87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hanchor Marble" /></a></p>

<p>The Chert on the other hand is a 51 l pack that will be made from XPac wx20 and has a removable frame pad and stays which will weigh in at 847 g or 961 g with the aluminum stays. It also comes with a lot of features: A roll top closure, 2 daisy chains for shock cord, accessories and gear, 2 removable aluminum stays, a removable, padded hip belt, 4 gear loops and straps and buckles for attaching ice axes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238994458" title="Hanchor Chert by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/16238994458_9a3d5dfa5e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hanchor Chert" /></a></p>

<p>The guys at Hanchor are also working on a new version of their patents-pending, built-in chock sock chalk bag. The opening of the built in chalk sock is constructed with a circular plastic ring that makes it super easy to fill in the chalk and the amount of chalk coming out is enhanced. If you can’t wait for it to come out, have a look at their <a href="http://www.hanchor.com/products/SUL%20Series/Steam_drawstring_backpack?locale=en">STEAM Cuben drawstring pack</a> which came out last December.</p>

<h2 id="porcelain-rocket">Porcelain Rocket</h2>

<p>The big news from <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com">Porcelain Rocket</a> is that they just opened a Workshop in the USA which will be manufacturing their most popular items in the most popular colours, decreasing lead times and making shipping within the States easier. There’s still the option for the custom gear you can dream up, with the usual lead times =)</p>

<p>New this years is the MCA Handlebar System which replaces the PR Mission Control as their sole handlebar offering. It is easier to use, accepts any commercial drybag in the 5 - 15 l range, is lighter and works with drop bars. It consists of a simple series of nylon webbing straps mounted to a rubberized fabric plate which will keep everything organized and tidy. The drybag loads hassle-free from the front and comes with the accessory pouch which is easy to attach &amp; detach. The whole set sans drybag weighs in at 284 g and is made from 500D Cordura and now available.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/53243955@N05/16327109566" title="Porcelain Rocket &quot;MCA&quot; by Sim Works, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7287/16327109566_29bd105424_b.jpg" width="900" height="900" alt="Porcelain Rocket &quot;MCA&quot;" /></a>
© Sim Works, used with Permission</p>

<p>You might have seen the custom-made PR Panniers in the past, which where probably what has led to the development of the Micro Panniers. They’re intended as an auxiliary to the other gear systems for more volume on longer tours and allow you to get rid of your Ortlieb panniers and invest into a pair of these. They attach to most popular racks on the market including fatbike-specific racks, and are made from 500D &amp; 1000D Cordura with a weight of 340 g per pannier. You don’t need to wait to get these, either, as they’re available now and cost $250 CAD for a set of two.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/53243955@N05/16350764831" title="Porcelain Rocket &quot;Micro Panniers&quot; by Sim Works, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7349/16350764831_46d48677a9_b.jpg" width="900" height="900" alt="Porcelain Rocket &quot;Micro Panniers&quot;" /></a>
© Sim Works, used with Permission</p>

<h2 id="mountain-laurel-designs">Mountain Laurel Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> has updated the Burn, Prophet, Exodus and Ark. They now come with hybrid solid/ mesh outside pockets which was done after research on the areas where mesh pockets wear or snag in brush - those parts are now solid Dyneema X. Also the side pocket’s front edges are solid and the bottom of the large rear pocket is solid, while the large mesh holes allows faster drying times. The 2015 packs also come with improved hardware and webbing: The 10 mm and 15 mm buckles MLD now uses are twice as strong as the 25/ 30 mm buckles of the past and the narrower webbing is a lot lighter without being thin and fragile. </p>

<p>MLD continues to uses their tried &amp; tested Dyneema X fabric, which has the highest strength and is much better than the weaker Robic fabric and regular ripstop nylons that some other manufacturers use. The reason for cheaper fabrics like Robic is obvious: It’s just $3 a yard - versus $25 a yard for DXG! I imagine you’re a gear freak if your following this blog, so you’ll appreciate this little nugget Ron shared: </p>

<p><em>Interestingly, the white Dyneema ripstop threads that makes the Dyneema X so recognizable and known for the highest quality has lead to some pack makers now using regular nylon woven with a plain white nylon thread ripstop pattern (no Dyneema in the weave at all) to look like it is Dyneema X ripstop!</em></p>

<p>So the next time you’re shopping for a pack, make sure to read the material descriptions well! Right, onwards to the new gear.  MLD has replaced the Newt with a small and ultra clean and simple pack code named Core, and all backpacks will be available in the new Wasabi Green and the signature MLD Stealth Gray colours, with a shipping date of Mid-February.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426661665" title="MLD Corepack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7400/16426661665_d61f16733b_b.jpg" width="720" height="918" alt="MLD Corepack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806623933" title="MLD Wasabi Exodus by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8615/15806623933_065e5e7684_b.jpg" width="720" height="907" alt="MLD Wasabi Exodus" /></a></p>

<p>Also coming from MLD in 2015 is an Apex Balaclavas in three sizes, <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?products_id=222">Cuben Packing Cubes</a> for the lightweight traveller and Size Small eVENT Rain Mitts, while all 2015 Mids now use the stronger 10 mm buckles &amp; the SuperLight bivys use the new Mountain 10d fabric and nicer nickel zip pulls. The Superlight Bivy Duo is already available and additional sizes of the <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=47&amp;products_id=127">PyraMid InnerNets</a> are on the website.</p>

<h2 id="nature-base">Nature-Base</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.naturebase.de/">Nature-Base</a> from Germany has several products on offer which are interesting for the ultralight winter backpacker. Their <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/pulka">Folding Pulka</a> has been improved and now can be ordered with a few options like skids, a stiffening rail and a pack sack. It’s a great option for lightweight ski and snow-shoe hikes where you might want to pull your kit instead of carrying it most of the time.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16424876091" title="Nature-Base UL Pulka by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8627/16424876091_61b77fc790_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Nature-Base UL Pulka" /></a></p>

<p>Great looking is the EtaProof 110g/m² <a href="http://www.naturebase.de/shop/ul_weste">Vest</a> which tips the scales at 130 g in Size L! The material is windproof and water-resistant which makes it ideal for your skiing adventures on the fjells, while it has a hood that also protects your head. EtaProof is a material with great environmental credentials, and all Nature-Base garments can be fully customized.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238993008" title="Nature-Base UL Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8661/16238993008_43813e7247_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Nature-Base UL Vest" /></a></p>

<h2 id="waldschneider">Waldschneider</h2>

<p><a href="">Waldschneider</a> is a new cottage in stealth mode that will launch in the summer 2015. Based in Germany they have been working since a couple of years on different shelter designs, from Tarps to Pyramids and Inners, as well as bivy bags and bathtub floors. You can check out some of their work here: <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/1643-solo-pyramide/page-2#entry28601">Trollhaus 1</a>, <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/2296-und-noch-ein-lavvu/">Laavu</a> and <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/983-nur-ein-tarp/page-2#entry30186">Sägewerk 2</a>. When they have launched their webshop you’ll hear it here first =)</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/16078382599" title="014 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8643/16078382599_0970a80c30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="014" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/16263679582" title="010 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7538/16263679582_169cfda566_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="010" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/87680147@N03/14463223102" title="001 by K. Andreas, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2902/14463223102_c7eb32716c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="001" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hyperlite-mountain-gear">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> has a lot of news coming in 2015 - though keeps its card close to their chest. Coming soon is their 100% Woven Dyneema Canyoneering Pack which you might already have spotted on their Social Media outlets. There are also inserts for the Ultamid 2 and Ultamid 4 coming, Chalk Bags for climbing, Throw Bags for packrafting and several other items. Right now <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-of-hyperlite-mountain-gear-two-years-on.html">Mike</a> and his team are working on getting inventory to be built up, so expect some of these items to be available soon!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16400660386" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Canyoneering Pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8619/16400660386_9b7eaf759e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Canyoneering Pack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="packrafting-store">Packrafting Store</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de">Packrafting Store</a> helps in 2015 even more people to enjoy packrafting. They will start to offer some alternative Packrafts in the familiar shape, from a reasonable material (TPU), a good construction, slightly heavier, less varied (= less colors etc.) and <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Packrafts/Nortik-Trekraft-no-deck::598.html">more affordable</a>. There will be also superlight and high performance packrafts available later this spring, but the Classic Alpacka Rafts will remain their prime product. </p>

<p>You’ll also be able to shop for a new paddle from them this year or build your own. There’s four options:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Anfibio Ultimate, a full Carbon Packraft Paddle, 730 g, 5 pieces, fully adjustable (length/angle), stiff and tough at 335€</li>
  <li>Anfibio Smash is the Whitewater Packraft Paddle, 1025 g, 4 pieces, rigid carbon shaft, full size blades, a real “smasher” 209€</li>
  <li>Anfibio Vertex is their well-loved combi paddle (Vertex multi) in a classic version (double blade), fine shaft and very reasonable specs (920 g/ 129€)</li>
  <li>Or make your own webbed paddle with the Shearwater DIY kits. Webbs, rods &amp; clamp shell are provide. Find your shaft (in the garage or in the forest) and follow the instructions (300 g/ 69€)</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425701182" title="Packrafting Store Paddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7282/16425701182_e436981b4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packrafting Store Paddle" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806595653" title="Anfibio Shearwater Paddle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8612/15806595653_19b14b066b_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Shearwater Paddle" /></a></p>

<p>The Anfibio Multibag come snow in 60 l and in black, selling for 39€. Also the Anfibio Buoy Boy grows up in Size and now will be available in XL (in black), gets pockets and secured inflation tubes for 89€. The Anfibio Packsuit gets enhanced materials and will be lighter (~100 g per suit), more breathable (25.000 g/m2/24h), softer (better packing) but retains its robustness and price! The fabric also now is Bluesign certificated (environmentally friendly). And as usually each suit can be tailored - That’s cottage style! Also new neoprene gloves, a lightweight whitewater PFD and other accessories as well as courses on the river Soca in Slovenia are coming, and most of this sweet gear will be launched on their 3rd anniversary on February 15th. Check their website then or subscribe to the <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/newsletter.php?language=en">Newsletter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426633735" title="Anfibio Vest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/16426633735_23a6f0bd9c_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Vest" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16240402769" title="Anfibio Multibag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8668/16240402769_bbd00aea0b_b.jpg" width="1000" height="665" alt="Anfibio Multibag" /></a></p>

<h2 id="as-tucas">As Tucas</h2>

<p><a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a> introduces the new schoeller®-ftc fabric with ecorepel® finish this year to their offerings. It’s not just a lighter fabric at 28 g/m2, it is also stronger, more breathable and softer to the skin than any other fabric they have seen so far. Their quilts, insulated &amp; windproof garments are being upgraded to this new fabric, which I find rather exciting. </p>

<p>Their collection of quilts just was expanded with a wearable quilt: the Sestrals 2 Poncho. It features an insulated collar, which they think is more efficient and elegant than the simpler slit designs. Marco expects it will become the cornerstone of those who are looking for a truly versatile sleeping system that also doubles as a insulation garment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806594903" title="As Tucas Sestrals 2 Poncho by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7377/15806594903_e65805e35a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Sestrals 2 Poncho" /></a></p>

<p>As Tucas enters in 2015 the waterproofs market with two new ultralight pants: the Otal Pants made with a 2,5 layer WPB fabric and the Acher Pants made with WPB Cuben fiber. Starting at 120 &amp; 85 grams respectively they are really light but don’t skimp on essential features like an elasticated waist and adjustable cuffs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238993098" title="As Tucas Otal Acher Pants by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/16238993098_f1c454c4e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Otal Acher Pants" /></a></p>

<p>Marco is very busy designing and testing new products, too: The Zilindro 2 collection of base layers made from a new grid fabric by Eschler is almost ready, a Sestrals 2 insulated bivy is under development, and their down quilts are coming soon, too! </p>

<h2 id="tarptent">Tarptent</h2>

<p>Henry has been busy at <a href="http://www.tarptent.com/">Tarptent</a>, redesigning the popular Contrail which is available from February onwards as the ProTrail. It includes all the feedback Tarptent has received over the years since they introduced the Contrail in 2006.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16426661605" title="Tarprent Proshelter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8674/16426661605_09c54b282d_o.jpg" width="640" height="360" alt="Tarprent Proshelter" /></a></p>

<p>Here’s a short statement from Henry on Cuben Fibre: <em>We receive our share of requests for cuben fiber products from the die-hards but have opted not to go that route due to the extreme cost. I have always prided myself on producing lightweight shelters that are also affordable and unfortunately cuben just isn’t. I understand that there are people who are willing to pay but if we’re going to do a product it has to pass the “would Henry buy it?” test and at the price of cuben (and the labor involved in hand seam-taping all the seams) the answer is no. I would very much love to move to lighter fabrics but is has to make cost/ benefit sense.</em> So for a Cuben Tarptent to become a reality CubicTech would need to drop their prices, which they as a Monopolist probably aren’t likely to do just yet. </p>

<h2 id="yama-mountain-gear">YAMA Mountain Gear</h2>

<p>Do you like the opener pic at the far top of this article? Because I do. It says freedom and ultralight to me. I think <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/interview-gen-shimizu-from-alpinlite-gear.html">Gen</a> from <a href="http://www.yamamountaingear.com">YAMA Mountain Gear</a> hopefully thinks the same, and maybe it even where some of the ideas he had in mind when he designed the <a href="http://www.yamamountaingear.com/swiftline-2P/">Swiftline Tent</a>, a sub 1 kilo, 2-person, side-entry tent. The versatile new design lets users roll up the walls in nice weather to enjoy bug-free views, while two unobstructed entrances make entry &amp; exit a breeze with a large vestibule that keeps your gear protected and out of the way.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15806594923" title="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7338/15806594923_3267baebdd_o.jpg" width="1200" height="803" alt="YAMA Mountain Gear Swiftline 2P" /></a></p>

<p>What I also like about YAMA is that they help thru-hikers. In 2015 they welcome five aspiring Pacific Crest Trail thru-hikers to the second year of their <a href="http://mYAMAdventure.com">mYAMAdventure program</a>. The program’s team of mentors is currently helping the 2015 hikers prepare for their upcoming hikes, which will also benefit the Pacific Crest Trail Association. It’s definitely something worth checking out if you plan to hike the PCT!</p>

<h2 id="katabatic-gear">Katabatic Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://katabaticgear.com">Katabatic Gear</a> has released three <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/category/backpacks/">backpacks</a> in 2014 will appeal to both the lightweight and traditional crowds, because they do not sacrifice function, comfort or design while shedding weight from your shoulders. All packs are Made in Colorado, and here’s a quick look at the three packs: </p>

<p>The Artemis is a lightweight, durable pack with 55 l Volume. It’s made from durable 420D nylon fabrics throughout with a Dual Density, Ventilated Framesheet with a removable Aluminum Stay. The ribbed and perforated backpanel provides airflow while the stretch side pockets expand to accommodate loads while keeping pockets low profile when empty. The large zippered front pocket allows for easy access and the stretch woven hipbelt pockets with have an inner key clip. Finally, dual hydration ports ensure you can keep hydrated on the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16400660046" title="Katabatic Gear Artemis 55 Quarter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7336/16400660046_eb5f583b1e_o.jpg" width="475" height="606" alt="Katabatic Gear Artemis 55 Quarter" /></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/helios-40-backpack/">Helios</a> is similar in design to the Artemis, but focuses more on saving weight. It is made from a lightweight Cuben Fiber laminate which delivers exceptional strength for it’s weight. The woven polyester face fabric gives it additional abrasion resistance and seam strength. The Helios features all of the same design elements as the Artemis, above except that the front pocket is zipper free and uses durable stretch panels. It is currently available in 40 and 55 liter volumes, with the 40 l version tipping the scales at around 850 g in Size Medium.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16424876241" title="Katabatic Gear Helios 55 Quarter by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8635/16424876241_4b8ef522a3_o.jpg" width="470" height="594" alt="Katabatic Gear Helios 55 Quarter" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, the Eos is their 30 l lightweight, durable alpine climbing pack. Made from the same durable and water resistant fabric as the Artemis it is designed with climbing and ski-mountaineering in mind. The compression straps allow for carrying skis while the front daisy chain and bungee securely carry ice tools and crampons. The webbing waist belt, compression straps, ice tool bungee, and aluminum stay can be removed when not needed - saving weight when you wanna go really fast &amp; light, but the padded bottom adds durability while carrying a climbing rack. The extension collar expands capacity to 39 l and the zippered inner security pocket with key hook stores your wallet and keys while you’re climbing your Dawn Wall. Finally, major seams are sewn with Dyneema thread for maximum seam strength. Expect this pack to last!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16425700432" title="Katabatic Gear Eos 30 Tool by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7403/16425700432_3234424f01_o.jpg" width="466" height="554" alt="Katabatic Gear Eos 30 Tool" /></a></p>

<h2 id="yamatomichi">YAMATOMICHI</h2>

<p><a href="http://yamatomichi.com">YAMATOMICHI</a> is also one of the fine Japanese cottages which add style to the ultralight + functionality equation. Right now in the prototyping stage are their YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap, the U.L.Backpack No.3 and their 5-Pockets Long pants. Here’s a couple of photos to get you curious, with the gear coming out in March.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239235120" title="YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7365/16239235120_a5f60764ca_o.jpg" width="640" height="640" alt="YAMATOMICHI Stretch Mesh Cap" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16239235200" title="YAMATOMICHI U.L.Backpack No.3 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7300/16239235200_e90cae49b8_o.jpg" width="640" height="640" alt="YAMATOMICHI U.L.Backpack No.3" /></a></p>

<h2 id="terra-rosa-gear">Terra Rosa Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.terrarosagear.com">Terra Rosa Gear</a> is teaming up with Australian DIY supplier and hammock maker <a href="http://www.tiergear.com.au">Tier Gear</a> for a hammock tarp. It will be available as a package with the Tier Gear hammock shortly.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15812036024" title="TRG Tarp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7404/15812036024_7300e9bf2e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="TRG Tarp" /></a></p>

<h2 id="underground-quilts">Underground Quilts</h2>

<p><a href="http://undergroundquilts.com/">Underground Quilts</a> has several new items coming in 2015. Just a month ago they released their <a href="http://undergroundquilts.com/renegade/default.html">RENEGADE TQ</a>. The cold weather quilt uses a combination of vertical and horizontal chambers and can be made with your choice of HyperDRY 800/ 850 fillpower down. The quilt is fully customizable so you can get the quilt of your dreams. Underground Quilts also now offers a 10d fabric option for the inner shell on their top and bottom quilts and 20d fabrics for their our tarps - going lighter!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16429141215" title="RENEGADE TQ by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8659/16429141215_4733bfa2f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="RENEGADE TQ" /></a></p>

<h2 id="flat-cat-gear">Flat Cat Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flatcatgear.com">Flat Cat Gear</a> has a new website! Besides that they offer a trio of DIY titanium Stove kits which should be interesting for the MYOG girls and guys out there: </p>

<ul>
  <li>The Epicurean Titanium UL 15 is designed for use with Esbit and will burn up to 50-60 minutes</li>
  <li>The Focus Fire 14 in Titanium is designed to burn Esbit efficiently, one 14 gram tablet can bring 4 cups of 70F water up to 200F</li>
  <li>The new TiLight stove is a tea light replacement stove and weighs 2,84 g</li>
</ul>

<p>They are pre-assembled and you do the final sanding and folding, and cost $10 in the USA and $15 Internationally.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16243283067" title="Flat Cat Gear Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/16243283067_4a53feef8e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="617" alt="Flat Cat Gear Website" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15804132074" title="Flat Cat Gear  Flight by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8584/15804132074_ab3b89bcfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="Flat Cat Gear  Flight" /></a></p>

<h2 id="zpacks">ZPacks</h2>

<p><a href="http://zpacks.com">ZPacks</a> has a few things coming soon, like a synthetic insulated jacket. It will be similar to their <a href="http://zpacks.com/accessories/wind_shell.shtml">wind shell</a> but with Climashield insulation. ZPacks has the insulation in stock and have a prototype which right now is out on the trail, but it needs some work on the patterns. Joe and his team also just got Dyneema X Gridstop fabric in stock and a prototyp Arc Blast and Arc Zip backpacks are being tested right now - expect some photos later this week. Finally Joe is working in a Dyneema pack that can handle 35-40 lbs. There will be some changes to their frame system and more padding on the belt and straps . again, a prototyp is being tested as I write this, so expect some news on it later on. What’s available already since last November is their <a href="http://zpacks.com/shelter/altaplex.shtml">Altaplex shelter</a>. The whole system weighs in at 479 g and is very versatile in use.</p>

<h2 id="warbonnet-outdoors">Warbonnet Outdoors</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.warbonnetoutdoors.com">Warbonnet Outdoors</a> is working on a new Camo pattern specifically designed for larger items like tarps and hopes to have it available later this spring. This should be pretty interesting for the hunters and Bushcrafters out there, so keep your eyes on the Warbonnet website this spring.</p>

<h2 id="more">More</h2>

<p>Cottage Manufacturers are busy people - some are just now out hiking, other’s are finishing up your gear. That’s why not every cottage is on this list. It’s a living document, though, and likely will be updated a couple of times during the next few days while more companies are added. Either check back at the end of the week or follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> where I will announce updates.</p>

<p>And if you liked this article, <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">buy me a cup of coffee or two</a> =)</p>

<p><strong>Want more gear news?</strong> Follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> &amp; <a href="http://instagram.com/hendrikm">Instagram</a> and subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">mailing list</a> for gear reviews and previews!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview Marco Sánchez of As Tucas]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/interview-marco-sanchez-of-as-tucas.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-01T12:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/interview-marco-sanchez-of-as-tucas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It truly is a pleasure to introduce you to Marco Sánchez, the owner of Spain’s only ultralight gear cottage <a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a>. I have been talking online for a long time with Marco, and we almost went on a packrafting trip together. While that tour wasn’t supposed to happen for me, I am certain that in the future I will be hiking with Marco in his home country and experience the beauty of the Pyrenees. But for now I’m very excited to let Marco tell his story and how he made his passion his work!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539401254" title="Camping in the snow, but enjoying the warmth of the sunrise. "><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7154/13539401254_e93214847a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Camping in the snow, but enjoying the warmth of the sunrise." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Marco, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking &amp; packrafting, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>Since my childhood I have been in close contact with nature, although I was born and bread in Zaragoza, a Spanish city. I fondly remember trips with my parents by the river and to the countryside. This is how my passion by nature started.</p>

<p>This passion has led me to play many mountain sports: backpacking, climbing, skiing, biking and more. It is a way to stay in touch with nature. My favorite area is the Pyrenees, which I consider my backyard.</p>

<p>Recently, I’ve started packrafting too. It’s a very interesting way of travelling that I had been pondering for a while. An expedition at Norway on 2012 with my friends <a href="http://thunderinthenight.blogspot.com.es/2012/07/always-have-plan-b-and-c.html">Joe Newton</a> and <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2012/07/vassfaret-slippery-and-wet-part-1/">Benjamin Morrison</a> was the perfect introduction.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539085615" title="Taking a break during a packrafting trip by the Gállego river."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7085/13539085615_53a5cf2af1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="688" alt="Taking a break during a packrafting trip by the Gállego river." /></a></p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>Almost everyday. It recharges my energy and makes me feel part of the environment. Thus, I try to be outdoors as much as possible. During the week I run and ride my mountain bike. I also go for quick walks. Longer trips are reserved for weekends and holidays. Since I founded As Tucas my free time has been considerably reduced. As a consequence, now I’m a fan of “micro adventures”. These, made ​​popular by <a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com">Alastair Humphreys</a>, are an excellent way to enjoy the surroundings when your time is limited. I recommend give it a shot!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539185913" title="Micro adventure by bike."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7207/13539185913_a281fb04be_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Micro adventure by bike." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are you more of a “weekend warrior” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>I make the most of weekends and holidays to go to the mountains. In addition, I like to do some week-long or longer trips every year. These longer trips, in a self-supported style, allow me a greater level of connection with nature.</p>

<p><strong>Which category would you put yourself in: SUL, UL, or Lightweight? What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>My base weight for a typical 3 season weekend trip is 3.5 kg. So, we can say that I’m an ultralight (UL) hiker. However, taking into account other criteria besides weight, I consider myself a super ultralight (SUL) hiker. I find revealing Ryan Jordan’s article <a href="http://www.backpackinglight.com/cgi-bin/backpackinglight/sul-mindset-jordan.html">The SUL Mindset</a>. I carry a very small number of items. Nothing is superfluous and everything works as an integrated system. I backpack in a mountain area with variable weather. Freezing nights are not unusual even during the summer. This requires a more solid and robust kit than the one required in other areas. This also makes more difficult lighten some items such your sleeping bag and shelter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539086675" title="Contemplating the Acherito mountain lake."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7064/13539086675_f3d9c56533_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Contemplating the Acherito mountain lake." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “<a href="http://astucas.com/en/">As Tucas</a>” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>“As Tucas” means “The summits” in Aragonese, the language of our region. It’s a humble recognition to our territory and mountaineer spirit. Furthermore, all our products are named after the local names of mountains, valleys and rivers.</p>

<p><strong>You have a degree in physics and have worked as a teacher before, and you live in a country where unemployment is sadly very high. Was it an easy decision to leave the security of a regular job behind in order to pursue a career in something that you like a lot?</strong></p>

<p>No, it was not an easy decision. However, I do not regret it at all. I have always valued my motivation and personal satisfaction above other factors, such as money. The desire to learn new things has led me to work in several companies at diverse positions: as a teacher, web developer or systems analyst. Unfortunately, the current economic crisis makes it much more difficult to move to another job. Without realizing it, I was stuck in a job that no longer satisfied me. That lack of motivation was crying for a pivot point. Nothing better than turning my passion into my way to make a living.</p>

<p><strong>As Tucas makes custom gear, garments, quilts and shelters. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</strong></p>

<p>I have been making most of my garments and gear as a hobby for years. However, I must admit that considering the thriving american cottages, I wondered if something like that would be possible in Europe.</p>

<p>My necessity to change prompted me to take action. Suddenly, I was full of energy and motivation, developing a bunch of ideas, learning new things and facing challenges. In short, I was turning a dream into a reality.</p>

<p>There are lots of work “behind the scenes” so As Tucas can make a difference. Its future involves bringing together the best of cottages and the best of big brands.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539396734" title="Marking out a Sestrals quilt on the cutting table."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7366/13539396734_d955c24a96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Marking out a Sestrals quilt on the cutting table." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in Spain?</strong></p>

<p>No, as far as I know. In Spain, like in the rest of Europe, starting up a business is more difficult than in the United States. The bureaucratic process is more complex and there is a higher tax burden. Therefore, the number of cottages is so small.</p>

<p><strong>Your company is a mere four months old and already has been received very well all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>I am very pleased with the As Tucas start. Moreover, it has exceeded all my expectations. It was a high-stakes movement, but market reception indicates me that this is the way to go. Now, it’s time to continue improving our product catalog, the production processes and our customer service, key points of our success.</p>

<p><strong>You entered a business segment which a) isn’t very well served by cottages because b) it’s perceived as difficult. How did you decide to offer <a href="http://astucas.com/en/clothing/">garments</a>, when so many others find it a hard business?</strong></p>

<p>Because it is a challenge, but a great opportunity too. Due to their design and the materials used to make them, each of our garments is unique. But more importantly, these garments are designed as an integrated system. They work together allowing you to face a broader range of conditions at a minimal weight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539081455" title="Setting up a machine at the sewing line."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7408/13539081455_fed0457b13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Setting up a machine at the sewing line." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of the <a href="http://astucas.com/en/clothing/cabietos-hoody">Cabietos Hoody</a>, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>Based on our experience, a base layer shirt for mountain activities should combine three key design elements: a hood that protects your face, wrist cuffs with thumb holes and a really long chest zipper. This combo provides an incredible versatility. Although there are excellent products on the market, none of them combines these three elements. The closest was the Backpacking Light Beartooth Merino Wool Hoody, which is no longer available. However, the Cabietos hoody has even greater thermoregulation capabilities and a more durable merino wool fabric.</p>

<p><strong>In addition to garments you also offer a cuben (and silnylon) tarp and a synthetic quilt. Will we see a tent/shelter in the future from As Tucas, or maybe a backpack? Or will you continue to concentrate on garment design, and maybe offer a windjacket/ hardshell soon?</strong></p>

<p>Our catalog is evolving, and will be extended with new products this year. However, we should concentrate our efforts to continue offering something unique and with exceptional value. For this reason, we are not going to enter in some market segments which, in our opinion, are already well served.</p>

<p><strong>Marco, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! Can you let us know what kind of new products you’re working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>Immediately, our high loft synthetic collection will be expanded with a jacket. As we did with the pants, we have exceeded the mythical Backpacking Light Cocoon collection again, with a lighter and better performing garment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539083065" title="The new Sestrals pullover."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/13539083065_e0e24eae66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="The new Sestrals pullover." /></a></p>

<p>In addition, we will make a major commitment to our down collection with new quilts. In doing so, we will be the very first to offer an integrated system of synthetic and down quilts. This combination, praised among others by the renowned alpinist <a href="http://www.andy-kirkpatrick.com/articles/view/double_up">Andy Kirkpatrick</a> and the hiker <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se / 2010/04/across-sarek-in-winter-sleep-system.html">Jörgen Johansson</a>, is a robust and modular 4 season sleeping system.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539183193" title="The new Foratata quilt."><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2807/13539183193_9bca885961_b.jpg" width="437" height="1024" alt="The new Foratata quilt." /></a></p>

<p>To go ahead with this, we have been searching high and low for a suitable down provider. We have started a collaboration with one of the largest polish down producers. They not only provides us the best down available (900 cuin) but does so certifying that it is collected with respect to animal welfare in accordance with European law, an important issue for us.</p>

<p><strong>Any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>We are always thinking how we can improve our products, and this often involves using new materials. We are going to introduce rainwear made ​​with a Cubic Tech CTF3 and eVent laminate, which is probably the lightest 3-layer waterproof and breathable material currently available. We also continue working with Schoeller in new and better fabrics for our garments and a forthcoming rainwear collection.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539396404" title="Evaluating the new Schoeller fabrics."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7185/13539396404_c81d1f97f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="742" alt="Evaluating the new Schoeller fabrics." /></a></p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at As Tucas, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems, which then are adopted in the As Tucas line-up?</strong></p>

<p>Our catalog was created around my personal needs, defined by my locale conditions and my own preferences. However, customers needs plays a more important role nowadays. This allows us to offer more versatile and robust products. Despite this, when your garments and gear are used from the deserts of Africa to the Arctic, the challenges are unique. For this reason, you need unique solutions too. Enter our custom works section, where we work directly with our customers to create their products.</p>

<p><strong>Where do your customer come from?</strong></p>

<p>Mainly from Europe. In addition, we have customers from other parts of the world like the USA and Japan. Curiously we don’t have many Spanish customers. Our mountaineering community is quite traditional and the ultralight philosophy is not widespread yet. Fortunately, the influence of other communities, such trail runners, is revolutionizing the mindset of many hikers.</p>

<p><strong>Are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Currently not many. We think that despite being competing companies, collaborating in some areas would be positive for both our businesses and our customers.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>This weekend! A snowshoeing trip at Ordesa Valley, one of my favorite places. This is an excellent time of the year. Sunny days, mild temperatures and plenty of snow to enjoy yet.</p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>Definitely Alaska. True wilderness at a large scale. More closely, the Sarek National Park in Lapland.</p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>A hoody (preferably a merino one) and a lightweight windshirt. This combo is so versatile that I use it year round in many activities. Another piece of gear that I consider my “luxury item” is a photographic tripod. I love photography. I appreciate its creative possibilities over the weight penalty. For that reason I carry it on many trips.</p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the Spanish spring?</strong></p>

<p>Of course! The Pyrenees are spectacular during spring and you should enjoy them. Days are longer and snow melting opens up lots of possibilities. By contrast, snow remains at high elevations, so you can plan really spectacular routes. We invite everyone to visit us. If you do so, do not hesitate to contact us and, why not! share a great day in the mountains.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/entrevista-marco-sanchez-de-as-tucas.html">Read the original Spanish version here</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539085565" title="Off-trail ridge walking."><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3828/13539085565_0788234ff8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Off-trail ridge walking." /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Entrevista: Marco Sánchez de As Tucas]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/entrevista-marco-sanchez-de-as-tucas.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-01T11:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/entrevista-marco-sanchez-de-as-tucas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Queridos lectores, es un placer para mi presentaros una entrevista con Marco Sánchez de <a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a>, el único “ultralight cottage manufacturer” de España. Estoy en contacto con Marco desde hace mucho, y por poco hicimos una excursión en Noruega hace unos años. Además, como esa excursión (en Noruega) tampoco fue posible para mi, tengo la esperanza de hacer una con Marco en los Pirineos más adelante. Pero ahora es una alegría el poder presentarte este entrevista en español.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539401254" title="Acampando en la nieve, aunque disfrutando del calor del amanecer."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7154/13539401254_e93214847a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Acampando en la nieve, aunque disfrutando del calor del amanecer." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Marco, preséntate brevemente y dinos quién eres. ¿Desde cuándo practicas senderismo y packrafting? ¿Cómo empezaste?</strong></p>

<p>Desde pequeño he estado en contacto con la naturaleza, aunque nací y me crié en Zaragoza, una ciudad española de tamaño medio. Recuerdo con mucho cariño las excursiones con mis padres junto al río y al campo. Así es como se inició mi pasión por la naturaleza.</p>

<p>Como parte de esta pasión he desarrollado muchas actividades de montaña: senderismo, escalada, esquí, bicicleta… Es una forma de estar en contacto con la naturaleza. Mi entorno favorito son los Pirineos, un lugar fascinante.</p>

<p>Más recientemente también he comenzado a practicar packrafting. Es una forma de viajar muy interesante que llevaba considerando desde hace tiempo. Una travesía en 2012 por Noruega con mis amigos <a href="http://thunderinthenight.blogspot.com.es/2012/07/always-have-plan-b-and-c.html">Joe Newton</a> y <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2012/07/vassfaret-slippery-and-wet-part-1/">Benjamin Morrison</a> fue la iniciación perfecta.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539085615" title="Descansando durante una excursión en packraft por el río Gállego."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7085/13539085615_53a5cf2af1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="688" alt="Descansando durante una excursión en packraft por el río Gállego." /></a></p>

<p><strong>¿Con qué frecuencia estás al aire libre actualmente?</strong></p>

<p>Casi a diario. Me recarga de energía y me hace sentir parte del medio ambiente. Por eso trato de estar al aire libre el máximo tiempo posible. Entre semana voy a correr y en bicicleta de montaña. También realizo alguna excursión rápida. Las excursiones más largas se reservan para los fines de semana y las vacaciones.</p>

<p>Desde que fundé As Tucas mi tiempo libre se ha reducido considerablemente. Por eso últimamente soy un asiduo a las “micro aventuras”. Éstas, popularizadas por <a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com">Alastair Humphreys</a>, son una manera excelente de disfrutar del entorno próximo cuando tu tiempo es limitado. ¡Es algo que recomiendo probar a todo el mundo!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539185913" title="Micro aventura en bicicleta."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7207/13539185913_a281fb04be_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Micro aventura en bicicleta." /></a></p>

<p><strong>¿Eres un “guerrero de fin de semana” o tienes alguna excursión de larga distancia a tus espaldas?</strong></p>

<p>Aprovecho todos los fines de semana y festivos para salir a la montaña. Además, todos los años me gusta realizar alguna salida de una semana o más. Este tipo de excursiones, realizadas en plena autonomía, me permiten un grado mayor de conexión con la Naturaleza. </p>

<p><strong>¿En qué categoria te incluyes: super ultraligero, ultraligero o ligero? ¿Cual es tu peso base típico?</strong></p>

<p>Mi peso base para una salida típica de fin de semana en 3 estaciones es de 3,5 kg. Por tanto, podemos decir que soy un senderista ultraligero (UL).</p>

<p>Sin embargo, basándome en otros criterios además del peso, me  considero un senderista super ultraligero (SUL). A este respecto es revelador el artículo de Ryan Jordan, <a href="http://www.backpackinglight.com/cgi-bin/backpackinglight/sul-mindset-jordan.html">The SUL Mindset</a>. El número de elementos que llevo es muy pequeño. Nada es superfluo y todo trabaja como un sistema integrado. El entorno en que me muevo es una zona montañosa con clima cambiante, donde incluso en verano no es extraño llegar a los 0 C durante las noches. Se precisa de un equipo más sólido y robusto que en otras zonas. Por eso resulta más difícil reducir el peso de alguno elementos como el saco y el refugio.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539086675" title="Contemplando el Ibón de Acherito."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7064/13539086675_f3d9c56533_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Contemplando el Ibón de Acherito." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Por favor, indícanos el origen del nombre “As Tucas” y su significado.</strong></p>

<p>“<a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a>” significa “Las cumbres” en aragonés, lengua de nuestra región. Es un guiño hacia nuestro territorio y espíritu montañero. Asimismo, todos nuestros productos se denominan con los nombres locales de montañas, valles, ríos…</p>

<p><strong>Eres licenciado en Ciencias Físicas y anteriormente has trabajado de profesor. Desgraciadamente donde vives el desempleo es muy elevado. ¿Fue una decisión fácil dejar atrás la seguridad de un trabajo por cuenta ajena para perseguir algo que te gusta?</strong></p>

<p>No, no fue una decisión sencilla. Sin embargo, es una decisión de la que no me arrepiento en absoluto.</p>

<p>Siempre he valorado mi motivación y satisfacción personal por encima de otros factores, como el económico. Las ganas por aprender cosas nuevas me han llevado a trabajar en varias empresas desempeñando labores tan diversas como profesor, programador Web o analista de sistemas.</p>

<p>Lamentablemente, la situación económica actual hace mucho más difícil esta movilidad laboral. Casi sin darme cuenta, me vi atrapado en un empleo que ya no me satisfacía. Sin motivación, precisaba de un cambio drástico. Nada mejor que convertir mi pasión en mi forma de ganarme la vida.</p>

<p><strong>As Tucas fabrica material a medida, edredones y refugios. ¿Puedes indicarnos como surgió la idea de crear la empresa y como ves su futuro?</strong></p>

<p>Desde hace años fabrico buena parte de mi ropa y material como afición. Sin embargo, debo reconocer que al ver la floreciente industria artesanal americana, pensaba si algo así sería posible en Europa.</p>

<p>Mi necesidad de cambio me impulsó a pasar a la acción. De repente recuperé toda mi energía y motivación: multitud de ideas que desarrollar, aprender cosas nuevas, retos que afrontar… En resumen, convertir un sueño en realidad. Hay mucho trabajo “entre bastidores” para hacer de As Tucas algo único. Su futuro pasa por ser una empresa que aúne todo lo bueno de las empresas artesanales y todo lo bueno de los grandes fabricantes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539396734" title="Marcando un edredón Sestrals en la mesa de corte."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7366/13539396734_d955c24a96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Marcando un edredón Sestrals en la mesa de corte." /></a></p>

<p><strong>¿Hay otros fabricantes artesanales en España?</strong></p>

<p>No, hasta donde yo conozco. En España, al igual que en el resto de Europa, crear una empresa es más difícil que en Estados Unidos. El proceso burocrático es más complejo y la presión fiscal mucho mayor. Por eso, el número de este tipo de empresas es tan reducido.</p>

<p><strong>Tu empresa únicamente lleva cuatro meses en el mercado y ya ha sido muy bien recibida en Europa. ¿Va bien el negocio?</strong></p>

<p>Estoy muy satisfecho con el arranque de As Tucas. Es más, ha superado todas mis previsiones.</p>

<p>La apuesta inicial ha sido fuerte, pero la acogida del mercado me indica que este es el camino a seguir. Ahora hay que continuar trabajando para mejorar el catálogo de productos, los procesos de producción y el servicio de atención al cliente, aspectos clave de nuestro éxito.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539081455" title="Preparando una máquina en la línea de costura."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7408/13539081455_fed0457b13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Preparando una máquina en la línea de costura." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Te has introducido en un segmento de negocio que a) no está muy bien atendido por las empresas artesanales porque b) se percibe como difícil. ¿Como te decidiste a ofrecer prendas de <a href="http://astucas.com/es/ropa/">ropa</a>, cuando muchos otros lo consideran un negocio difícil?</strong></p>

<p>Porque es un reto y también una gran oportunidad. Tanto por su diseño como por los materiales utilizados, cada una de las prendas ofrecidas es única. Más importante aún, estas prendas están ideadas como un sistema integrado, que trabajan juntas para permitirnos afrontar una mayor variedad de condiciones con el mínimo peso posible.  </p>

<p><strong>¿Puedes contarnos un poco sobre cómo fue el proceso de diseño de la camiseta con capucha <a href="http://astucas.com/es/ropa/camiseta-capucha-cabietos">Cabietos</a> y de dónde vino la inspiración?</strong></p>

<p>En base a nuestra experiencia, una camiseta base para actividades de montaña debe reunir tres elementos de diseño clave: una capucha que proteja la cara, puños con agujeros para los pulgares y una cremallera de pecho realmente larga. Esta combinación proporciona una versatilidad increíble. </p>

<p>Si bien hay productos excelentes en el mercado, no hay ninguno que combine estos tres elementos. Lo más próximo era la camiseta Backpacking Light Beartooth Merino Wool Hoody, ya descatalogada. Sin embargo, la camiseta con capucha Cabietos ofrece unas posibilidades de ventilación aún mayores y un tejido de lana merina más duradero.</p>

<p><strong>Además de prendas de ropa también ofreces un toldo de Cuben (y silnylon) y un edredón sintético. ¿Veremos una tienda/refugio en el futuro? ¿O tal vez una mochila? ¿O continuarás concentrándote en el diseño de ropa y, tal vez, ofrecer una chaqueta cortavientos o impermeable?</strong></p>

<p>Nuestro catálogo está en plena evolución, y este año se verá ampliado con nuevos productos. Sin embargo, debemos concentrar esfuerzos para continuar ofreciendo algo único y con un valor excepcional. Por este motivo no vamos a entrar a competir en determinados segmentos del mercado que, consideramos, ya están cubiertos.</p>

<p><strong>Marco ¡nos encantaría conocer tus proyectos en curso! ¿Puedes contarnos en que nuevos productos estás trabajando ahora?</strong></p>

<p>De forma inmediata, la colección Sestrals de ropa aislante sintética se va a ampliar con una chaqueta. Al igual que ya hicimos con los pantalones, hemos vuelto a superar a la mítica colección Backpacking Light Cocoon con una prenda más ligera y con mejores prestaciones.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539083065" title="El nuevo pullover Sestrals."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/13539083065_e0e24eae66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="El nuevo pullover Sestrals." /></a></p>

<p>Por otro lado, vamos a realizar una importante apuesta por nuestra línea de plumón con nuevos edredones. De esta forma, vamos a ser los primeros en ofrecer un sistema integrado de edredones sintéticos y de plumón. Esta combinación, alabada entre otros por el reconocido alpinista <a href="http://www.andy-kirkpatrick.com/articles/view/double_up">Andy Kirkpatrick</a> y el senderista <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se/2010/04/across-sarek-in-winter-sleep-system.html">Jörgen Johansson</a>, permite crear un robusto sistema modular de 4 estaciones.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539183193" title="El nuevo edredón Foratata."><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2807/13539183193_9bca885961_b.jpg" width="437" height="1024" alt="El nuevo edredón Foratata." /></a></p>

<p>Para realizar este movimiento hemos  buscado ampliamente un proveedor de plumón adecuado. Hemos comenzado a trabajar con uno de los mayores productores de plumón de Polonia. Éste no solo nos ofrece el mejor plumón disponible (900 cuin) sino que nos certifica que ha sido obtenido respetando el bienestar animal de acuerdo a la normativa europea, un asunto importante para nosotros.</p>

<p><strong>¿Algunos materiales ligeros nuevos emocionantes?</strong></p>

<p>Siempre estamos buscando la forma de mejorar nuestros productos y esto, a menudo, involucra utilizar nuevos materiales. Vamos a introducir ropa de lluvia fabricada con un laminado de fibra Cubic Tech CTF3 y eVent, que es probablemente el material impermeable y transpirable más ligero del mercado. Asimismo, continuamos trabajando con Schoeller en nuevos y mejores tejidos para nuestras camisetas y una próxima colección de ropa de lluvia.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539396404" title="Evaluando los nuevos tejidos de Schoeller."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7185/13539396404_c81d1f97f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="742" alt="Evaluando los nuevos tejidos de Schoeller." /></a></p>

<p><strong>¿Cómo funciona el I+D en As Tucas? ¿Se trata de una necesidad personal que tratas de resolver o te inspiran algunos de tus clientes que buscan soluciones a sus problemas?</strong></p>

<p>Nuestro catálogo se formó a partir de mis propias necesidades personales, definidas tanto por las condiciones de mi entorno como por mis propias preferencias. Cada vez hay más influencias de las necesidades de nuestros clientes, lo que nos permite ofrecer productos todavía más versátiles y robustos.</p>

<p>Sin embargo, cuando la ropa y material que creas se usa desde los desiertos de África hasta las zonas árticas, los retos son únicos. Por ese motivo, en ocasiones se precisan soluciones también únicas. Es aquí cuando entra en escena nuestra sección de trabajos a medida, donde trabajamos directamente con los clientes para crear sus productos.</p>

<p><strong>¿De donde provienen tus clientes?</strong></p>

<p>Principalmente de Europa. Sin embargo, también tenemos clientes en otras partes del mundo como Estados Unidos y Japón. Paradójicamente tenemos pocos clientes de España. La comunidad montañera de nuestro país es bastante tradicional y la filosofía de lo ultraligero todavía no está extendida. Afortunadamente, la influencia de sectores como el de las carreras de montaña, está revolucionando la mentalidad de muchos senderistas.</p>

<p><strong>¿Estás en contacto con otros fabricantes artesanales de Europa, Japón, Canadá o Estados Unidos?</strong></p>

<p>Actualmente tan apenas. Pensamos que a pesar de ser competencia, la colaboración en determinadas áreas sería positiva tanto para las empresas como para los clientes.</p>

<p><strong>¿Cuando y dónde fue tu última excursión?</strong></p>

<p>¡Este fin de semana! Una excursión con raquetas por el Valle de Ordesa, uno de mis lugares preferidos. Esta es una excelente época del año. Días soleados, temperaturas agradables y todavía mucha nieve para disfrutar.</p>

<p><strong>¿Y dónde te lleva tu excursión de ensueño?</strong></p>

<p>Sin duda Alaska. Naturaleza en estado puro, salvaje y a gran escala. En un entorno más próximo, el Parque nacional de Sarek, en Laponia.</p>

<p><strong>¿Algún elemento favorito que siempre llevas contigo?</strong></p>

<p>Una camiseta con capucha, preferentemente de lana merina, y una chaqueta cortavientos ligera. Esta combinación de ropa es tan versátil, que la utilizo todo el año en multitud de actividades. Otro elemento, que considero mi “elemento de lujo”, es un trípode fotográfico. Me encanta la fotografía. Valoro más las posibilidades creativas que un trípode me ofrece que la penalización de peso. Por ese motivo, me acompaña en muchas de mis excursiones.</p>

<p><strong>¿Estás pensando en una excursión pronto y disfrutar de la primavera española?</strong></p>

<p>¡Por supuesto! Los Pirineos en primavera son espectaculares y hay que aprovecharlos. Los días cada vez más largos y el retroceso de la nieve abren muchas posibilidades. La nieve en zonas de altura nos acompaña todo el año, por lo que se pueden crear rutas realmente espectaculares.</p>

<p>Os invitamos a todos a visitarnos. Si lo hacéis, no dudéis en contactar con nosotros para aconsejaros  y, por qué no, compartir un estupendo día en las montañas.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539085565" title="Caminando fuera de sendero por una cresta."><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3828/13539085565_0788234ff8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Caminando fuera de sendero por una cresta." /></a></p>

<p><em><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/interview-marco-sanchez-of-as-tucas.html">Read the English version of this interview</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Gear from the Cottages 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-05T11:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m just back from my first ISPO, but first it’s time to look again at what our favourite ultralight gear cottages have in store for us in 2014. Like in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2013.html">2013</a>, <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">Benjamin</a> and me teamed up to present you the latest and greatest New Gear from the Cottages for 2014!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318735523/" title="New Gear from the Cottages 2014"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3687/12318735523_a808768d20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="479" alt="New Gear from the Cottages 2014" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="as-tucas">As Tucas</h2>

<p>The new kid on the block is already making quiet a name for itself. <a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a> hails from Spain and makes garments and gear, as well as custom works. Their Sestrals collection of insulated garments and gear will be expanded with new and cozy members: An insulated hoody top (in both jacket and pullover versions), a flat quilt and a wearable quilt for those who love true multi-use tools.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12321392944/" title="Sestrals Flat Quilt"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2854/12321392944_88e2b53444_b.jpg" width="960" height="640" alt="Sestrals Flat Quilt" /></a></p>

<p>Before the snow (which snow?) transforms into rain, As Tucas will offer a whole new line of rainwear. Ultralight yet functional jackets and pants made with 2,5 layer fabric and WPB Event - Cuben fiber. </p>

<p>Also their silnylon flat tarp is almost ready, and will be a more affordable version of their Arazas cuben tarp - made with same care to detail, coming seam sealed to you. If you like to ride your bike, you will soon be able to keep your hands warm and happy with their new pogies.</p>

<p>In the back-end, the As Tucas workshop has been equipped with new machines, including a flat lock and an embroidery machine. New fabrics are on their way to the workshop, and many others are being tested. New colours of their flagship shell fabric (Momentum 50) will be available in March. Also their already great website will be further improved, so keep an eye out on that.</p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/astucas">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/astucas">Twitter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12319094504/" title="As Tucas fabrics"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3741/12319094504_6eec0d984f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="479" alt="As Tucas fabrics" /></a></p>

<h2 id="packrafting-store">Packrafting Store</h2>

<p>Lets wander a bit north and hear what the <a href="http://packrafting-store.de/">Packrafting Store</a> has for news. Well, they will celebrate their second anniversary on February 15th this year, and you might want to subscribe to their <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/newsletter.php?language=en">newsletter</a> for that occasion.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318667885/" title="Anfibio Buoy Boy by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7310/12318667885_370cd4ed90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Anfibio Buoy Boy" /></a></p>

<p>The long awaited Packafting vest, the Anfibio Buoy Boy, is an inflatable jacket serving much like a PFD, yet it can’t be claimed that way, since you need (<em>and could forget</em>) to blow it up! That is the official rules. No regular life jacket (ISO Norm), only standard CE for quality production. Nevertheless, it features two independent chambers at combined 80 N buoyancy. The all mesh back does not interfere with your packrafts back rest, and is made from sturdy 210den TPU laminated nylon and a chunky front zipper provides some back up. Weight is 310g (medium), the extra crotch strap 30g. Packing size is second to none. It will sell for 79€ within the European Union only. Comes in blue (medium) and light red (large). </p>

<p>And in case you’re wondering, Anfibio is the gear brand of the Packrafting Store, specialising in packrafting accessories. It is a design and development label based on user experiences. Sourcing up partners with manufacturing expertise allows them to create a range of products directly suited to packrafting’s unique requirements.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318818153/" title="Cargo Fly by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3792/12318818153_3e1b807d9f_b.jpg" width="900" height="600" alt="Cargo Fly" /></a></p>

<p>Secondly, the workshop at the Packrafting Store HQ can now provide Cargo Fly retrofits within the European Union. Any used Alpacka Raft can get upgraded with this unique feature - probably the best thing you can add to your boat! Price including return shipping in the EU will most likely be 299€.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318666075/" title="Shearwater webbed paddle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7313/12318666075_21d8b86c2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shearwater webbed paddle" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318666605/" title="Shearwater webbed paddle by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3784/12318666605_5987acf8c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shearwater webbed paddle" /></a></p>

<p>Bike rafters will like the Shearwater webbed paddle, a collapsible paddle that packs down really small. There is real science behind it (bionics) providing economic propulsion and ergonomic handling, despite the looks (duck feet, anyone?). And then there’s the Anfibio Multibag. A multifuntion dry-/compression-/water-/shower bag with real tight top closure. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12319099774/" title="Anfibio Multibag by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7429/12319099774_582c01c312_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Anfibio Multibag" /></a></p>

<p>Furthermore: The Alpacka CuriYak will be available front them, for the competitive price of 680€. Likewise, Hyperlite Mountain Gear joins the Packrafting Store and offers you thus a one-stop shop for all your packrafting needs.</p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/PackraftingStore">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/PackraftingDe">Twitter</a>.</p>

<h2 id="laufbursche">LAUFBURSCHE</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/">LAUFBURSCHE</a> has been very, very busy in the last months, and launches three new packs which surely will reign supreme in the UL market.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12320452523/" title="PACKsack"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3753/12320452523_558bd4791f_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="PACKsack" /></a></p>

<p>Introducing: The LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack. A 24 l pack which will be available in weights of 130 g (70den Ripstop Nylon) and 165 g (210den DxG). It’s THE pack for SUL enthusiasts, as it has a comfort limit of 5 to 6 kg. The red YKK Aquaguard zipper keeps snow (which snow?) and rain out, and you can strap your poles, mat and rain jacket to the outside. Clean lines, small size, gorgeous, and in 2014 also as a very special HiF Edition available. Yeps, that’s right.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12320291555/" title="PACKraum by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3812/12320291555_2d86fed2c4_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="PACKraum" /></a></p>

<p>Introducing: The LAUFBURSCHE PACKraum. A 38 l pack which weighs 320 g and has a comfort limit of 10 kg, this pack combines with your Klymit AirBeam frame. It’s One size fits all and has two large side pockets (2 l each), and carries as comfortable as you’re used to from LAUFBURSCHE - if not even more, as the re-designed shoulder straps are now 12 mm thick. An ideal pack for the Ultralight backpacker and those that need a backpack for their urban every-day adventures.</p>

<p>And then there’s still the huckePACK. But you’ll need to check Benjamin’s post for it =)</p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/LAUFBURSCHE-gear/197297190298337">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/laufbursche_">Twitter</a>.</p>

<h2 id="katabatic-gear">Katabatic Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://katabaticgear.com/">Katabatic Gear</a> is entering the backpack market with two backpack designs. Coming in spring 2014 there will be a lightweight climbing pack and an ultralight backpacking pack. The climbing packs will feature durable fabrics and construction and should be ideal for fast and light climbers. The streamlined design easily carries ice tools and crampons, with removable compression straps for larger items like skis. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318806013/" title="Katabatic Gear climbing pack by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7346/12318806013_db6c0e3330_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Katabatic Gear climbing pack" /></a></p>

<p>The ultralight backpacking pack will be made of the Cuben Fiber hybrid fabric, making it a lightweight option that doesn’t cut corners on features, durability, or design. Both of the packs will utilize their proprietary frame system, featuring a supportive, dual-density back panel and removable aluminium stay. The contoured frame design offers more support than traditional UL frame systems, while remaining extremely lightweight and comfortable.</p>

<p>Then there’s also a new quilt in the line up. The Grenadier 5°F has a Pertex Endurance shell and a generous loft, making it a versatile cold weather bag for the ultralight traveler. Available with the premium 900 fill-power down or 850 fill power water-resistant down, the <a href="http://katabaticgear.com/shop/grenadier-sleeping-bag/">Grenadier is available now</a>.</p>

<h2 id="flat-cat-gear">Flat Cat Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://flatcatgear.com/">Flat Cat Gear</a> now has their Bobcat Jr. Cooking System available in titanium, while the Focus Fire 14 Titanium will be in BETA Testing soon. This stove was designed to maximise the efficiency of a single 14 gram Esbit solid fuel tablet. Jon can bring 4 cups of water up from 70 F to 200 F in bench top testing. The Focus Fire 14 Titanium UL 15 weighs 5 grams.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318817523/" title="Focus Fire 14 Titanium by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2818/12318817523_f6550dc190_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Focus Fire 14 Titanium" /></a></p>

<p>The Epicurean Titanium UL stove has been updated for better robustness. It is a solid fuel stove designed for dry baking and will burn a 14 gram Esbit tablet for 50 to 60 minutes. It weighs 7 g.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318665535/" title="Epicurean Titanium UL15 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3770/12318665535_a806dc4fd8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Epicurean Titanium UL15" /></a></p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/flatcatgear1">Facebook</a>.</p>

<h2 id="locus-gear">Locus Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://locusgear.com/">LOCUS GEAR</a> will launch their “Nyx”  synthetic quilt in March. Made from a Pertex Quantum GL shell and what has been know thus far as PrimaLoft ONE, and should weigh around 540 g including stuff sack.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318815173/" title="Nyx quilt"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3696/12318815173_8226c2c44f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="nyx (3)" /></a></p>

<p>The new color Silnylon colour for 2014 is called Bronze Mist and it is a yellowish light brown. All Sil shelters are already available in this new colour, which looks very pretty, if I may say so.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12318657455/" title="Khafra Sil Bronze Mist with Aquaguard red zipper"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7443/12318657455_557bdfc891_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Khafra Sil Bronze Mist with Aquaguard red zipper" /></a></p>

<p>Locus Gear also started to offer various inner shelters for both the Khufu and the Khafra, which are also already available, while the Menkura shelter will be available soon.</p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/locusgear">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/locusgear">Twitter</a>.</p>

<h2 id="hariyama-productions">Hariyama Productions</h2>

<p><a href="http://hariyama.net/">Hariyama Productions</a> is a Japanese cottage that will launch in the near future. I have seen and used some of their products already, and am delighted. High quality craftsmanship, made in Japan. </p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Hariyama-Productions/183435505038499">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hariypro">Twitter</a>.</p>

<h2 id="ogawand">Ogawand</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.ogawand.com/home/OGAWAND_top.html">OGAWAND</a> is another Japanese cottage which makes some great looking and functional gear. Their <a href="http://www.ogawand.com/prpducts/OGAWAND_backpack_OWN.html">OWN</a> backpack is a pack which adapts in size to your needs, and can go from 25 to 50 l in no time. It even can carry your rope. I have seen this pack in use and it is beautifully made, and weighs in at 530 g - available now. New for 2014 will be the OWN-Light. It will have an updated pattern and uses the Dyneema 140 denier material, but will be about 100 g lighter. </p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Ogawand">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/OGAWAND_twt">Twitter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12321077705/" title="Ogawand OWN"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7296/12321077705_d83df1f40a_b.jpg" width="700" height="460" alt="Ogawand OWN" /></a></p>

<h2 id="wanderlust-equipment">WANDERLUST EQUIPMENT</h2>

<p><a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/">WANDERLUST EQUIPMENT</a> is the final Japanese cottage in this article which designs and manufacturers really innovative gear. Their <a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/products/orbiter-pack/">Orbiter Pack</a> is a unique take on the burrito style of packing, as the pad is in this design the frame - and you pack your gear inside of it. It’s very much a slimmed down ULA EPIC, as this pack weighs just 330 g. I can see this working as a good trailrunning pack, too, so it’s really multi-use. Check them out, they have some sweet cooking gear, a UL pick cover for your ice axes and a UL Mesh peg case!</p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/WanderlustEquipment">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/wanderlust_eq">Twitter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12319146875/" title="Wanderlust Orbiter Pack"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7341/12319146875_a67fa7864b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Wanderlust Orbiter Pack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bushbuddy">BushBuddy</h2>

<p><a href="http://bushbuddy.ca/">BushBuddy</a> is continuing to work on the the development and testing of the titanium stove. And it might be available, possibly maybe, towards the end of this year.</p>

<h2 id="six-moon-designs">Six Moon Designs</h2>

<p>In 2013 Brian Frankle joined <a href="http://www.sixmoondesigns.com/">Six Moon Designs</a>, and a year later we can see finally the fruits of this collaboration. There are four new packs split into two pack families, with a possible additional pack release later in the year. The first packs should be available by April this year, and the first infos on the <a href="http://www.sixmoondesigns.com/smdnews/152-flight-backpacks.html">Flight series</a> came out on Monday. The packs come with a Vest Harness and an optional hipbelt is available, while sizes will be 30 and 44 l, weighing 425 g and 879 g, respectively. </p>

<p>Furthermore, they are reworking their Cuben Fiber lineup of shelters and have just finished updating the Haven CF tarp, which will start production soon. It is stronger, easier to setup, more stable and incorporates the Hidden Seam Technology. Last year’s production run of Skyscape X’s had a second door, but the next production run will include some additional changes that will lighten the tent, simplify setup and make it easier to reconfigure. Also the Serenity NetTent has undergone a makeover, and the new version will support an 8” deep bathtub floor, and a taller canopy that is more centred over the sleeping area.</p>

<p>Follow them on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/sixmoondesigns">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/sixmoondesigns">Twitter</a>.</p>

<h2 id="more">More</h2>

<p>Behold! There is more! <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">Benjamin</a> shares with you the new gear from FlyWeight Designs, HMG and MLD, showcases what Suluk has been up to, and also gives you the low-down on the new LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK (Damn, that’s a sweet pack!). Thus direct thee browser to <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">hrxxlight.com</a>, pronto!</p>

<p><em>You have a cottage and should be on this list with your new gear? <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Email me</a>!</em> </p>

<p>If you liked this article, <a href="https://holvi.com/shop/hikinginfinland/product/dd006c907dfc0805441be88068460867/">buy me a cup of coffee</a>! And sure, you may follow me on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Gear from the Cottages 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2013.html"/>
    <updated>2013-02-05T09:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/new-gear-from-the-cottages-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cottage manufacturers make the Lightweight &amp; Ultralight gear we use and love. And while OR in the USA, and ISPO in Munich right now give us an overload of shiny, new and often not that lightweight gear, <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/">Benjamin</a> and me decided to get together and present you the latest and greatest New Gear from the Cottages for 2013!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8446343273/" title="New Gear from the Cottages! by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8364/8446343273_6d67eaaf24_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="New Gear from the Cottages!" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="elemental-horizons">Elemental Horizons</h2>

<p>Matthew from Elemental Horizons launched the <a href="http://www.elementalhorizons.com/aduro-sl-pack.aspx">Aduro SL Pack</a> at the start of the year. A unique clam shell panel load design makes packing your pack &amp; organizing gear easy, and the Klymit Air Beam frame sheet helps to provide excellent support and comfort. This 42 l backpack - roomy enough to hold a weekend bear canister inside - comes in two torso lengths and weighs 663 g with a Frame Sheet, or 570 g without, and is made in the USA.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8446355199/" title="Aduro by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8352/8446355199_bc2584250f_b.jpg" width="800" height="800" alt="Aduro" /></a></p>

<h2 id="yama-mountain-gear">YAMA Mountain Gear</h2>

<p>YAMA Mountain Gear will soon release a single wall version of the <a href="http://yamamountaingear.com/gear-room/shaped-tarps/cirriform">Cuben Cirriform Tarp</a> and expand their DIY line to include a Cirriform Kit - great news for Cuben Lovers &amp; MYOGers alike. The Cuben Cirriform in the minimal configuration will weigh a scant 213 g; and the craftsmanship going into this shelter is going to make is (water-) bomb proof. </p>

<p>YAMA is also giving back to the community with their <a href="http://yamamountaingear.com/mYAMAdventure">mYAMAdventure</a> program. It will assist hikers with their first ‘big adventure’ while giving back to those maintaining and protecting the trail systems, and is a unique case of a cottage giving back to the community - Respect!</p>

<p><a href="http://yamamountaingear.com/gear-room/shaped-tarps/cirriform" title="Cuben Cirriform"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8092/8447430740_929ec610dd_b.jpg" width="800" height="539" alt="yama_cirriform-sw" /></a></p>

<h2 id="mountain-laurel-designs">Mountain Laurel Designs</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> has a lot of new gear coming this year, and does that while staying 100% in-house, craftsman-driven, and made in the USA! Those who order from MLD will also like to hear that the company expanded their production to allow for shorter wait times. </p>

<p>Ron has sourced a 10d 3XDWR fabric and ClimaShield Apex insulation which means there are going to be some new quilts coming this year. Their current quilt is well-liked, and this is surely going to be a hit with the synthetic quilt crowd.</p>

<p>SUL Fans are surely going to like the 99 g Cuben pack MLD is going to release this year. Design-wise it will be like the Newt with one rear pocket; so really something for SUL/ XUL backpackers who pack a minimal kit, or those who look for a very light daypack/ summit pack.</p>

<p>The Burn and Prophet packs will get an inflatable frame option plus load lifters, which means they get an internal frame pad sleeve that fits the current Klymit backpack frames, like the current Exodus FS minus the CF rod rigid frame. Made for those who need a bit more support and don’t like using the traditional virtual frame (Burrito-Style sleep pad inside the pack), this gives you more vertical support.</p>

<p>Oh, and women’s versions of all packs are due as well. That’s great news!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8447689596/" title="TrailStar Compact by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8055/8447689596_cf7e242655_b.jpg" width="720" height="182" alt="TrailStar Compact" /></a></p>

<p>The prototype TrailStar Compact (a better name is sought) is in the works, and should fit smaller people better. It’s lighter, too - about 71 grams. It will be about 15% smaller with a 6’ baseline at the edge vs the 7’ of the regular one. A date when it will be available has yet to appear.</p>

<h2 id="trail-designs">Trail Designs</h2>
<p>The guys at Trail Designs just released the <a href="http://www.traildesigns.com/stoves/fissure-ti-tri-system">Fissure</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.traildesigns.com/stoves/fusion-ti-tri">Fusion</a> split cone systems, which means there’s more protection for your stove and pot while still allowing you to pack the cone inside your pot. They’re also working on a little add-on which will come later this year, and should make cooking on your Trail Designs stoves a lot easier!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.traildesigns.com/stoves/fusion-ti-tri" title="Fusion"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8186/8446355173_d92e3d6311.jpg" width="500" height="500" alt="Fusion" /></a></p>

<h2 id="lite-trail">Lite Trail</h2>
<p><a href="http://litetrail.com/">Lite Trail</a> not only sells a wide variety of very useful UL accessories, they also have some very exciting new gear coming for us UL backpackers! The <a href="http://litetrail.com/shop/litetrail-hline-dyneema-hang-haul-cord">LiteTrail H-Line Hang and Haul Dyneema Cordage</a> is already available, which is a 2.5 mm diameter high quality Dyneema cordage. A slick nano coating and 580 kg breaking strength means you also can haul not so UL loads with it! </p>

<p>The lightest <a href="http://litetrail.com/shop/litetrail-titanium-solid-fuel-cook-system">Solid Fuel Cook System</a> on the market just got better! The pot gets handles with heat resistant rubberized covers (<em>the photo shows an early prototype</em>), and the windscreen is redesigned with spot welding so paper clips are no longer required (they’re easy to lose if you’re not careful). A narrower spaced hole pattern that goes 50% around the circumference and a nice contoured cutout for those new handles was also added. A 900 ml pot is also coming some time this year and all pots should be lighter than what’s currently available, so good reason to be excited!</p>

<p><a href="http://litetrail.com/shop/litetrail-titanium-solid-fuel-cook-system" title="Ti Cook System 2013"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8331/8447430236_3b94dc7a52_b.jpg" width="700" height="823" alt="Ti Cook System 2013" /></a></p>

<p>Winter backpackers who need to melt snow will like the 1600 ml Titanium pot that LiteTrail is hoping to bring out soon, which would also make a great group pot for summer trips. A flat top lid, possibly a bail wire handle for hanging from a tripod over a wood fire (yay!) and again lighter than any other 1600 ml titanium pot on the market.</p>

<h2 id="zpacks">ZPacks</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.zpacks.com/">ZPacks</a>’ owners Joe and Sheryl Valesko are thru-hiking the Te Araroa Trail in New Zealand at the moment, and while Joe gets a lot of ideas while on the trail these will need to wait until April to be constructed! At ZPacks Matt Favero is managing the store and it is open, and all the gear is available as usual.</p>

<h2 id="ula-equipment">ULA Equipment</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=45265&amp;pw=73183">ULA Equipment</a> has been going from strength to strength in 2012, and have made a lot of people very happy by releasing their backpacks in camo and purple besides the standard green. For 2013 ULA will offer any of their packs also in Cuben, which is very exciting for those who want to save even more weight!</p>

<p>The ULA packs are now made from the new ULA 210 Robic fabric, which is three times as hard to puncture than Dyneema. However, the packs remain the same weight, which means you are getting a lot more durability now.</p>

<p>I also asked Chris about how he feels that Brian Frankle (who is the Founder of ULA until he sold the company) joined Six Moon Designs. Chris was very positive about it and thinks that Brian will help SMD to improve on their current pack line, and he wishes them all the best with their cooperation.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=45265&amp;pw=73183" title="ULA Catalyst in Multicam"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8229/8447453198_4e79e850af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="ULA Catalyst in Multicam" /></a></p>

<h2 id="warbonnet">Warbonnet</h2>
<p><a href="http://warbonnetoutdoors.com/">Warbonnet Outdoors</a> is coming out with a new version of their popular <a href="http://warbonnetoutdoors.com/blackbirds.php">Blackbird</a> hammock, the Blackbird XLC. It is longer, and has a convertible top. Here is <a href="http://youtu.be/CRoO_hx33Cg">a video</a> where Brandon shows it off.</p>

<h2 id="jacks-r-better">Jacks ‘R’ Better</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.jacksrbetter.com/">Jacks ‘R’ Better</a> has a new website! But that’s not all that got re-designed: JRB top quilts now come with 14 baffle sections versus the older 10 baffle sections for better down stability. You’ll also like the price reductions across the board for quilts and hammocks - JRB quilts are now even better &amp; more affordable! The Jacks will also have a limited quantity run of a digital camo down quilt. If that’s something for you, subscribe to their Newsletter as these are bound to sell out quickly!</p>

<p><a href="http://jacksrbetter.com/" title="Old Rag Mtn Quilt"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8080/8446355261_61c0b1d966_b.jpg" width="1000" height="1000" alt="Old Rag Mtn Quilt" /></a></p>

<h2 id="lightheart-gear">LightHeart Gear</h2>
<p>Judy from <a href="http://lightheartgear.com/">LightHeart Gear</a> has a couple of great ideas, which she is Alpha testing on the trail at the moment and hence can’t tell us more. There’s also going to be a camouflage silnylon version of the great Solo Tent, and in case you didn’t know yet, yes, you can get a Solo now in Cuben!</p>

<h2 id="laufbursche">Laufbursche</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/">LAUFBURSCHE</a> is coming out with an UL shoulder bag for those who want to carry a minimalistic bag when they head to a meeting or to the office. Impeccably made German quality, this is going to be the next ‘in’ item in the UL community, I reckon. </p>

<h2 id="gardner-outdoor-lightweight-designs">Gardner Outdoor Lightweight Designs</h2>
<p>Nothing new here besides the cottage itself! <a href="http://www.etsy.com/shop/GOLDGearLite">Gardner Outdoor Lightweight Designs</a> offers Polycryo tarps, trekking poles and a variety of stoves. Prices are reasonable, so give them a look.</p>

<h2 id="lawson-equipment">Lawson Equipment</h2>
<p><a href="http://lawsonequipment.com/">Mountainfitter</a>, also known as Lawson Equipment, sells a variety of UL accessories that you might need but are hard to find. While in the past they have offered Cuben shelters, these are at the moment not available. </p>

<h2 id="klymit">Klymit</h2>
<p>While <a href="http://klymit.com/">Klymit</a> is not really a cottage I’d say, those who like amphibian travel options (aka packrafting) will be delighted to hear that the company is planning to bring out <a href="http://gearjunkie.com/best-in-show-outdoor-retailer-winter-2013">a small packraft</a>. 907 grams light and it packs as small as a book. It looks like another company realizes that packrafting is a growing segment for outdoors people, and at $225 it is even cheaper than the FlytePacker!</p>

<h2 id="flyweight-designs">FlyWeight Designs</h2>
<p>Speaking of <a href="http://flyweightdesigns.com/">FlyWeight Designs</a>, besides the new website (well, it went life last year in spring =) there’s not much information coming from the company. They were working on a inflatable seat last year, as well as on a new sub-2 kg packraft, but otherwise there hasn’t been much news from them. <em>I heard back from Marc and they’re indeed still working on some prototypes, so keep you eyes on their site for news.</em></p>

<h2 id="hyperlite-mountain-gear">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> is set to enter the Pyramid Shelter segment this year, with one-person, two-person and four-person sizes. Yes, that’s right - and that’s all I’m able to tell you at the moment. Sorry! Keep your eyes on their website &amp; social media channels to get a glimpse of these shelters at some point!</p>

<p>In 2012 HMG released a couple of note-worthy UL items, like a 3400 cu in version of their ice climbing and winter mountaineering pack, the <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/packs/3400-ice-pack.html">Ice Pack</a>. I have the 2400 version and love it, so the extra space in this pack means you can go for a weekender to the mountains and carry it all in your pack. A removable, padded hip belt adds a bit more comfort and support, and the exterior patch for crampon and ice axe attachment makes sure nothing spiky can destroy your pack. Oh, and a 4400 cu in version of this pack, as well as the Windrider, are in the works, too. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/packs/3400-ice-pack.html" title="3400 Ice Pack"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8224/8446343289_f740b6036b_b.jpg" width="681" height="1024" alt="3400-ice-front" /></a></p>

<p>Another pack I’ve been using for a long time now got a 2400 cu in version: The <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/packs/hmg-porter-pack-72.html">Porter Pack</a>. This smaller brother comes without a frame and weighs 737 gram, and now comes with the option to add two Spectra Hardline, zippered hip belt pockets, and of course has the simplicity of its big brothers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/hiking-climbing-shelters/tarps/hmg-flat-tarps.html">Cuben fiber flat tarps</a> in three sizes came out in 2012 as well. A flat tarp is a great, versatile shelter and it’s good to see these kind of shelters being offered. </p>

<h2 id="more">More</h2>
<p>That ain’t all! Today (Wednesday) you should head over to Benjamin from <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/?p=1712">hrXXLight</a> to see what’s new from LOCUS GEAR, enLIGHTened equipment, Aarn Designs and others! </p>

<p><em>Itching to buy some of this new gear? Once it becomes available you should surf to <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/index.php?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a> your European source for many of these brands, and save yourself the hassle on shipping &amp; expensive customs charges. They will carry much of the new gear, I was told!</em></p>

<p><strong>Did you know</strong> that I am trying to make Hiking in Finland my main job? If you liked this article, <a href="https://holvi.com/shop/hikinginfinland/product/dd006c907dfc0805441be88068460867/">buy me a cup of coffee</a> to support me!</p>

<p><em>Are you a cottage manufacturer or know of one and should be included in this &amp; future articles? <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#046;&#109;&#111;&#114;&#107;&#101;&#108;&#064;&#103;&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">Email me</a>!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
