<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Patagonia | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/patagonia/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-15T22:21:48+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-08T11:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What if <a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a> would go and build an alpine climbing pack that is minimalistic, comfortable, highly water-resistant and durable? Would it work also for backpacking?</em> These and other questions I answer in this review.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193953927" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/14193953927_5201bcbb49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia/rucksack.html">Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L</a> landed here in March 2014 and has been used various times at the local crag and in Chamonix, a week backpacking in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/lake-district/">Lake District</a> and a week climbing &amp; hiking in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/poland/">Polish Tatras</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193760149" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2916/14193760149_8ba4f829a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>This is a streamlined alpine climbing backpack with more space than it’s litte brothers (there’s a <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia/rucksack.html">25 l</a> and <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia/rucksack.html">35 l</a> version available), made to carry more climbing gear for big ascents and/ or an overnight kit. It carries very well thanks to the Aluminium frame and easily can be used for week-long ultralight backpacking strips.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14378961872" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2926/14378961872_aeec0f6d90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>This is what Patagonia says about their pack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Light and durable nylon ripstop with excellent tear and abrasion resistance </li>
  <li>The spindrift collar opens wide for easy packing; drawcord simultaneously cinches collar and closes lid for a secure seal; additional spindrift collar deploys to protect your gear when you have overstuffed your pack</li>
  <li>Aluminium stay frame with tensioned mesh center gives the pack structure and helps to support heavy loads and can be removed for Fast &amp; Light adventures</li>
  <li>Padded hip belt can be removed to create a simple webbing hip belt</li>
  <li>Center sheath ice axe carry system accommodates a wide assortment of axes</li>
  <li>Daisy chains on front and side panels provide lashing options; compression straps on sides help manage different size loads; zippered pocket on lid provides easy access to small items</li>
</ul>

<p>What they fail to mention is that this pack is the brain-child of Steve House, one of the world’s top alpinists. This pack won’t make you climb like him, but at least you can carry your gear like him =)</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/FnWap_pZ3YU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Something I haven’t seen before is the internal frame system that Patagonia uses in this pack. It’s an aluminium frame that’s covered by mesh and that’s super flexible - you can twist it 180° so it gives the pack great freedom of movement. The DWR on the material is also very good and kept my gear inside dry during hikes in sustained, heavy rain from all angles. Also the inside rain-cover is a nice way to not need an external one when you carry more gear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624434903" title="Patagonia Ascensionist internal frame by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5530/14624434903_5969025411_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist internal frame" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After over two weeks of backpacking, climbing and scrambling with it it still shows no tears or signs of weakness. The DWR also still holds up very well, and all seams - despite some heavier loads and being fully packed - are still perfect like on day one. I think this pack will be with me for many hikes and climbs to come.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624459203" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3918/14624459203_a9bd18b0f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Patagonia Ascensionist is available in two lengths and I have the S/ M length of the pack. </p>

<p>Stripped Pack: 847
Frame: 151 g
Hipbelt: 140 g</p>

<p>TOTAL: 1138g</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417796848" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3838/14417796848_c8389e3d6c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="770" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>It’s Patagonia who made this pack so you know it has top-notch environmental credentials. ‘Nuff said!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602382524" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2939/14602382524_dd6979ab34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a wide variety of <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/kletterrucksack.html">climbing backpacks</a>, very good ones are the <a href="http://bit.ly/1qR0yaH">Crux AK-47</a> and the <a href="http://www.campsaver.com/speed-22-pack">Black Diamond Speed</a> packs. <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/">Cilogear</a> also makes top-notch climbing packs, as does <a href="http://www.mchalepacks.com/ultralight/index.htm">McHale</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14581386756" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3904/14581386756_39bdddd491_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The closure of the pack is really nice. It is easy to open and close, even if it seems like an old-fashioned closure it is a smart system in my opinion. You can close it with one hand, opening with both. You pull the cord to close it, and then put the aluminium hook through the webbing loop. Even when fully packed it’s easy to open and close and most important - it stays closed. The front aluminium hook can be moved up if it’s really fully loaded. </p>

<p>The elastic loops to tie down straps are a very nice detail. This way webbing does not dangle around when the straps are pulled tight - if you’re anal-retentive about straps and stuff dangling around on your pack and like things to be orderly you will really like this small addition to all the straps.</p>

<p>Your ice axes or <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools.html">ice tools</a> are connected to the pack via a small and durable ice axe pocket with a buckle at the front pocket and the shafts are held in place by the side compression straps. It’s a safe, good system for transport to the mountain and when you really won’t need it. For in between sections where you won’t need the tools you can store the ice axe He-Man style between your shoulder blade and strap.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14581388176" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2903/14581388176_f817a9ed5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<p>The top pocket is surprisingly spacious and I can fit a large amount of stuff in there. Map, compass, sunscreen, lip balm, snacks, shades, extra camera lens - and still room to spare. It’s fairly weatherproof too, so in case you forgot your phone’s rain cover it’s safe in there (but even safer inside the pack!).</p>

<p>For a 45 l pack the Ascensionist is super spacious. Food and UL kit for six days + 2 l water were no problem for it, and there would have been even more space - that large opening + inside rainflap makes it a very large backpack. But also a full trad kit, helmet, harness, crampons and rope + UL sleeping gear and snacks fit in there with some room left. I really like the form of the pack with the narrow bottom and the wider top - it makes for easy packing. Food or climbing gear go in the bottom, followed by down garments and rain clothes, kitchen, quilt, bivy, shelter and helmet. Water bottles I store on the top of everything for easy access.</p>

<p>So is the Ascensionist better with the frame or without? That’s a difficult question to answer. In the Lake District I had the frame in the pack and found it worked superb. In the Polish Tatras I left the frame at home and also found it excellent. Subjectively I feel with the frame it carries slightly better and transfers weight more effectively to the hipbelt. The pack has what feels like a closed cell foam pad in the back which does a good job of keeping the shape of the pack when the frame is removed and also gives a bit of extra cushioning against your back. </p>

<p>Moving with it - climbing, hiking, scrambling - is wonderful. It rides high on the waist and does not limit movement at all. As it is a streamlined pack it you also have no stuff at the sides in your way, and low chances of the pack snagging something along the route or trail. As the pack is narrow and not very deep it’s close to the body so you can squeeze through tight passages, and your centre of gravity is close to where it’s supposed to be. The thickly cushioned shoulder straps are comfy also on long days, as is the hip belt. The gear loops on the hip belt are solid and a welcome addition to rack gear on long routes.</p>

<p>Oh, and you also can attach the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Designs Capture PRO</a> wonderfully to the shoulder straps!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417878278" title="Hiking in the Polish Tatras by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5507/14417878278_ff97606b7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking in the Polish Tatras" /></a></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>When climbing with the frame in the pack I often would hit my head on it when looking up, which is not good. Removing the frame solves this, but it’s better with the frame inside for carrying heavier loads. If it’s possible I’d imagine making the internal frame shorter would solve this, as would a gap for the helmet when climbing/ looking up. </p>

<p>You can remove the padded hipbelt (and save 140 gram weight) but it’s too complicated - mainly because the wide webbing belt is sewn to the pack and can’t be removed. So you need to thread the webbing through the padding loops to take it off. I’d wish that everything could have been removed easily - I don’t see much sense in using the webbing as a hipbelt.</p>

<p>Water Management is not as straight forward as I’d like it to be. There’s no hydration system exit and no side pockets, so you need to take the pack off to drink. When climbing this is fine as you likely take the pack off at the belay and then can drink, but when hiking it’s not convenient to stop every 30 minutes to take the pack off to access your water bottle. You could attach your water bottle with a carabiner to the gear loop on the hipbelt, though I think that would be annoying if you have a bottle dangling in front of your legs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417828779" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3924/14417828779_643901874a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>At the moment the Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L is my favourite backpack. It carries very well, is large enough for week-long trips - be it climbing or backpacking - and can take a lot of abuse. It’s weatherproof, easy to pack, the big haul loop makes it easy to grab the pack &amp; put on, and the cushioned shoulder straps and hip belt make it comfortable to carry also on 30 km days with 2000+ m of ascent. Most importantly it does not bother me when climbing or scrambling and gives me freedom of movement to go to those high places I enjoy so much! If you’re in the market for a large-volume alpine climbing backpack I can really recommend the Ascensionist 45L from <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia.html">Patagonia</a>.</p>

<p>Oh, in orange it also looks great - Hup Holland Hup!</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Get your Ascensionist pack at <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia/rucksack.html">Unterwegs.biz</a> if you are in Europe, from <a href="http://bit.ly/1qG5cXo">CampSaver</a> if you’re in the USA or directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1lPYO9Z">Patagonia</a> everywhere else. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602411384" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3917/14602411384_f4f4f02911_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lightweight Hiking Pants]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-pants.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-28T18:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-pants</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Together with a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts.html">lightweight shirt</a> you’ll need something lightweight to cover your legs - unless you like sunburn, nettle and mosquito stings, and dust - lots of dust because you are so fast &amp; light!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6966862963/" title="Seven-legged hiking pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7176/6966862963_aa9a9fffb2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Seven-legged hiking pants" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Pants =/= Pants. I didn’t think so in the beginning, but have realized through much experience since that lighter pants are a lot more comfortable than <em>“heavy”</em> pants. I don’t have objective proof that they make you hike faster and better, but a well fitting, light pants just makes the hiking in my experience more comfortable. All pants underneath I have picked with durability, windproofness, comfort and quick-drying in mind and they’ve seen years of use, so if you’re looking for a new pair of pants - check these out! <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157629182054730/">More photos of all pants on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-palisade">Arc’teryx Palisade</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 307 g</td>
      <td> Material: 94% TerraTex—nylon, 6% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>My go-to pants since they arrived three years ago. Have they held up well in those years? Absolutely. The only damage to them is a tiny burn hole in the leg as I was sitting too close to the fire and a spark burned through it, but other than that they’re still in tip-top shape. And I haven’t been kind to them: Backpacking, bouldering, climbing, bikepacking, hiking, and because they’re so comfortable I’ve also worn them during “normal” activities whenever I could get away with it. All pockets are zipped which is superb, because that way your phone, wallet, keys and whatnot stays inside and doesn’t fall out of your pocket while you hike, run, climb or sit. They are absolutely windproof, dry very quickly, are a slim fit and very minimalistic in their appearance so fit well under a pair of rain pants. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Get a pair at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-palisade-pant-graphite.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/10Fk74J">Backcountry.com</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13XfHu6">CampSaver.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870574360/" title="Arc'teryx Palisade pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7291/8870574360_d19a99c37e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Arc'teryx Palisade pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="backpacking-light-thorofare-pants">Backpacking Light Thorofare Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: M</td>
      <td> Weight: 113 g</td>
      <td> Material: 100% Nylon (I guess)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The Thorofare pants get’s a honourable mention - not because it’s the lightest pants I own, but because it ain’t available anymore (unless you happen to pick one up on Gear Swap). Windproof, light like a feather, quick drying, two pockets and two cargo pockets, and an elastic “belt” to keep the pants up (don’t overload those pockets thus). In hot environments where there’s no wind going they might be a tad hot, but other than that they’re excellent. If you can get your hands on one, get a pair for those SUL trips where the lightest pants is what you want.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870106505/" title="BPL Thorofare pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5453/8870106505_333a97a2a7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="BPL Thorofare pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-traverse-pants">Rab Traverse Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 295 g</td>
      <td> Material: 93% Polyamide, 7% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The second-most worn pants, the <a href="http://rab.uk.com/">Rab</a> Traverse pants also sports zipped pockets, which in my book is always good as it is just a bit safer. It has a push-button closure, which is very comfortable and is bomb-proof. UPF 35 gives plenty of UV protection for your legs, and if you only carry one pant and want to wash it on the trail - the Traverse pants will be dry again in no time. A very comfortable fit that’s also excellent for acrobatic climbing moves, this is a pants that is great in the backcountry as well as in town. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870099019/" title="Rab Traverse Pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2880/8870099019_9bc4a6648d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab Traverse Pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="patagonia-zip-off-pants">Patagonia Zip-Off Pants</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 32</td>
      <td> Weight: 326 g</td>
      <td> Material: 96% Polyamide, 4% Spandex</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>A Zip-off pants?</em> Yes! <em>Why?</em> Because in very hot &amp; humid environments I like shorts. So instead of trapping my athletic calves in polyamide, I let them taste the sun and wind. It’s getting too windy? Just zip them back on. Patagonia was extremely smart when making the zippers for this pants: They’re two different colours, so no more mixing up left &amp; right legs. Also this pant is durable, windproof and dries very fast, and if you walk a lot in environments where the weather lets you wear shorts during the day while in the evenings a long pair of pants is preferable, check these out.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-nomader-zip-off-hose-stone.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/18x7PAt">Backcountry.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870750934/" title="Patagonia Pants by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3783/8870750934_9dcbf1d205_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Pants" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fjllrven-greenland-trousers">Fjällräven Greenland Trousers</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: 44</td>
      <td> Weight: 537 g</td>
      <td> Material: G-1000 aka 65% polyester, 35% cotton</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><em>Fjällräven pants?</em> Yes, because I still own a pair. The defacto standard trouser for the outdoors man &amp; women population in Scandinavia, it feels like it’s the pants you gotta wear when you go to the Fjell. I thought so too when I was a young grasshopper, but not anymore. If you waxed them before you head out they’re OK waterproof-ish, though they will soak through in a deluge just as much as the other pants above. And then they need more time to dry. They got seven pockets, which would mean an SUL backpacker could just carry his gear in this pants. I also needed a belt with these pants, as the sizing of them is even in the smallest size too big for me.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/s/fj%C3%A4llr%C3%A4ven/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/fjaellraeven-trekkinghose/">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13Xglb4">Backcountry.com</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8870061787/" title="Fjällräven Greenland trousers by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8546/8870061787_7a2846ab8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fjällräven Greenland trousers" /></a></p>

<p>There are a lot more pants - but I haven’t worn them and hence can’t judge them. The most worn ones for me are the Arc’teryx and Rab pants, as I like their zippered pockets, I know that they’re super-durable and allow enough movement for climbing and bouldering, they’re windproof and dry quickly if they get wet. Oh, and they look both also rather good! <strong>What are your favourite lightweight pants?</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lightweight Hiking Shirts]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T18:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/05/lightweight-hiking-shirts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Summer. What better time to be outdoors: The sun shines, a breeze goes through the grass, a light pack is on your back, butterflies fly by, and you wear a light shirt to keep you cool.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bmp_creep/8698798735/" title="2012-08-02 00.40.02 by b.m.p., on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8268/8698798735_4a8df70265_b.jpg" width="1024" height="679" alt="2012-08-02 00.40.02" /></a>
© <a href="http://hikesinatra.blogspot.com/">bmp</a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="patagonia-mens-capilene-1-silkweight-t-shirt">Patagonia Men’s Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: M</td>
      <td> Weight: 94 g</td>
      <td> Material: 100% Polyester</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>If you look for the lightest shirt with the best environmental credentials and great looks, then you won’t need to look further than the Patagonia Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirts. I love mine and its probably my most-worn shirt if I hit the trail. It dries in mere minutes in the sun, the funk (<em>that’s informal American English for smelly</em>) is minimal and 15-UPF sun protection keeps you from burning (although it could be more). It’s surprisingly durable for being so light, climbing and bushwacking didn’t pull a single thread from it, and it’s been in use since two years already. It feels very good on the skin and you’ll look good with this shirt on the trail as well as walking the dog in town.  My go-to shirt, if it’s not in the wash!</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/patagonia-capilene-1-sw-graphic-t-shirt.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/patagonia-capilene-1-silkweight-stretch-t-shirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.patagonia.com/us/product/mens-capilene-baselayer-1-silkweight-graphic-t-shirt?p=45321-1-791">Patagonia</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13nUCrw">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/18qa7T1">REI</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/13nUQ1Z">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717114654/" title="Patagonia Men's Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7425/8717114654_2ecd5b0f2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Men's Capilene 1 Silkweight T-Shirt" /></a></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-ether-crew-ss">Arc’teryx Ether Crew SS</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 108 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 100% Polyester</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This shirt has been updated since I got it (it’s the problem of testing gear long-term, ya see!) and now sports mesh underarm panels, which does seem like a very nice improvement. However, my “old” shirt is still looking good as it is quite durable. It’s a good looking shirt, though after a few days wearing it on the trail it needs a wash as the guff (that’s informal Scottish for smelly) is tangible. It’s UPF Rating of 50+ keeps your skin aristocratic white, while the flatlocked seams add much comfort to the wearing experience. The fabric comes in a bunch of nice colours, and once you’ve hiked up a mountain in 35°C and the shirt is drenched in your sweat the fabric’s quick-drying capabilities will kick in and you’ll have a dry shirt in no time (well, maybe about 10 to 15 minutes).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/16OIeod">Backcountry</a> </td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-ether-comp-crew-ss-funktionsshirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717116334/" title="Arc'teryx Ether Crew SS by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7328/8717116334_8431851723_b.jpg" width="1024" height="546" alt="Arc'teryx Ether Crew SS" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-meco-120tee">Rab MeCo 120 Tee</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 111 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 65% Merino, 35% Cocona</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>A shirt made of <em>ethically sourced Australian Merino wool and recycled polyester with Cocona technology</em> which has gotten a lot of positive reviews. I have found them great shirts, the 120g/m² fabric is light and dries very fast, rivalling the synthetic shirts above. They do pill a bit, but it’s just a cosmetic thing and doesn’t affect it’s durability. Speaking off, I used mine for climbing, hiking, cycling and everyday use for over 12 months, and they still look great. The reflective details are a nice touch which cyclists and pedestrians will appreciate, and the flatlock seams make them comfortable to wear. They also do not easily smell, I can wear mine for five days and more and they still don’t reek. If you’re looking for the best of both worlds - that’s merino &amp; synthetic combined - then you’ve found it with Rab’s MeCo garments. Here’s more <a href="http://rab.uk.com/reference/technology/baselayer/meco.html">info on Cocona</a> if you’re of the curious kind.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/10lOht7">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/baselayer/meco-120-tee.html">Rab</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/rab_meco_120_tee.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8715999439/" title="Rab MeCo 120 Tee by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7339/8715999439_0eccb79614_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab MeCo 120 Tee" /></a></p>

<h2 id="rab-meco-120ls-tee">Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 148 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 65% Merino, 35% Cocona</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The same material and properties than the Rab MeCo 120 Tee above, I have used this longsleeve on colder days in spring and autumn, and as a layering piece in winter. Because it dries so fast it is in winter quite nice to wear, but not on its own - an Aclima Woolnet longsleeve underneath it is a great combination. Also for summer use, if you want to protect your arms a bit more from the sun or easily get cold in a stiff breeze, this longsleeve fits the bill. </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/11eqJNm">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://rab.uk.com/products/mens-clothing/baselayer/meco-120-long-sleeve-tee.html">Rab</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.ultralightoutdoorgear.co.uk/rab_meco_120_long_sleeved_tee.html">Ultralight Outdoor Gear</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8717116892/" title="Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7393/8717116892_7af29e03fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Rab MeCo 120 LS Tee" /></a></p>

<h2 id="icebreaker-tech-t-lite-short-sleeve-lancewood">icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Size: S</td>
      <td> Weight: 138 g</td>
      <td>  Material: 100% Merino</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>It’s a fancy name, but then it’s a fancy shirt as well! The only 100% Merino summer shirt in my closet at the moment, this is a great T-shirt in so many respects: Even after a week on the trail it doesn’t reek (maybe just a tiny bit), it dries reasonably fast (slower than the synthetic shirts, though), it’s very comfortable on the skin and it too looks superb. Where the synthetic shirts dry fast, the Merino one needs a bit longer to get dry, though that also can be a benefit if you’re hiking in sweltering heat - in that case the shirt provides a bit more cooling. If you’re hiking on a trail where you’ll be in the company of a lot of other people (staying in huts, for example) this one might be your best choice - you’ll smell less and look good =)</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://bit.ly/10lFBTB">icebreaker</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/icebreaker-sf150-tech-t-lite-lancewood-funktionsshirt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10060&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Ficebreaker-tech-lite-stripe-mountain-t-shirt-short-sleeve-mens">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;mi=10008&amp;pw=73183&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Ftech-t-lite-short-sleeve-men-s">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/icebreaker-tech-t-lite-ridge-stealth.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8715996421/" title="icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7322/8715996421_6cca361558_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="icebreaker Tech T Lite Short Sleeve Lancewood" /></a></p>

<p>Of course these aren’t all lightweight shirts that are available. You can get good shirts from <a href="http://www.chocolatefishmerino.co.uk/">Chocolate Fish</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/17JcA9E">The North Face</a>, <a href="http://www.mountainhardwear.eu/mens-shirts-tees/mens-tops,default,sc.html?prefn1=productSubcategory&amp;prefv1=Short%20Sleeve&amp;prefn2=activity&amp;prefv2=024">Mountain Hardwear</a>, <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/or-gear/shirts.html">Outdoor Research</a> (which also make <a href="http://www.outdoorresearch.com/en/or-gear/shirts/mens-echo-sentinel-l-s-crew.html">Insect Shield</a> shirts!), <a href="http://www.salomonrunning.com/ir/segment/trail-running-tees.html">Salomon</a>, <a href="http://marmot.com/catalog/mens/shirts/ultralight/216-132-185--4?ft=185">Marmot</a> and many more.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8716001087/" title="Lightweight hiking shirts by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7389/8716001087_df160b3591_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lightweight hiking shirts" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
