<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: interviews | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/interviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-08T18:03:54+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barry Blanchard Interview]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-23T11:11:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-interview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An interview with Barry Blanchard, one of Canada’s most famous Alpinists, in which we chat about music, fear and his book “<a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">The Calling</a>”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15606594195" title="Barry Blanchard by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5608/15606594195_52bea0a1b6_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Barry Blanchard" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Barry, thanks for taking the time to answer a few questions from an aspiring Alpinist in Finland. First things first: What song are you right now listening too?</strong></p>

<p><em>Snake Farm by Ray Wylie Hubbard. I’ve listen his music since I was teenager and had the pleasure of meeting the man, and his wife, Judy, yesterday at a concert in the park. Very, very cool.</em></p>

<p><strong>What’s your favourite medium: MP3, Vinyl or Cassettes?</strong></p>

<p><em>I listen to most music on my computer these days so I guess its MP3, although I still listen to CDs in my truck.</em></p>

<p><strong>If you would make a mixtape for a road trip, which songs would definitely be on there?</strong></p>

<p><em>On my road tripping mix there would definitely be: King of the Road by Roger Miller, Six Days on the Road by Dave Dudley and a cover by Steve Earle, Hurtin Albertan by Corb Lund and by Tim Hus, Running on Empty by Jackson Browne, Continental Trailways Blues by Steve Earle, Brand New Cadillac by the Clash, Cadillac Ranch by Bruce Springsteen, Born to Run by Bruce Springsteen … and the list goes on.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15421002960" title="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/15421002960_d3178af41a_b.jpg" width="678" height="1024" alt="Me at Les Calanques on the south coast of France,.where Wally and I went to rock climb and get our.heads together before attempting Les Droites..Photo: Kevin Doyle" /></a></p>

<p><strong>I really enjoyed reading your book, by the way. It was raw, to the point and I had a few good laughs. It also had a Quentin Tarantino-esque feel to it at times: Good music, story lines that interweave and come together at the end. Did you plan it like that?</strong></p>

<p><em>My friend, Mark Twight, told me that my book would not end up being what I thought it would be, and that it would be more work than I thought it would be. He was right on both counts. I wanted to write a full 360 degree view of my life and climbing as I believe that much of the value in my writing is that which is common to all people: love, loss, desire, fear, hurt, joy. I believe I share the most that way and that is what writing is for me, a hope to share a little something about life with people.</em></p>

<p><strong>The weather this summer in Chamonix seems to have been much the same as you first visited the crucible of European Alpinism. Any idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer?</strong></p>

<p><em>I have no idea how many people climbed the North Face of Les Droites this summer. Mark Twight and I were pleased to see that our route, The Richard Cranium Memorial, had several repeats in the last couple years and that the ascensionists seemed to enjoy it.</em></p>

<p><strong>Reinhold Messner, another of your idols judging from your book, just got 70 in September. Did you send him a card or where even invited?</strong></p>

<p><em>Reinhold didn’t invite me to his birthday, but he might have invited my guiding mentor, Rudi Kranibitter, who took Reinhold out climbing in Reinhold’s early days and taught him some stuff. Rudi once told me “Ya, that guy was a fast learner!”</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14985858864" title="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3946/14985858864_8c1c2399df_b.jpg" width="710" height="1024" alt="Out of the leading with a bruised and battered.right shoulder blade, I ride the jumars on the.east face of Mount Fay. Photo: David Cheesmond" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You are well-read and have devoured a lot of books - from Heinrich Harrer’s “The White Spider” to Lionel Terray’s “Conquistadors of the Useless”. If you could recommend just three books to aspiring alpinists, which ones would that be?</strong></p>

<p><em>I would recommend: <a href="http://amzn.to/1xc7z5m">The Great Days</a> by Walter Bonatti, <a href="http://amzn.to/1vRe3bB">The Seventh Grade</a> by Reinhold Messner and <a href="http://amzn.to/12gRwtY">Feeding the Rat</a> by Al Alvarez.</em></p>

<p><strong>One of your colleagues, Andy Kirkpatrick from the UK, made in his essay “How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche” his first point to not have kids. You’re a father of two - do you feel you climbed harder pre-fatherhood or that you stayed on the same level?</strong></p>

<p><em>I definitely climbed harder before the birth of my daughters but I became a father at 45 and I was, by then, far past my physical prime that was, for me, between 25 and 35. I just can’t climb as hard now, especially at 55! as I could when I was younger. But! the inner journey up the easier mountain is still as challenging and rewarding, maybe more so on both counts.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15582918726" title="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3951/15582918726_29591133dd_b.jpg" width="672" height="1024" alt="Kevin, Jim, Albi, and I jump for joy and relief.on hearing that Sharon and Dwayne are OK.after making the summit of Mount Everest..Photo: Bob Lee" /></a></p>

<p><strong>As someone who likes to climb mountains myself it feels like the majority of climbers nowadays are rather enjoying themselves in gyms or bouldering. How would you try to get these people outside?</strong></p>

<p><em>I think that once gym climbers and boulders experience the added challenges of traditional climbing, especially dealing with risk, some of them will be called to the richness of alpinism, but it is a dangerous game so it is not for everyone.</em></p>

<p><strong>Is there a chapter of your climbing life that you wished would have made it in the book still?</strong></p>

<p><em>When I sat down to write The Calling I thought that it would cover my whole climbing life, but I’ve been cursed with a long memory and seemed to have a lot to write. I’d like to write a second book to cover the rest of my climbing life beyond 1988.</em></p>

<p><strong>Well Barry, many thanks again and have fun on the book tour!</strong></p>

<p><em>You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/barry-blanchard-the-calling.html">read my Review of Barry’s book “The Calling” here</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview Marco Sánchez of As Tucas]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/04/interview-marco-sanchez-of-as-tucas.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-01T12:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/04/interview-marco-sanchez-of-as-tucas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It truly is a pleasure to introduce you to Marco Sánchez, the owner of Spain’s only ultralight gear cottage <a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a>. I have been talking online for a long time with Marco, and we almost went on a packrafting trip together. While that tour wasn’t supposed to happen for me, I am certain that in the future I will be hiking with Marco in his home country and experience the beauty of the Pyrenees. But for now I’m very excited to let Marco tell his story and how he made his passion his work!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539401254" title="Camping in the snow, but enjoying the warmth of the sunrise. "><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7154/13539401254_e93214847a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Camping in the snow, but enjoying the warmth of the sunrise." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Marco, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking &amp; packrafting, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>Since my childhood I have been in close contact with nature, although I was born and bread in Zaragoza, a Spanish city. I fondly remember trips with my parents by the river and to the countryside. This is how my passion by nature started.</p>

<p>This passion has led me to play many mountain sports: backpacking, climbing, skiing, biking and more. It is a way to stay in touch with nature. My favorite area is the Pyrenees, which I consider my backyard.</p>

<p>Recently, I’ve started packrafting too. It’s a very interesting way of travelling that I had been pondering for a while. An expedition at Norway on 2012 with my friends <a href="http://thunderinthenight.blogspot.com.es/2012/07/always-have-plan-b-and-c.html">Joe Newton</a> and <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2012/07/vassfaret-slippery-and-wet-part-1/">Benjamin Morrison</a> was the perfect introduction.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539085615" title="Taking a break during a packrafting trip by the Gállego river."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7085/13539085615_53a5cf2af1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="688" alt="Taking a break during a packrafting trip by the Gállego river." /></a></p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>Almost everyday. It recharges my energy and makes me feel part of the environment. Thus, I try to be outdoors as much as possible. During the week I run and ride my mountain bike. I also go for quick walks. Longer trips are reserved for weekends and holidays. Since I founded As Tucas my free time has been considerably reduced. As a consequence, now I’m a fan of “micro adventures”. These, made ​​popular by <a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com">Alastair Humphreys</a>, are an excellent way to enjoy the surroundings when your time is limited. I recommend give it a shot!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539185913" title="Micro adventure by bike."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7207/13539185913_a281fb04be_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Micro adventure by bike." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are you more of a “weekend warrior” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>I make the most of weekends and holidays to go to the mountains. In addition, I like to do some week-long or longer trips every year. These longer trips, in a self-supported style, allow me a greater level of connection with nature.</p>

<p><strong>Which category would you put yourself in: SUL, UL, or Lightweight? What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>My base weight for a typical 3 season weekend trip is 3.5 kg. So, we can say that I’m an ultralight (UL) hiker. However, taking into account other criteria besides weight, I consider myself a super ultralight (SUL) hiker. I find revealing Ryan Jordan’s article <a href="http://www.backpackinglight.com/cgi-bin/backpackinglight/sul-mindset-jordan.html">The SUL Mindset</a>. I carry a very small number of items. Nothing is superfluous and everything works as an integrated system. I backpack in a mountain area with variable weather. Freezing nights are not unusual even during the summer. This requires a more solid and robust kit than the one required in other areas. This also makes more difficult lighten some items such your sleeping bag and shelter.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539086675" title="Contemplating the Acherito mountain lake."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7064/13539086675_f3d9c56533_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Contemplating the Acherito mountain lake." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “<a href="http://astucas.com/en/">As Tucas</a>” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>“As Tucas” means “The summits” in Aragonese, the language of our region. It’s a humble recognition to our territory and mountaineer spirit. Furthermore, all our products are named after the local names of mountains, valleys and rivers.</p>

<p><strong>You have a degree in physics and have worked as a teacher before, and you live in a country where unemployment is sadly very high. Was it an easy decision to leave the security of a regular job behind in order to pursue a career in something that you like a lot?</strong></p>

<p>No, it was not an easy decision. However, I do not regret it at all. I have always valued my motivation and personal satisfaction above other factors, such as money. The desire to learn new things has led me to work in several companies at diverse positions: as a teacher, web developer or systems analyst. Unfortunately, the current economic crisis makes it much more difficult to move to another job. Without realizing it, I was stuck in a job that no longer satisfied me. That lack of motivation was crying for a pivot point. Nothing better than turning my passion into my way to make a living.</p>

<p><strong>As Tucas makes custom gear, garments, quilts and shelters. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</strong></p>

<p>I have been making most of my garments and gear as a hobby for years. However, I must admit that considering the thriving american cottages, I wondered if something like that would be possible in Europe.</p>

<p>My necessity to change prompted me to take action. Suddenly, I was full of energy and motivation, developing a bunch of ideas, learning new things and facing challenges. In short, I was turning a dream into a reality.</p>

<p>There are lots of work “behind the scenes” so As Tucas can make a difference. Its future involves bringing together the best of cottages and the best of big brands.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539396734" title="Marking out a Sestrals quilt on the cutting table."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7366/13539396734_d955c24a96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Marking out a Sestrals quilt on the cutting table." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in Spain?</strong></p>

<p>No, as far as I know. In Spain, like in the rest of Europe, starting up a business is more difficult than in the United States. The bureaucratic process is more complex and there is a higher tax burden. Therefore, the number of cottages is so small.</p>

<p><strong>Your company is a mere four months old and already has been received very well all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>I am very pleased with the As Tucas start. Moreover, it has exceeded all my expectations. It was a high-stakes movement, but market reception indicates me that this is the way to go. Now, it’s time to continue improving our product catalog, the production processes and our customer service, key points of our success.</p>

<p><strong>You entered a business segment which a) isn’t very well served by cottages because b) it’s perceived as difficult. How did you decide to offer <a href="http://astucas.com/en/clothing/">garments</a>, when so many others find it a hard business?</strong></p>

<p>Because it is a challenge, but a great opportunity too. Due to their design and the materials used to make them, each of our garments is unique. But more importantly, these garments are designed as an integrated system. They work together allowing you to face a broader range of conditions at a minimal weight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539081455" title="Setting up a machine at the sewing line."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7408/13539081455_fed0457b13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Setting up a machine at the sewing line." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of the <a href="http://astucas.com/en/clothing/cabietos-hoody">Cabietos Hoody</a>, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>Based on our experience, a base layer shirt for mountain activities should combine three key design elements: a hood that protects your face, wrist cuffs with thumb holes and a really long chest zipper. This combo provides an incredible versatility. Although there are excellent products on the market, none of them combines these three elements. The closest was the Backpacking Light Beartooth Merino Wool Hoody, which is no longer available. However, the Cabietos hoody has even greater thermoregulation capabilities and a more durable merino wool fabric.</p>

<p><strong>In addition to garments you also offer a cuben (and silnylon) tarp and a synthetic quilt. Will we see a tent/shelter in the future from As Tucas, or maybe a backpack? Or will you continue to concentrate on garment design, and maybe offer a windjacket/ hardshell soon?</strong></p>

<p>Our catalog is evolving, and will be extended with new products this year. However, we should concentrate our efforts to continue offering something unique and with exceptional value. For this reason, we are not going to enter in some market segments which, in our opinion, are already well served.</p>

<p><strong>Marco, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! Can you let us know what kind of new products you’re working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>Immediately, our high loft synthetic collection will be expanded with a jacket. As we did with the pants, we have exceeded the mythical Backpacking Light Cocoon collection again, with a lighter and better performing garment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539083065" title="The new Sestrals pullover."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/13539083065_e0e24eae66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="The new Sestrals pullover." /></a></p>

<p>In addition, we will make a major commitment to our down collection with new quilts. In doing so, we will be the very first to offer an integrated system of synthetic and down quilts. This combination, praised among others by the renowned alpinist <a href="http://www.andy-kirkpatrick.com/articles/view/double_up">Andy Kirkpatrick</a> and the hiker <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se / 2010/04/across-sarek-in-winter-sleep-system.html">Jörgen Johansson</a>, is a robust and modular 4 season sleeping system.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539183193" title="The new Foratata quilt."><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2807/13539183193_9bca885961_b.jpg" width="437" height="1024" alt="The new Foratata quilt." /></a></p>

<p>To go ahead with this, we have been searching high and low for a suitable down provider. We have started a collaboration with one of the largest polish down producers. They not only provides us the best down available (900 cuin) but does so certifying that it is collected with respect to animal welfare in accordance with European law, an important issue for us.</p>

<p><strong>Any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>We are always thinking how we can improve our products, and this often involves using new materials. We are going to introduce rainwear made ​​with a Cubic Tech CTF3 and eVent laminate, which is probably the lightest 3-layer waterproof and breathable material currently available. We also continue working with Schoeller in new and better fabrics for our garments and a forthcoming rainwear collection.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539396404" title="Evaluating the new Schoeller fabrics."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7185/13539396404_c81d1f97f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="742" alt="Evaluating the new Schoeller fabrics." /></a></p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at As Tucas, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems, which then are adopted in the As Tucas line-up?</strong></p>

<p>Our catalog was created around my personal needs, defined by my locale conditions and my own preferences. However, customers needs plays a more important role nowadays. This allows us to offer more versatile and robust products. Despite this, when your garments and gear are used from the deserts of Africa to the Arctic, the challenges are unique. For this reason, you need unique solutions too. Enter our custom works section, where we work directly with our customers to create their products.</p>

<p><strong>Where do your customer come from?</strong></p>

<p>Mainly from Europe. In addition, we have customers from other parts of the world like the USA and Japan. Curiously we don’t have many Spanish customers. Our mountaineering community is quite traditional and the ultralight philosophy is not widespread yet. Fortunately, the influence of other communities, such trail runners, is revolutionizing the mindset of many hikers.</p>

<p><strong>Are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Currently not many. We think that despite being competing companies, collaborating in some areas would be positive for both our businesses and our customers.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>This weekend! A snowshoeing trip at Ordesa Valley, one of my favorite places. This is an excellent time of the year. Sunny days, mild temperatures and plenty of snow to enjoy yet.</p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>Definitely Alaska. True wilderness at a large scale. More closely, the Sarek National Park in Lapland.</p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>A hoody (preferably a merino one) and a lightweight windshirt. This combo is so versatile that I use it year round in many activities. Another piece of gear that I consider my “luxury item” is a photographic tripod. I love photography. I appreciate its creative possibilities over the weight penalty. For that reason I carry it on many trips.</p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the Spanish spring?</strong></p>

<p>Of course! The Pyrenees are spectacular during spring and you should enjoy them. Days are longer and snow melting opens up lots of possibilities. By contrast, snow remains at high elevations, so you can plan really spectacular routes. We invite everyone to visit us. If you do so, do not hesitate to contact us and, why not! share a great day in the mountains.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/entrevista-marco-sanchez-de-as-tucas.html">Read the original Spanish version here</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539085565" title="Off-trail ridge walking."><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3828/13539085565_0788234ff8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Off-trail ridge walking." /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Entrevista: Marco Sánchez de As Tucas]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/04/entrevista-marco-sanchez-de-as-tucas.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-01T11:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/04/entrevista-marco-sanchez-de-as-tucas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Queridos lectores, es un placer para mi presentaros una entrevista con Marco Sánchez de <a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a>, el único “ultralight cottage manufacturer” de España. Estoy en contacto con Marco desde hace mucho, y por poco hicimos una excursión en Noruega hace unos años. Además, como esa excursión (en Noruega) tampoco fue posible para mi, tengo la esperanza de hacer una con Marco en los Pirineos más adelante. Pero ahora es una alegría el poder presentarte este entrevista en español.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539401254" title="Acampando en la nieve, aunque disfrutando del calor del amanecer."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7154/13539401254_e93214847a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Acampando en la nieve, aunque disfrutando del calor del amanecer." /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Marco, preséntate brevemente y dinos quién eres. ¿Desde cuándo practicas senderismo y packrafting? ¿Cómo empezaste?</strong></p>

<p>Desde pequeño he estado en contacto con la naturaleza, aunque nací y me crié en Zaragoza, una ciudad española de tamaño medio. Recuerdo con mucho cariño las excursiones con mis padres junto al río y al campo. Así es como se inició mi pasión por la naturaleza.</p>

<p>Como parte de esta pasión he desarrollado muchas actividades de montaña: senderismo, escalada, esquí, bicicleta… Es una forma de estar en contacto con la naturaleza. Mi entorno favorito son los Pirineos, un lugar fascinante.</p>

<p>Más recientemente también he comenzado a practicar packrafting. Es una forma de viajar muy interesante que llevaba considerando desde hace tiempo. Una travesía en 2012 por Noruega con mis amigos <a href="http://thunderinthenight.blogspot.com.es/2012/07/always-have-plan-b-and-c.html">Joe Newton</a> y <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2012/07/vassfaret-slippery-and-wet-part-1/">Benjamin Morrison</a> fue la iniciación perfecta.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539085615" title="Descansando durante una excursión en packraft por el río Gállego."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7085/13539085615_53a5cf2af1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="688" alt="Descansando durante una excursión en packraft por el río Gállego." /></a></p>

<p><strong>¿Con qué frecuencia estás al aire libre actualmente?</strong></p>

<p>Casi a diario. Me recarga de energía y me hace sentir parte del medio ambiente. Por eso trato de estar al aire libre el máximo tiempo posible. Entre semana voy a correr y en bicicleta de montaña. También realizo alguna excursión rápida. Las excursiones más largas se reservan para los fines de semana y las vacaciones.</p>

<p>Desde que fundé As Tucas mi tiempo libre se ha reducido considerablemente. Por eso últimamente soy un asiduo a las “micro aventuras”. Éstas, popularizadas por <a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com">Alastair Humphreys</a>, son una manera excelente de disfrutar del entorno próximo cuando tu tiempo es limitado. ¡Es algo que recomiendo probar a todo el mundo!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539185913" title="Micro aventura en bicicleta."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7207/13539185913_a281fb04be_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Micro aventura en bicicleta." /></a></p>

<p><strong>¿Eres un “guerrero de fin de semana” o tienes alguna excursión de larga distancia a tus espaldas?</strong></p>

<p>Aprovecho todos los fines de semana y festivos para salir a la montaña. Además, todos los años me gusta realizar alguna salida de una semana o más. Este tipo de excursiones, realizadas en plena autonomía, me permiten un grado mayor de conexión con la Naturaleza. </p>

<p><strong>¿En qué categoria te incluyes: super ultraligero, ultraligero o ligero? ¿Cual es tu peso base típico?</strong></p>

<p>Mi peso base para una salida típica de fin de semana en 3 estaciones es de 3,5 kg. Por tanto, podemos decir que soy un senderista ultraligero (UL).</p>

<p>Sin embargo, basándome en otros criterios además del peso, me  considero un senderista super ultraligero (SUL). A este respecto es revelador el artículo de Ryan Jordan, <a href="http://www.backpackinglight.com/cgi-bin/backpackinglight/sul-mindset-jordan.html">The SUL Mindset</a>. El número de elementos que llevo es muy pequeño. Nada es superfluo y todo trabaja como un sistema integrado. El entorno en que me muevo es una zona montañosa con clima cambiante, donde incluso en verano no es extraño llegar a los 0 C durante las noches. Se precisa de un equipo más sólido y robusto que en otras zonas. Por eso resulta más difícil reducir el peso de alguno elementos como el saco y el refugio.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539086675" title="Contemplando el Ibón de Acherito."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7064/13539086675_f3d9c56533_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Contemplando el Ibón de Acherito." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Por favor, indícanos el origen del nombre “As Tucas” y su significado.</strong></p>

<p>“<a href="http://astucas.com/">As Tucas</a>” significa “Las cumbres” en aragonés, lengua de nuestra región. Es un guiño hacia nuestro territorio y espíritu montañero. Asimismo, todos nuestros productos se denominan con los nombres locales de montañas, valles, ríos…</p>

<p><strong>Eres licenciado en Ciencias Físicas y anteriormente has trabajado de profesor. Desgraciadamente donde vives el desempleo es muy elevado. ¿Fue una decisión fácil dejar atrás la seguridad de un trabajo por cuenta ajena para perseguir algo que te gusta?</strong></p>

<p>No, no fue una decisión sencilla. Sin embargo, es una decisión de la que no me arrepiento en absoluto.</p>

<p>Siempre he valorado mi motivación y satisfacción personal por encima de otros factores, como el económico. Las ganas por aprender cosas nuevas me han llevado a trabajar en varias empresas desempeñando labores tan diversas como profesor, programador Web o analista de sistemas.</p>

<p>Lamentablemente, la situación económica actual hace mucho más difícil esta movilidad laboral. Casi sin darme cuenta, me vi atrapado en un empleo que ya no me satisfacía. Sin motivación, precisaba de un cambio drástico. Nada mejor que convertir mi pasión en mi forma de ganarme la vida.</p>

<p><strong>As Tucas fabrica material a medida, edredones y refugios. ¿Puedes indicarnos como surgió la idea de crear la empresa y como ves su futuro?</strong></p>

<p>Desde hace años fabrico buena parte de mi ropa y material como afición. Sin embargo, debo reconocer que al ver la floreciente industria artesanal americana, pensaba si algo así sería posible en Europa.</p>

<p>Mi necesidad de cambio me impulsó a pasar a la acción. De repente recuperé toda mi energía y motivación: multitud de ideas que desarrollar, aprender cosas nuevas, retos que afrontar… En resumen, convertir un sueño en realidad. Hay mucho trabajo “entre bastidores” para hacer de As Tucas algo único. Su futuro pasa por ser una empresa que aúne todo lo bueno de las empresas artesanales y todo lo bueno de los grandes fabricantes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539396734" title="Marcando un edredón Sestrals en la mesa de corte."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7366/13539396734_d955c24a96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Marcando un edredón Sestrals en la mesa de corte." /></a></p>

<p><strong>¿Hay otros fabricantes artesanales en España?</strong></p>

<p>No, hasta donde yo conozco. En España, al igual que en el resto de Europa, crear una empresa es más difícil que en Estados Unidos. El proceso burocrático es más complejo y la presión fiscal mucho mayor. Por eso, el número de este tipo de empresas es tan reducido.</p>

<p><strong>Tu empresa únicamente lleva cuatro meses en el mercado y ya ha sido muy bien recibida en Europa. ¿Va bien el negocio?</strong></p>

<p>Estoy muy satisfecho con el arranque de As Tucas. Es más, ha superado todas mis previsiones.</p>

<p>La apuesta inicial ha sido fuerte, pero la acogida del mercado me indica que este es el camino a seguir. Ahora hay que continuar trabajando para mejorar el catálogo de productos, los procesos de producción y el servicio de atención al cliente, aspectos clave de nuestro éxito.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539081455" title="Preparando una máquina en la línea de costura."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7408/13539081455_fed0457b13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Preparando una máquina en la línea de costura." /></a></p>

<p><strong>Te has introducido en un segmento de negocio que a) no está muy bien atendido por las empresas artesanales porque b) se percibe como difícil. ¿Como te decidiste a ofrecer prendas de <a href="http://astucas.com/es/ropa/">ropa</a>, cuando muchos otros lo consideran un negocio difícil?</strong></p>

<p>Porque es un reto y también una gran oportunidad. Tanto por su diseño como por los materiales utilizados, cada una de las prendas ofrecidas es única. Más importante aún, estas prendas están ideadas como un sistema integrado, que trabajan juntas para permitirnos afrontar una mayor variedad de condiciones con el mínimo peso posible.  </p>

<p><strong>¿Puedes contarnos un poco sobre cómo fue el proceso de diseño de la camiseta con capucha <a href="http://astucas.com/es/ropa/camiseta-capucha-cabietos">Cabietos</a> y de dónde vino la inspiración?</strong></p>

<p>En base a nuestra experiencia, una camiseta base para actividades de montaña debe reunir tres elementos de diseño clave: una capucha que proteja la cara, puños con agujeros para los pulgares y una cremallera de pecho realmente larga. Esta combinación proporciona una versatilidad increíble. </p>

<p>Si bien hay productos excelentes en el mercado, no hay ninguno que combine estos tres elementos. Lo más próximo era la camiseta Backpacking Light Beartooth Merino Wool Hoody, ya descatalogada. Sin embargo, la camiseta con capucha Cabietos ofrece unas posibilidades de ventilación aún mayores y un tejido de lana merina más duradero.</p>

<p><strong>Además de prendas de ropa también ofreces un toldo de Cuben (y silnylon) y un edredón sintético. ¿Veremos una tienda/refugio en el futuro? ¿O tal vez una mochila? ¿O continuarás concentrándote en el diseño de ropa y, tal vez, ofrecer una chaqueta cortavientos o impermeable?</strong></p>

<p>Nuestro catálogo está en plena evolución, y este año se verá ampliado con nuevos productos. Sin embargo, debemos concentrar esfuerzos para continuar ofreciendo algo único y con un valor excepcional. Por este motivo no vamos a entrar a competir en determinados segmentos del mercado que, consideramos, ya están cubiertos.</p>

<p><strong>Marco ¡nos encantaría conocer tus proyectos en curso! ¿Puedes contarnos en que nuevos productos estás trabajando ahora?</strong></p>

<p>De forma inmediata, la colección Sestrals de ropa aislante sintética se va a ampliar con una chaqueta. Al igual que ya hicimos con los pantalones, hemos vuelto a superar a la mítica colección Backpacking Light Cocoon con una prenda más ligera y con mejores prestaciones.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539083065" title="El nuevo pullover Sestrals."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7381/13539083065_e0e24eae66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="El nuevo pullover Sestrals." /></a></p>

<p>Por otro lado, vamos a realizar una importante apuesta por nuestra línea de plumón con nuevos edredones. De esta forma, vamos a ser los primeros en ofrecer un sistema integrado de edredones sintéticos y de plumón. Esta combinación, alabada entre otros por el reconocido alpinista <a href="http://www.andy-kirkpatrick.com/articles/view/double_up">Andy Kirkpatrick</a> y el senderista <a href="http://www.fjaderlatt.se/2010/04/across-sarek-in-winter-sleep-system.html">Jörgen Johansson</a>, permite crear un robusto sistema modular de 4 estaciones.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539183193" title="El nuevo edredón Foratata."><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2807/13539183193_9bca885961_b.jpg" width="437" height="1024" alt="El nuevo edredón Foratata." /></a></p>

<p>Para realizar este movimiento hemos  buscado ampliamente un proveedor de plumón adecuado. Hemos comenzado a trabajar con uno de los mayores productores de plumón de Polonia. Éste no solo nos ofrece el mejor plumón disponible (900 cuin) sino que nos certifica que ha sido obtenido respetando el bienestar animal de acuerdo a la normativa europea, un asunto importante para nosotros.</p>

<p><strong>¿Algunos materiales ligeros nuevos emocionantes?</strong></p>

<p>Siempre estamos buscando la forma de mejorar nuestros productos y esto, a menudo, involucra utilizar nuevos materiales. Vamos a introducir ropa de lluvia fabricada con un laminado de fibra Cubic Tech CTF3 y eVent, que es probablemente el material impermeable y transpirable más ligero del mercado. Asimismo, continuamos trabajando con Schoeller en nuevos y mejores tejidos para nuestras camisetas y una próxima colección de ropa de lluvia.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539396404" title="Evaluando los nuevos tejidos de Schoeller."><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7185/13539396404_c81d1f97f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="742" alt="Evaluando los nuevos tejidos de Schoeller." /></a></p>

<p><strong>¿Cómo funciona el I+D en As Tucas? ¿Se trata de una necesidad personal que tratas de resolver o te inspiran algunos de tus clientes que buscan soluciones a sus problemas?</strong></p>

<p>Nuestro catálogo se formó a partir de mis propias necesidades personales, definidas tanto por las condiciones de mi entorno como por mis propias preferencias. Cada vez hay más influencias de las necesidades de nuestros clientes, lo que nos permite ofrecer productos todavía más versátiles y robustos.</p>

<p>Sin embargo, cuando la ropa y material que creas se usa desde los desiertos de África hasta las zonas árticas, los retos son únicos. Por ese motivo, en ocasiones se precisan soluciones también únicas. Es aquí cuando entra en escena nuestra sección de trabajos a medida, donde trabajamos directamente con los clientes para crear sus productos.</p>

<p><strong>¿De donde provienen tus clientes?</strong></p>

<p>Principalmente de Europa. Sin embargo, también tenemos clientes en otras partes del mundo como Estados Unidos y Japón. Paradójicamente tenemos pocos clientes de España. La comunidad montañera de nuestro país es bastante tradicional y la filosofía de lo ultraligero todavía no está extendida. Afortunadamente, la influencia de sectores como el de las carreras de montaña, está revolucionando la mentalidad de muchos senderistas.</p>

<p><strong>¿Estás en contacto con otros fabricantes artesanales de Europa, Japón, Canadá o Estados Unidos?</strong></p>

<p>Actualmente tan apenas. Pensamos que a pesar de ser competencia, la colaboración en determinadas áreas sería positiva tanto para las empresas como para los clientes.</p>

<p><strong>¿Cuando y dónde fue tu última excursión?</strong></p>

<p>¡Este fin de semana! Una excursión con raquetas por el Valle de Ordesa, uno de mis lugares preferidos. Esta es una excelente época del año. Días soleados, temperaturas agradables y todavía mucha nieve para disfrutar.</p>

<p><strong>¿Y dónde te lleva tu excursión de ensueño?</strong></p>

<p>Sin duda Alaska. Naturaleza en estado puro, salvaje y a gran escala. En un entorno más próximo, el Parque nacional de Sarek, en Laponia.</p>

<p><strong>¿Algún elemento favorito que siempre llevas contigo?</strong></p>

<p>Una camiseta con capucha, preferentemente de lana merina, y una chaqueta cortavientos ligera. Esta combinación de ropa es tan versátil, que la utilizo todo el año en multitud de actividades. Otro elemento, que considero mi “elemento de lujo”, es un trípode fotográfico. Me encanta la fotografía. Valoro más las posibilidades creativas que un trípode me ofrece que la penalización de peso. Por ese motivo, me acompaña en muchas de mis excursiones.</p>

<p><strong>¿Estás pensando en una excursión pronto y disfrutar de la primavera española?</strong></p>

<p>¡Por supuesto! Los Pirineos en primavera son espectaculares y hay que aprovecharlos. Los días cada vez más largos y el retroceso de la nieve abren muchas posibilidades. La nieve en zonas de altura nos acompaña todo el año, por lo que se pueden crear rutas realmente espectaculares.</p>

<p>Os invitamos a todos a visitarnos. Si lo hacéis, no dudéis en contactar con nosotros para aconsejaros  y, por qué no, compartir un estupendo día en las montañas.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13539085565" title="Caminando fuera de sendero por una cresta."><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3828/13539085565_0788234ff8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Caminando fuera de sendero por una cresta." /></a></p>

<p><em><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/interview-marco-sanchez-of-as-tucas.html">Read the English version of this interview</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview: Mike St. Pierre of Hyperlite Mountain Gear - Two Years On]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-of-hyperlite-mountain-gear-two-years-on.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-28T17:13:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-of-hyperlite-mountain-gear-two-years-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last time I <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/08/interview-mike-st-pierre-from-hyperlite-mountain-gear.html">interviewed Mike</a> was in April 2010, as Hyperlite Mountain Gear had just arrived on the doorstep of the Ultralight Cottage Gear maker scene. Two years on HMG has made it to the pages of several big outdoor magazines, has got high praise from Ryan Jordan at BackpackingLight.com, and has received lots of favourable reviews of their gear. Time to sit down once more and see how the company has developed.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7807585778/" title="HMG Porter by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8447/7807585778_bd6d41d3d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG Porter" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Hei Mike, nice to talk again. The last time we did an interview was in summer 2010, how has business been since then for Hyperlite Mountain Gear?</em></p>

<p>HMG has grown exponentially since we last sat down. And its been a great ride. When we last spoke I think we were still working out of a basement and in borrowed space with only a few staff and only two or three products. Now we’ve got a full product line of cuben fiber backpacks, shelters, stuff packs and accessories, we’ve got a great team of committed employees, and we’ve moved into 3000 plus square feet of high-tech manufacturing space. That being said, I am committed to keeping HMG small, innovative and nimble. We do not want to join the large corporate culture that seems to dominate the outdoor industry these days. HMG will continue to grow organically, focusing all of our design and product energies specifically on the outdoor athletes and enthusiasts who are pursuing a light approach to their outdoor activities. That’s what we believe in, and that’s what our customers expect from us. </p>

<p><em>Do you still enjoy the cottage manufacturing business, or have there been moments where you thought “I wish I would still be a chef in New York”?</em></p>

<p>Working as chef was fun, but running Hyperlite Mountain Gear is my dream job. As an entrepreneur growing a small company there are some tough days but I wouldn’t want to do anything else. I get to see my ideas become reality as HMG designs and builds cutting-edge gear, I’m surrounded by smart outdoor enthusiasts who are motivated see HMG become the leader in the industry, and I get to take my own company’s gear our on the trail or packrafting when I grab some downtime. What more could I want? </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7888339254/" title="Mike_02 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8320/7888339254_4b16751801_b.jpg" width="720" height="540" alt="Mike_02" /></a></p>

<p><em>So now, you told me, you’re working on implementing a lean manufacturing philosophy, something that one normally finds in technology startups. How’s the implementation going, and more importantly, what drove you to implement it?</em></p>

<p>I was finding that a lot of time was being wasted by a traditional, inefficient manufacturing process. The result was higher build costs for our products and longer lead times for our customers. We carefully analyzed each step in our manufacturing process to cut out all unnecessary and repetitive actions, we optimized the flow of raw materials from the source through our production line, and we carefully repositioned the physical location of staff and equipment along that line so that, for example, a stitcher need not get up and walk across the room for a part in the middle of a build. Although most of this is invisible to our customers, I think they appreciate the results: we are able to build all our products by hand in the USA, our products have consistently high build quality, and our order turnaround times are some of the best in the market. I think we’ve achieved a level of efficiency which is unsurpassed by a company of our size in this industry. And its still a work in progress so I think we’ll get it even more dialed-in as HMG continues to grow.</p>

<p><em>How big is HMG nowadays in terms of employees?</em></p>

<p>HMG is up to nine full time employees, most of whom are working in production. We also have several more part time employees. And we’re growing, so I expect to add more staff soon. Its been really rewarding to create new jobs in these difficult economic times, especially in manufacturing, a sector that has been in decline in the USA for many years.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7886532870/"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8039/7886532870_2373aba2a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="photo(13)" /></a></p>

<p><em>Hikers outside the USA will probably be delighted to know that they now also can buy HMG packs &amp; shelters at <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/index.php?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a> in Europe and at <a href="http://hikersdepot.jp/">Hiker’s Depot</a> in Japan. I think that’s a great cooperation for those who want to get your gear but don’t want to go through the hassle that dealing with the customs can be, and cuts down on waiting time. How did that cooperation come to be, and are there any special products for the European and Asian markets in the works from HMG?</em></p>

<p>Trekking-Lite-Store and Hiker’s Depot have been excellent retail partners and both Europe and the Asia/ Pacific region are becoming important markets for HMG’s products. Both Trekking-Lite-Store and Hiker’s Depot have the same enthusiasm for innovative gear and the outdoors as we do here at Hyperlite Mountain Gear. Will built these relationships after making initial contacts at trade shows and other events like the annual Outdoor Retailer Show in Salt Lake City, Utah. I plan to slowly expand our network international retailers, selecting only those that I believe to be true enthusiasts for the light hiking and outdoor movement. I think our cuben fiber backpacks, shelters, stuff packs and accessories and our approach to design translate well into international markets and we’re seeing a lot of growth there. We’re going to continue to innovate and expand our product line across the board.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7886570006/" title="Screenshot_Shops by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8450/7886570006_cc9c7ee1cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="640" alt="Screenshot_Shops" /></a></p>

<p><em>Another interesting move from HMG was to cooperate with <a href="http://outlier.cc/">Outlier</a> in New York and produce a ultralight daypack for them. Did Outlier approach you, or you them, for this cooperation?</em></p>

<p>Like many of the connections HMG has made, Outlier found us. I believe that if HMG puts it head down and focuses on designing and building excellent products, customers and other interested parties will come to us. We already had a backpack in development that was just exactly what Outlier was looking for, so the fit was obvious.</p>

<p><em>GoLite has been accused of selling out as it moved away from its core business in really lightweight gear, have you heard such acquisitions already, given that you’ve been branching out a bit already (but always staying very light with your daypack for Outlier and the IcePack)?</em></p>

<p>We haven’t heard much of that, but I expect there will always be a few detractors for any decision a company makes in this industry. Hyperlite Mountain Gear is committed to building packs, shelters and accessories which pursue the light approach to the outdoors. We want to offer our customers durable, lightweight, well designed backpacks, shelters and other products that will help them increase their speed, distance, efficiency and overall enjoyment of the outdoors. That’s what I get up every day to do and that’s not going to change. So long as we focus on that, I believe HMG will succeed. I don’t get hung up on light vs. ultralight and I don’t see this as an approach that is reserved only to the elite or to one type of outdoor pursuit, I see the light approach to the outdoors as a methodology that can be a great benefit all level of outdoor enthusiast across all types of outdoors sports and activities. HMG is working to spread the word. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7886536006/" title="photo(21) by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8300/7886536006_be1d81dcfe_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="photo(21)" /></a></p>

<p><em>Can we expect more changes in your business model in the future, or will you keep on selling direct, with a few selected online shops overseas carrying your gear, as well as some cooperations?</em></p>

<p>Hyperlite Mountain Gear is going to continue our focus on direct-to-customer sales via the internet while slowly growing our network of retailers in select markets. We want to grow the retailer network, because it allows customers to interact directly with our backpacks, shelters and other products before purchasing and, especially in international markets, it allows us to avoid some of the time and other difficulties involved with shipping. We plan to expand our retail network slowly, by developing long term relationships with retailers who I believe to be true enthusiasts for the light hiking and outdoor movement and have top notch customer service. Regarding direct-to-consumer sales, we love dealing directly with our customers. No call centers, just a group of committed HMG staff who actually answer the phone or write back personally on email when customers contact us. In addition to great design, great customer service is the second plank in the foundation of HMG’s business.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7886532546/" title="photo(12) by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8037/7886532546_8d04f5b90e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="photo(12)" /></a></p>

<p><em>Which brings us to the HMG product line. You adjusted your products after getting feedback from users and reviews, and introduced only a few new products - the Porter/ Expedition Packs, the Ice Pack and the Stuff Pack, the Hammock Tarp and made the Windrider available with Spectra Hardline pockets as the Soutwest, plus some smaller items. Are you secretly designing &amp; testing the next big thing, or is this it for the time being?</em></p>

<p>I love innovating and we’re always working on new products at HMG. Some never make it off the back of the cocktail napkin, but some, and we’ve got a few in the R&amp;D stage now, will be added to our product line as soon as we can perfect the designs and complete a thorough set of real world, on trail testing.</p>

<p>We’ve got a few products that we plan to roll out in the short term, including a removable accessory pocket for our Summit Pack which will be similar in function to the Stuff Pocket we offer as an accessory for our Porter Pack and Expedition Pack. We also plan to add to our line of stuff sacks.  </p>

<p>Longer term we’re excited about adding one or more significant new products to our shelters line and we’re going to continue to expand our packs line with additional activity-specific packs, like our Ice Pack which is targeted at the ice climbing community. Look for Hyperlite Mountain Gear products addressing the mountaineering, backcountry skiing and packrafting communities.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7886533904/" title="photo(17) by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8310/7886533904_d64c246ac9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="photo(17)" /></a></p>

<p><em>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering quilts and bivys?</em></p>

<p>I’m always looking at ways to spread the “light” approach and our core cuben fiber-based technology. We have no specific plans to get into other segments.  But I would say, watch this space.  HMG will continue to innovate.  We’re not just making a few cool packs at HMG, we’re looking to be on the leading edge of an industry-wide refocusing on the benefits of light, efficient and design-lead gear.  </p>

<p><em>So what are the waiting times for HMG items at the moment?</em></p>

<p>We have recently put significant effort into building our inventory of completed products so that, even in rush periods, we are simply pulling a orders from the shelf rather than custom building as the orders come in. I think this differentiates Hyperlite Mountain Gear significantly from other smaller gear manufacturers. If you are ordering a product we have in inventory we take only a day or so to turnaround and ship the order. If there are custom features that needs to be added to your order or if we do not currently have the product in inventory, a one week lead time is typical. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7886534398/" title="photo(18) by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8300/7886534398_f5292cd56d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="photo(18)" /></a></p>

<p><em>Lets talk a bit about Social Media. HMG is active on <a href="https://twitter.com/HyperliteMGear">Twitter</a>, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/hyperlitemountaingear">Facebook</a> and <a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/hyperlitemtgear">Youtube</a>, and you have a good following on these channels. Was it an easy decision to join them, or did you ponder about it, wondering if there is much sense to invest time in being present on them, interacting with (prospective) clients instead of sewing packs and shelters?</em></p>

<p>Social media has become an absolutely necessary tool for reaching and communicating with consumers in the outdoor space, especially for a small company like ours that does not have a large traditional advertising budget and can’t be at every show and event. Reaching our community, primarily through a social media presence on Facebook and Twitter has allowed HMG to build a successful and growing direct-to-consumer sales business and it is simply the quickest and most direct means of sharing happenings at HMG with those who may be interested. We also have our <a href="http://blog.hyperlitemountaingear.com/">own blog</a> on the Hyperlite Mountain Gear website which gives us a platform for longer articles and more meaningful discussion of topics.</p>

<p>But social media does require time and there is a learning curve. Consumers in the outdoor industry are smart and they rightfully demand meaningful content, not just a series of push ads. Creating that content and then keeping up with the engaged followers is both the trickiest and most rewarding part of social media.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.facebook.com/hyperlitemountaingear"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8173/7886702788_d097eefcca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="640" alt="Screen Shot 2012-08-29 at 2.39.02 PM" /></a></p>

<p><em>Lets talk about the sustainability of HMG. Do you use electricity from renewable energy at your new facility, have programs in place to cut down &amp; recycle waste and maybe even have plans to offer credit for old products and recycle them for your customers like e.g. Klättermusen does it?</em></p>

<p>For now, we’re on the grid, but I am pleased to report that our new office and manufacturing facility is located in a 100-plus year-old textile mill complex in Biddeford, Maine that, instead of being wastefully torn down and replaced, is being carefully redeveloped as a sustainable urban community. Among other things, the mill complex is planning a single-stream recycling program, will be linked to local commuter transport to get folks away from using their cars and will have green-roof gardens. HMG is proud to be an anchor tenant in this green redevelopment.</p>

<p><em>HMG could for example accept old packs and tarps back and give the person some store credit, and recycle them into stuff sacks, prolonging the life of the material - what do you think about that?</em></p>

<p>Its funny you ask about pack recycling because that is something we’ve recently been working on. There is the possibility of recycling some used HMG products into stuff sacks or other small items that could be re-sold. But we’ve been thinking more broadly, along the lines of allowing any customer to trade-in their old pack, no matter what the material. The trade-ins that are in useable condition could be cleaned and donated to charitable organizations which distribute such items to folks in need like school-age children who cannot afford book bags or the homeless. And the trade-in packs that are unusable could be stripped for re-usable parts and material with the remainder possibly being shredded and used as filler or stuffing for unrelated products. These concepts are something we are working on at Hyperlite Mountain Gear. We see this as another area where we can innovate because we are small and nimble. HMG would like to set an example for the broader outdoor industry.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7886534812/" title="photo(19) by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8041/7886534812_c917deed0d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="photo(19)" /></a></p>

<p><em>Finally, who are your customers nowadays? Avid backpackers and thru-hikers who’re out every time they can and who value durable yet light gear, or are there also more “normal” backpackers who somehow find your products and try them out?</em></p>

<p>Our primary customer base remains the avid backpacking and hiking consumer. These are the people who are most likely to have already adopted the light approach to the outdoors, and if they haven’t already made the jump, they can at least readily appreciate that going light will increase their efficiency, performance and enjoyment of the outdoors. We have also made inroads into other niche communities of outdoor enthusiasts, such as the ice climbing and packrafting communities, each of which also readily recognizes that lighter is better and appreciates  the durability of our cuben fiber-based products. But we have an ever growing number of less avid outdoor enthusiasts who come across our products on the shelves of retailers or by seeing them in action on the trail. We love to help these consumers make the jump into an approach that might take them to the next level.</p>

<p><em>Hyperlite Mountain Gear has been featured in a few US outdoor magazines if I remember correctly - how does that work for you? The day the magazine comes out the people flock to the site and order your gear till the shelves are empty, or is it less wild?</em></p>

<p>HMG has been featured in several major publications, including Backpacker, Trailrunner, Outside, and most recently, Petersen’s Hunting where the Echo Shelter System was given this year’s Editor’s Choice award for tents/shelters. Each time we get some of this nationwide coverage we do see a jump in phone and internet traffic and orders, but its not as dramatic as all that. This type of publicity helps HMG grow and helps us get the word out about the light approach to the outdoors, but its still organic measured growth. And we like it that way. </p>

<p><em>Alright, that’s a wrap from my part. Anything you want to add?</em></p>

<p>Thanks for taking the time to do this interview! The team at Hyperlite Mountain Gear really appreciates all the great information you put out there for the light hiking community on your blog and I’m so glad that HMG can be part of that. See you on the trail!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview: Scott Felter of Porcelain Rocket]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/08/interview-scott-felter-of-porcelain-rocket.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-13T20:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/08/interview-scott-felter-of-porcelain-rocket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bikepacking is <em>the trend</em> in the UL scene of 2012 (and it will carry over into 2013 as more and more will start to explore the forests and hills with their bike) and hence it is my pleasure to interview one of the most exciting bikepacking cottage manufacturers, Scott Felter of <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com/&quot;target=&quot;_blank&quot;">Porcelain Rocket</a>. Scott makes superb bikepacking frame &amp; seat packs and in this interview he tells us how Porcelain Rocket came to be, where that name comes from, and what the future holds. <em>Enjoy!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/porcelainrocket/5583834822/" title="Scott AZT by Porcelain Rocket, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5309/5583834822_01cca3fa5c_b.jpg" width="800" height="534" alt="Scott AZT" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Scott, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking &amp; bikepacking, and how did you start?</strong><br />
My name is Scott Felter, and was born and raised in New Orleans. The Deep South is not exactly known as the epicenter of backcountry adventure, so I suppose it all really started when I was a junior on a road racing team in New Orleans. There were several mountain bike races that took place up in the ‘mountains’ of Mississippi and Arkansas, and I was drawn to those events for some reason. That is where the trail took hold of me, I would say. Ever since, I’ve made conscious choices to make my home in places where mountain biking and trail culture were alive and paramount. I have lived in and amongst the Appalachians of SW Virginia, the Sangre de Cristo mountains of Northern New Mexico, the Canadian Rockies, and now the rainforest of Vancouver Island.</p>

<p><strong>How often are you out bikepacking nowadays?</strong><br />
I am out on the trails fairly regularly, mountain biking or hiking. I try and squeeze 1-2 night local bike tours into my schedule about once a month, with the aim of doing a major tour (1-3 months) every other year.</p>

<p><strong>Are you more of a “weekend cycler” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong><br />
I would consider myself a little of both. I certainly enjoy a nice evening trail session with friends, followed by a few pints, but there is also a part of me that really craves a bit more. There is something incomparable about being a few weeks into a multi-month off-road bike tour. The challenges of logistics, physical preparedness, and technical riding are something that really attract me. I have ridden many of the big ‘bikepacking’ routes in North America, mainly the Divide Route, the Arizona Trail, the Kokopelli Trail, Kananaskis Country, and tons in the Moab, UT area. While living in Santa Fe, NM, I regularly spent weeks riding and exploring in the amazing landscape of Northern New Mexico and Southern Colorado. All self-supported, of course!  </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/porcelainrocket/6816160810/" title="The Current State of the Hunter - Full-on Touring Setup by Porcelain Rocket, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7060/6816160810_e4b18e0d41_b.jpg" width="1024" height="739" alt="The Current State of the Hunter - Full-on Touring Setup" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Which category would you put yourself in: SUL, UL, or Lightweight? What is your typical baseweight?</strong><br />
I’ve never been much of a weight-weenie. I definitely like to have a few comforts along on a bike tour, so if I had to characterize my packing style, I would say that I am a Lightweight kind of guy. My complete bikepacking setup, ready to ride, weighs right at 50 pounds, or about 23 kilos. This includes the bike, gear, and enough food and water for 2-3 days. My bike is a custom, fillet-brazed steel, Rick Hunter 29er. It is built with bikepacking in mind, so Rick built it to accept a Rohloff internal gear hub, lots of bottle mounts and big open spaces in the frame for framebags. </p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “Porcelain Rocket” came from, and what it stands for.</strong><br />
Haha!  This is a frequently asked question!  Well, it has been a long, winding, journey to the gear-building phase of life that I currently find myself in. While studying for a design degree at Virginia Tech, I worked as an assistant for a ceramist in Blacksburg, VA. Mostly studio assistant type jobs, and manual labour kinds of tasks. However, I really found the physicality of making beautiful, and functional objects with one’s own hands insanely attractive. It wasn’t long before I began identifying myself as a ceramic artist, and my whole world revolved around clay; porcelain in particular. I worked in many different facets of the ceramics industry, from studio assistant to mold-making. All the while, I was growing as a mountain biker, and soon the moniker The Porcelain Rocket took hold. I think it still defines my personality almost perfectly. While I no longer work in any ceramic medium, I still think that there is nothing in this world more beautiful than well-made porcelain, and I will forever hold handmade culture near to my heart.  </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/porcelainrocket/7271108570/" title="In the Works I by Porcelain Rocket, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7089/7271108570_e0d146881b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="782" alt="In the Works I" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Porcelain Rocket makes custom bicycle bags. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</strong><br />
I began making my own gear mostly out of necessity and curiosity. At the time, ‘bikepacking’ was just getting going, and availability of gear was tough.  I, like many folks still, was planning a trip and needed gear. I had a plan for some commercial gear, but in the end that didn’t pan out, so I made my own. It turned out surprisingly well, and it performed better than I had hoped. It wasn’t long before friends began asking, word of mouth took over, and well, that’s it… </p>

<p>Honestly, I never intended to go into building gear commercially. I just made packs to the best of my ability, acquiring the tools as necessity dictated, and I started a blog, mostly so that my friends and family that lived far away could see what I was up to. I’ve had a build queue ever since. </p>

<p>Porcelain Rocket has grown a lot in the last year or two. I now have 4 specialty sewing machines, tons of cutting and patterning tools, and an ever-growing stock of raw materials. I am forever finding a need for more advanced tools, and equipment to make things better, easier and faster. My father once said to me, “You should never regret buying tools. They will only make you better at what you do.” </p>

<p>I am planning a fairly big change to the way things work at Porcelain Rocket in the coming months. I would really like to focus on making the highest quality, custom gear possible.  It may mean making less, but making better, and more inspired work.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/porcelainrocket/7271110418/" title="In the Works III by Porcelain Rocket, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7095/7271110418_9f63c2e7f3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="In the Works III" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You have a degree in design, did that help in any way in starting to sew frame and seat packs?</strong><br />
Of course.  I reference my design training daily.  I would say that the aspects that I draw on most often are those of clean aesthetics and colour.  I’m a maker, and will always be.  So, I really respect and admire traditions where design and making are one-in-the-same.  </p>

<p><strong>What makes Porcelain Rocket different from other cottages?</strong><br />
Obsessive attention to detail, and pride in perfection are the things that I think set Porcelain Rocket apart.  I would much rather make fewer amazing packs, than lots of mediocre ones.</p>

<p><strong>You’re starting to get more exposure in bikepacking circles, previously it was only Eric from Revelation who came to mind when commercial bikepacking bags were a topic. You think some of the big cycling companies will start offering bike packing packs in the future?</strong>
I’m sure.  It seems only natural that a larger bike company would want to outfit their bikes with gear, and be able to offer a complete package to the consumer.  Sort of a ready-to-roll setup.  </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/porcelainrocket/7271107750/" title="In the Works IV by Porcelain Rocket, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7244/7271107750_56f8bde280_b.jpg" width="981" height="1024" alt="In the Works IV" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of the El Gilberto Frame Pack, and where the inspiration came from?</strong>
El Gilberto is my top-the-line custom frame pack. It draws inspiration from the truly inspiring velojournalist and adventurer, Cass Gilbert. Cass is my ongoing hardcore R&amp;D guy, and a great friend. Features in El Gilberto are those that mimic the style in which Cass prefers in his own setup. When Cass comes up with a new feature, it gets added to El Gilberto. Bombproof and highly functional are the two things that will always be paramount for Cass, and El Gilberto.</p>

<p><strong>You recently introduced the Salsa Aything Cage bags - what drove this development?</strong>
I had tons of requests!  I was receiving an inquiry at least once a week for custom bags to fit these little racks. So, after a while, I just gave in and designed something! They have been very popular.   </p>

<p><strong>Scott, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! Can you let us know what kind of new products you’re working on at the moment?</strong>
I am always mentally designing and redesigning, while I work.  I am really excited with the direction that things have been going lately, and would like to continue pushing the boundaries of what people have come to expect from bikepacking gear.   I have built a few prototypes for new top tube packs, and an improved seatpack design.  I am also stoked to be working with Jeff Jones on packs designed specifically for his unique brand of bikes.  </p>

<p><strong>Any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong><br />
Well, I think like many gear-builders these days, I’m liking all of the Dyneema materials that are becoming more available.  This stuff is truly amazing from a lightweight and abrasion resistance standpoint.  </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/porcelainrocket/7271089324/" title="In the Works VI by Porcelain Rocket, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7211/7271089324_30cc52dde2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="624" alt="In the Works VI" /></a></p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at Porcelain Rocket, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems?</strong><br />
I receive lots of feedback from clients.  One thing that I am continually amazed with is the willingness of people, who have paid their hard-earned money, to give back to Porcelain Rocket, in the way of feedback and critique of the gear that I produce.  And it is all 100% unsolicited.  I really like that.  Being a custom-oriented business, I rely on this sort of thing to make suggestions and to help clients make the best choices possible for their own gear requirements.</p>

<p><strong>Where do your customer come from?</strong><br />
All over, but I think the popularity of bikepacking is biggest in the US, so that is where a large majority of my gear goes. Europeans are really starting to get into this style of travel, so I am seeing a growing number of across-the-pond inquiries.</p>

<p>**Do you think bikepacking and the ultralight principles it is based on will become more popular and break into the mass market, or will it continue to be something for a small group of people?’‘<br />
I think the popularity of bikepacking will peak at some point. Just like any niche outdoor activity, I think there will always be a core group of folks who will always need the highest quality custom gear, and that is where I feel like I would like to focus my attention. I’ve never been a mass market kind of guy!  </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/porcelainrocket/7271091040/" title="In the Works VIII by Porcelain Rocket, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8012/7271091040_2f1974d26c_b.jpg" width="714" height="1024" alt="In the Works VIII" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Canada, the USA, Europe, Japan, and other places?</strong><br />
When I was starting out, I connected with a few small builders, and the help that I received from them was amazing. Sometimes, just seeing someone else’s shop space, or finding out about a source for a certain material is so helpful. I would love to have a community of gear-builders close-by, but there just aren’t that many of us in Canada. I also love talking to guys who are just starting out themselves, as I believe strongly in building communities, not competitors.</p>

<p><strong>Any other favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong><br />
Haha. Honestly, my gear choices change almost every trip. I do have a few foods that I bring along religiously. Mostly Haribo gummy bears, Jolly Ranchers, and peanut butter &amp; honey. You can put peanut butter and honey on anything. And of course Nutella. My father-in-law carved me a wooden spoon on a trip to Mt. Assiniboine a couple years ago, and it has become a staple in my kit now.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last bikepacking trip?</strong><br />
A friend and I are working on pioneering a route that will eventually traverse BC’s Vancouver Island from Port Hardy to Victoria (north to south), on as much dirt as possible.  So, we have been doing lots of scouting trips.  Once we have linked it all together, we hope to host an ‘event’ to showcase what is possible on this little-known island paradise.  While it is a necessary evil of modern society, logging has been a major industry on Vancouver Island, and as a result there are endless forestry roads zig-zagging the island, many of which are out of service, but still very accessible by bike.  </p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream bikepacking trip taking you?</strong><br />
Well.  There are a few ideas kicking around in the ol’ noggin these days. The more adventurous, hardcore route would be the Canning Stock Route in Australia. The more luxurious, but more mountain bike-oriented trip would be the Swiss Alps. Something will happen in 2013!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/porcelainrocket/7277125750/" title="In the Works IX by Porcelain Rocket, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8009/7277125750_a72e673aa4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="823" alt="In the Works IX" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the Canadian summer?</strong><br />
Always. I have been very busy lately with endurance racing season gear-building, so I am in need of a little getaway. The great thing about living in BC, is there is always something close by!</p>

<p><strong>Scott, I thank you very mucho for taking the time to answer my questions =) Is there something you would like to add?</strong><br />
Just a big THANK YOU to all of those that believe in and continually support handmade culture.  There is hope for this world, after all!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
