<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Abisko | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/abisko/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-08T23:09:53+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/02/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T09:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/02/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In three weeks the second <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> kicks off, and it’s set to be pretty amazing again. In case you’re still on the edge about going - I will give you plenty of good reasons to travel to the northern most Ice Climbing Festival!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553149630/" title="Lapporten ice climbing"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8380/8553149630_34b8f7fee8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lapporten" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html">Last year’s AICF</a> was fantastic and I learned a lot. It’s not every day that you can pick the brains of Alpinists like Robert Jasper and the guys from Petzl, so as the 2nd AICF was announced, with a pretty fantastic line-up of instructors and clinics, it was an easy decision to travel north to Abisko this year again.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553049416/" title="Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8086/8553049416_5a073d5199_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Canyon" /></a></p>

<p>Like last year, the AICF is something for everyone: From the complete novice who has never climbed ice to advanced climbers, who want to hone their skills. You can loan all the ice climbing gear, and will be very well instructed on its use and technique. Accommodation is in the very nice <a href="http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/upptack/Omraden/Lappland/Fjallstationer/STF-Abisko-Turiststation/">STF Turiststation Abisko</a>, and if you travel with the family: There’s plenty to do there for kids and partners, from sledging and snowshoe walks to skiing and watching Aurora Borealis.</p>

<p>For the climbing, this year’s clinics include <em>Traditional Scottish mix lead</em>, <em>Efficient multi pitch</em>, <em>Basic Ice/Mix</em> as well as <em>Efficient and safe belay</em> and <em>Ice strength/ belay/ rappel/ abalakov</em>. There’s going to be a competition, the relaxed After Climb sessions, and which is surely going to be spectacular, the “Petzl night with Said Belhaj”. Said had just a big feature in the current Rock &amp; Ice 216 (great read, go get the Magazin!), and I met him briefly last year at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">Outdoor</a> so am very much looking forward to climbing with him. But there’s more, Stefan Lindblom and Krister Jonsson as well as UIAGM Mountain Guide &amp; Organizer Anders Bergwall are again along to teach you about proper crampon &amp; tool techniques, and show you how multi-pitch climbing is done well. And they’ll let you pick their brains from years of climbing on ice and mixed and other outdoor shenanigans!</p>

<p>As you see, there’s really plenty for everyone, and the four days surely will fly by way too fast. You can read all the details on the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Arctic Guides</a> website, and then it’s time to <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/wp-system/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/AICF-2014-Prices.pdf">book your festival pass</a> and plan the trip north! You can also <a href="https://www.facebook.com/AbiskoIceClimbingFestival">follow on Facebook</a> and keep an eye on the new <a href="http://www.abiskoiceclimbing.com/">Abisko Ice Climbing</a> website which will launch soon. See you in Absiko!</p>

<p><em>If you’re coming from Finland, we still have one seat free in the car from Vaasa (via a night in Rovaniemi on the way up), if you want to drive with us - <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#101;&#110;&#100;&#114;&#105;&#107;&#064;&#104;&#105;&#107;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#105;&#110;&#108;&#097;&#110;&#100;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">be in touch</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577421940/" title="Stefan leading by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8089/8577421940_6db928fa2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stefan leading" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2013 Experiences]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-21T20:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2013-experiences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having been invited to the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2013</a> was an opportunity I couldn’t resist. A four hour ferry ride to Umeå and a nine hour train ride to Abisko later I arrived in one of Sweden’s Northernmost trail towns, which offers stunning Aurora Borealis, downhill skiing, husky tours and superb ice climbing.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553149630/" title="Lapporten by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8380/8553149630_34b8f7fee8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Lapporten" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>“Hendrik?”</em></p>

<p><em>Yes.</em></p>

<p><em>“Welcome to the Abisko Ice Climbing Festival! I see you’re already wearing your climbing shoes, just drop your stuff here and head down to the canyon, you can get all the gear at the Petzl tent and the Demo Session is soon starting!”</em></p>

<p>After this friendly welcome from Anders Bergwall, UIAGM/ IFMGA Mountain Guide, owner of <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/">Arctic Guides</a>, and Organiser of the AICF I quickly changed into my climbing pants and headed down to the Abisko river canyon, where indeed already a lot of people where climbing and chatting. But before I could climb I needed some gear, and so I went into the huge Tentipi tent and got from the friendly employees from <a href="http://www.c2safety.com/">C2 Vertical Safety</a> a pair of crampons (Petzl Darts), a pair of ice tools (Petzl Quarks), a harness (the new Petzl Sama) and a helmet (the new Petzl Sirocco, wonderfully light!). Well equipped I headed down to the canyon and started to chat with some of the other climbers while I was waiting for my turn.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8544509865/" title="Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2013 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8238/8544509865_6caa945cb0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Abisko Ice Climbing Festival 2013" /></a></p>

<p>It didn’t take too long and after a quick introduction and a buddy check with my belayer Rafael Jensen I was up the ice. The route was not too difficult, and already pretty hewn out from previous climbers, but for someone who was already travelling for about 12 hours it was just right. Back down Rafael gave me a few tips, and then I was already again knotting a Figure 8 knot and going up the second route. </p>

<p>After getting in five climbs it was time to check out the Demo Session from the Petzl climbers. They showed some nice Mixed climbing on a vertical cliff and ice climbing on an impressive waterfall further back in the canyon. But I was getting hungry, so I returned most of the Petzl gear as I brought my own, and just held on the the Sirocco helmet, which is wonderful. At the <a href="http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/sv/upptack/Omraden/Lappland/Fjallstationer/STF-Abisko-Turiststation/">STF Turist Station Abisko</a> I relaxed till Dinner started, and then headed shortly to the cabin to drop my backpacks before heading back to the presentations.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8551930773/” title=”Robert Jasper</td>
      <td>Mixed by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8111/8551930773_b4d37a11a8_b.jpg” width=”1024” height=”625” alt=”Robert Jasper</td>
      <td>Mixed”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.robert-jasper.de/">Robert Jasper</a>, a German Alpinist, had a presentation about his ascent of the Eiger Northface by the Japanese Route, Erwann from Petzl showed us a video of a truly impressive ice climb up a waterfall which he can see from his office (<a href="http://youtu.be/xLsFUtbX51Y">see it here</a>) while Alban told us more about the new Petzl gear we could try this weekend. After such a long day it was time to hit the hay, and I went with my room mates back to the cabin. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577557260/" title="Robert Jasper Presentation by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8088/8577557260_2ae285196d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Robert Jasper Presentation" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553057432/" title="Beginner's Wall by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8112/8553057432_beb9b3473a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Beginner's Wall" /></a></p>

<p>Friday morning I got up early and headed for breakfast to the STF Station. In case you haven’t been there, the breakfast alone is a good reason to visit - it was superb! Delicious, freshly baked breads, scrambled eggs &amp; bacon, porridge and different berry soups guarantee a great start into the day. After we made our own lunches from the breakfast buffet, with a few tasty additions like GORP, Chocolate and drinks, it was gathering the gear and heading to the Lounge, waiting for the cars. </p>

<p>Todays climbing was at a nearby roadside cliff, which had about ten frozen waterfalls waiting for us. We were quickly separated into different groups while a few of the Pros set up Topropes for us, and then it was ice climbing time! </p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;a href=”http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8553065820/” title=”Anders</td>
      <td>Proper Crampon use by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr”&gt;&lt;img src=”http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8370/8553065820_a802df0044_b.jpg” width=”680” height=”1024” alt=”Anders</td>
      <td>Proper Crampon use”&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>I was with the Beginner group, and Anders from Arctic Guides started off with telling us about proper crampon use. After that we traversed in half a meter height along a ice fall, while the Guides checked on how we used the crampons and gave us tips on how to do it better. After this it was time to get climbing on topropes, first at the beginner’s wall, then, as confidence, technique and skills increased on the intermediate wall.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8551950715/" title="Intermediate Wall by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8368/8551950715_f738b9cd1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Intermediate Wall" /></a></p>

<p>In between there were some more clinics, and especially the “How to create an Abalakov thread” one was very interesting. By using an ice screw you create a V shaped channel in solid ice, through which you then thread a cord or the rope directly to abseil. It allows you to leave no expensive gear behind (and with a single <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/eisschrauben.html">ice screw</a> costing upwards of 50€, that’s very welcome indeed!) and if done correctly is very safe.</p>

<p>After six hours of intense climbing and clinics we were shuttled back to the STF Station, but some of us still had enough energy left and so headed down to the Abisko Canyon. Together with Sanna, a local Skiguide, we climbed in the canyon, first on the same wall as the previous day, then we decided to try our skills on the waterfall behind the open pool where the advanced climbers were climbing the previous day. </p>

<p>Sanna went first, and standing next to the flowing water on a thin strip of frozen ice I was belaying her. She climbed the route until she was out of sight, topping out on a small ledge. Over the roaring of the water we communicated, and I abseiled her down, we both psyched that she did this hard route! I knotted in and set off, though half way up I needed to get down - my hands were pumped and to my defence I can say that Erwann from Petzl needed to go up the route to clean it - it was already late, and we were the last ones climbing =) </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577417208/" title="Looking down by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8238/8577417208_9a6ebc7f66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Looking down" /></a></p>

<p>In the After Climb Lounge <a href="http://www.kristerjonsson.se/Kristerjonson/International_Mountainguide_because_of_his_great_passion_for_Mountains_and_People.html">Krister Jonsson</a> took us to Kyrgisiztan, where he climbed   in 2012 for three weeks with his fiancée magnificent peaks and walls in a superb setting.  After a good Dinner the presentations continued, taking us on a expedition to Patagonia and ice climbing in China, both very inspiring. But Saturday we would start early, so it was to bed early, too.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576322159/" title="Great Ice! by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8251/8576322159_bf671406fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Great Ice!" /></a></p>

<p>The Alarm rang at six o’clock, and an half hour later the great breakfast was enjoyed again. I joined Alban &amp; Erwann from Petzl and Robert Jasper in their car as we journeyed to Spansdalen in Norway. It was a fun trip, and all of us were in awe: As soon as we passed the Swedish - Norwegian border high peaks rose upward,  much higher and steeper than anything we had seen to date in Sweden. Later the Swedes told us that it indeed seems to be along the complete Border this way - the round fjells on the Swedish side, the high peaks on the Norwegian side. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576525701/" title="Norway by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8509/8576525701_d6ae3f091d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Norway" /></a></p>

<p>We arrived in Spansdalen, the “Valley of Ice” in Norway and dropped the Pros and Advanced climbers at Henrikkafossen, a 8-Pitch route which looked like superb fun. We drove a bit further up the valley to more moderate climbs, and while the first four groups set off to climb various Multipitch routes others stayed behind and took part in a few more clinics - from building belay stations to different alternatives of rappelling. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576320223/" title="Rappeling Clinic by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8516/8576320223_933ccd7e4b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rappeling Clinic" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576321517/" title="Intermediate Wall by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8378/8576321517_603b5b90bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Intermediate Wall" /></a></p>

<p>After a while it was Sara and my turn to go climbing, and we joined Stefan Lindblom from <a href="http://www.vertikalguiden.se/concrete/">Vertikal Guiden</a>. Stefan lead climbed on a half-rope so that he could belay Sara &amp; me from the belay ledge, and once he set up his belay Sara &amp; me simu-climbed up to him. The belay was on an exposed ledge and the wind was blowing coldly, so it was good that I brought my belay vest along to stay warm. </p>

<p>Sara belayed Stefan this time on the 2nd pitch, which was a lot harder than the first one, with a very steep vertical section. My hands pumped, the cold wind blowing, I pushed on, taking out the ice screws &amp; quick-draws Stefan placed, until I finally made it to the top. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577421940/" title="Stefan leading by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8089/8577421940_6db928fa2c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stefan leading" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577422832/" title="Sorting ropes by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8250/8577422832_61f31c64b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sorting ropes" /></a></p>

<p>Up on the top Stefan belayed Sara till she too made was with us. If you go up, you also need to get back down and so we sorted ropes and set up everything for abseiling back down. We used the new <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-reverso-4-belay-device.html">Petzl Reverso 4</a> to go down, and abseiling the 45 m ice fall was good fun. After we were all safely back at the start of the climb it was time to coil ropes and head back to the car, as it was getting late and we had still a 1,5 hour ride back to Abisko in front of us.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577735844/" title="Petzl Reverso 4 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8234/8577735844_86d4c770cb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Reverso 4" /></a></p>

<p>But what should have been 1,5 hour ride became a 3 hour ride, as we were waiting for 1,5 hours to cross the pass back into Sweden. Because of the strong winds the road was closed and one could only pass it in a convoy. There also was an accident, and so we sat in the car, chatting and waiting for the support vehicles to arrive and escort us across the pass. As we crossed the pass in the convoy the wind was blowing strongly, though I still spotted a few skiers on the loipes, heading back to their huts or cars.</p>

<p>Back in Abisko we enjoyed a presentation from Stefan, who ice climbs a lot in abandoned mines in his region, rather interesting places with many curious stories connected to them. After the Festival Dinner we listened closely as Rafael Jensen told of the first Swedish expedition to K2, a very touching story as three of the six members who stood on the summit of this Himalayan peak died on the descent. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576458309/" title="Abisko Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8392/8576458309_581552ba62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abisko Canyon" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576458643/" title="Petzl Laser Ice Screw by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8098/8576458643_fee6677709_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Petzl Laser Ice Screw" /></a></p>

<p>On Sunday we started a bit later than the previous days, and I headed after nine to the Abisko canyon for the final ice climbing of the weekend. It was a beautiful, sunny day with temps in the -14°C range. Stefan and Anders set a few topropes for us, and so we soon started to climb again. I tried various mixed routes that day, where one climbs rock &amp; ice with tools &amp; crampons, and while I was sceptical at first I enjoyed it immensely. It is a whole new sort of climbing, in parts easier, in parts harder than pure ice climbing or rock climbing. Heading up a steep wall with fine cracks, and only here and there ice features, is something every climber should try - it is great fun, and pushes your thinking to new levels. </p>

<p>But all good things come to an end, and so slowly the participants from near and far started to depart, catching trains, buses, planes or car rides down south. I myself stored my ice climbing gear away and got my Hyperlite Mountain Gear Porter, a pair of Dynafit Broadpeak skis and TLT5 boots and headed for the Kungsleden. But that’s another story.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157632964937798/">View more photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p>Did this get you psyched about ice climbing in Abisko and surroundings, trying out new gear and learning from the Pros? Then follow the Arctic Guides on <a href="http://www.facebook.com/arcticguides">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/arcticguides">Twitter</a> to hear about the AICF 2014, or visit one of their <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/courses/isklattring">ice climbing courses</a>.</p>

<p>I’d like to thank all the awesome participants of the AICF, especially Anders &amp; Merja from Arctic Guides, Stefan, Rafael, Robert and Krister for teaching &amp; guiding us, my room mate Dorian for the good company, Lo for letting me sleep at her place, Sara &amp; Mikeal from C2 Vertical Safety as well as Alban &amp; Erwann from Petzl for the possibility to loan great gear. I’m looking forward to climbing with you again next year!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577415840/" title="Clinic with Robert Jasper by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8369/8577415840_05ea7e4ca0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Clinic with Robert Jasper" /></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abisko Ice Climbing Festival]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/01/abisko-ice-climbing-festival.html"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T09:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/01/abisko-ice-climbing-festival</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the end of February the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a> kicks off in Abisko, Sweden. Clinics, trying new gear and plenty of ice climbing are on the programme - a good reason to go and check it out!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/paddymurphy/8357101058/" title="Ice climbing by PaddyMurphy, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8493/8357101058_15f372dac9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Ice climbing" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Since last year I’m enamoured with ice climbing, and this year is going to be the year where I whack my ice tools and crampon-fitted boots into frozen waterfalls until I reach the summit. While <a href="http://amzn.to/TB6oXw">reading</a> about it is certainly a good way to get prepared, you actually should do a <a href="http://www.adventurepartners.fi/pirunkallio.aspx">course</a> or visit an <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">Ice Climbing Festival</a> like this one in beautiful Abisko, Sweden - rather famous as being a) the Village where the superb Kungsleden Trail starts and b) one of the best places to see Northern Lights. </p>

<p>The Abisko Ice Climbing Festival (AICF), organized by the <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/">Arctic Guides</a>, is an arctic festival for all ice climbing enthusiasts, so it is perfectly suited for everyone, from the beginner over to those who have a basic foundation in ice climbing and now want to strengthen their skills as well as seasoned ice climbers. At the festival you can join climbing clinics and get coaching by professional instructors &amp; international climbers, which is the best way to learn about this fascinating sport. You also can test new gear - <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl.html">Petzl</a> is one of the Partners, so expect there to be plenty of <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-nomic-eisgeraet.html">Nomic tools</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-lynx-steigeisen.html">Lynx crampons</a> around! - and, if you’re competitively minded, join a competition! The climbing takes places on the ice falls around Abisko, from Kaisepakte till Spansdalen in Norway so besides great climbing you can expect superb scenery. And with <a href="http://www.xn--hjdmeter-n4a.se/">Höjdmeter.se</a> as another Partner I imagine there will also be some opportunities to try some great skiing gear!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/nilssonharhund/3643632092/" title="Nuolja looking southeast by NilssonHarHund, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3580/3643632092_2f32d77563_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Nuolja looking southeast" /></a></p>

<p>After the climbing you can listen to interesting lectures and watch the latest climbing films, or just chill with fellow climbers from around the world. The festival base camp is at the <a href="http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/en/Discover-Sweden/Facilities-and-activities/Lappland/Fjallstationer/STF-Mountain-station-Abisko/">STF Abisko mountain station</a> which offers accommodation, too - so you don’t need to travel far! Transportation to the climbing locations is included in the Festival Pass, so that’s also taken care of!</p>

<p>Want to go? <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/wp-system/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/aicf_esite_www.pdf">Check the flyer</a> for more information on schedules &amp; Guides, and <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/events">book your Festival Pass here</a>. I’m very excited to travel north to Abisko and visit this Festival, I think it will be the perfect place to ice climb, meet like-minded people and enjoy the stunning scenery of Northern Sweden. If you’re going - comment underneath, it’d be cool to meet &amp; climb together! <strong>Getting to Abisko</strong> is easy: Jump on the train in Stockholm and get out in Abisko! Get your ticket at <a href="http://www.sj.se/">SJ</a>. If you prefer to fly, take a plane to Kiruna and then travel onwards by train or taxi to Abisko. </p>

<p><em>You can follow <a href="http://www.facebook.com/arcticguides">Arctic Guides on Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/arcticguides">Twitter</a>, and check out their <a href="http://www.arcticguides.com/">website</a> - they offer some truly unique trips and have experience guiding you in the Arctic &amp; Antarctic, Greenland, Baffin Island, Svalbard and Greenland!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/napdsp/6764561053/" title="Level 5 Aurora Borealis in Abisko by nate2b, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7030/6764561053_760eacd342_b.jpg" width="900" height="600" alt="Level 5 Aurora Borealis in Abisko" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
