<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: The Dolomites | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-dolomites/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-22T22:35:26+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Love the Dolomites Tour]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/love-the-dolomites-tour.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-17T23:53:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/love-the-dolomites-tour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friends. Good food. Wine. Three Guidebooks. No plan. Equals a fantastic time in the Dolomites.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19872954152/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19872954152_05a10af0d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Enjoying the cloud inversion near the Gardena Pass" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In March I let you in on a well-kept secret: That I will be going to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html">Dolomites</a> in July. With four friends. A rental car. An obscene amount of climbing, camping, Via ferrata and backpacking gear. So obscene that I needed to ditch one of my twin-topes on my mate Stu, with whom I was flying out of Helsinki way to early on a Sunday morning. A good thing that a sweltering heat was welcoming us in Venice, as well as our three companions and a rental car. Packed to the brim with only a dim idea how to get to Cortina we directed our vehicle North. And somehow I was able to navigate us securely to the <a href="http://www.dolomiti.org/ita/cortina/laga5torri/ospitalita/CinqueTorri/index.html">Rifugio Cinque Torri</a>. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19259485003/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Cinque Torri Refugio in the morning"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/350/19259485003_a0a9541eef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cinque Torri Refugio in the morning" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Gorgeous, stunning, breath-taking, <em>I love it</em>, where words that were uttered after the engine was switched off. We lost no time and shouldered ropes and climbing kit and hit the first crag, Torre Quarta Bassa. An easy 6a/ 5 Multi-Pitch route was picked for warm-up by Stu and me, as well as popping our Multi-Pitch Cherries. Our vocabulary soon was enhanced by meaningful phrases like <em>Where’s the next bolt?</em> and <em>That’s not a 5a!</em> As the sun was making the five beautiful towers of the Cinque Torri draw long shadows on the meadows we were rappelling down, walking back to the Rifugio. Dinner was calling, and so was the wine. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692381198/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Abseil"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/365/19692381198_dfdebbbb20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Abseil" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20660448541/in/dateposted/" title="Cinque Torri"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/730/20660448541_7fb341c5b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cinque Torri" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It’s common for climbers to get up early, and so we decided on a 6 o’clock start to climb a route on Cima Grande’s Southwest Face, which gets backed in the sun during the day. Rosamunde was climbed by Sam, Stu and me, and then breakfast was calling us back. Yes, half-board at the Rifugios is mandatory and highly recommended. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19257749664/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Morning Session on Rosamund"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/19257749664_f16b5152cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Morning Session on Rosamund" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stu and me were the Multi-Pitch team, and as we were in the company of a battalion of Italian soldiers it was the Via Normale on Torre Inglese which we climbed. There was exposure, sweaty palms, smiles, running it out, more smiles, squeezes and a hard-earned summit with trad gear. More smiles, two abseils and then some Apfelstrudel and Cappuccino. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19885405791/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Stu at the summit of Torre Inglese"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/524/19885405791_0e4b6fb8af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stu at the summit of Torre Inglese" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A few easy climbs at the School of Rock sector on the way back to a hot shower and a slab attempt that ended with the rain. Doesn’t matter, because there’s wine, dinner, card games, laughter, sitting outside and taking in the view. The next morning it was up before sunrise at 5 o’clock and another attempt on the slab. Stu on-sighted it, I failed, and so it was back to breakfast, packing up and heading onwards.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692379838/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Stu in the early morning light after having topped out on the Trephor Slab"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/386/19692379838_e315f1fc7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Stu in the early morning light after having topped out on the Trephor Slab" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A resupply in Cortina and we drove onwards. The Sorapiss Circuit was <em>The Plan™</em>. Car parked, backpacks with bivy gear shouldered and onwards we went. A coffee at the Rifugio on the way and up that lovely scree field in the 30°C heat. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19257748424/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="On the approach to the Sorapiss Circuit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/452/19257748424_cfb90f08d2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On the approach to the Sorapiss Circuit" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20660450391/in/dateposted/" title="Lago di Sorapiss and a wonderful scree field"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5692/20660450391_04f879eb54_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Lago di Sorapiss and a wonderful scree field" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It was getting late, the clouds were closing in, and so we stayed put at the end of the world. A un-secured hike 1000 m over a valley on narrow ledges was to be done fresh &amp; full of energy. The thunderstorms hitting us shortly after the bivies were rolled out made us congratulate ourselves for our smart decision. It was early to bed, sleep in, lightning storms all night. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19692405060/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="A break between Thunderstorms"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/309/19692405060_906ac422e5_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="A break between Thunderstorms" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As the sky cleared in the morning we decided against the sketchy approach, strolled back and drove to mountains with fairer weather. We found it in the Val Gardena, where we rolled out our sleeping bags on the Parking lot, shared wine with other campers and were looking forward to the Via Ferrata Brigata Tridentina.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19693765169/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="After the rain on the Gardena Pass"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/545/19693765169_d3bb7e6da4_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="After the rain on the Gardena Pass" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19854193206/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="The Bridge on the Brigata Tridentina Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3736/19854193206_49e12f1c1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="The Bridge on the Brigata Tridentina Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning a cloud inversion in the valley (<em>yeps, the opening photo</em>) made us dally around, but we were still in good time on the Via Ferrata and topped out happy at the top. A Kaiserschmarn later Matt, Sam, Stu and me explored the high plateau before it was back to the valley, which involved more scree, steel cables, snow fields and the urge to run it all down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20653770955/in/dateposted/" title="&quot;Easy&quot; Downclimb"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5717/20653770955_0e4089c4d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="&quot;Easy&quot; Downclimb" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I rolled out my bivy under a Boulder Problem called Sella benath Sassolunga that night, taking in the fine view of a star-filled sky. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19885410521/in/album-72157656091400816/" title="Sassolunga at night"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3834/19885410521_a0c2b49e98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sassolunga at night" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Easy climbs ensued the next morning after breakfast, followed by a check in to the fine <a href="http://www.dolomitesrefugeandhut.it">Rifugio Carlo Valentini</a>. A private bunk room, warm showers and more climbing followed by more showers followed, topped by a delicious dinner which had us wonder if we understood the quoted price right. The next morning saw us drive our car to the start of the Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata, the <em>most difficult</em> Via ferrata yet. An inexperienced Via Ferrata-ist before us had us wondering if we weren’t pokering too high, but as climbers we dispatched the first difficult bit in no time and hence enjoyed in peace the rest of the Via Ferrata. Suspension bridges, views on the Marmolada, ridge walks and caves made for an atmospheric hike. Just the long, steep walk back, we could have done without it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20466763028/in/dateposted/" title="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/610/20466763028_99e525a09a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20645582602/in/dateposted/" title="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/639/20645582602_a3565a0977_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Via delle Trincee Via Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And that was it. A long, or rather short night later I was on my way to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-soa-jury-meeting.html">SOA Jury Meeting</a> and the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/08/outdoor-news-2015-i.html">OutDoor 2015</a>, while my good friends travelled on to other parts of the world. But we were sure of one thing: That we loved the Dolomites, and that we will be back. And if you like mountains, good food &amp; wine, great climbing and fun Via Ferratas, you too should pay the Dolomits a visit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20465766490/in/dateposted/" title="At the End of the World, there is happiness"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5670/20465766490_422c576db0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="At the End of the World, there is happiness" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-13T21:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>How do you go about planning a trip to the Dolomites with a mate who is currently in Australia?</em> Easy: You both get the same guide book, book the flights together and then start going via Skype through the book to pick the climbs you wanna do. And that’s exactly how we are planning our trip to the Dolomites this summer, with our guide book of choice being <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata</a>. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16614176108" title="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7607/16614176108_d918a4f9ea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’ve been dreaming/ planning/ pondering/ almost-booking-flights-to-the-Dolomites since around four years. Vivid are the memories of driving through them as a child with mom and dad on the way to Southern Italy and back to Germany, then a <a href="http://www.rockandice.com">Rock &amp; Ice article</a> a few years ago re-kindled that love to go and visit one of the most beautiful areas in Italy. Sure, there would be some sweet hiking and cycling there, but it will still be there at another time. Now, this trip, it will be about climbing Multi-Pitch Routes and do Via Ferratas, visit a <a href="http://www.messner-mountain-museum.it">Messner Mountain Museum</a> and enjoy the good life with a great mate.</p>

<p>And with the <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">The Dolomites: Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata</a> Guide Book the good life already starts at home with the planning. I have been since a few weeks each evening going through the Guide Book and found it a superb resource to plan our trip. It’s so easy to send a short message á la <em>“Check out that sweet Multi-Pitch climb on page 384! Wanna do that?”</em> and literally be on the same page. It makes deciding on climbs a lot faster and easier, too, because opening a page in a book is faster &amp; more convenient than surfing to a webpage.</p>

<p>So how is this book lay out? Well, it starts with a bit of (climbing) history of the region and its geology, gives tips on other books and maps, and then tells you all you need to know about the Logistics of getting there, getting around, where to eat, sleep and what to bring. Then there’s a chapter each on Via Ferratas and Climbing, with explanations of grades, gear and how to plan a trip on the routes. Very useful and open pretty much all the time is the overview map of the Region (page 26/ 27 ;) before the book goes into the details.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16800637951" title="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7620/16800637951_e9fa1116c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="The Dolomites Rock Climbs &amp; Via Ferrata" /></a></p>

<p>And details means in this case detailed maps of the Region/ sector, photos with drawn-in topos and in-depth descriptions of the Via Ferratas and climbs. I found these descriptions very good, they give a bit of extra information on how hard the climb could be and how long it could take. What I like best about the <a href="http://www.rockfax.com">Rockfax.com</a> Guide Book is that you can download either the sectors/ climbs or the whole book onto your smartphone, allowing you to leave the 926 g Guide Book at home and don’t need to carry it up a climb - smart stuff. At the end there’s a Route Index and another map of the region with a General Index. </p>

<p>So, for me this has been a wonderful Guide Book thus far. The photos are top-notch and have me very much looking forward to this trip. What could be improved would be probably a larger fold-out/ take-out map as I feel I’m checking it all the time - we’re not staying in one Region/ Sector but plan to see a lot, though if you have more time and/ or stay in one Region you’ll probably be happy as it is. Overall I’d say you should get this Guide Book if you plan to visit the Dolomites for climbing and Via Ferrata hiking - or you should get it if you want to have a very good reason to visit them =) It’s a beautiful book with inspiring photos, all the information we needed to plan the trip logistics and it has in-depth information on the climbs and Via Ferratas of the region. It has been a source of joy for me in the last weeks and has me very much looking forward to visit this Region again - lets hope the weather will be kind for climbing!</p>

<p>Buy the book directly from <a href="http://www.rockfax.com/climbing-guides/books/the-dolomites-rock-climbs-and-via-ferrata/">Rockfax.com</a>, at your local climbing or book shop or order it from your favourite taste of <a href="http://amzn.to/1x0WARt">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1GMfr5H">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1GMfYVk">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
