<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: photography | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-06T09:20:13+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TrailPix Ultralight Tripod]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T12:42:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you enjoy taking photos when hiking? Do you carry a pair of trekking poles? Then you want a <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">TrailPix</a> to create a truly Ultralight Tripod!</p>

<p><a href="hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html" title="TrailPix Custom"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7373/10290298325_d976bd2c90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Multi-functionalism is one of the ideas of ultralight backpacking. Gear you carry should have more than one function. Trekking poles are superb multifunction items - besides walking aides they can be used to pitch your shelter, be transformed into a paddle for packrafting, can be used as a tenkara rod, and with the TrailPix they make your trekking poles a superb tripod!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290300815/" title="TrailPix Custom w/ ball head"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3736/10290300815_3e6db8a058_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom w/ ball head" /></a></p>

<p>I first got aware of TrailPix last year when <a href="http://briangreen.net/">Brian Green</a> posted about the original design on his blog. I liked the idea a lot, though didn’t find the design too refined. Apparently I wasn’t alone, as the Kickstarter project didn’t reach its goal. In the end, this was positive for us, because Andy - the inventor of TrailPix - didn’t give up and started to refine the TrailPix during the last nine months, and the result is a truly superb tool to transform your trekking poles into a tripod.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8752858727/" title="Trail Pix Early Prototype from nv8design.com"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/8752858727_f88d56390e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Trail Pix from nv8design.com" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290190004/" title="TrailPix Custom vs an earlier Prototype"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3796/10290190004_969dcbfb71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom vs an earlier Prototype" /></a></p>

<p>I have been testing one of the earlier Prototypes (see above), which I liked a lot. But the final design, the one you can get if you <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">back Andy’s Kickstarter project</a> is even better. There are two versions available, the Universal and the Custom. I have a Custom version, made for the tips of my <a href="http://www.rutalocura.com/trekking_poles.html">Ruta Locura Yana poles</a>. These poles have Black Diamond Flex Tech Tips which also are used on my <a href="http://gossamergear.com/trekking/trekking/lt4-trekking-poles-all.html">Gossamer Gear LT4 poles</a>. They also do fit well on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cRcjH7">MSR Surelock poles</a> and OK-ish on my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekkingstoecke/">Black Diamond Z-Poles</a>. However, they have the tightest and hence most secure fit with the Ruta Locura Poles, which the TrailPix Custom was made for.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290300105/" title="TrailPix Custom and suitable trekking poles for it"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3784/10290300105_18d701d7fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom and suitable trekking poles for it" /></a></p>

<p>The Custom version (27 gram) has the option of an accessory pole which is the third leg, and at 70 g the accessory pole is not too heavy. It’s custom made for your trekking poles, and you can let Andy know which size you need when you’re ordering it. The Universal version on the other hand fits a wide variety of poles, so if you hike with a friend you could loan one of his poles, or use a tent pole to make your tripod. The Custom version is excellent if you have one pair of poles and usually hike solo, the Universal version is for you if you have many different trekking poles and want your TrailPix to fit each pair.</p>

<p>In use on the trail TrailPix is quickly deployed. I keep the accessory pole and TrailPix with the Ballhead in a side pocket, so I can quickly grab them when I need a tripod. I turn the trekking poles around, put the poles in the holes, unfold the accessory pole and insert it, and <em>Voilá</em> - there’s your tripod. Now you just add your camera, switch it on and you can start taking photos. It’s very fast and you don’t need to take off your backpack, either!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290196014/" title="TrailPix Custom &amp; Panasonic GH2"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3717/10290196014_1f1f0985d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom &amp; Panasonic GH2" /></a></p>

<p>Andy has made it really easy to chose the version you need, and offers a host of useful extras. I highly recommend getting a ball head (49 gram) additionally to the TrailPix (unless you already have one) and the accessory pole (70 gram) if you go for the Custom Version. If you’re a <a href="http://www.peakdesignltd.com/">Peak Designs</a> Capture user, you can even get a ARCA-style quick release base from him and make them compatible! So, if you want one, <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">back Andy’s Kickstarter project</a> now - it closes on Friday morning. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290418393/" title="TrailPix Custom Set"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3747/10290418393_cc175766b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157636580175493/">Some more photos</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Velbon V-Pod - Worlds Lightest Tripod]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T15:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For years the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/04/joby-gorillapod-slr.html">Joby GorillaPod</a> has been my “tripod” of choice. And while I certainly still use it and often have it along on trips, in above tree line environments or when a real tripod would be more convienent than a GorillaPod, I needed something that’s still light enough to carry but can get high enough for photos, timelapses and video. Enter the Velbon V-Pod, probably the Worlds Lightest Tripod.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8570950041/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8374/8570950041_bf2f8aa725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I first read about the Velbon V-Pod a few year’s ago on Dave’s, the <a href="http://www.armchair-adventurer.com/">Armchair Adventurer</a>, blog. But it still has taken me an unreasonably long time to purchase a V-Pod, which I now, with hindsight, regret. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8572168042/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8091/8572168042_0c9f8fe4c1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>My Velbon V-Pod weighs 279 gram, has a transport length of 29 cm, is fully extended 100 cm tall and has a minimum height of 28 cm. It carries my <a href="http://amzn.to/ZXzy8j">Sony NEX-5r</a> with a <em>heavy</em> Pentax Asahi 55mm lens (body + lens = 570 g) without problems, though if you go outdoors with a Canon 7D or similar you might want to use something more substantial as a tripod. But for the M43 crowd and Point-and-Shoot photographers, the Velbon V-Pod is a superb tool. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8572072576/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8383/8572072576_14246b0ebd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>I used it since for shooting <a href="https://vimeo.com/60198868">timelapse movies</a>, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">aurora borealis and stars</a>, videos and stills. It is small enough to go inside the backpack or put it under a strap or a mesh pocket on the outside, and is ready to use in less than 30 seconds. It has a ball head which allows for great fluid movements and picking almost any position you’d like. If it is windy you can attach a weight (your backpack) to the centre strut of the V-Pod to pull it down and keep it in place.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8570973041/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8247/8570973041_b7a3a01d23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>It comes with a carrying pouch (12 g) and a holder for smartphones (25 g). Especially the latter is pretty neat (unless you have a <a href="http://amzn.to/10cFigF">Glif</a>) as it allows you to use your smartphone for videos, stop-and-go animations and photos. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8571075403/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8098/8571075403_e11c051320_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>In short: I’m sorry that I waited so long to buy the Velbon V-Pod. It’s a superb tool for photographers who use lightweight cameras, and nowadays the V-Pod finds its way into my pack on pretty much each trip, long or short. If you’re searching for a lightweight tripod for your Micro Four Thirds or similar camera, look no further. The Velbon V-Pod is the answer for us lightweight backpackers &amp; photographers.</p>

<p><strong>Get a Velbon V-Pod</strong> at <a href="http://amzn.to/XdRZGO">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/145x1P0">Amazon.de</a> (they’re not available at Amazon.com, sorry). <em>If you buy via these Affiliate Links, I earn a few cents. Don’t worry, it doesn’t cost you anything extra =)</em></p>

<p><em><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633031907155/">More photos of the Velbon V-Pod</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GoPro HERO3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/10/gopro-hero3.html"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T14:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/10/gopro-hero3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new GoPro, again? Yes! The GoPro HERO3 was just announced this morning, and the underneath video, shot entirely with the third re-incarnation of the best action camera available looks like it just again jumped ahead in front of the competition. Hit play, get psyched and then read more!</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/A3PDXmYoF5U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’ve had my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/10/gopro-hd-hero2.html">HERO2</a> since last year, and it has been out on a lot of trips where it has seen some <a href="https://vimeo.com/43411086">great action</a>. The GoPro is a very special kind of camera, and shines best in my opinion if you do action sports - packrafting, climbing, paragliding, bikepacking &amp; mountain biking, and to a limited extent also backpacking. If you plan to use your GoPro solely for backpacking videos and photos there might be <a href="http://amzn.to/RsjOGr">better cameras</a> out there for that, which take probably better photos - on the other hand <a href="http://www.barefootjake.com/">Barefoot Jake</a> for example only uses a GoPro for his photos, thus it is possible and certainly a compact and light option to document your trips.</p>

<p>But in my opinion the HERO3 (and HERO2 for that matter) shines for these kind of adventures where you want to give the viewer an exciting point-of-view of the action you’re doing, and with a small camera that you can mount on your helmet, bike, packraft, chest or pole that’s certainly going to be easier than with a small camera. A <a href="http://amzn.to/TurPcZ">Point-and-Shoot</a> might work, but attaching these to a helmet, bike or packraft is more complicated, plus the lack the waterproof housing. Thus, if you want to film your outdoor adventures, a POV camera like the GoPro or a <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=85857&amp;pw=73183">Contour+2</a> are the way to go - if you have a need for it!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8096507889/" title="GoPro HERO3 Black Edition by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8466/8096507889_a232820b5a_b.jpg" width="683" height="426" alt="GoPro HERO3 Black Edition" /></a></p>

<p>Which brings us to the GoPro HERO3: Black Edition, which has a very long list of great improvements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It got 30% smaller and 25% lighter (the camera now weighs only 74 gram!)</li>
  <li>Built-in Wi-Fi</li>
  <li>A new waterproof housing which you can take up to 60 meters deep with an updated flat-lens that will deliver sharp videos above and under water</li>
  <li>Includes the Wi-Fi Remote</li>
  <li>Compatible with the <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gopro-app/id561350520?mt=8">GoPro iPhone App</a></li>
  <li>Can shot 12 Megapixel photos at a rate of 30 frames per second</li>
  <li>A new Continuous Photo mode</li>
  <li>Plenty of even higher quality video formats</li>
  <li>A better audio system</li>
  <li>Two times better low light performance!</li>
  <li>User-selectable Ultra-wide, Medium and Narrow field-of-views</li>
</ul>

<p>Being smaller &amp; lighter with better video and photo capabilities and built-in Wi-fi are the top points here, followed by better low light performance. It is compatible with the old batteries (BacPacs) as well as LCD Touch BacPac, so that’s great news for those who already own these accessories, and it also keeps the <a href="https://vimeo.com/32251546">timelapse mode</a>, which is very nice. Being able to select the field-of-view will mean hopefully more videos which are shot in a “Fisheye” ultra-wide mode, which is something many can’t stand watching (at least for very long); you can take this off in post-processing but being able to shot in a more normal field-of-view is a welcome option. </p>

<p>Taking a peek at the competition and the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=85857&amp;pw=73183">Contour+2</a>, I think the HERO3 still is ahead. While they share now some of the same features - Wi-Fi and smartphone apps, for example - the HERO3 is having a few more options - dead simple time-lapse, for example. The Contour+2 on the other hand could be better if you use your action camera on you helmet a lot, as you can attach it to the side more easily than a HERO3. The Contour+2 also offers GPS tagging, but is double as heavy as a HERO3. Finacially, they’re both the same price, so at least there none has an advantage!</p>

<p><em>So should you get one</em>? The answer is if you go (a lot) packrafting, bikepacking, skiing, climbing or maybe even canyoning, diving, surfing and paragliding <strong>YES</strong>! If you usually just hike and bike in the city then you’re likely not using the full potential of this camera and are better of just loaning one from a friend if you need one. While I am lusting over the HERO3 I am not certain that it would see any more action than my HERO2, so I’ll stick with what I have for the time being.</p>

<p>You can preorder the Premium GoPro HERO3: Black Edition for $399.99 at <a href="http://www.kqzyfj.com/on118zw41w3JPPLNKRTJLKRMQLKM" target="_top" onmouseover="window.status='http://gopro.com';return true;" onmouseout="window.status=' ';return true;">GoPro.com</a><img src="http://www.ftjcfx.com/k9122r6Az42OUUQSPWYOQPWRVQPR" width="1" height="1" border="0" />, it is shipping in the middle of November. Also available are a White Edition for $199.99 and a Silver Edition for $299.99 which have slightly less impressive video capabilities, but are, like the Black Edition, smaller &amp; lighter with built-in Wi-Fi so an improvement over the older GoPros. <em>Finally, if you get HERO3 - make sure to use mix things up and shot with more than one POV!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2nd HIF Photo Contest - FIRE]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/10/2nd-hif-photo-contest-fire.html"/>
    <updated>2012-10-15T16:57:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/10/2nd-hif-photo-contest-fire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/1st-hif-reader-photo-contest.html">1st Hiking in Finland Reader Photo Contest</a> was a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/hif-photo-contest-winners.html">great success</a>, and many awesome photos were submitted. Now were back with a burning desire to see more splendid photos - and win some fiery gear, too!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/6993051489/" title="Fire by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7046/6993051489_05478b8d23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Nothing says outdoors and backpacking like a warm fire. It gives you light, warmth and allows you to cook. It’s a gathering place to sit around in the evenings after a day of skiing or backpacking, and its glow in the distance means there’s a warm place to go to. I love a good fire in the evenings at camp, and I love to take photos of the burning wood and flames. So for this contest I’d like to see your interpretation of FIRE. Is it a camping fire? A forest fire? Flames? A BushBuddy? Whatever it is, the topic is wide open to interpretation and I hope for many creative submissions. </p>

<p>How to participate:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Leave a comment with a link to your [one] photo on <a href="http://www.flickr.com/">Flickr</a> and tag the photo with “<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/hifirecontest/">HIFireContest</a>” so that it’s easy to find, and tell us a bit about the story behind the photo.</li>
  <li>Deadline is the 30th of October, 2012, Midnight Finnish time.</li>
  <li>I will pick the top three photos and award a price to the winner and runner-ups.</li>
</ol>

<p>The Price? The top three each get a <a href="http://www.lightmyfire.com/products/sparking-fire-collection/swedish-fireknife.aspx">Swedish FireKnife</a>, courtesy of <a href="http://www.lightmyfire.com/">Light-My-Fire</a>. A super-sharp Mora knife, paired with a Light-My-Fire FireSteel and coming in a bunch of great colours, this is a light (109 gram) and useful tool to carry when going outdoors.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8080007017/" title="IMG_0112 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8184/8080007017_a08ab8fa00_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="IMG_0112" /></a></p>

<p>So that’s it. I’m looking forward to seeing your photos. Happy photographing - and don’t burn yourself!</p>

<p><strong>Why Flickr?</strong> Because it is easy for me and others to see all entries in one go. You can sign up for free in case you don’t have an account yet.<br />
<strong>Will you showcase the winner’s photo?</strong> I sure hope so! So please allow others to embed your photo. You keep all rights to your photo, and it will be shown one time on Hiking in Finland. With participating you thus grant me permission to embed your photo <em>one time</em> here, for free. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8039428191/" title="Light-My-Fire Knife by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8171/8039428191_e17b7dc96d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Light-My-Fire Knife" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HIF Photo Contest Winners]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/08/hif-photo-contest-winners.html"/>
    <updated>2012-08-22T21:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/08/hif-photo-contest-winners</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you everyone who participated in the first <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/1st-hif-reader-photo-contest.html">Hiking in Finland Photo Contest</a>. There were well over 30 entries, and it was hard to narrow it down three, let alone pick a winner.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7751534778/" title="Magic forest by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8448/7751534778_8cb0b606cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Magic forest" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Picking the top three was hard, I sat for well over fourty minutes looking at all the entries, discussing them with my wife (always have female input in important decisions!), until I finally was able to settle on the winning three.</p>

<h2 id="place-1">Place 1:</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/84534588@N03/7799962514/" title="Teufelsslucht by Samen Buiten, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8285/7799962514_8e8b5b1b42_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Teufelsslucht" /></a></p>

<p><em>It is a very interesting view of a broad-leaved forest in Luxembourg, with cliffs to one side. The brown, dead leaves on the floor stand in nice contrast with the bright green leaves of the trees, as does the dead wood on the ground with the living trees. The rocks on the right side are a stark contrast to the living matter around them, funnily enough one of the rocks looks like a skull. The photo appears to be not manipulated [missing EXIF data :/]. All in all a very nice scene, one where I feel like jumping in and going for a hike and climb. However, I think the photo could have been improved by not having been taken in the middle of the day - morning or evening light could have improved the photo. Nevertheless, my favourite of the submitted photos. Congratulations Samen Buiten!</em></p>

<h2 id="place-2">Place 2:</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/familyjonesnow/4419539761/" title="Honeymoon - Kamikochi, Japan by The real Jonesnow, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm5.staticflickr.com/4040/4419539761_9863957f49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Honeymoon - Kamikochi, Japan" /></a></p>

<p><em>In this photo I really like the perspective it gives - the person in the photo gives you a sense of the surroundings. The infalling sunbeams from the right give the impression of it being very early, which is further enhanced by the rising mist and the clouds in the sky. Broad-leaf trees in the foreground till close to the river, with some conifers on the side and the mountains shows how different and adaptable the forest can be. I really feel how the moisture is in the air in this photo, how the leafs and stones are covered in dew and can imagine how nice it must be to walk there, waiting for the sun to come over the tree tops. Maybe the sky is slightly overlighted, though all in all a very great photo, and a worthy second place! Congratulations Gareth!</em></p>

<h2 id="place-3">Place 3:</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/74188980@N08/6942323674/" title="IMGP8848 by Tanglefist, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5336/6942323674_ff751190d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="685" alt="IMGP8848" /></a></p>

<p><em>A very nice capture, illustrating that forests not only can be a relaxing, serene place, but also invite us to enjoy adrenaline-laden activities like mountain biking in them. The fuzzy, brown conifer forest with a bit of green shining through in the background are a nice contrast to the sharp mountain biker in the centre. Taking photos like these isn’t easy, especially as this one was shot in a moment as it presented itself; though it would have been nice if the mountain biker would have been really crisp and sharp. Here I feel like I’d like to join the two mountain bikers and race over the trails in the shadow of the forest. Congratulations Court Harding!</em></p>

<p>Please all three of you of you contact me via Email. The first place gets the Berghaus Arete Backpack, while I have a small surprise for the second and third place.</p>

<h2 id="honourable-mentions">Honourable Mentions:</h2>

<p>Picking three out from the 30+ entries was hard, and so I show you the three more photos which were in the top six: </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/7775627836/" title="Birchy by valppaus, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8284/7775627836_c0a34f32a1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="685" alt="Birchy" /></a></p>

<p><em>Joni from Finland photographed the prettiest tree of Finland - the Birch. I like the texture in the photo, and the autumny look.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/84698967@N04/7804463118/" title="DSC00911 by Levonjensen, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8441/7804463118_0c2de4c494_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="DSC00911" /></a></p>

<p><em>Levon Jensen presents us with a classic autumn view from Waterton Park. Great autumn colours and the mountains and clouds in the background make for a majestic scenery.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sticksblog/7756590274/" title="P1030316 by Sticks Blog, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8445/7756590274_259b61e1c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="P1030316" /></a></p>

<p><em>Chad Poindexter’s forest path in the mist is a very beautiful photograph, which makes you feel like you want to walk down that path towards the light.</em></p>

<p>Again, a big THANK YOU to all participants. It was a great pleasure to go through all the different, creative and beautiful photos which were entered, and a tough job to pick the three I liked the most. Once September comes by, expect a second photography contest!</p>

<p><em>All rights to the shown photos are with their respective owners. Thanks for allowing me to showcase them.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
