<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: photography | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-04T10:56:38+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony RX100 IV Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/sony-rx100-iv-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2016-10-24T23:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/sony-rx100-iv-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What camera do you use?</em> is probably the most common question I am asked when out on a trip or when someone sees my photos, and an astounding expression is often the result when I show my Sony RX100 IV - a pocket camera. But because size &amp; weight matter ever less in the fast evolving world of photography, the results of this small camera speak for it - be it here on the blog or in print magazines. <em>A comprehensive Field Report.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30417082542/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5818/30417082542_bc653b28b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100 IV" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p><em>The Sony RX100 IV is the camera you want to document your adventures when you prefer light weight, a small size and superb image quality.</em></p>

<h2 id="what-i-want-from-a-camera-and-how-i-ended-up-choosing-the-rx100-iv">What I want from a camera (and how I ended up choosing the RX100 IV)</h2>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: I bought the RX 100 IV myself and have no affiliation with Sony.</p>

<p>This blog started out about my backpacking trips in Finland &amp; my journey to lighten up the load on my back when outdoors, and has morphed into what I call an Outdoor Adventure Travel Blog nowadays. But I remember my Ultralight roots in everything I start, from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/bikepacking-in-pirkanmaa.html">bikepacking</a> to mountaineering, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/08/ultralight-climbing.html">climbing</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring.html">ski-touring</a>. I have dabbled with big, heavy cameras, used M43s like the still superb <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/04/panasonic-lumix-gf1-field-report.html">Panasonic Lumix GF1</a>, graduated to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Sony A7R full-frame camera</a>, had a short affair with the Olympus OM-D E-M5 and its successor and then just simply returned to what I consider the best camera for outdoor enthusiasts &amp; photographers who are outside, the subject of this article, the Sony RX100 IV. I enjoyed its predecessor, the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html">RX 100 III</a>, but haven’t pulled the trigger on my RX100 IV till last year December, when I ordered it on <a href="http://amzn.to/2eUfshc">Amazon</a>. </p>

<p><em>Why did I buy the RX 100 IV?</em> you might ponder, a valid question as do I own some other <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/photography/">cameras</a> too. Well, that’s where the ultralight thought comes up again. I wanted something that I can put in a pocket and is light. While I love the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture Pro</a> I have been out a lot in weather which has been anything than sunshine &amp; blue sky, and while I could add a <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/covers/shell/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Shell Cover</a> I prefer to keep it simple. And what is simpler than putting your camera into the chest pocket of your hardshell? After this lengthy introduction, let me quote myself:</p>

<p><em>“I’m still looking for the *Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> in terms of photographic equipment. It’s the camera which has only advantages, satisfies all my needs and is good enough for all my requirements”*:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Print-quality photographs</li>
  <li>Nightshots possible</li>
  <li>Video capable</li>
  <li>Tiltscreen</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
  <li>Weatherproof</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25866478752/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Flag"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/2/1690/25866478752_fd77e5ee83_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Flag" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bad">The Bad</h2>

<p>Before delving into these points and others in detail, let me first highlight the disadvantages of the RX 100 IV: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Only F11</li>
  <li>No hotshoe for a microphone or similar</li>
  <li>The Video Microphone is not good in real wind</li>
  <li>Included Flash in underpowered</li>
  <li>Menu is a bit unorganized and could be clearer</li>
  <li>No touch screen</li>
  <li>Tedious to switch focus point at times</li>
  <li>Back screen scratches easily</li>
  <li>No charger included</li>
  <li>Camera has sometimes difficulties with very bright or grey skies</li>
</ul>

<p>Now lets look at these in a bit more detail.</p>

<p><em>Only F11</em>. That might not seem like a big complaint, but for someone like me who loves sun stars F11 is often not enough. Add  some clouds or something to the sky and you can pretty much be sure that the RX100 IV is gonna make it a glowing white ball in the sky. When the sky is clear, however, it does produce acceptable sunstars: </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28044201296/in/album-72157669978279411/" title="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7797/28044201296_a750b77c3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>No hotshoe for a microphone or similar</em>. I really, really, really wish Sony would have said <em>We don’t need no underpowered flash in this camera, but lets put on a Hotshoe</em> because honestly, for me this camera is aimed at professionals, videography and photography enthusiasts who have the accessories which would need a hotshoe. This goes hand-in-hand with the next two complaints: </p>

<p><em>The Video Microphone is not good in real wind</em> and <em>Included Flash in underpowered</em>. Watch the underneath video and wait five seconds after the intro and see how useless the microphone is in real wind - and this is with wind cancellation et al. activated. If I would have been able to attach my beloved <a href="http://amzn.to/2eAihzK">Rode VideoMic</a> you could have understood me clear like in an empty studio, but so the wind is pretty much drowning me out completely. Also the underpowered flash is next-to-useless and I’d rather would not have it on the camera - I have NEVER used it - and have the possibility to attach a real flash via a hotshoe. I hope that in Version VI of this camera Sony will give it a Hotshoe, because that would make it even more versatile.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1ZN99LOKqjQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The <em>Menu is a bit unorganized and could be clearer</em> is something most camera manufacturers seem to have problems with if I read or watch reviews. It’d be nice to be able to create an own “My Menu” point where I could add these Menu points which are important to me so that I can access them fast instead of trying to find them in the buried Menu structure. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29900767693/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV Menu"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5608/29900767693_c7380e2ab6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sony RX100 IV Menu" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That there’s <em>No touch screen</em> is a problem if you want to again quickly navigate through the Menu, or, even more important, set the Focus point somewhere. Because it can be <em>Tedious to switch the focus point at times</em> as you a) need to be in the right Focus Mode and b) then need to push the button and then navigate it with the wheel to where you want it. With a touchscreen I ideally would put my finger where I want the focus to be and <em>Voilá!</em> I could shoot. So I often need to try very fast to switch the focus point when my subject is moving. </p>

<p>Lets stay with the back of the camera for one more moment, as the <em>Back screen scratches easily</em>. It’s purely optical - probably the protective layer on it - but it’s still a bit annoying. After all this is a 1.200€ camera, and you’d expect that the screen is scratch resistant - it is a pocket camera, after all. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30417089442/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV Scratched scree"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5542/30417089442_7990889a3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Sony RX100 IV Scratched scree" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>What really has me scratching my head is why Sony did not <em>include a charger</em> in the package. You can <a href="http://amzn.to/2emViNX">buy one</a> but it feels strange to spend almost 20€ on something that should be included. You can charge the battery otherwise via the included USB cable, but that also means you can not use the camera to shoot. This is a short-sighted and unfriendly customer policy which I really don’t like, and I hope the next RX100 cameras will come with a charger included. </p>

<p>Which bring me to the final complaint, and here we enter the technical capabilities of the camera. It <em>sometimes has difficulties with very bright or grey skies</em> aka <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_range#Photography">Dynamic Range</a>, or in layman terms: If there’s a dark foreground and a very bright background (or vice versa). While the Sony RX100 IV has a built in, electronic ND Filter which can help with making the image better, it only helps so much (and you need to remember to switch it on). Happily this is something I usually am able to fix in <a href="http://amzn.to/2eJtrTR">Lightroom and Photoshop</a> afterwards as I always photograph in RAW. If you can’t fix it then images come out like this, though:</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30497509756/in/dateposted/" title="High Dynamic Range Anyone?"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8618/30497509756_a663420ddf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="High Dynamic Range Anyone?" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Which looks OK but you have no idea what’s happening in the foreground. </p>

<h2 id="the-good">The Good</h2>

<p>So, these are my complaints about the camera, which I hope Sony will fix in the next versions of this camera. Thus onwards to the positive sides of the RX100 IV, which really shine. </p>

<p>Print-quality photographs ✓</p>

<p>Besides Hiking in Finland I write for over a dozen of magazines and while that could be an excuse to splurge on a Full-Frame camera and some fancy lenses it really isn’t needed nowadays. The RX100 IV produces superb photos for print, with all the details and colours you’d want. Even if I was out on an assignment for clients I just stood by the fact that I have this wee camera and not a heavy DSLR to shot for them, and once they saw the images there never has been a complaint. I know that I am very lucky with my clients which are open-minded, and that sometimes you just have to show up with a DSLR to a gig to look the part, but as I usually work on my own I really don’t need to impress anyone with the size of my camera. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26160876304/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="Fjord sunset"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/2/1489/26160876304_454bd5c53c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fjord sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Nightshots possible  ✓</p>

<p>I love me some pretty night shots. Standing out in the cold and dark, starring at the stars, maybe shivering a wee bit - that’s me feeling alive, small, happy and behind my camera, taking photos of these stars and Northern Lights. Or of impressive city scapes, like last December as <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/arcteryx-workshop-tour.html">I visited Arc’teryx in Vancouver</a>. It sometimes feels a bit like hit-and-miss with the focus, but if the focus is spot-on then the tiny camera produces great images of nightscapes.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29902998894/in/dateposted/" title="Vancouver at night"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8571/29902998894_25c96d4288_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vancouver at night" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30446319961/in/dateposted/" title="Night in the Dolomites"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5805/30446319961_84734d2be7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night in the Dolomites" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Video capable ✓</p>

<p>The Sony RX100 IV can shoot 4K Movies, which is the next step up from 1080 HD. It’s pretty heavy on the Memory Cards (you might want to bring a 128GB card or three) but if it is something you need you will be delighted to know it is possible. I shot at 1080 HD and that’s plenty good, too, and is a lot friendlier for data storage. You can see the <a href="https://youtu.be/1ZN99LOKqjQ">MSR Access 2 Video</a> above for an example of the camera’s video capabilities. I have to say that I find it annoying that Movies can only be recorded when the tiny red Movie button on the back is pushed AND the programme wheel is in Movie mode - if the latter is e.g. in Manuel mode you’ll get a warning on the screen. I would like that I also could start videos by push the shutter button, as that would make sense if the programme wheel is on Movies. </p>

<p>Tilt-able screen? ✓</p>

<p>While I always carry a tripod and a remote Selfies are a great way to be up-close in a photo, and for videos it’s very useful to see yourself when you’re filming. The screen on the RX100 IV can be tilted fully up which is great for Selfies and filming. It can be tilted around 45° downwards which makes it useful for shooting over your head, for example if you’re in a crowd and want to get a good angle from thw back</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30235575070/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV with screen fully up"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5644/30235575070_192148fce5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100 IV with screen fully up" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30417085852/in/dateposted/" title="Selfie on Seekofel"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5539/30417085852_4c94913803_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfie on Seekofel" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Long battery life ✓</p>

<p>Oh wow, the battery life. Is. <strong>AMAZING</strong>. When other reviewers complain about the poor battery life of the RX100 IV I can only wonder what they’re doing, but I took in winter, at -5°C outside temperature, 1.200 photos with the RX100 IV on the mountain and the camera’s battery was still half full. On the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/autumn-backpacking-in-the-dolomites.html">Dolomites trip</a> this month I used one battery on average for three days and around 1.500 photos. These are amazing stats for me as I know that with a full battery in the camera and a back-up battery in the chest pocket of my baselayer I can be out a full day and shoot whatever comes my way without needing to worry to run out of juice. I even can browse the photos in the evening and send a shot or five via the in-built Wifi to my phone where I can edit it in the Lightroom and Photoshop Apps before uploading the days shot to <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>. Seriously, the battery life is out-of-this-world and if you’re an occasional shooter you probably can go on a week long trip and shoot all you want to shoot without needing to worry that the battery runs out. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24373293681/in/album-72157663594014166/" title="Sunrise on the Baltic!"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1527/24373293681_a8bfcc613e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Sunrise on the Baltic!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Easy to use ✓</p>

<p>One of the main reasons to get a small camera is that it is easier to use, especially for people that don’t want to dive into deep Menus. The Auto Mode on the RX100 IV is really good and I occasionally use it with great success - often indoors when the lightning is difficult, but also outdoors it produces very good images. You can put it on Auto Mode and give it a friend in the hand and he’ll be fine to take good photos. Pop-up the EVF if it’s bright out there and they will be able to compose the shot via it without problems. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24772101730/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="Powder Shower"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1441/24772101730_36bd02d8e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Powder Shower" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Lightweight ✓</p>

<p>The camera without SD Card and battery is 262 g light, an original Sony battery weighs 24 g and the SD card is 2 g, which means the functioning camera weighs 288 g. I added a wee hand lop which weighs 3 g, so that brings it up to 291 g. Lighter is just using a phone camera (which are not even close as good as the RX100 IV, see further underneath) or no camera at all. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634869063/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Cave Gorna Slatinska 13"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7265/26634869063_296b974bce_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Cave Gorna Slatinska 13" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Weatherproof ✓</p>

<p>While Sony doesn’t advertize the RX100 IV as highly weatherproof it has been just that in my experience. I had it out in snow and rain storms - and because that’s when you’re getting the best photos I of course also had the camera out in that weather. It has no problems with getting wet, and even when moisture has collected on the lens and the extendable lens, I never had a failure on it. Sure, this all has been with care and I wouldn’t hold the camera under a waterfall, but for quick shots in the snow and rain the RX100 IV is more than enough weatherproof. I also don’t have a case for it - I 99% of the time carry it in my hand or chest pocket, so that’s all the weather protection it has had over the last ten months. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24460363514/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="I love me a nice cabin!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1466/24460363514_7edaab5590_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I love me a nice cabin!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another advantage is that the camera has an Electronic Viewfinder. This makes the camera look more like an old-fashioned film camera, which is really useful in street photography when you want to shoot people and not awaken the impression it’s a digital camera. Also for portraits I find the EVF great as it allows the subjects to take you more serious &amp; relax while you’re behind the camera, instead of looking on a screen in front of you. It’s also so small that I can hold it in my hand and shot from the hip, or place it inconspicuously on a table and take a photo of a situation.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30446312051/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV with Flash &amp; EVF open, from behind"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/6/5795/30446312051_11e87408d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100 IV with Flash &amp; EVF open, from behind" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29902998494/in/dateposted/" title="Social Me time"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5463/29902998494_c6a07d2a46_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Social Me time" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24442006569/in/dateposted/" title="Week 4"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1605/24442006569_4b17663d4e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Week 4" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>One thing I love is the possibility of sending via In-built Wifi photos from the camera to my phone, where I can edit it in Lightroom &amp; Photoshop and upload it to Instagram. Gone the times where one needs to first upload everything to the Mac, then edit it there and then transfer it somehow back to the phone. The App and Wifi work great once set up, and is used often and with pleasure. </p>

<p>Where I’m already talking about my phone: <em>How’s the Sony RX100 IV in comparison to the iPhone 6S?</em> you might ponder. I bought the iPhone 6S (800+€) because I thought the camera in that phone finally has reached a level which is great. How wrong I was. Sure, the iPhone 6S is still lighter and smaller than the Sony camera, but there’s World’s between these two devices in photographic terms. I am very disappointed by the quality of the iPhone 6S photos as I expected a lot better quality, but especially in the above mentioned High Dynamic Range situations - think sunsets and sunrises - the iPhone 6S comes not even close in quality to what the Sony RX100 IV can do. The iPhone simply overburdened with a lot of photographic situations, and even if Apple tries to make us think otherwise - I wouldn’t spend so much money on an iPhone ever again. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26741128546/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1508/26741128546_756a100b4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Bikepacking with the Sony RX100 IV is great. I had it along on a few trips where I was riding tours for magazine stories, and capturing the environment &amp; action while on the bike, hands on a handlebar, is still a bit different than hiking, ski-touring or climbing. I stored the camera in my <a href="http://www.ovejanegrathreadworks.com/12-packtrade-frame-bag.html">Oveja Negra 1/2 Pack</a> where it fitted in with all the other kit I have in there. It’s very easy to get out of there - with one hand! - and allows me to capture situations from the bike in around 15 seconds max. I also can fit in my tripod and remote in the 1/2 Pack, and can set things up in a minute or two, which is great for those photos where I + bike need to be completely in the frame. I have experimented with a few cameras on bikepacking &amp; cycle-touring trips and the RX100 IV has been my favourite by far because it is so convenient to use when on (and off) the bike. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22836352233/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Mandatory cycling selfie"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5817/22836352233_1fb4de4f0d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mandatory cycling selfie" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And at the end, still some words on durability. I now have the RX100 IV since December 2015 in use, and it has been with me on at least 14 trips where it has been in the cold, bumped against rocks while climbing, hiked in the sleet and snow of the Dolomites, endured 35°C in Greece and two trade fairs. I have shot well over 27.000 images with it in these ten months, and while it feels that it doesn’t start up as fast anymore as when it was new it still functions as great as on Day one. I expect that I’ll get another year or two of use out of this camera - although I am tempted to update to the RX100 V which was announced a couple of weeks ago as it fixes some of my complaints. But even if I don’t update, I think that a small camera like this one, which has seen so much use and the only <em>“damage”</em> it has taken are scratches on the back screen and some chipped paint, is speaking for the high quality of the Sony RX100 IV.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30235574520/in/dateposted/" title="Field Notes x Sony RX100 IV"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5596/30235574520_5d0d6a1605_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Field Notes x Sony RX100 IV" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-accessories">The Accessories</h2>

<p>Accessories I carry along include always a second <a href="http://amzn.to/2emiMQU">SanDisk Extreme 64GB SDXC Card</a>, as they have an amazing price-to-quality ratio and the write speed of 90MB/ second is great for long bursts. 64GB can last for up to a week of being outdoors and a wee video in between. If I know I will shot more video or lots, and lots of photos, then I’ll take two or three extra cards along - at 30€ a card I consider them pretty affordable (I wish <a href="http://amzn.to/2eJBvUV">External Storage</a> would be as cheap!).</p>

<p>My <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod.html">Velbon V-Pod</a> is still usually along as I might want to take night photos, videos or need to be in the photo and have no-one around to take a photo of me. I also bought a <a href="http://amzn.to/2eAjUzM">Pixel RW221 Remote</a> which is very good - you can be up to 100 m away and still operate the camera, which is great for all kind of photos. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30446316381/in/dateposted/" title="Sony RX100 IV Ports open"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5344/30446316381_0f082d6397_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100 IV Ports open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then I own three extra batteries and a charger for them. I bought two original <a href="http://amzn.to/2eeYQy1">Sony NP-BX1/M8 Lithium-Ion X Type Batteries</a> and one <a href="http://amzn.to/2eJ8reG">Bundlestar battery</a> as the latter was half the price. The Bundlestar battery feels like it usually last a bit shorter than the original Sony ones, but I haven’t tested this in-depth to see it. The Bundlestar battery works just fine, so if you’re on a budget and need more power take it. The charger I bought is the <a href="http://amzn.to/2emViNX">Charger for Sony NP-BX1 Bundlestar Baxxtar</a> which seems to also be available under different names, usually costing around 16€ or double that with two batteries included. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30497922806/in/dateposted/" title="Accessories"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5528/30497922806_f61b441a91_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Accessories" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bottomline">The Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Sony RX100 IV is not cheap - at almost 1.000€ it is amongst the most expensive pocket cameras you can find and chances are that you don’t need this good a camera. If you’re, however, a passionate photographer &amp; outdoor enthusiast who likes to document his adventures and be able to possibly print large photos of them, then the Sony RX100 IV is worth considering. Also for professional photographers who want to go lighter or need a high-quality back-up camera the RX100 IV is worth a look, as it shots RAW and 4K Video.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748741131/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Bodensee"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8007/29748741131_a681170dde_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodensee" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With this cave-eat out of the way: This is the camera you want to document your adventures. When you’re heading out on a once-in-a-lifetime trip, like hiking a long trail, visit the Annapurna Basecamp or go ski-touring on Svalbard, then you want to have the Sony RX100 IV along to make photos of your adventure. Superb image quality with an impressive 16.0 FPS you can shot face-paced action like skiing, climbing and trailrunning, while the small size allows for shots from the hip for street photography. The EVF lets you operate the camera in the brightest sunlight without problems, and the colours and images this little ultralight camera produces are simply superb and often on-par with much larger &amp; more expensive DSLRs. Did I mention how light and small it is and that I usually carry it in my chest pocket? This is the ultralight backpacking &amp; climbing camera to rule them all. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is the camera you want to document your adventures. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>By the way: On my many trips with athletes which create images and videos for their own Social Media channels, the Sony RX100 IV (or an earlier version) is what they carry. I have friends who ski, climb, mountaineer and trailrun professionally, and like me they carry this wee camera along on their adventures, because they too consider it the best tool to create content for their Social media presences while not carrying too much weight.  </p>

<p>Convinced and want to take a Sony RX100 IV along on your trips? Then buy one via one of these affiliate links: <a href="http://amzn.to/2eYWA1p">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/2eUfshc">Amazon.de</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/2emVv3K">Amazon.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p><em>More photos of the camera and its details on <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157675534458596">Flickr</a>.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148754883/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="What a view!"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/2/1694/26148754883_8441890563_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="What a view!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Sidenote: If you want a relative light weight camera with the absolute best possible image quality I would recommend getting a Full-Frame camera like the <a href="http://amzn.to/2eZqouN">Sony A7RII</a> with a <a href="http://amzn.to/2eZvk2z">great all-round lens</a>. It is just that that combo costs you upwards of 5.400€ and weighs at least 1.511 g, which is more than five times what the RX100 IV puts on the scales. And honestly, unless you’re going to print A1 prints or larger you likely won’t need the power the A7RII has.</em></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>:  <em>There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. You either can avoid them like hell or click them and buy gear via them to support me. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Power of Gear Photos]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/the-power-of-gear-photos.html"/>
    <updated>2016-10-20T23:30:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/the-power-of-gear-photos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What does get you more in the mood to put on your shoes and head outdoors: A photo of a tent in an epic location or a photo of someone staring of into an epic distance?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7807828972/in/album-72157634093995294/" title="Locus Gear Khufu CTF3, Julian Alps, Slovenia"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8300/7807828972_4d0605c010_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Locus Gear Khufu CTF3, Julian Alps, Slovenia" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Things have changed quite a bit in the time I have run this blog: When I started off with outdoor blogging people would usually not show themselves in their articles *¹ - at most a photo of oneself staring off into the distance. Maybe I was naive, young, or both, but back then I didn’t have a problem with showing myself (something that possibly has changed a bit in the last years as I have a family now and am more private). Nowadays, however, Selfies are an accepted form of portraying oneself, nowhere as ubiquitous as on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>. </p>

<p>What is also ubiquitous on Instagram are these “<em>epic</em>” shots where a tiny person stars of into what looks like the wilderness. Here’s one of these: </p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div><p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BHAgSC6vhs9/" style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;" target="_blank">A photo posted by Hendrik Morkel (@hendrikm)</a> on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-06-23T18:58:05+00:00">Jun 23, 2016 at 11:58am PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>
<script async="" defer="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>

<p><br /> Personally I really am not a big fan of them, although I do see their appeal. My main problem is usually that it is always the same places that get these shots, and what is portrayed as epic wilderness or <em>“off-the-beaten-track”</em> are in truth places where you park your car 5 minutes away and then walk on a wide path to the spot. Add in a sunrise, sunset or a headlamp &amp; the Milky Way, do some Photoshop Magic and you have the standard Instagram photo which will attract thousands of likes. Why? Well, because people have seen that image, or a minor variation of it, already hundreds of times, and what is familiar is easy to like.
<br />
<br />But this article isn’t supposed to be on the failings of Instagram photography and my dislike of it, but the power of gear photos. It’s something I have been pondering over the last months, as I occasionally also post the tiny-person-in-big-environment-photo, and while they get a lot of engagement, it are the photos of gear - tents, backpacks, stoves, even a pair of shoes - that get even more engagement. It might be that my <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook Fans</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter Followers</a> are just as big gear nerds as me, or it might be something else. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763145235/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/4/3700/9763145235_51b887b518_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That something else it is what I’d like to ponder about (because we all know that we are gear nerds ;). I think that these, lets call them in contrast to the <em>tiny-person-in-big-environment-photos</em>, great-gear-in-an-epic-environment-photos, are so popular, because a photo of a tent in a beautiful spot, the stove that’s just set up to prepare dinner or the shoes hiking on a trail allow the viewer to put oneself literally in those shoes, behind that stove and in that tent. Sure, one could imagine that that’s you who looks of into the distance high in the mountains, but somewhere inside you know you haven’t been there. But that piece of equipment there - you might own that tent or stove - allows the viewer to put him- or herself there. You can imagine how pretty it would be to lay in that tent and stare into the sunrise in the morning, or sit behind that stove, ready to put the water on so that dinner can be served in a wee bit. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193489569/in/album-72157644166894052/" title="Dinner in the making"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5568/14193489569_090587cee9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dinner in the making" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At least that are my thoughts why these gear photos are more popular than photos of a friend skiing down a fine line, starring up that impressive mountain face or hiking on a cool path. That person shown there, the viewer knows, isn’t her, but in that tent there, that could be where he’d like to go to bed. And with that comes maybe also the idea that it’d be nice to own that pair of shoes, that pack, tent, quilt or stove - because one could use it right there, and have with some luck of the weather fairy, the same great experience than the photographer of that gear photo.</p>

<p><strong>Agree or disagree?</strong> Leave a comment and let us know!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26741129446/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="Sunset skiing"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1719/26741129446_117610d8ae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset skiing" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7728232746/in/album-72157634093995294/" title="Taking in the view"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8289/7728232746_bb9a1e666c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Taking in the view" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703316503/in/album-72157650519579023/" title="Spring snow"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/1/334/18703316503_2ff0aeff59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Spring snow" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376799841/in/album-72157644166894052/" title="Camp"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5592/14376799841_388679cf67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Camp" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17482621798/in/album-72157650519579023/" title="Lunch with a view"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5455/17482621798_55e05af41e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lunch with a view" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634876793/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Happy hiking!"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7674/26634876793_253babe29e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy hiking!" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8701207971/in/album-72157634093995294/" title="Packrafting &amp; Camping"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8257/8701207971_7bdcd68cd4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Packrafting &amp; Camping" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>*¹ An exception to that statement is <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com">Chris Townsend</a> who always has been showing himself in his photos, as far as I can remember.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GoPro HERO4 Session]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/gopro-hero4-session.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T23:27:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/gopro-hero4-session</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Small, rugged, ultralight 71 g, waterproof out of the box, can be controlled with your phone and is pretty affordable - with the HERO4 Session <a href="https://gopro.com">GoPro</a> has created a great little action camera for active outdoor enthusiasts! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29646888770/in/dateposted/" title="GoPro HERO4 Session"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8328/29646888770_5e14d97ac1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GoPro HERO4 Session" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I met GoPro at the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/ispo-2016-news-iii.html">ISPO</a> earlier this year and had a nice chat with them, and when they asked if I’d be interested in testing their HERO4 Session I said yes. While my experience with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/10/gopro-hd-hero2.html">GoPro Hero 2</a> was more like <em>Meh</em> and also the Garmin Virb was something I seldom would take along, I have had the HERO4 Session a lot outdoors in the last months. As a Photographer video is usually just a side-consideration for me, but as I am pondering videos more seriously it is nice to have a small, light and good video camera.</p>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>As usually I put my <a href="http://shop.gopro.com/EMEA/cameras/hero-session/CHDHS-102-master.html">HERO4 Session</a> through a serious testing period to see how it performs in many different situations. The HERO4 Session arrived in February at Hiking in Finland HQ and has been along ski-touring in Norway, hiking, paddling and caving in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/multi-adventures-in-macedonia.html">Macedonia</a>, bouldering and sea kayaking on <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/cycling-and-bouldering-on-aland.html">Åland</a> and climbing, hiking and watching the sun set in Greece, and comes with me when I am going to South Tyrol next month and most likely also to Mexico in November. As the Session 5 was just announced last week I felt it is about time to review this wee camera cube (though GoPro wished I’d done it ages ago =). </p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The GoPro HERO4 Session’s function is summed up pretty easily: Document your adventures, be they skiing in Lyngen, climbing in Greece, hiking in Finland or enjoying the beach with your family. It takes crisp 1080 HD Videos, makes pretty Timelapses and photos from your activities, and lets you easily share them. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M5XH4xSksyo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li>One Button Video Recording - and push it once more to stop recording and turn the camera off</li>
  <li>One Button Timelapse out of the box, easy to adjust via the camera or the GoPro app on your phone</li>
  <li>Wifi and Bluetooth allows you to control the Session via your tablet or smartphone</li>
  <li>Waterproof to 10 m without a housing</li>
  <li>Dozens and dozens of mounts to attach it to almost anything imaginable</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810989151/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="On the way back to Mariehamn from Kobba Klintar"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8695/28810989151_e0db3046b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="On the way back to Mariehamn from Kobba Klintar" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The Session is one of the smallest action cameras on the market. It’s a tiny cube which is why I found it so useful to take along on my trips. The “Press one button and it records” feature is also great, gone the times of where you’re wearing a GoPro and first push it on and then hit the record button, often not sure if it actually is now recording or not. That same button you can push a wee bit longer and it records a Timelapse, and this I found pretty cool as video and timelapse with one push of a button is a great step forward in user friendliness. </p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The camera itself is high-quality and bumps into the rock wall, dropping it into my pack and letting it go dive in the salty Baltic and fresh water lakes didn’t bother it at all. The front lens glass protector has been kept scratch-free during all this time, one just needs to be careful to not touch it with greasy fingers as that can get messy (but easy enough to clean). I believe this camera can survive several years of use and abuse without problems. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634868293/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Exit through the Gift Shop"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/8/7419/26634868293_442d643a1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Exit through the Gift Shop" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Session weighs a mere 71 g. Add in a case (16 g) and a mount like an <a href="http://amzn.to/2dt32sU">adhesive mount</a> (11 g) or the <a href="http://amzn.to/2cZCP9C">Tripod/ Selfie Stick</a> (215 g) and it’s a bit more, but especially with the latter you can take pretty ace photos and videos of yourself in action or fold the legs out and take a time-lapse of the sunset, all for a combined weight of 303 g (That’s the 3-Way Arm, a cage for the camera and the Session itself).</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>You can <a href="http://shop.gopro.com/EMEA/refurbished/">buy refurbished cameras from GoPro</a> directly, which is a cool move and puts less GoPros into the waste streams of the world. Also on their website they have a lengthy website dedicated to <a href="https://gopro.com/casupplychaindisclosure">social and environmental matters</a>, while <a href="https://gopro.com/goproforacause">GoPro Cause</a> lets you get involved or donate with social projects around the world.</p>

<p>How to get rid of an old GoPro, though? If you life in Europe you should be aware of the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/waste/weee/index_en.htm">WEEE Directive</a> which means electronic waste does not belong into your normal household waste. It gives you ideas where you can get rid of your old camera (and other electronic garbage, like that TV, the old Playstation and the broken cellphone from 2003). </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29857913641/in/dateposted/" title="The tiny GoPro HERO4 Session likes the autumn"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5542/29857913641_e98d176270_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The tiny GoPro HERO4 Session likes the autumn" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I have used the HERO4 Session more as I thought I would. Unlike some of my blogger friends (Hey there <a href="http://www.travelingjackie.com">Jackie</a>!) who often only use a GoPro and their smartphone my main tool is a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/photography/">camera</a> as I earn money with my photography. Now while the Session does take photos they’re usually not something a magazine is looking for, hence I carry my <a href="http://amzn.to/2drNeXo">Sony RX 100 IV</a> wherever I go. But the HERO4 Session is so small, light and intuitive that it’s a great addition to a small camera, especially for activities like climbing, skiing and cycling where it’s nice to attach the camera to yourself or your equipment and film your adventure. </p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lI1uuFphJSU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>What I like most about the HERO4 Session - and I might repeat myself here - is that it is so easy to use. Push the button and it records - push again and it’s finished. Push the button 3 seconds and it starts to record a timelapse. Push again and it stops. Accessing the settings is easy on the device as the User Interface is really smartly designed, and you can change the camera angle (from wide to medium), timelapse settings - from 0,5 seconds to 60 seconds - and a bunch more, all via the two buttons on the camera</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29646889400/in/dateposted/" title="GoPro HERO4 Session SD Card and USB Door"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8010/29646889400_4f4f9edb42_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GoPro HERO4 Session SD Card and USB Door" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All you need to start is a <a href="http://amzn.to/2cFiX8B">MicroSDXC Card</a> and you’re ready to head out. The <a href="http://amzn.to/2cZCP9C">GoPro 3-Way Grip &amp; Tripod</a> aka a fancy Selfie Stick with tripod legs that hide away has been something that I was very sceptical of (who wouldn’t be sceptical of Selfie Sticks?) but after using it a couple of times and seeing what great footage one can shot with it I was a convert. Now my Session is usually connected to the 3-Way Grip, as it allows for cool angles on the go, a more stable flow when hiking (though I’d like a gimbal for it) and the Tripod legs make it great for filming a timelapse. </p>

<p>The camera is also really durable - bumps against the rock when climbing didn’t bother it, it dived in and out of salt and fresh water without problems, and also took the daily abuse of being carried in a sidepocket or backpack without problems.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29826592252/in/dateposted/" title="GoPro 3-Way Arm &amp; Tripod + legs"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8212/29826592252_1c7fa02698_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GoPro 3-Way Arm &amp; Tripod + legs" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The battery life depends quite a bit on how you use the camera, the temperature, and also if you have Wi-Fi and Bluetooth turned on or off (off means longer battery life but then you can’t control it with your phone). I had the HERO4 Session along in Macedonia and Greece and got a solid two weeks of use out of the camera, and if my memory doesn’t betray me I only once topped it shortly up in the middle of the trip. I take short clips - anything between 10 seconds and 3 minutes, as well as timelpases. Overall I got some 5 timelapses and around 60 clips shot during those two weeks, almost on a single charge (topped up once!). As the HERO€ Session can be charged via USB it is easy to charge it on the trail with a power bank, too. GoPro themselves also answers the <a href="https://gopro.com/support/articles/hero4-session-battery-life">battery life question</a> in detail.</p>

<p>What I found really great is that you can connect the Session to your smartphone, grab a photo or video, edit it on your phone and share it on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>. Put the camera down and control the Session from your phone - hit record, adjust settings, whatever. It is so easy, you’ll love this feature if you use Social Media and previously just sat on a ton of footage but never did anything with it. There’s even the possibility to <em>find your GoPro</em> in case you’ve lost it under a bunch of papers! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29646890370/in/dateposted/" title="Connected GoPro HERO4 Session"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8338/29646890370_77414e7ea1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Connected GoPro HERO4 Session" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29313588014/in/dateposted/" title="iPhone connected to the GoPro HERO4 Session"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8515/29313588014_baeac60c5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="iPhone connected to the GoPro HERO4 Session" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29646896530/in/dateposted/" title="Viewing the Media on the GoPro HERO4 Session"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8448/29646896530_bb2fbfe0a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the Media on the GoPro HERO4 Session" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Speaking of editing, GoPro has its own <a href="https://shop.gopro.com/EMEA/softwareandapp/">Apps</a> - for free! - which help you make a movie out of that footage. On the phone and desktop you even can let the App do all the work and you just sit back and see what it comes up with! </p>

<p>As for the footage coming out of it, I found it very nice indeed - for online publication. The photos (see the kayaking photo above) are of good quality for blogs and Social Media and probably could be used in a pinch in a magazine. The videos in 1080 HD are crisp with nice colours &amp; good sound, and the file size is wonderfully small in comparison what my other cameras throw out (as I already own four <a href="http://amzn.to/2dm7Z6l">HD External Hard Drives</a> storage is always a concern!). The HERO4 Session is a big step forward from my older action cameras, as adjusting from dark to bright is now quick &amp; good, and it even works great when <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/videos/1193176694045994/">spelunking in dark caves with bats</a>.</p>

<p>Finally, while I got the HERO4 Session for free without obligations you can find the action camera for as little as 200€ (GoPro themselves ask for <a href="http://shop.gopro.com/EMEA/cameras/hero-session/CHDHS-102-master.html">230€ on their webstore</a>). That’s a pretty good price for such a well-designed camera, although there are action cameras out there which cost just half or less of that. If you’d like to support a company which in those cases rips off GoPro is up to you, I wouldn’t. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29314382373/in/dateposted/" title="GoPro HERO4 Session and lots of mounts"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8535/29314382373_91792ceef4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GoPro HERO4 Session and lots of mounts" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>It is hard to pin-point things that I think could be better with the HERO4 Session, but as the HERO5 Session  was just launched I’d say GoPro addressed at least some of my concerns: Better video quality (now with 4K!) and Image stabilization. It now also has 10 Megapixel Photos but remains just as simple &amp; easy to use out of the box as the HERO4 Session I review here. But these were just tiny complaints from my side and I have been more than happy with the HERO4 Session.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29857687411/in/dateposted/" title="GoPro HERO4 Session - On"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8031/29857687411_3ea4033c53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GoPro HERO4 Session - On" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a range of Action Cameras which try to grab some of GoPros market share, most notably Garmin with the VIRB and Sony with its action cameras. Also DJI has tried to enter the market with the <a href="http://amzn.to/2d3fCkD">Osmo</a>, though it serves a slightly different niche. And then there’s the low-cost but still impressive action cameras which cost even less than the Session - I linked to some of these in recent <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">The Week In Reviews</a> so browse them to read about these.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29826592702/in/dateposted/" title="GoPro HERO4 Session Outdoors"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7559/29826592702_395ccb285d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GoPro HERO4 Session Outdoors" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>In the end the question you should ask yourself is: Do I need a one-click action camera? Are you out enough hiking, climbing, skiing, swimming, paddling, mountaineering, surfing &amp; cycling and wishing you had a small video camera along which films you &amp; your adventurous activities? Do you have the time afterwards to edit your footage and share it with your friends (or will you <a href="https://shop.gopro.com/EMEA/softwareandapp/">use the GoPro Quick Desktop or smartphone app</a> to do so)? Are you ready to drop around 300€ on the HERO4 Session, a MicroSDXC Card and some mounts?</p>

<p>If the answer is yes to all of these questions then I think you will find the GoPro Session a great little action camera. While I was sceptical if I’d use the Session at all - after all I hadn’t used the previous two action cameras I own in many years - it quickly has become something I take along on assignments &amp; when I head out for fun. Because it is so easy to use I am way more likely to actually take it out of my pack and push that button - knowing it will record crisp, cool videos of my friends &amp; me doing what we like most - being outside and having fun! Add in that it does so in an almost unobtrusive way, and that viewing, editing and sharing the footage I have recorded has never been easier and you have a winning package that fits in the palm of your hand.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>As the Session 5 will come out in a few weeks the HERO4 Session - the one reviewed here - is available for good discounts already. <a href="http://bit.ly/2d9nrnr">REI</a> has a great package and you also find it at <a href="http://amzn.to/2cDx7aA">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/2d1EmYT">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/2du8aA6">Amazon.de</a> for a good price. </p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29314379553/in/photostream/" title="GoPro HERO4 Session and a variety of mounts"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8004/29314379553_00673a9f8a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GoPro HERO4 Session and a variety of mounts" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The Session was sent for free to me by and GoPro asked me to have fun with it. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Panasonic Lumix DMC-FZ1000 Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/panasonic-dmc-fz1000-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2015-11-11T23:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/panasonic-dmc-fz1000-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Would you like a camera that goes from wide angle to super zoom up-close with just one lens for your outdoor adventures? Then look no further than the DMC-FZ1000, Panasonic’s Super Zoom with a super-sweet Leica 25 - 400 mm lens! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22925198412/in/dateposted/" title="Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 Top Shot"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5643/22925198412_4cfd6c8c07_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 Top Shot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Panasonic suggested I try their new <a href="http://www.panasonic.com/fi/consumer/video-ja-digitaalikamerat/lumix-digitaalikamera-point-shoot/dmc-fz1000ep.html">Lumix DMC-FZ1000</a> Super Zoom camera and see how I liked it for my trips. I was a bit sceptical at first - it’s a big camera for me, lenses can’t be switched and I wasn’t sure if I need a 400 mm long lens. But always curious to try something new, I agreed to take the camera out for a few trips - that was in autumn 2014! It’s been a longer than usual loan, which probably gives you already an idea that I do like to use this camera. And not just I like it, a couple of photographer friends comment that the Leica lens on this camera makes pretty sweet photos with nice colours and contrasts. But from the start.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22925195532/in/dateposted/" title="Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 On"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/637/22925195532_315575d3e5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 On" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html">Sony RX 100 III</a>, first a look at my (updated) requirements for a camera:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Print-quality photographs</li>
  <li>High Burst mode and fast Autofocus</li>
  <li>Nightshots possible</li>
  <li>HD Video capable</li>
  <li>Tiltscreen</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
</ul>

<p>The DMC-FZ1000 weighs with lens shade (23 g), battery (51 g) and SD Card (7 g) 854 g total. Add in your strap of choice and a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO plate</a> and this will be around 900 g for the camera et al. That’s more heavy than other cameras I use, but still lighter than a modern Full-Frame DSLR which often weighs around 1,5 kg with a standard kit lens. Add in a 400 mm lens and you might look at complete weight of over 2,5 kg or more - nearly three times the weight of the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000. Overall I didn’t find the weight a big deal, though it’s bigger than my usual cameras which during transport sometimes is a bit more of a hassle. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22912631486/in/dateposted/" title="All it needs: Battery, SD Card and Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/666/22912631486_06bbd19c63_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="All it needs: Battery, SD Card and Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22520314228/in/photostream/" title="Good layout on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/739/22520314228_1e1c6a2fed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Good layout on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22317481133/in/photostream/" title="Great handling of the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5744/22317481133_581d536d8f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Great handling of the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The handling however is very nice. The shutter button sits comfortably at the front on the protruding hand grip, where also the zoom lever is. The camera zooms fast and the focus is quick. Something I really like is the silent shutter, the camera can take photos completely without noise, which is great if you photograph in nature or do street photography. For a full-on look at the technical details I as usually send you to my colleagues of <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/panasonic-lumix-dmc-fz1000">DP Review</a>, who gave the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 their Gold Award and loved their 1-inch sensor which <em>produces excellent image quality</em>. Besides the 1 inch sensor I would blame that great image quality also on the superb Leica F2.8-4 lens. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22520264407/in/dateposted/" title="Big lens on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/745/22520264407_8e7acfe721_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Big lens on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22546485669/in/dateposted/" title="Lovely Leica glass on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/671/22546485669_b360b30872_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lovely Leica glass on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The results of the lens + sensor + creative photographer means you get stunning images in print-quality. Over the year that I have used the FZ1000 the photos I shot with it have appeared in half a dozen or more magazines. The camera shoots in RAW with the files ending up between 18 and 23 MB in size after converting them to DNG. The battery life is also pretty good, I usually get three to four days of use out of the battery, or around 600+ photos. That high number is likely due to the fact that I rarely review photos on the go or watch photos from the screen.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22939018535/in/dateposted/" title="Photos taken with the DMC-FZ1000 that have made it into magazines"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5657/22939018535_51439dbaab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Photos taken with the DMC-FZ1000 that have made it into magazines" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22925199962/in/dateposted/" title="Swivel screen on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/655/22925199962_3c247d62a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swivel screen on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Speaking of the screen, it’s a swivel screen that turns 180° to the front as well as up &amp; down which makes it great for filming yourself, shooting low on the ground or above your head. If you use the screen (which isn’t a touchscreen) or the high resolution XGA electronic viewfinder you have the possibility to let a <em>“water-level”</em> be displayed which shows you if your frame is aligned evenly to the horizon. I found this at the beginning a bit annoying, but as I often take photos on the go I started to like this feature quite a bit and found it very useful. Unless I was shooting from above my head or low on the ground I was by the way using the EVF which I found very comfortable. It has a large eye-piece which blocks out the outside light fairly well, and the small screen is high in contrast and is also easy to check or review a frame from. </p>

<p>Around the big lens there’s a very nice focus/ zoom ring which is easy to use if you’re into manual zooming/ focussing. I myself prefer the lever and using the cursors to set focus points and let the camera get it, but if you want to be more hands-on I can see how this might be useful. The lens also has an Imaging Stabilizator which can be switched on and off and comes in handy if you’re shooting at 400 mm handheld. </p>

<p>A feature which I really like is the Timelapse function. For some of my work it is important to be myself in the photo, and as I didn’t want to buy a remote for the FZ1000 and didn’t want (or could, as I was shooting myself packrafting) run to the camera for the self timer the Timelapse function is a great feature. You can set in-camera the amount of photos the camera should take as well as the time between shots - say take 200 photos, each 5 seconds apart. The FZ1000 then either assembles the images in-camera into a timelapse movie and saving you a work step on the computer, or you can just let it save the photos separately. Either way, it’s a great feature that I find very useful - both for photography and making Timelapse movies.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14840716884/in/album-72157645805765757/" title="Canada Geese"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3894/14840716884_77c021bded_b.jpg" width="1024" height="646" alt="Canada Geese" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So lets look at some of my other requirements and see how the DMC-FZ1000 performs there:</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21836572460/in/album-72157645805765757/" title="Aurora Borealis"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/656/21836572460_c48aab5ce1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Aurora Borealis" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Nightshots possible ✓</p>

<p>Once you figured out the settings it is surprisingly easy to take beautiful photos of the stars and aurora borealis, as the above photo shows. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15877047812/in/album-72157647589227685/" title="Christoph trying Godspeed, 7c, Dyno"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7478/15877047812_70a9fb2bc2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Christoph trying Godspeed, 7c, Dyno" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>High Burst mode and fast Autofocus ✓</p>

<p>The FZ1000 can shoot 12 frames per second (fps) which is great for sports photography. The Autofocus is snappy and fast which means you end up with more usable shoots to pick your frame from. </p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zugVQS52VPA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>HD Video capable ✓</p>

<p>Press the red button on the top of the camera and you start filming, or switch the dial to the Manual Movie mode to have some more control over the settings. The output in HD is crisp and beautiful with superb Stereo sound, and you can take photos while filming without interrupting the movie. The FZ1000 can record 4k Video at 100Mbps so if you’re dealing in high-quality video this camera is ready for it. If you want an <a href="http://amzn.to/1MA5xqg">external Microphone</a> - you’re in luck, that also can be attached to the Hotshoe and has a jack on the left side. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15909703263/in/album-72157645805765757/" title="Winter Bliss"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8641/15909703263_1634276c02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Winter Bliss" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So what are the short-comings for an outdoor photographer with the DMC-FZ1000? Well, it is chunky. Chunky and big like a DSLR, although that allows for a good handling. I also would have wished that it would have had a constant maximum aperture, and maybe that it would have had a Bulb function and be compatible with my <a href="http://amzn.to/1WMuDZE">Pixel Wireless Shutter Remote</a>. The list is pretty short, because the FZ1000 has a lot of good sides. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15692018457/in/album-72157647589227685/" title="Sunset"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/15692018457_b91eed1fa6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bottomline">The Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 has a lot speaking for it: Great images out of the camera, 4k Video, an awesome Timelapse function, the superb Leica 25 - 400 mm lens with f2.8 to 4 and a very intuitive and easy handling. Yes, it is a bit more heavy and bulky in comparison to other system cameras, but if you want a large focal length spectrum without carrying a couple of lenses then the FZ1000 quickly is lighter than a system with comparable lenses. The Autofocus is very fast &amp; reliable which is great if you photography sports or kids. Did I already mention the beautiful photos it makes? Well, it does make very good photos with vivid colours which can be printed in large sizes. If you want a camera quiver of one and don’t want to deal with carrying more lenses for different lengths, the Lumix DMC-FZ1000 is worth a look. </p>

<p>View more photos taken with the Panasonic Lumix DMC-FZ1000 in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157645805765757">DMC-FZ1000</a> or <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157653077170250">Kronplatz Album</a> on Flickr.</p>

<p>You can <strong>support Hiking in Finland and buy the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 at</strong> <a href="http://bit.ly/1HygubE">pictureline</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1MnyjXu">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1NqOxPB">Amazon.de</a> or get it from your <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/panasonic-lumix-dmc-fz1000-musta.html">local photography shop</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15632190602/in/album-72157646843881095/" title="Kezban Camping, Main House"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3936/15632190602_3760215cbf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kezban Camping, Main House" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Thanks to <a href="http://www.panasonic.com/fi/">Panasonic Finland</a> for loaning me the DMC-FZ1000 for this Field Report.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear of the Year 2015: Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html"/>
    <updated>2015-10-19T23:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is reasonably light, connects to any of my backpacks and is the #1 tool I have along on every trip? It’s the Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip - my Gear of the Year 2015.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22265356552/in/photostream/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/740/22265356552_51b9767b0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I own a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> since over two years and it has been on every trip I have been on in that time, from day packrafting in the Kvarken Archipelago over mountaineering in Chamonix to backpacking in Bosnia and Herzegovina - the Capture PRO has seen it all. When I pack my backpack for a trip, attaching the camera clip to my left shoulder strap is always the first thing I do, and it does not matter if that’s a big <a href="http://bit.ly/1W1xPjI">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Porter</a> or a small <a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/packs/packsack-plus/">LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack Plus</a>, the clip fits on any shoulder strap and allows me to have my camera always at the ready. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22089327210/in/photostream/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/733/22089327210_8b0d8808d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/capturepro/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Capture PRO</a> Clip weighs 113 g and the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/microplate?acc=97">Micro Plate</a> weighs 21 g and is a perfect match for any of my smaller cameras, from the compact &amp; ultralight <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html">Sony RX 100 III</a> to the slightly bigger Olympus OM-D E-M5. For even bigger cameras I use the standard ARCAplate Quick Release Plate which tips the scales at a reasonable 29 g and which works great with e.g. the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Sony A7R</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963271736/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2847/11963271736_fa16b81885_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the trail, in the city and at trade fairs like the OutDoor and ISPO alike my Capture PRO always arouses the interest of fellow outdoor enthusiasts who look for a better way to carry their camera. After two plus years of use &amp; dozens of long trips for me it is clear: It’s the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/capturepro/?acc=97">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a>. Because being able to have my camera in my hand in a second or two to not miss a photo opportunity is very important - it can be the difference between a good photo and an outstanding photo. If you’re a photography professional or a hobby enthusiast - give this system a try, there is no better way to carry your camera always at the ready. And that’s why I chose the Capture PRO Camera Clip from Peak Design to be my Gear of the Year 2015!</p>

<p><strong>Get 10% off your Peak Design Order!</strong> I partnered with Peak Design and am happy to offer you 10% off their products. Simply enter the <strong>Coupon Code “hikingfin”</strong> at checkout and you get ten percent off your order!</p>

<p><em>For more thoughts and information on it, please read my detailed <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Capture PRO Camera Clip Review</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
