<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: photography | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-21T23:13:48+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony A7R Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T06:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A 407 g Full Frame camera? Yes please. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15457679781" title="Sony A7R without lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3935/15457679781_9874095671_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R without lens" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Earlier in the year I had the pleasure of test-driving the latest creation from <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/kamerat">Sony</a>, their <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/jarjestelmakamerat/ilce-7r">A7R camera</a>. I’ve been a user of Sony cameras since over three years and while my Sony NEX-5n is still a trusty companion on many trips, I’m in the market for a new camera. So having being able to use the A7R in what I usually do was a superb opportunity that I wasn’t going to pass up, even if our love affair only was to last for several weeks and I knew saying good bye to it would hurt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460816735" title="Sony A7R and Sony NEX-5n by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15460816735_9cda8d1df7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R and Sony NEX-5n" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re looking for pixel-peeping and very detailed technical information, I’d like to send you to <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-alpha-a7r/">DP Review</a> who do a rather spectacular job with that sorts of things. If you’re an outdoor photographer, journalist or writer who wants to know how the A7R performs in the outdoors, I invite you to stay for a while and read my thoughts on this camera. I will delve first a (little) bit into the technical details and how the camera handles, and then discuss in detail how the camera works in the field.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274063999" title="Sony A7R - Back view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3934/15274063999_ae9d765df2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R - Back view" /></a></p>

<p>First off: At a suggested retail price of 2300€ for the body only and a good lens setting you back another 800€, the A7R is in my opinion a camera for people who earn a living with photos. Sure, if you have the spare change to buy a 3000€ camera you could get it, but chances are you either way don’t know how to use its full potential. And a lot of potential she has, the A7R.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15458998652" title="Sony A7R - Having a good grip on it by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15458998652_82cf23ce8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Having a good grip on it" /></a></p>

<p>The camera lays beautiful in the hand and it is easy to operate the different controls and functions with one hand. The sealed alloy and composite body is weatherproof and allows for a good, reassuring grip, even with gloves on. The 3-inch tilting LCD turns up and down and makes shooting e.g. Macros easier, although the XGA electronic viewfinder is where it’s at. The viewfinder eyepiece is large and comfortable, and far enough away so that you also can use it with (sun) glasses on. I have been sceptical of viewfinders in the past as (good) LCD screens are more than adequate in composing photos, but as my photographic needs evolve I come back to viewfinders and find them increasingly a necessity for my kind of shooting.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272647760" title="Sony A7R - View on top with thumb on the trigger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5601/15272647760_fddc5ae121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - View on top with thumb on the trigger" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272582069" title="Sony A7R - Thumb access to different buttons on the back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15272582069_311a4c0d93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Thumb access to different buttons on the back" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re a control freak you will love the possibilities the A7R offers: Three customizable buttons and four dials (front, rear, exposure compensation &amp; an additional rear dial around the four-way controller), and several buttons for accessing different settings (Menu, Trash, Playback, etc.). If you shot Manual the front and rear dials allow you to adjust shutter speed and aperture, while the directional controller lets you set the drive mode, white balance mode and what’s displayed on the screen. The shutter button sits above the On/ Off switch which I found comfortable in use - I could switch the camera on with my index finger and then have my thumb immediately on the shutter. The camera did need a moment to start up, something that might be better nowadays with an updated Firmware.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272723658" title="Sony A7R - Back view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3934/15272723658_9fc99380d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Back view" /></a></p>

<p>On the right side of the body you see in the above photo the dedicated movie recording button (red), which for my liking was a bit far in the back. The A7R has Full HD video recording capabilities which makes it a mighty fine video camera to produce super-sharp HD videos.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/QUHHBay1x14?list=UU927vE_KkPy6pFJboaJ9Lig" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>On the left side you have four ports behind two plastic doors: Micro, Headphones, Multi (allows you to charge the battery) and micro-HDMI. On the top there’s a Hotshoe which accepts an external flash or <a href="http://amzn.to/1yJHYWK">Microphone</a>. The A7R uses the NP-FW50 Lithium battery like the NEX-5n, which was very useful for me as I so could use my charger and spare batteries on tour. The default charging method is via the USB port which I think is a hassle, so I recommend getting the external charger or the battery grip.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274058359" title="Sony A7R - Side I/O ports with the Rode Video Pro on top &amp; connected by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3936/15274058359_b578a549e7_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Sony A7R - Side I/O ports with the Rode Video Pro on top &amp; connected" /></a></p>

<p>The A7R has an E-Mount like my NEX camera which means I can use E-Mount lenses - though they will crop the photo it’s useful if you already have a NEX camera - and with an <a href="http://amzn.to/1pMVoI0">adapter</a> also allows you to use Canon, Nikon, Pentax and other lenses. This could make it interesting for people who are switching from Nikon or Canon but want to keep to use their glass. With an adapter you’re also able to use other Sony A-mount lenses. To really get the most out this full frame sensor you’ll want to invest into a (few) Sony FE-series lenses. I used the <a href="http://amzn.to/1xl9bKL">35mm F2.8 Carl Zeiss</a> and found it a superb lens, though for outdoor photography I would have found a faster 16 mm or 20 mm lens even more useful.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460475032" title="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15460475032_be1fa0e188_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens" /></a></p>

<p>With 36 megapixels and a max resolution of 7360 x 4912 it are photos where the A7R really shines, so lets have a look how the camera handles in the field.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274057619" title="Sont A7R - Composing a photo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15274057619_9d2c7a6105_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sont A7R - Composing a photo" /></a></p>

<p>Together with the Carl Zeiss 35mm F2.8 lens (120 g) the A7R weighs 585 g (including battery, which is 58 g). With this lens it is a compact package that fits into large jacket pockets and comfortably under the jacket in bad weather. It’s also light enough to not bother you when wearing around your neck, though I would update the strap to one from <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/slide?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design</a> for more functionality. </p>

<p>The first time I used the camera was at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a>, which was a good test for it. Lots of white in different shades, colourful clothing, early dusks, northern lights. It performed well, and would have been outstanding if I would have had the functions dialled in better. With gloves on the camera was easy to use, but things like smaller buttons where more difficult to control. That meant either setting White Balance, ISO, Aperture et al. before hand or take the gloves off to fine adjust settings.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445682176" title="Sony A7R - Roadtrippin&#x27; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15445682176_9e35c9589d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Roadtrippin&#x27;" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15282159468" title="Sony A7R - Ice climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15282159468_f9a430f0c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Ice climbing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465648641" title="Sony A7R - Aurora Borealis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15465648641_46952da3d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p>In warm daylight the camera was a pleasure to use and produced almost perfect images without needing much post processing. Colours were bright and true to colour, and given that this can be a very hard environment for good photos, with all the snow and ice, I was very happy with the output. The LCD screen is great to review photos on the fly and it’s fast to delete bad shots, but also works well to compose a photo if you can not/ don’t want to use the Viewfinder. The Viewfinder is great in use, and helped in the bright and snowy environment of Northern Sweden to compose a few good shots.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15281893779" title="Sony A7R - All Smiles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15281893779_8c91a81b2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - All Smiles" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465644681" title="Sony A7R - Getting schooled by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15465644681_f1772308e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Getting schooled" /></a></p>

<p>The Magnesium Alloy Body didn’t get very cold, and bumps against the ice and rock didn’t bother it. Something that did bother me was the shutter sound, which I didn’t manage to silence. I like stealth photography and even if large landscapes aren’t scared away by the sound, animals are, and also during street photography it’s something that can give you away. The shutter also seemed to be slow, taking a good moment to make its <em>“Clack”</em> sound to take a picture. While I got used to it, it’s something I’d very much would like to be seen improved. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445745166" title="Sony A7R - Snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15445745166_75ff8416ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Snow" /></a></p>

<p>One of the big benefits of the A7R is obviously that it is a full frame. The detail you get from the camera is pretty amazing and  allows you to reduce the resolution in post or crop aggressively. The example of this lonely reed against a late March afternoon sky is a good example:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465621521" title="Sony A7R - Reed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5597/15465621521_cd0f005fa2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Reed" /></a></p>

<p>And now the crop of the above photo:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468757625" title="Sony A7R - Reed Crop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3932/15468757625_5293bd9a0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Sony A7R - Reed Crop" /></a></p>

<p>The amount of sharp detail you get is wonderful and gives you a lot more creative options when working with this camera. You can include a lot more of the subject’s environment and still capture plenty of detail which is highly useful if you decide to crop the photo later, which is great if you are in a hurry to capture a unique moment but can’t compose the image perfectly.</p>

<p>The A7R also has a good Auto Focus/ Facial Recognition, even if the subject isn’t 100% to be identified. Take this <em>“Portrait”</em> I shot of myself for a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/trekking-magazin/">trekking Magazin</a> article as an example:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445671636" title="Sony A7R - &quot;Portrait&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5598/15445671636_c449958015_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - &quot;Portrait&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>This photo has not been touched in post, but with a few easy adjustments was perfect for my article. However, I really loved how good the camera put the focus on me (and I wasn’t standing behind the Viewfinder, obviously =) and blurred out the background. The colours again are rich and lush out of the camera and details like the Ripstop pattern on the windjacket are clearly to be seen.</p>

<p>Night and low-light shooting is something that you really need to put an effort in to get it right, but with a good camera and a good lens things get easier. I think one could get some really nice illuminated-shelters-in-the-hills with the A7R + 35 mm lens, sadly I didn’t have time for such a test so this twilight shot from town needs to do. With focus peaking on it’s easy to get the stuff sharp that matter, and it’s something I highly recommend always using - also in daylight shots.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468453232" title="Sony A7R - Twilight by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15468453232_b2c0eedd0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Twilight" /></a>
ƒ/2.8, 2 seconds, ISO 800</p>

<p>The pine has a lot of detail and the stars that you can see are nice and crisp. I edited it lightly in <a href="http://amzn.to/1vL8VDP">Lightroom</a> to bring out some details and added a bit of clarity, but even in camera on the screen it looked already good. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468786525" title="Sony A7R - Waterdrops by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15468786525_8408833471_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Waterdrops" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15284760469" title="Sony A7R - Scarpa Rebel Ultra Gtx in the snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3941/15284760469_052c55e581_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Scarpa Rebel Ultra Gtx in the snow" /></a></p>

<p>Taking product shots is something I do quite a bit for the blog and the magazines, and also here the A7R performed very satisfying. On the top you see clearly that the focus is on the water drops on the pants, and in these you can see how they reflect their surroundings - the kitchen windows, in this case. Underneath we again have a difficult case: Patterned orange and snow. A combination which gives some of my other cameras a headache, but the A7R produced a perfect image.</p>

<p>Also indoors the A7R did very well, and I snapped some nice shots at the Art Museum here in Vaasa at an exhibition earlier in winter. Again colours and sharpness are outstanding and as the full frame sensor records so much detail it would have been easy to crop this composition if needed (but it wasn’t, I was quite happy with this shot).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468829345" title="Sony A7R - Art Museum by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2950/15468829345_b99c8ecb23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Art Museum" /></a></p>

<p>In conclusion I can say that my experiences with the Sony A7R were nothing but superb. Sure, it took a second longer to start up as I’d like, it took a moment between shots to be ready again, the shutter was a bit loud, there’s still just a fairly limited selection of FE lenses out, and yes, it’s pricey. But the plusses outweigh these small complaints for me. The biggest advantage is that with the 35 mm lens you have a Full Frame camera which is less than 600 g. In comparison: The Canon EOS 5D Mk III is 950 g for the body only, and the Nikon D800 still puts 900 g for the body only around your neck. </p>

<p>Then there’s the weatherproof body that withstood at least light impacts on ice and rock and had no problems operating in light minus temperatures this winter. The layout of the dials and buttons needs some getting used to, but once you have internalized the layout you’ll be able to use the camera with your eye to the viewfinder.  I loved that it had a regular sized Microphone port, and if I ever get a phone with NFC I’m happy to know that I can just touch it against the A7R and have the two linked, being able to send photos from the camera to the phone very easily. </p>

<p>A large plus is also that thanks to various adapters you’re able to use a massive variety of 35 mm lenses with no field-of-view crop, and if you’re already a Sony NEX camera user you will be able to use your E-Mount lenses on the A7R (with field-of-view crop, though). What’s nice about the 35 mm lens possibility is obviously that many of these lenses can be bought cheaply, and as I have used a few old lenses on my NEX-5n I know how wonderful it is to use a manual lens. Sony is set to release some more FE lenses in 2015, and also Zeiss just announced at the photokina a very nice pair of manual Full-Frame lenses for the A7R and its siblings. </p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline:</strong> The Sony A7R is a lightweight, compact camera that produces outstanding photos and video. If you’re an (outdoor) photographer, journalist or writer who needs high-quality photos with lots of details and the ability to crop the A7R will appeal as it’s such a portable camera and won’t weigh you down when you’re hiking and climbing far off the beaten track.</p>

<p>I recommend you go visit your local camera shop to have a look at the camera and the lenses. If you’re in Finland, <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/sony-ilce-7r-runko.html">Rajala</a> has the A7R right now on offer for 1600€ for the body only. </p>

<p>You can see <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157643203488075/">more photos of the Sony A7R and photos taken with it on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460817595" title="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15460817595_676a7bca38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-15T12:45:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The Best Camera is the Camera that you have close at hand</em> goes a smart saying amongst photographers, and the <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/capturepro?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> helps you to have your camera so close at hand, that you never will lose a shot again. No more fumbling around with zipper and Velcro closures which are noisy and scare away wild life - a silent tab of a button and your camera is in you hand.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963271736/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2847/11963271736_fa16b81885_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In the pre <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/capturepro?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> era I used the ZPacks Multipack for several years to carry my cameras close to where I needed them. It still is a great way to carry your camera, but it lacks speed and convenience in accessing the camera when on the trail, and if you carry more gear in it getting the camera out can get fiddly. Enter the <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/capturepro?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Capture PRO</a>: A clip attached to your shoulder strap or belt and a Quick Release Plate that you screw onto your camera. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963261976/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2876/11963261976_45cbca4c78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>The clip is super easy to attach to your shoulder strap, and fits straps up to 7,6 cm wide. You simply open one or both bolts and slide the clip open, slide the shoulder strap between it, close the clip and screw the bolts tight - done! A matter of less than sixty seconds, as you can see here.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963271106/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5472/11963271106_33892e24dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11962734993/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2860/11962734993_45073ccb48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>Then just shoulder your pack and go out for a hike! Once there’s a <em>Photo Moment™</em> press the red button to release the Quick Release Plate with your camera on it, switch the camera on and you are ready to shoot:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11962884664/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5498/11962884664_67aff0fd51_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963272806/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5508/11963272806_ec04c64ecb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963267396/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3667/11963267396_55aa8139e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>The Capture PRO weighs 142 g, the weight is divided as follows: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Clip 113 g</li>
  <li>ARCAplate Quick Release Plate 29 g</li>
</ul>

<p>At the beginning I thought it’s pretty heavy - that’s almost three Snickers - but in use it really didn’t bother me. I also was concerned that it might be in the way when going through dense shrubbery as on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho Kekkonen trip</a> or that the clip might bother me when moving, but neither has been a problem in use. The camera rides nicely high up on my shoulder straps and even when I bushwack it’s safe &amp; sound next to me, while the round design of the plate has meant there where no pressure points when moving. </p>

<p>The Capture PRO also allows you to lock the Quick Release Plate when connected to the clip via the black knob on top, and the red quick-release button has a safety lock - it can be twisted to prevent theft and accidental drops. If you also carry a tripod outdoors and are concerned that you might need to mess around with screwing baseplates on and off: No worries! The Capture PRO can be either screwed atop your tripod and be used as a quick-release clamp (you might want to get two Clips in that case, one for the tripod, one for your shoulder strap) or, even simpler, cheaper and better: The PROplates Quick Release Plate work with most ARCA-type tripods, while the DUALplate also works with Manfrotto RC2 tripods. Sweet!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963272466/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5526/11963272466_dc38754136_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>The plates come in three different sizes, once the standard ARCAplate as pictured in my photos here, then there’s the already mentioned Manfrotto RC2 tripod-compatible DUALplate and for the M43 and Point’n’Shoot crowd there’s the MICROplate. And with the brand-new <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/pov-kit/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">POV Kit</a> you also can wear your <a href="http://bit.ly/1b2P7An">GoPro</a> or a point-and-shoot on the clip and make POV videos. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11962872414/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5500/11962872414_0475d0d15d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>As you see, the Capture PRO is a versatile and very useful accessory for photographers who go out backpacking, skiing and climbing. It allows you to have your camera always close by so you never miss a <em>Photo Moment™</em>. Many successful photographers use it, from <a href="http://www.alexandrebuisse.org/">Alexandre Buisse</a> and <a href="http://terorepo.com/">Tero Repo</a> to backpackers like <a href="http://briangreen.net/2013/07/hands-on-with-capture-camera-clip-v2.html">Brian</a> and <a href="http://sticksblog.com/">Chad</a>. I have used mine for almost half a year now, and can’t imagine going on a hike without it. The convenience of having the camera with the push of a button in my hand has meant less missed photos and made taking photos more intuitive: Its a difference to push one bottom and have the camera in hand or open a zipper/ Velcro closure. </p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>You can buy the Capture PRO directly at <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design</a> or at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/peak-design-capture-camera-clipv2-kamerahalfter-plus-arcaplate/">Bergzeit</a> in Europe. If you choose the former, I’m happy to offer you the Coupon Code <strong>“hikeinfin”</strong> which gets you 10% off your order! Get together with a friend and order two, and worldwide shipping is even free!</p>

<p>More photos of the Capture PRO on <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157639796017274/">Flickr</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11962873554/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5533/11962873554_eddda4f03c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TrailPix Ultralight Tripod]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T12:42:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you enjoy taking photos when hiking? Do you carry a pair of trekking poles? Then you want a <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">TrailPix</a> to create a truly Ultralight Tripod!</p>

<p><a href="hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html" title="TrailPix Custom"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7373/10290298325_d976bd2c90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Multi-functionalism is one of the ideas of ultralight backpacking. Gear you carry should have more than one function. Trekking poles are superb multifunction items - besides walking aides they can be used to pitch your shelter, be transformed into a paddle for packrafting, can be used as a tenkara rod, and with the TrailPix they make your trekking poles a superb tripod!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290300815/" title="TrailPix Custom w/ ball head"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3736/10290300815_3e6db8a058_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom w/ ball head" /></a></p>

<p>I first got aware of TrailPix last year when <a href="http://briangreen.net/">Brian Green</a> posted about the original design on his blog. I liked the idea a lot, though didn’t find the design too refined. Apparently I wasn’t alone, as the Kickstarter project didn’t reach its goal. In the end, this was positive for us, because Andy - the inventor of TrailPix - didn’t give up and started to refine the TrailPix during the last nine months, and the result is a truly superb tool to transform your trekking poles into a tripod.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8752858727/" title="Trail Pix Early Prototype from nv8design.com"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/8752858727_f88d56390e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Trail Pix from nv8design.com" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290190004/" title="TrailPix Custom vs an earlier Prototype"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3796/10290190004_969dcbfb71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom vs an earlier Prototype" /></a></p>

<p>I have been testing one of the earlier Prototypes (see above), which I liked a lot. But the final design, the one you can get if you <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">back Andy’s Kickstarter project</a> is even better. There are two versions available, the Universal and the Custom. I have a Custom version, made for the tips of my <a href="http://www.rutalocura.com/trekking_poles.html">Ruta Locura Yana poles</a>. These poles have Black Diamond Flex Tech Tips which also are used on my <a href="http://gossamergear.com/trekking/trekking/lt4-trekking-poles-all.html">Gossamer Gear LT4 poles</a>. They also do fit well on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cRcjH7">MSR Surelock poles</a> and OK-ish on my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekkingstoecke/">Black Diamond Z-Poles</a>. However, they have the tightest and hence most secure fit with the Ruta Locura Poles, which the TrailPix Custom was made for.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290300105/" title="TrailPix Custom and suitable trekking poles for it"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3784/10290300105_18d701d7fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom and suitable trekking poles for it" /></a></p>

<p>The Custom version (27 gram) has the option of an accessory pole which is the third leg, and at 70 g the accessory pole is not too heavy. It’s custom made for your trekking poles, and you can let Andy know which size you need when you’re ordering it. The Universal version on the other hand fits a wide variety of poles, so if you hike with a friend you could loan one of his poles, or use a tent pole to make your tripod. The Custom version is excellent if you have one pair of poles and usually hike solo, the Universal version is for you if you have many different trekking poles and want your TrailPix to fit each pair.</p>

<p>In use on the trail TrailPix is quickly deployed. I keep the accessory pole and TrailPix with the Ballhead in a side pocket, so I can quickly grab them when I need a tripod. I turn the trekking poles around, put the poles in the holes, unfold the accessory pole and insert it, and <em>Voilá</em> - there’s your tripod. Now you just add your camera, switch it on and you can start taking photos. It’s very fast and you don’t need to take off your backpack, either!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290196014/" title="TrailPix Custom &amp; Panasonic GH2"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3717/10290196014_1f1f0985d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom &amp; Panasonic GH2" /></a></p>

<p>Andy has made it really easy to chose the version you need, and offers a host of useful extras. I highly recommend getting a ball head (49 gram) additionally to the TrailPix (unless you already have one) and the accessory pole (70 gram) if you go for the Custom Version. If you’re a <a href="http://www.peakdesignltd.com/">Peak Designs</a> Capture user, you can even get a ARCA-style quick release base from him and make them compatible! So, if you want one, <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">back Andy’s Kickstarter project</a> now - it closes on Friday morning. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290418393/" title="TrailPix Custom Set"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3747/10290418393_cc175766b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157636580175493/">Some more photos</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Velbon V-Pod - Worlds Lightest Tripod]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T15:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For years the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/04/joby-gorillapod-slr.html">Joby GorillaPod</a> has been my “tripod” of choice. And while I certainly still use it and often have it along on trips, in above tree line environments or when a real tripod would be more convienent than a GorillaPod, I needed something that’s still light enough to carry but can get high enough for photos, timelapses and video. Enter the Velbon V-Pod, probably the Worlds Lightest Tripod.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8570950041/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8374/8570950041_bf2f8aa725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I first read about the Velbon V-Pod a few year’s ago on Dave’s, the <a href="http://www.armchair-adventurer.com/">Armchair Adventurer</a>, blog. But it still has taken me an unreasonably long time to purchase a V-Pod, which I now, with hindsight, regret. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8572168042/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8091/8572168042_0c9f8fe4c1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>My Velbon V-Pod weighs 279 gram, has a transport length of 29 cm, is fully extended 100 cm tall and has a minimum height of 28 cm. It carries my <a href="http://amzn.to/ZXzy8j">Sony NEX-5r</a> with a <em>heavy</em> Pentax Asahi 55mm lens (body + lens = 570 g) without problems, though if you go outdoors with a Canon 7D or similar you might want to use something more substantial as a tripod. But for the M43 crowd and Point-and-Shoot photographers, the Velbon V-Pod is a superb tool. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8572072576/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8383/8572072576_14246b0ebd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>I used it since for shooting <a href="https://vimeo.com/60198868">timelapse movies</a>, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">aurora borealis and stars</a>, videos and stills. It is small enough to go inside the backpack or put it under a strap or a mesh pocket on the outside, and is ready to use in less than 30 seconds. It has a ball head which allows for great fluid movements and picking almost any position you’d like. If it is windy you can attach a weight (your backpack) to the centre strut of the V-Pod to pull it down and keep it in place.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8570973041/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8247/8570973041_b7a3a01d23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>It comes with a carrying pouch (12 g) and a holder for smartphones (25 g). Especially the latter is pretty neat (unless you have a <a href="http://amzn.to/10cFigF">Glif</a>) as it allows you to use your smartphone for videos, stop-and-go animations and photos. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8571075403/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8098/8571075403_e11c051320_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>In short: I’m sorry that I waited so long to buy the Velbon V-Pod. It’s a superb tool for photographers who use lightweight cameras, and nowadays the V-Pod finds its way into my pack on pretty much each trip, long or short. If you’re searching for a lightweight tripod for your Micro Four Thirds or similar camera, look no further. The Velbon V-Pod is the answer for us lightweight backpackers &amp; photographers.</p>

<p><strong>Get a Velbon V-Pod</strong> at <a href="http://amzn.to/XdRZGO">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/145x1P0">Amazon.de</a> (they’re not available at Amazon.com, sorry). <em>If you buy via these Affiliate Links, I earn a few cents. Don’t worry, it doesn’t cost you anything extra =)</em></p>

<p><em><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633031907155/">More photos of the Velbon V-Pod</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2nd HIF Photo Contest Winners]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/11/2nd-hif-photo-contest-winners.html"/>
    <updated>2012-11-08T21:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/11/2nd-hif-photo-contest-winners</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have winners! Many thanks again for the numerous submissions, it yet again was hard to choose the winners and honourable mentions - you are truely a very talented readership! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8149921876/" title="Sunpillar by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8326/8149921876_a89106822e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunpillar" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="winners">Winners</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/18839278@N00/8090625988/" title="Poll Doo Glen by flanagandave, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8184/8090625988_40a7c5b2f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Poll Doo Glen" /></a></p>

<p>David takes the crown this time around. A very fine photo, a big, blazing fire and a beautiful sky and background. After a day of bouldering the three friends sit around the fire, while the starry sky is circling above them. While there is a lot of movement in the photo, I find this is part of the charm of it. All in all a very fine photo that interprets the topic of fire well, and adds a scent of adventure, friendship and nature to it. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/familyjonesnow/6137831658/" title="Forgewood Camping by The real Jonesnow, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6062/6137831658_2ba0bc2b13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Forgewood Camping" /></a></p>

<p>Gareth submitted a very beautiful and touching image of his son taking in the fire. You can imagien how the little boy enjoys the warmth of the fire after a cold &amp; wet day, and just stars relaxed into the Wilderness TV channel. A beautiful, very emotional image that communicates warmth and security.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/walloftvs/7539459798/" title="Campfire, Mirror Lake, Spanish Peaks, Madison Range, Montana by samhDOTnet, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8292/7539459798_72411a9056_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Campfire, Mirror Lake, Spanish Peaks, Madison Range, Montana" /></a></p>

<p>Sam’s fianceé contemplates life at a campfire in the Madison Range. <em>Magnificent scenery</em> was my first thought. 
I like how the fire and person are just subtle parts of this photo, the mountains, snow and tree tops grab a lot of attention, and I can imagine how a fire in such a setting is like a beacon of warmth and “civilization”.</p>

<p><em>All three of you, please contact me <a href="hendrik.morkel@gmai.com">via email</a>. Each of you wins an awesome Light-My-Fire Swedish FireKnife!</em></p>

<h2 id="honourable-mentions">Honourable Mentions</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/kermiitintarinat/8138113705/" title="IMG_7719 by Askemux, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8336/8138113705_7529272200_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="IMG_7719" /></a></p>

<p>Kermiitti’s dog, who’s sleeping peacefully by the fire. An emotional and peaceful photo.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/88697876@N02/8092393902/" title="Fire by christophersussman, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8326/8092393902_9cbdd58f30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<p>Christopher and his wife thru-hiked the PCT this year, and this was the fire they made on the 2nd last day on the trail. A fine way to celebrate a great achievement!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/61712293@N03/7289352196/" title="Aufwärmen am Feuer"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7100/7289352196_8e4d99a0f2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Aufwärmen am Feuer" /></a></p>

<p>Beni and Anatol warming up by the fire on a trip in the Alps earlier this year. Contemplating, warming up, while in the background you can see hints of the scenery.</p>

<hr />

<p>Again, a big THANK YOU to all participants. It was a great pleasure to go through all the different, creative and beautiful photos &amp; stories which were entered, and it was a tough job to pick the three I liked the most. Later this month the 3rd round of this photography contest will come around, so keep your cameras ready!</p>

<p><em>All rights to the shown photos are with their respective owners. Thank you for allowing me to showcase them.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
