<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: photography | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-07T18:58:49+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-15T12:45:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The Best Camera is the Camera that you have close at hand</em> goes a smart saying amongst photographers, and the <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/capturepro?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> helps you to have your camera so close at hand, that you never will lose a shot again. No more fumbling around with zipper and Velcro closures which are noisy and scare away wild life - a silent tab of a button and your camera is in you hand.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963271736/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2847/11963271736_fa16b81885_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In the pre <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/capturepro?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> era I used the ZPacks Multipack for several years to carry my cameras close to where I needed them. It still is a great way to carry your camera, but it lacks speed and convenience in accessing the camera when on the trail, and if you carry more gear in it getting the camera out can get fiddly. Enter the <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/capturepro?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Capture PRO</a>: A clip attached to your shoulder strap or belt and a Quick Release Plate that you screw onto your camera. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963261976/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2876/11963261976_45cbca4c78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>The clip is super easy to attach to your shoulder strap, and fits straps up to 7,6 cm wide. You simply open one or both bolts and slide the clip open, slide the shoulder strap between it, close the clip and screw the bolts tight - done! A matter of less than sixty seconds, as you can see here.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963271106/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5472/11963271106_33892e24dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11962734993/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2860/11962734993_45073ccb48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>Then just shoulder your pack and go out for a hike! Once there’s a <em>Photo Moment™</em> press the red button to release the Quick Release Plate with your camera on it, switch the camera on and you are ready to shoot:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11962884664/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5498/11962884664_67aff0fd51_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963272806/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5508/11963272806_ec04c64ecb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963267396/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3667/11963267396_55aa8139e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>The Capture PRO weighs 142 g, the weight is divided as follows: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Clip 113 g</li>
  <li>ARCAplate Quick Release Plate 29 g</li>
</ul>

<p>At the beginning I thought it’s pretty heavy - that’s almost three Snickers - but in use it really didn’t bother me. I also was concerned that it might be in the way when going through dense shrubbery as on my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho Kekkonen trip</a> or that the clip might bother me when moving, but neither has been a problem in use. The camera rides nicely high up on my shoulder straps and even when I bushwack it’s safe &amp; sound next to me, while the round design of the plate has meant there where no pressure points when moving. </p>

<p>The Capture PRO also allows you to lock the Quick Release Plate when connected to the clip via the black knob on top, and the red quick-release button has a safety lock - it can be twisted to prevent theft and accidental drops. If you also carry a tripod outdoors and are concerned that you might need to mess around with screwing baseplates on and off: No worries! The Capture PRO can be either screwed atop your tripod and be used as a quick-release clamp (you might want to get two Clips in that case, one for the tripod, one for your shoulder strap) or, even simpler, cheaper and better: The PROplates Quick Release Plate work with most ARCA-type tripods, while the DUALplate also works with Manfrotto RC2 tripods. Sweet!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963272466/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5526/11963272466_dc38754136_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>The plates come in three different sizes, once the standard ARCAplate as pictured in my photos here, then there’s the already mentioned Manfrotto RC2 tripod-compatible DUALplate and for the M43 and Point’n’Shoot crowd there’s the MICROplate. And with the brand-new <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/pov-kit/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">POV Kit</a> you also can wear your <a href="http://bit.ly/1b2P7An">GoPro</a> or a point-and-shoot on the clip and make POV videos. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11962872414/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5500/11962872414_0475d0d15d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>

<p>As you see, the Capture PRO is a versatile and very useful accessory for photographers who go out backpacking, skiing and climbing. It allows you to have your camera always close by so you never miss a <em>Photo Moment™</em>. Many successful photographers use it, from <a href="http://www.alexandrebuisse.org/">Alexandre Buisse</a> and <a href="http://terorepo.com/">Tero Repo</a> to backpackers like <a href="http://briangreen.net/2013/07/hands-on-with-capture-camera-clip-v2.html">Brian</a> and <a href="http://sticksblog.com/">Chad</a>. I have used mine for almost half a year now, and can’t imagine going on a hike without it. The convenience of having the camera with the push of a button in my hand has meant less missed photos and made taking photos more intuitive: Its a difference to push one bottom and have the camera in hand or open a zipper/ Velcro closure. </p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>You can buy the Capture PRO directly at <a href="https://peakdesignltd.com/store/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design</a> or at <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/peak-design-capture-camera-clipv2-kamerahalfter-plus-arcaplate/">Bergzeit</a> in Europe. If you choose the former, I’m happy to offer you the Coupon Code <strong>“hikeinfin”</strong> which gets you 10% off your order! Get together with a friend and order two, and worldwide shipping is even free!</p>

<p>More photos of the Capture PRO on <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157639796017274/">Flickr</a>. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11962873554/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5533/11962873554_eddda4f03c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TrailPix Ultralight Tripod]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T12:42:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you enjoy taking photos when hiking? Do you carry a pair of trekking poles? Then you want a <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">TrailPix</a> to create a truly Ultralight Tripod!</p>

<p><a href="hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/trailpix-ultralight-tripod.html" title="TrailPix Custom"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7373/10290298325_d976bd2c90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Multi-functionalism is one of the ideas of ultralight backpacking. Gear you carry should have more than one function. Trekking poles are superb multifunction items - besides walking aides they can be used to pitch your shelter, be transformed into a paddle for packrafting, can be used as a tenkara rod, and with the TrailPix they make your trekking poles a superb tripod!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290300815/" title="TrailPix Custom w/ ball head"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3736/10290300815_3e6db8a058_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom w/ ball head" /></a></p>

<p>I first got aware of TrailPix last year when <a href="http://briangreen.net/">Brian Green</a> posted about the original design on his blog. I liked the idea a lot, though didn’t find the design too refined. Apparently I wasn’t alone, as the Kickstarter project didn’t reach its goal. In the end, this was positive for us, because Andy - the inventor of TrailPix - didn’t give up and started to refine the TrailPix during the last nine months, and the result is a truly superb tool to transform your trekking poles into a tripod.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8752858727/" title="Trail Pix Early Prototype from nv8design.com"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/8752858727_f88d56390e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Trail Pix from nv8design.com" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290190004/" title="TrailPix Custom vs an earlier Prototype"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3796/10290190004_969dcbfb71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom vs an earlier Prototype" /></a></p>

<p>I have been testing one of the earlier Prototypes (see above), which I liked a lot. But the final design, the one you can get if you <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">back Andy’s Kickstarter project</a> is even better. There are two versions available, the Universal and the Custom. I have a Custom version, made for the tips of my <a href="http://www.rutalocura.com/trekking_poles.html">Ruta Locura Yana poles</a>. These poles have Black Diamond Flex Tech Tips which also are used on my <a href="http://gossamergear.com/trekking/trekking/lt4-trekking-poles-all.html">Gossamer Gear LT4 poles</a>. They also do fit well on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cRcjH7">MSR Surelock poles</a> and OK-ish on my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekkingstoecke/">Black Diamond Z-Poles</a>. However, they have the tightest and hence most secure fit with the Ruta Locura Poles, which the TrailPix Custom was made for.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290300105/" title="TrailPix Custom and suitable trekking poles for it"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3784/10290300105_18d701d7fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom and suitable trekking poles for it" /></a></p>

<p>The Custom version (27 gram) has the option of an accessory pole which is the third leg, and at 70 g the accessory pole is not too heavy. It’s custom made for your trekking poles, and you can let Andy know which size you need when you’re ordering it. The Universal version on the other hand fits a wide variety of poles, so if you hike with a friend you could loan one of his poles, or use a tent pole to make your tripod. The Custom version is excellent if you have one pair of poles and usually hike solo, the Universal version is for you if you have many different trekking poles and want your TrailPix to fit each pair.</p>

<p>In use on the trail TrailPix is quickly deployed. I keep the accessory pole and TrailPix with the Ballhead in a side pocket, so I can quickly grab them when I need a tripod. I turn the trekking poles around, put the poles in the holes, unfold the accessory pole and insert it, and <em>Voilá</em> - there’s your tripod. Now you just add your camera, switch it on and you can start taking photos. It’s very fast and you don’t need to take off your backpack, either!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290196014/" title="TrailPix Custom &amp; Panasonic GH2"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3717/10290196014_1f1f0985d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom &amp; Panasonic GH2" /></a></p>

<p>Andy has made it really easy to chose the version you need, and offers a host of useful extras. I highly recommend getting a ball head (49 gram) additionally to the TrailPix (unless you already have one) and the accessory pole (70 gram) if you go for the Custom Version. If you’re a <a href="http://www.peakdesignltd.com/">Peak Designs</a> Capture user, you can even get a ARCA-style quick release base from him and make them compatible! So, if you want one, <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">back Andy’s Kickstarter project</a> now - it closes on Friday morning. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10290418393/" title="TrailPix Custom Set"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3747/10290418393_cc175766b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="TrailPix Custom" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157636580175493/">Some more photos</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Velbon V-Pod - Worlds Lightest Tripod]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T15:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2013/03/velbon-v-pod</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For years the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/04/joby-gorillapod-slr.html">Joby GorillaPod</a> has been my “tripod” of choice. And while I certainly still use it and often have it along on trips, in above tree line environments or when a real tripod would be more convienent than a GorillaPod, I needed something that’s still light enough to carry but can get high enough for photos, timelapses and video. Enter the Velbon V-Pod, probably the Worlds Lightest Tripod.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8570950041/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8374/8570950041_bf2f8aa725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I first read about the Velbon V-Pod a few year’s ago on Dave’s, the <a href="http://www.armchair-adventurer.com/">Armchair Adventurer</a>, blog. But it still has taken me an unreasonably long time to purchase a V-Pod, which I now, with hindsight, regret. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8572168042/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8091/8572168042_0c9f8fe4c1_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>My Velbon V-Pod weighs 279 gram, has a transport length of 29 cm, is fully extended 100 cm tall and has a minimum height of 28 cm. It carries my <a href="http://amzn.to/ZXzy8j">Sony NEX-5r</a> with a <em>heavy</em> Pentax Asahi 55mm lens (body + lens = 570 g) without problems, though if you go outdoors with a Canon 7D or similar you might want to use something more substantial as a tripod. But for the M43 crowd and Point-and-Shoot photographers, the Velbon V-Pod is a superb tool. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8572072576/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8383/8572072576_14246b0ebd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>I used it since for shooting <a href="https://vimeo.com/60198868">timelapse movies</a>, <a href="http://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">aurora borealis and stars</a>, videos and stills. It is small enough to go inside the backpack or put it under a strap or a mesh pocket on the outside, and is ready to use in less than 30 seconds. It has a ball head which allows for great fluid movements and picking almost any position you’d like. If it is windy you can attach a weight (your backpack) to the centre strut of the V-Pod to pull it down and keep it in place.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8570973041/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8247/8570973041_b7a3a01d23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>It comes with a carrying pouch (12 g) and a holder for smartphones (25 g). Especially the latter is pretty neat (unless you have a <a href="http://amzn.to/10cFigF">Glif</a>) as it allows you to use your smartphone for videos, stop-and-go animations and photos. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8571075403/" title="Velbon V-Pod by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8098/8571075403_e11c051320_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Velbon V-Pod" /></a></p>

<p>In short: I’m sorry that I waited so long to buy the Velbon V-Pod. It’s a superb tool for photographers who use lightweight cameras, and nowadays the V-Pod finds its way into my pack on pretty much each trip, long or short. If you’re searching for a lightweight tripod for your Micro Four Thirds or similar camera, look no further. The Velbon V-Pod is the answer for us lightweight backpackers &amp; photographers.</p>

<p><strong>Get a Velbon V-Pod</strong> at <a href="http://amzn.to/XdRZGO">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="http://amzn.to/145x1P0">Amazon.de</a> (they’re not available at Amazon.com, sorry). <em>If you buy via these Affiliate Links, I earn a few cents. Don’t worry, it doesn’t cost you anything extra =)</em></p>

<p><em><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633031907155/">More photos of the Velbon V-Pod</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2nd HIF Photo Contest Winners]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/11/2nd-hif-photo-contest-winners.html"/>
    <updated>2012-11-08T21:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/11/2nd-hif-photo-contest-winners</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have winners! Many thanks again for the numerous submissions, it yet again was hard to choose the winners and honourable mentions - you are truely a very talented readership! </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8149921876/" title="Sunpillar by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8326/8149921876_a89106822e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunpillar" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="winners">Winners</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/18839278@N00/8090625988/" title="Poll Doo Glen by flanagandave, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8184/8090625988_40a7c5b2f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Poll Doo Glen" /></a></p>

<p>David takes the crown this time around. A very fine photo, a big, blazing fire and a beautiful sky and background. After a day of bouldering the three friends sit around the fire, while the starry sky is circling above them. While there is a lot of movement in the photo, I find this is part of the charm of it. All in all a very fine photo that interprets the topic of fire well, and adds a scent of adventure, friendship and nature to it. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/familyjonesnow/6137831658/" title="Forgewood Camping by The real Jonesnow, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6062/6137831658_2ba0bc2b13_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Forgewood Camping" /></a></p>

<p>Gareth submitted a very beautiful and touching image of his son taking in the fire. You can imagien how the little boy enjoys the warmth of the fire after a cold &amp; wet day, and just stars relaxed into the Wilderness TV channel. A beautiful, very emotional image that communicates warmth and security.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/walloftvs/7539459798/" title="Campfire, Mirror Lake, Spanish Peaks, Madison Range, Montana by samhDOTnet, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8292/7539459798_72411a9056_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Campfire, Mirror Lake, Spanish Peaks, Madison Range, Montana" /></a></p>

<p>Sam’s fianceé contemplates life at a campfire in the Madison Range. <em>Magnificent scenery</em> was my first thought. 
I like how the fire and person are just subtle parts of this photo, the mountains, snow and tree tops grab a lot of attention, and I can imagine how a fire in such a setting is like a beacon of warmth and “civilization”.</p>

<p><em>All three of you, please contact me <a href="hendrik.morkel@gmai.com">via email</a>. Each of you wins an awesome Light-My-Fire Swedish FireKnife!</em></p>

<h2 id="honourable-mentions">Honourable Mentions</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/kermiitintarinat/8138113705/" title="IMG_7719 by Askemux, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8336/8138113705_7529272200_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="IMG_7719" /></a></p>

<p>Kermiitti’s dog, who’s sleeping peacefully by the fire. An emotional and peaceful photo.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/88697876@N02/8092393902/" title="Fire by christophersussman, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8326/8092393902_9cbdd58f30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<p>Christopher and his wife thru-hiked the PCT this year, and this was the fire they made on the 2nd last day on the trail. A fine way to celebrate a great achievement!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/61712293@N03/7289352196/" title="Aufwärmen am Feuer"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7100/7289352196_8e4d99a0f2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Aufwärmen am Feuer" /></a></p>

<p>Beni and Anatol warming up by the fire on a trip in the Alps earlier this year. Contemplating, warming up, while in the background you can see hints of the scenery.</p>

<hr />

<p>Again, a big THANK YOU to all participants. It was a great pleasure to go through all the different, creative and beautiful photos &amp; stories which were entered, and it was a tough job to pick the three I liked the most. Later this month the 3rd round of this photography contest will come around, so keep your cameras ready!</p>

<p><em>All rights to the shown photos are with their respective owners. Thank you for allowing me to showcase them.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GoPro HERO3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/10/gopro-hero3.html"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T14:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2012/10/gopro-hero3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new GoPro, again? Yes! The GoPro HERO3 was just announced this morning, and the underneath video, shot entirely with the third re-incarnation of the best action camera available looks like it just again jumped ahead in front of the competition. Hit play, get psyched and then read more!</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/A3PDXmYoF5U" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’ve had my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/10/gopro-hd-hero2.html">HERO2</a> since last year, and it has been out on a lot of trips where it has seen some <a href="https://vimeo.com/43411086">great action</a>. The GoPro is a very special kind of camera, and shines best in my opinion if you do action sports - packrafting, climbing, paragliding, bikepacking &amp; mountain biking, and to a limited extent also backpacking. If you plan to use your GoPro solely for backpacking videos and photos there might be <a href="http://amzn.to/RsjOGr">better cameras</a> out there for that, which take probably better photos - on the other hand <a href="http://www.barefootjake.com/">Barefoot Jake</a> for example only uses a GoPro for his photos, thus it is possible and certainly a compact and light option to document your trips.</p>

<p>But in my opinion the HERO3 (and HERO2 for that matter) shines for these kind of adventures where you want to give the viewer an exciting point-of-view of the action you’re doing, and with a small camera that you can mount on your helmet, bike, packraft, chest or pole that’s certainly going to be easier than with a small camera. A <a href="http://amzn.to/TurPcZ">Point-and-Shoot</a> might work, but attaching these to a helmet, bike or packraft is more complicated, plus the lack the waterproof housing. Thus, if you want to film your outdoor adventures, a POV camera like the GoPro or a <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=85857&amp;pw=73183">Contour+2</a> are the way to go - if you have a need for it!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8096507889/" title="GoPro HERO3 Black Edition by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8466/8096507889_a232820b5a_b.jpg" width="683" height="426" alt="GoPro HERO3 Black Edition" /></a></p>

<p>Which brings us to the GoPro HERO3: Black Edition, which has a very long list of great improvements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It got 30% smaller and 25% lighter (the camera now weighs only 74 gram!)</li>
  <li>Built-in Wi-Fi</li>
  <li>A new waterproof housing which you can take up to 60 meters deep with an updated flat-lens that will deliver sharp videos above and under water</li>
  <li>Includes the Wi-Fi Remote</li>
  <li>Compatible with the <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gopro-app/id561350520?mt=8">GoPro iPhone App</a></li>
  <li>Can shot 12 Megapixel photos at a rate of 30 frames per second</li>
  <li>A new Continuous Photo mode</li>
  <li>Plenty of even higher quality video formats</li>
  <li>A better audio system</li>
  <li>Two times better low light performance!</li>
  <li>User-selectable Ultra-wide, Medium and Narrow field-of-views</li>
</ul>

<p>Being smaller &amp; lighter with better video and photo capabilities and built-in Wi-fi are the top points here, followed by better low light performance. It is compatible with the old batteries (BacPacs) as well as LCD Touch BacPac, so that’s great news for those who already own these accessories, and it also keeps the <a href="https://vimeo.com/32251546">timelapse mode</a>, which is very nice. Being able to select the field-of-view will mean hopefully more videos which are shot in a “Fisheye” ultra-wide mode, which is something many can’t stand watching (at least for very long); you can take this off in post-processing but being able to shot in a more normal field-of-view is a welcome option. </p>

<p>Taking a peek at the competition and the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=85857&amp;pw=73183">Contour+2</a>, I think the HERO3 still is ahead. While they share now some of the same features - Wi-Fi and smartphone apps, for example - the HERO3 is having a few more options - dead simple time-lapse, for example. The Contour+2 on the other hand could be better if you use your action camera on you helmet a lot, as you can attach it to the side more easily than a HERO3. The Contour+2 also offers GPS tagging, but is double as heavy as a HERO3. Finacially, they’re both the same price, so at least there none has an advantage!</p>

<p><em>So should you get one</em>? The answer is if you go (a lot) packrafting, bikepacking, skiing, climbing or maybe even canyoning, diving, surfing and paragliding <strong>YES</strong>! If you usually just hike and bike in the city then you’re likely not using the full potential of this camera and are better of just loaning one from a friend if you need one. While I am lusting over the HERO3 I am not certain that it would see any more action than my HERO2, so I’ll stick with what I have for the time being.</p>

<p>You can preorder the Premium GoPro HERO3: Black Edition for $399.99 at <a href="http://www.kqzyfj.com/on118zw41w3JPPLNKRTJLKRMQLKM" target="_top" onmouseover="window.status='http://gopro.com';return true;" onmouseout="window.status=' ';return true;">GoPro.com</a><img src="http://www.ftjcfx.com/k9122r6Az42OUUQSPWYOQPWRVQPR" width="1" height="1" border="0" />, it is shipping in the middle of November. Also available are a White Edition for $199.99 and a Silver Edition for $299.99 which have slightly less impressive video capabilities, but are, like the Black Edition, smaller &amp; lighter with built-in Wi-Fi so an improvement over the older GoPros. <em>Finally, if you get HERO3 - make sure to use mix things up and shot with more than one POV!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
