<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: photography | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-17T23:22:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Panasonic Lumix DMC-FZ1000 Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/panasonic-dmc-fz1000-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2015-11-11T23:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/11/panasonic-dmc-fz1000-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Would you like a camera that goes from wide angle to super zoom up-close with just one lens for your outdoor adventures? Then look no further than the DMC-FZ1000, Panasonic’s Super Zoom with a super-sweet Leica 25 - 400 mm lens! </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22925198412/in/dateposted/" title="Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 Top Shot"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5643/22925198412_4cfd6c8c07_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 Top Shot" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Panasonic suggested I try their new <a href="http://www.panasonic.com/fi/consumer/video-ja-digitaalikamerat/lumix-digitaalikamera-point-shoot/dmc-fz1000ep.html">Lumix DMC-FZ1000</a> Super Zoom camera and see how I liked it for my trips. I was a bit sceptical at first - it’s a big camera for me, lenses can’t be switched and I wasn’t sure if I need a 400 mm long lens. But always curious to try something new, I agreed to take the camera out for a few trips - that was in autumn 2014! It’s been a longer than usual loan, which probably gives you already an idea that I do like to use this camera. And not just I like it, a couple of photographer friends comment that the Leica lens on this camera makes pretty sweet photos with nice colours and contrasts. But from the start.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22925195532/in/dateposted/" title="Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 On"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/637/22925195532_315575d3e5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 On" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html">Sony RX 100 III</a>, first a look at my (updated) requirements for a camera:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Print-quality photographs</li>
  <li>High Burst mode and fast Autofocus</li>
  <li>Nightshots possible</li>
  <li>HD Video capable</li>
  <li>Tiltscreen</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
</ul>

<p>The DMC-FZ1000 weighs with lens shade (23 g), battery (51 g) and SD Card (7 g) 854 g total. Add in your strap of choice and a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO plate</a> and this will be around 900 g for the camera et al. That’s more heavy than other cameras I use, but still lighter than a modern Full-Frame DSLR which often weighs around 1,5 kg with a standard kit lens. Add in a 400 mm lens and you might look at complete weight of over 2,5 kg or more - nearly three times the weight of the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000. Overall I didn’t find the weight a big deal, though it’s bigger than my usual cameras which during transport sometimes is a bit more of a hassle. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22912631486/in/dateposted/" title="All it needs: Battery, SD Card and Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/666/22912631486_06bbd19c63_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="All it needs: Battery, SD Card and Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22520314228/in/photostream/" title="Good layout on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/739/22520314228_1e1c6a2fed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Good layout on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22317481133/in/photostream/" title="Great handling of the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5744/22317481133_581d536d8f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Great handling of the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The handling however is very nice. The shutter button sits comfortably at the front on the protruding hand grip, where also the zoom lever is. The camera zooms fast and the focus is quick. Something I really like is the silent shutter, the camera can take photos completely without noise, which is great if you photograph in nature or do street photography. For a full-on look at the technical details I as usually send you to my colleagues of <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/panasonic-lumix-dmc-fz1000">DP Review</a>, who gave the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 their Gold Award and loved their 1-inch sensor which <em>produces excellent image quality</em>. Besides the 1 inch sensor I would blame that great image quality also on the superb Leica F2.8-4 lens. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22520264407/in/dateposted/" title="Big lens on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/745/22520264407_8e7acfe721_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Big lens on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22546485669/in/dateposted/" title="Lovely Leica glass on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/671/22546485669_b360b30872_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lovely Leica glass on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The results of the lens + sensor + creative photographer means you get stunning images in print-quality. Over the year that I have used the FZ1000 the photos I shot with it have appeared in half a dozen or more magazines. The camera shoots in RAW with the files ending up between 18 and 23 MB in size after converting them to DNG. The battery life is also pretty good, I usually get three to four days of use out of the battery, or around 600+ photos. That high number is likely due to the fact that I rarely review photos on the go or watch photos from the screen.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22939018535/in/dateposted/" title="Photos taken with the DMC-FZ1000 that have made it into magazines"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5657/22939018535_51439dbaab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Photos taken with the DMC-FZ1000 that have made it into magazines" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22925199962/in/dateposted/" title="Swivel screen on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/655/22925199962_3c247d62a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swivel screen on the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Speaking of the screen, it’s a swivel screen that turns 180° to the front as well as up &amp; down which makes it great for filming yourself, shooting low on the ground or above your head. If you use the screen (which isn’t a touchscreen) or the high resolution XGA electronic viewfinder you have the possibility to let a <em>“water-level”</em> be displayed which shows you if your frame is aligned evenly to the horizon. I found this at the beginning a bit annoying, but as I often take photos on the go I started to like this feature quite a bit and found it very useful. Unless I was shooting from above my head or low on the ground I was by the way using the EVF which I found very comfortable. It has a large eye-piece which blocks out the outside light fairly well, and the small screen is high in contrast and is also easy to check or review a frame from. </p>

<p>Around the big lens there’s a very nice focus/ zoom ring which is easy to use if you’re into manual zooming/ focussing. I myself prefer the lever and using the cursors to set focus points and let the camera get it, but if you want to be more hands-on I can see how this might be useful. The lens also has an Imaging Stabilizator which can be switched on and off and comes in handy if you’re shooting at 400 mm handheld. </p>

<p>A feature which I really like is the Timelapse function. For some of my work it is important to be myself in the photo, and as I didn’t want to buy a remote for the FZ1000 and didn’t want (or could, as I was shooting myself packrafting) run to the camera for the self timer the Timelapse function is a great feature. You can set in-camera the amount of photos the camera should take as well as the time between shots - say take 200 photos, each 5 seconds apart. The FZ1000 then either assembles the images in-camera into a timelapse movie and saving you a work step on the computer, or you can just let it save the photos separately. Either way, it’s a great feature that I find very useful - both for photography and making Timelapse movies.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14840716884/in/album-72157645805765757/" title="Canada Geese"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3894/14840716884_77c021bded_b.jpg" width="1024" height="646" alt="Canada Geese" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So lets look at some of my other requirements and see how the DMC-FZ1000 performs there:</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21836572460/in/album-72157645805765757/" title="Aurora Borealis"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/656/21836572460_c48aab5ce1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Aurora Borealis" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Nightshots possible ✓</p>

<p>Once you figured out the settings it is surprisingly easy to take beautiful photos of the stars and aurora borealis, as the above photo shows. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15877047812/in/album-72157647589227685/" title="Christoph trying Godspeed, 7c, Dyno"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7478/15877047812_70a9fb2bc2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Christoph trying Godspeed, 7c, Dyno" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>High Burst mode and fast Autofocus ✓</p>

<p>The FZ1000 can shoot 12 frames per second (fps) which is great for sports photography. The Autofocus is snappy and fast which means you end up with more usable shoots to pick your frame from. </p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zugVQS52VPA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>HD Video capable ✓</p>

<p>Press the red button on the top of the camera and you start filming, or switch the dial to the Manual Movie mode to have some more control over the settings. The output in HD is crisp and beautiful with superb Stereo sound, and you can take photos while filming without interrupting the movie. The FZ1000 can record 4k Video at 100Mbps so if you’re dealing in high-quality video this camera is ready for it. If you want an <a href="http://amzn.to/1MA5xqg">external Microphone</a> - you’re in luck, that also can be attached to the Hotshoe and has a jack on the left side. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15909703263/in/album-72157645805765757/" title="Winter Bliss"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8641/15909703263_1634276c02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Winter Bliss" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So what are the short-comings for an outdoor photographer with the DMC-FZ1000? Well, it is chunky. Chunky and big like a DSLR, although that allows for a good handling. I also would have wished that it would have had a constant maximum aperture, and maybe that it would have had a Bulb function and be compatible with my <a href="http://amzn.to/1WMuDZE">Pixel Wireless Shutter Remote</a>. The list is pretty short, because the FZ1000 has a lot of good sides. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15692018457/in/album-72157647589227685/" title="Sunset"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/15692018457_b91eed1fa6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bottomline">The Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 has a lot speaking for it: Great images out of the camera, 4k Video, an awesome Timelapse function, the superb Leica 25 - 400 mm lens with f2.8 to 4 and a very intuitive and easy handling. Yes, it is a bit more heavy and bulky in comparison to other system cameras, but if you want a large focal length spectrum without carrying a couple of lenses then the FZ1000 quickly is lighter than a system with comparable lenses. The Autofocus is very fast &amp; reliable which is great if you photography sports or kids. Did I already mention the beautiful photos it makes? Well, it does make very good photos with vivid colours which can be printed in large sizes. If you want a camera quiver of one and don’t want to deal with carrying more lenses for different lengths, the Lumix DMC-FZ1000 is worth a look. </p>

<p>View more photos taken with the Panasonic Lumix DMC-FZ1000 in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157645805765757">DMC-FZ1000</a> or <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157653077170250">Kronplatz Album</a> on Flickr.</p>

<p>You can <strong>support Hiking in Finland and buy the Panasonic DMC-FZ1000 at</strong> <a href="http://bit.ly/1HygubE">pictureline</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1MnyjXu">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1NqOxPB">Amazon.de</a> or get it from your <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/panasonic-lumix-dmc-fz1000-musta.html">local photography shop</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15632190602/in/album-72157646843881095/" title="Kezban Camping, Main House"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3936/15632190602_3760215cbf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kezban Camping, Main House" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Thanks to <a href="http://www.panasonic.com/fi/">Panasonic Finland</a> for loaning me the DMC-FZ1000 for this Field Report.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear of the Year 2015: Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html"/>
    <updated>2015-10-19T23:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is reasonably light, connects to any of my backpacks and is the #1 tool I have along on every trip? It’s the Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip - my Gear of the Year 2015.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22265356552/in/photostream/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/740/22265356552_51b9767b0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I own a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> since over two years and it has been on every trip I have been on in that time, from day packrafting in the Kvarken Archipelago over mountaineering in Chamonix to backpacking in Bosnia and Herzegovina - the Capture PRO has seen it all. When I pack my backpack for a trip, attaching the camera clip to my left shoulder strap is always the first thing I do, and it does not matter if that’s a big <a href="http://bit.ly/1W1xPjI">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Porter</a> or a small <a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/products/packs/packsack-plus/">LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack Plus</a>, the clip fits on any shoulder strap and allows me to have my camera always at the ready. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22089327210/in/photostream/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/733/22089327210_8b0d8808d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/capturepro/?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Capture PRO</a> Clip weighs 113 g and the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/microplate?acc=97">Micro Plate</a> weighs 21 g and is a perfect match for any of my smaller cameras, from the compact &amp; ultralight <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html">Sony RX 100 III</a> to the slightly bigger Olympus OM-D E-M5. For even bigger cameras I use the standard ARCAplate Quick Release Plate which tips the scales at a reasonable 29 g and which works great with e.g. the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Sony A7R</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/11963271736/" title="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2847/11963271736_fa16b81885_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the trail, in the city and at trade fairs like the OutDoor and ISPO alike my Capture PRO always arouses the interest of fellow outdoor enthusiasts who look for a better way to carry their camera. After two plus years of use &amp; dozens of long trips for me it is clear: It’s the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/clips/capturepro/?acc=97">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a>. Because being able to have my camera in my hand in a second or two to not miss a photo opportunity is very important - it can be the difference between a good photo and an outstanding photo. If you’re a photography professional or a hobby enthusiast - give this system a try, there is no better way to carry your camera always at the ready. And that’s why I chose the Capture PRO Camera Clip from Peak Design to be my Gear of the Year 2015!</p>

<p><strong>Get 10% off your Peak Design Order!</strong> I partnered with Peak Design and am happy to offer you 10% off their products. Simply enter the <strong>Coupon Code “hikingfin”</strong> at checkout and you get ten percent off your order!</p>

<p><em>For more thoughts and information on it, please read my detailed <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Capture PRO Camera Clip Review</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Wide Open]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Wide Open</em> has the byline <em>New Outdoor and Landscape Photography</em>. If it is really new and if you should get a copy, you read in my review.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968932345/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/319/19968932345_8fc222df65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gestalten-verlag/">Gestalten Verlag</a>. They make cool coffee table books with great photos and texts, so when <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">The Great Wide Open</a> appeared on my radar I was eager to check it out. An email and a few days later the heavy book slammed on my porch, ready to be browsed. </p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19780862558/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3665/19780862558_72b216d413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>However, opening the book the euphoria quickly ended. Sure, there are very fine images in there, but just as much of them look like they’re shot on an iPhone for Instagram and not for a large coffee table book. It feels like every other photo is a grainy mess that looked great on your Instagram feed when seen on a smartphone but shouldn’t have been printed in such a large format. Speaking of Instagram, if you’re on it and follow some landscape photographers then you’ll have seen the vast majority of these images in one form or another already. Another disappointment was that you could clearly see in many images that they have been taken not far away from a road or civilization - given that the Prologue of the book refers to <a href="http://amzn.to/1SFXAis">Ansel Adams</a> and how he would set off on long expeditions to capture expansive, wild landscapes that feels a bit wrong. Oh, and if you don’t like Chris Burkard - don’t get the book. Half the images are from him, and while they’re technically very good I personally find them a bit boring. On ther other hand, if you love him - get the book!</p>

<p>But for all that there’s also some very great &amp; inspiring photos in the book. The pictures from Anki Grøthe, Kilian Schönberger, Jimmy Chin, Logan Watts and a few others are crisp, sharp and with a fresh perspective on the outdoors. Add in the small stories and anecdotes from the photographers, athletes and outdoor folks and you get a book that will inspire you at least for one afternoon. Well, maybe a couple more. And if you like Instagram photos and would love to see them in a big book, you’ll probably read it every day! So if you feel like you want to give The Great Wide Open a chance and browse it yourself then order it directly at <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">Gestalten</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1RXDe9B">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJyEz">Amazon.co.uk</a> &amp; <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJFzT">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968931705/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/374/19968931705_29152e803e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony RX100III Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T18:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/sony-rx100iii-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You want to go lighter than a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html">Full Frame Camera</a> but still want to have superb images for online and print? Then the Sony RX100III is what you want - an Ultralight Backpackers &amp; Climber’s Dream.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033934580" title="Sony RX100III Size Comparison with a Field Notes notebook by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7571/16033934580_a455c13d76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III Size Comparison with a Field Notes notebook" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I’m still looking for the <em>Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> in terms of photographic equipment. It’s the camera which has only advantages, satisfies all my needs and is good enough for all my requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Print-quality photographs</li>
  <li>Nightshots possible</li>
  <li>Video capable</li>
  <li>Tiltscreen</li>
  <li>Long battery life</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Lightweight</li>
</ul>

<p>That are <strong>MINE</strong>. Yours might be different. Mine are from a perspective of someone who needs high-quality photos for articles in magazines and online, likes to shot videos once in a while and does not like to carry heavy. I have plenty of colleagues who think like me, while others prefer something more substantial in terms of cameras. There’s no wrong or right and it always depends on your needs, and add in that I like to experiment and you can see why I was happy to give the <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/cyber-shot-kompaktikamerat/dsc-rx100m3">Sony RX100III</a> a spin when Sony asked me to. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033806418" title="Sony RX100III with EVF open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/16033806418_f4324c7d8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III with EVF open" /></a></p>

<p>Like usual this is no pixel-peeping review. <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-cybershot-dsc-rx100-m3">DP Review</a> does a good job looking at all the tech inside, I prefer to take the camera along outdoors and see how it performs in the field. So, 80% of the photos in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html">Höga Kusten Trip Report</a> where shot with the RX100III, which means I got a full four days of photos out of the RX100III, or a total of 632 photos on one fully charged battery. That’s significantly above what is claimed (that would be 320 on one battery charge), and given that the weather on the Högakustenleden was cold and wet I find it a superb performance. It ticked one need of my list, so lets see how the others fared.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601476623" title="Sony RX100III in Selfie Mode by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8646/15601476623_65c5770695_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III in Selfie Mode" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033910680" title="Sony RX100III side with screen open by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7476/16033910680_49c341d4d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III side with screen open" /></a></p>

<p>Tilt-able screen? ✓</p>

<p>The screen can be tilted fully up, great for Selfies, or at an angle, which is great if you want to shoot very low or from above your head. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033949750" title="Sony RX100III handling by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7462/16033949750_519d7a2c36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III handling" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219705131" title="Viewing the view stop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7514/16219705131_dd6c0e5321_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the view stop" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601446823" title="Sony RX100III with Flash open and EVF on by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7573/15601446823_fea0a0e911_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III with Flash open and EVF on" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601438203" title="Sony RX100III taking a photo with the EVF by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7479/15601438203_b4d5205bc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III taking a photo with the EVF" /></a></p>

<p>Easy to use? ✓</p>

<p>Yeps, it is. Give it a mate in the hand who is not a camera geek and he will be able to make a great photo of you &amp; be delighted about the lightweight and easy to use camera. Sun is shining? No problem: Pop up the EVF and use it to take a photo. Although it does look a bit funny if you put that tiny camera up to your face to take a photo. </p>

<p>Print-quality photographs? ✓</p>

<p>Yes, it does produce stunning photos which have and will be printed in magazines from me. It can shoot in Sony’s Raw format which is fully supported by <a href="http://amzn.to/1LLfGPC">Lightroom</a> which makes it a great choice for professional photographers, too - I even have colleagues which only use this camera for all their photos. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15598868014" title="Sony RX100III front with open battery compartment and battery &amp; SDHD Card out by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/15598868014_e442886a44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III front with open battery compartment and battery &amp; SDHD Card out" /></a></p>

<p>Lightweight ✓</p>

<p>The RX100III is 290 g with the battery inside, with an extra 9 g for the <a href="http://amzn.to/1LLgc01">SanDisk Extreme 16GB Memory Card</a> I use. Which tips the scales at less than 300 g. Which is superb. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034258558" title="Night Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8603/16034258558_8d5ccdb6a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night Selfie" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15306067413" title="Helsinki Adventure Night by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15306067413_6fb9848e71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Helsinki Adventure Night" /></a></p>

<p>Nightshots possible ✓</p>

<p>You might think that a small and lightweight camera like the RX100III might need to have some things it does not excel at. Low light and night time photography is difficult already, usually requiring high ISO capabilities and large sensors. I wasn’t sure what I could expect from this little camera, but was positively surprised at the photos it produced in low light and at night. That Night Selfie was just after dusk, and while it’s not 100% sharp it’s a fine image, capturing the rain well, giving it a nice atmosphere. Also the indoor shot at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/helsinki-adventure-night.html">Helsinki adventure Night</a> came out superb, which ticks this point for me. Sadly I wasn’t able to try star photography with it, though I am positive that it should be possible.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220528902" title="Sony RX100III back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8624/16220528902_74fa472068_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III back" /></a></p>

<p>Video capable ✓</p>

<p>Yes, the RX100III also shoots some crisp, fine videos. It’s a bit counter-intuitive to shoot video after you took a photo, as you need to turn the dial on top into the Video mode to be able to record something. I also found the Record button at a strange location, and operating it with anything else than super-thing liner gloves is something where you can learn patience. Once it is rolling you can make adjustments to settings, too. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220497942" title="Sony RX100III handling with index finger on trigger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7524/16220497942_678635c6ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III handling with index finger on trigger" /></a></p>

<p><strong>And then for some further usability thoughts on it.</strong> I used the RX100III with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture PRO Camera Clip</a> and the <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/leash?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Leash</a> which I found a superb combo. I bought the <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/microplate?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design Micro Plate</a> for it which is ideal with it and allows me to have the small &amp; lightweight camera securely attached to me. Speaking of small &amp; light: If you’re used to large &amp; heavy cameras this will be quite a change. I use usually cameras which are slightly bigger in size so having such a tiny camera, which easily fits in even the smallest chest pockets, is something I first needed to get used to. But then it was great.</p>

<p>Because the camera is so small people with large hands also might it difficult to operate. I have probably Medium-sized hands and found it OK to use with one hand, but usually used two. One with the finger on the trigger, the other to slightly stabilize it. Taking Selfies with the camera is easy as pie, and the Flash and EVF which can be stored away are good, too. The Focal length is 24–70 mm and the Aperture is a magnificent F1.8 - F2.8 which I liked a lot. The lens is from ZEISS which means it’s high-quality, take a look at the photos in some of the mentioned articles above or Albums underneath and you’ll see. </p>

<p>I found the battery life superb, sadly you can charge the battery online inside the camera via an USB cable, which is crap if you want to take photos with it while it loads. There’s an external Sony car charger available so at least if you’re on the go you can charge it, as well as several third-party chargers. For longer trips I’d always take an extra battery or two along, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033758968" title="Sony RX100III top and On by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16033758968_295fa5532c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony RX100III top and On" /></a></p>

<p>But are there problems with it? Well, I’m again hard-pressed to say something negative about the camera. Sure, looked at some things in isolation you could find some errors. But if I keep in mind that this is a 290 g, super-compact camera which produces superb images and has a long battery life then complaining about things like little buttons seem senseless. At 900€ the RX100III isn’t cheap, either, but there’s only a handful of cameras which play in the same league than it, and those all are a tad heavier and more expensive. </p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong>. If weight is at a premium in your pack or on your harness, but I still want to take great photos, then the RX100III would be my choice. I have <a href="http://hikeitlikeit.com/2014/the-sony-rx100/">discussed with Jacob</a> about the different iterations of the RX100 before and agree that the high price might be what might keep most people getting it. But once you have it and take it on a trip, see how it performs on the trail and on the rock, in sunshine and rain, and the fine photos it takes you’re very unlikely to leave it at home. If only the lightest and best image quality does the job for you, consider the RX100III. For me it is the closest to an <em>Eierlegende Wollmilchsau</em> yet. </p>

<p>View <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157649751997029/">more photos of the Sony RX100III on Flickr</a> and more photos shot with it in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157648982512379/">Höga Kusten Album</a>.</p>

<p>You can support Hiking in Finland and buy the RX100III at your flavour of <a href="http://amzn.to/1BUbRPZ">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1DESZa3">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1DET2Ta">Amazon.de</a> or get it from your local <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/sony-dsc-rx100m3-kompaktikamera.html">photography shop</a> or directly from <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/cyber-shot-kompaktikamerat/dsc-rx100m3">Sony</a>. And if you think that you won’t need the latest Sony RX100 camera then you’re in luck: The <a href="http://amzn.to/1BUdbCp">RX100II</a> can be found in a tasty bundle for as low as $600 and the still great <a href="http://amzn.to/1yGsLAC">RX100</a> I found in a sweet bundle for as low as $400. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035685067" title="Views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8682/16035685067_1c22604b18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sony A7R Field Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T06:55:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/10/sony-a7r-field-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A 407 g Full Frame camera? Yes please. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15457679781" title="Sony A7R without lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3935/15457679781_9874095671_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R without lens" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Earlier in the year I had the pleasure of test-driving the latest creation from <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/kamerat">Sony</a>, their <a href="http://www.sony.fi/electronics/jarjestelmakamerat/ilce-7r">A7R camera</a>. I’ve been a user of Sony cameras since over three years and while my Sony NEX-5n is still a trusty companion on many trips, I’m in the market for a new camera. So having being able to use the A7R in what I usually do was a superb opportunity that I wasn’t going to pass up, even if our love affair only was to last for several weeks and I knew saying good bye to it would hurt.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460816735" title="Sony A7R and Sony NEX-5n by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15460816735_9cda8d1df7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R and Sony NEX-5n" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re looking for pixel-peeping and very detailed technical information, I’d like to send you to <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/sony-alpha-a7r/">DP Review</a> who do a rather spectacular job with that sorts of things. If you’re an outdoor photographer, journalist or writer who wants to know how the A7R performs in the outdoors, I invite you to stay for a while and read my thoughts on this camera. I will delve first a (little) bit into the technical details and how the camera handles, and then discuss in detail how the camera works in the field.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274063999" title="Sony A7R - Back view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3934/15274063999_ae9d765df2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R - Back view" /></a></p>

<p>First off: At a suggested retail price of 2300€ for the body only and a good lens setting you back another 800€, the A7R is in my opinion a camera for people who earn a living with photos. Sure, if you have the spare change to buy a 3000€ camera you could get it, but chances are you either way don’t know how to use its full potential. And a lot of potential she has, the A7R.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15458998652" title="Sony A7R - Having a good grip on it by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15458998652_82cf23ce8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Having a good grip on it" /></a></p>

<p>The camera lays beautiful in the hand and it is easy to operate the different controls and functions with one hand. The sealed alloy and composite body is weatherproof and allows for a good, reassuring grip, even with gloves on. The 3-inch tilting LCD turns up and down and makes shooting e.g. Macros easier, although the XGA electronic viewfinder is where it’s at. The viewfinder eyepiece is large and comfortable, and far enough away so that you also can use it with (sun) glasses on. I have been sceptical of viewfinders in the past as (good) LCD screens are more than adequate in composing photos, but as my photographic needs evolve I come back to viewfinders and find them increasingly a necessity for my kind of shooting.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272647760" title="Sony A7R - View on top with thumb on the trigger by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5601/15272647760_fddc5ae121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - View on top with thumb on the trigger" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272582069" title="Sony A7R - Thumb access to different buttons on the back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15272582069_311a4c0d93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Thumb access to different buttons on the back" /></a></p>

<p>If you’re a control freak you will love the possibilities the A7R offers: Three customizable buttons and four dials (front, rear, exposure compensation &amp; an additional rear dial around the four-way controller), and several buttons for accessing different settings (Menu, Trash, Playback, etc.). If you shot Manual the front and rear dials allow you to adjust shutter speed and aperture, while the directional controller lets you set the drive mode, white balance mode and what’s displayed on the screen. The shutter button sits above the On/ Off switch which I found comfortable in use - I could switch the camera on with my index finger and then have my thumb immediately on the shutter. The camera did need a moment to start up, something that might be better nowadays with an updated Firmware.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15272723658" title="Sony A7R - Back view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3934/15272723658_9fc99380d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sony A7R - Back view" /></a></p>

<p>On the right side of the body you see in the above photo the dedicated movie recording button (red), which for my liking was a bit far in the back. The A7R has Full HD video recording capabilities which makes it a mighty fine video camera to produce super-sharp HD videos.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="http://hikinginfinland.com//www.youtube.com/embed/QUHHBay1x14?list=UU927vE_KkPy6pFJboaJ9Lig" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>On the left side you have four ports behind two plastic doors: Micro, Headphones, Multi (allows you to charge the battery) and micro-HDMI. On the top there’s a Hotshoe which accepts an external flash or <a href="http://amzn.to/1yJHYWK">Microphone</a>. The A7R uses the NP-FW50 Lithium battery like the NEX-5n, which was very useful for me as I so could use my charger and spare batteries on tour. The default charging method is via the USB port which I think is a hassle, so I recommend getting the external charger or the battery grip.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274058359" title="Sony A7R - Side I/O ports with the Rode Video Pro on top &amp; connected by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3936/15274058359_b578a549e7_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Sony A7R - Side I/O ports with the Rode Video Pro on top &amp; connected" /></a></p>

<p>The A7R has an E-Mount like my NEX camera which means I can use E-Mount lenses - though they will crop the photo it’s useful if you already have a NEX camera - and with an <a href="http://amzn.to/1pMVoI0">adapter</a> also allows you to use Canon, Nikon, Pentax and other lenses. This could make it interesting for people who are switching from Nikon or Canon but want to keep to use their glass. With an adapter you’re also able to use other Sony A-mount lenses. To really get the most out this full frame sensor you’ll want to invest into a (few) Sony FE-series lenses. I used the <a href="http://amzn.to/1xl9bKL">35mm F2.8 Carl Zeiss</a> and found it a superb lens, though for outdoor photography I would have found a faster 16 mm or 20 mm lens even more useful.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460475032" title="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3927/15460475032_be1fa0e188_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens" /></a></p>

<p>With 36 megapixels and a max resolution of 7360 x 4912 it are photos where the A7R really shines, so lets have a look how the camera handles in the field.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274057619" title="Sont A7R - Composing a photo by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15274057619_9d2c7a6105_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sont A7R - Composing a photo" /></a></p>

<p>Together with the Carl Zeiss 35mm F2.8 lens (120 g) the A7R weighs 585 g (including battery, which is 58 g). With this lens it is a compact package that fits into large jacket pockets and comfortably under the jacket in bad weather. It’s also light enough to not bother you when wearing around your neck, though I would update the strap to one from <a href="https://peakdesign.com/store/slide?coupon_code=hikeinfin">Peak Design</a> for more functionality. </p>

<p>The first time I used the camera was at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/abisko-ice-climbing-festival-2014.html">Abisko Ice Climbing Festival</a>, which was a good test for it. Lots of white in different shades, colourful clothing, early dusks, northern lights. It performed well, and would have been outstanding if I would have had the functions dialled in better. With gloves on the camera was easy to use, but things like smaller buttons where more difficult to control. That meant either setting White Balance, ISO, Aperture et al. before hand or take the gloves off to fine adjust settings.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445682176" title="Sony A7R - Roadtrippin&#x27; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15445682176_9e35c9589d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Roadtrippin&#x27;" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15282159468" title="Sony A7R - Ice climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5600/15282159468_f9a430f0c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Ice climbing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465648641" title="Sony A7R - Aurora Borealis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15465648641_46952da3d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p>In warm daylight the camera was a pleasure to use and produced almost perfect images without needing much post processing. Colours were bright and true to colour, and given that this can be a very hard environment for good photos, with all the snow and ice, I was very happy with the output. The LCD screen is great to review photos on the fly and it’s fast to delete bad shots, but also works well to compose a photo if you can not/ don’t want to use the Viewfinder. The Viewfinder is great in use, and helped in the bright and snowy environment of Northern Sweden to compose a few good shots.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15281893779" title="Sony A7R - All Smiles by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15281893779_8c91a81b2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - All Smiles" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465644681" title="Sony A7R - Getting schooled by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15465644681_f1772308e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Getting schooled" /></a></p>

<p>The Magnesium Alloy Body didn’t get very cold, and bumps against the ice and rock didn’t bother it. Something that did bother me was the shutter sound, which I didn’t manage to silence. I like stealth photography and even if large landscapes aren’t scared away by the sound, animals are, and also during street photography it’s something that can give you away. The shutter also seemed to be slow, taking a good moment to make its <em>“Clack”</em> sound to take a picture. While I got used to it, it’s something I’d very much would like to be seen improved. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445745166" title="Sony A7R - Snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15445745166_75ff8416ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Snow" /></a></p>

<p>One of the big benefits of the A7R is obviously that it is a full frame. The detail you get from the camera is pretty amazing and  allows you to reduce the resolution in post or crop aggressively. The example of this lonely reed against a late March afternoon sky is a good example:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15465621521" title="Sony A7R - Reed by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5597/15465621521_cd0f005fa2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Reed" /></a></p>

<p>And now the crop of the above photo:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468757625" title="Sony A7R - Reed Crop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3932/15468757625_5293bd9a0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Sony A7R - Reed Crop" /></a></p>

<p>The amount of sharp detail you get is wonderful and gives you a lot more creative options when working with this camera. You can include a lot more of the subject’s environment and still capture plenty of detail which is highly useful if you decide to crop the photo later, which is great if you are in a hurry to capture a unique moment but can’t compose the image perfectly.</p>

<p>The A7R also has a good Auto Focus/ Facial Recognition, even if the subject isn’t 100% to be identified. Take this <em>“Portrait”</em> I shot of myself for a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/trekking-magazin/">trekking Magazin</a> article as an example:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15445671636" title="Sony A7R - &quot;Portrait&quot; by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5598/15445671636_c449958015_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - &quot;Portrait&quot;" /></a></p>

<p>This photo has not been touched in post, but with a few easy adjustments was perfect for my article. However, I really loved how good the camera put the focus on me (and I wasn’t standing behind the Viewfinder, obviously =) and blurred out the background. The colours again are rich and lush out of the camera and details like the Ripstop pattern on the windjacket are clearly to be seen.</p>

<p>Night and low-light shooting is something that you really need to put an effort in to get it right, but with a good camera and a good lens things get easier. I think one could get some really nice illuminated-shelters-in-the-hills with the A7R + 35 mm lens, sadly I didn’t have time for such a test so this twilight shot from town needs to do. With focus peaking on it’s easy to get the stuff sharp that matter, and it’s something I highly recommend always using - also in daylight shots.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468453232" title="Sony A7R - Twilight by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15468453232_b2c0eedd0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Twilight" /></a>
ƒ/2.8, 2 seconds, ISO 800</p>

<p>The pine has a lot of detail and the stars that you can see are nice and crisp. I edited it lightly in <a href="http://amzn.to/1vL8VDP">Lightroom</a> to bring out some details and added a bit of clarity, but even in camera on the screen it looked already good. </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468786525" title="Sony A7R - Waterdrops by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15468786525_8408833471_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Waterdrops" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15284760469" title="Sony A7R - Scarpa Rebel Ultra Gtx in the snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3941/15284760469_052c55e581_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Scarpa Rebel Ultra Gtx in the snow" /></a></p>

<p>Taking product shots is something I do quite a bit for the blog and the magazines, and also here the A7R performed very satisfying. On the top you see clearly that the focus is on the water drops on the pants, and in these you can see how they reflect their surroundings - the kitchen windows, in this case. Underneath we again have a difficult case: Patterned orange and snow. A combination which gives some of my other cameras a headache, but the A7R produced a perfect image.</p>

<p>Also indoors the A7R did very well, and I snapped some nice shots at the Art Museum here in Vaasa at an exhibition earlier in winter. Again colours and sharpness are outstanding and as the full frame sensor records so much detail it would have been easy to crop this composition if needed (but it wasn’t, I was quite happy with this shot).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15468829345" title="Sony A7R - Art Museum by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2950/15468829345_b99c8ecb23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sony A7R - Art Museum" /></a></p>

<p>In conclusion I can say that my experiences with the Sony A7R were nothing but superb. Sure, it took a second longer to start up as I’d like, it took a moment between shots to be ready again, the shutter was a bit loud, there’s still just a fairly limited selection of FE lenses out, and yes, it’s pricey. But the plusses outweigh these small complaints for me. The biggest advantage is that with the 35 mm lens you have a Full Frame camera which is less than 600 g. In comparison: The Canon EOS 5D Mk III is 950 g for the body only, and the Nikon D800 still puts 900 g for the body only around your neck. </p>

<p>Then there’s the weatherproof body that withstood at least light impacts on ice and rock and had no problems operating in light minus temperatures this winter. The layout of the dials and buttons needs some getting used to, but once you have internalized the layout you’ll be able to use the camera with your eye to the viewfinder.  I loved that it had a regular sized Microphone port, and if I ever get a phone with NFC I’m happy to know that I can just touch it against the A7R and have the two linked, being able to send photos from the camera to the phone very easily. </p>

<p>A large plus is also that thanks to various adapters you’re able to use a massive variety of 35 mm lenses with no field-of-view crop, and if you’re already a Sony NEX camera user you will be able to use your E-Mount lenses on the A7R (with field-of-view crop, though). What’s nice about the 35 mm lens possibility is obviously that many of these lenses can be bought cheaply, and as I have used a few old lenses on my NEX-5n I know how wonderful it is to use a manual lens. Sony is set to release some more FE lenses in 2015, and also Zeiss just announced at the photokina a very nice pair of manual Full-Frame lenses for the A7R and its siblings. </p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline:</strong> The Sony A7R is a lightweight, compact camera that produces outstanding photos and video. If you’re an (outdoor) photographer, journalist or writer who needs high-quality photos with lots of details and the ability to crop the A7R will appeal as it’s such a portable camera and won’t weigh you down when you’re hiking and climbing far off the beaten track.</p>

<p>I recommend you go visit your local camera shop to have a look at the camera and the lenses. If you’re in Finland, <a href="http://www.rajalacamera.fi/sony-ilce-7r-runko.html">Rajala</a> has the A7R right now on offer for 1600€ for the body only. </p>

<p>You can see <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157643203488075/">more photos of the Sony A7R and photos taken with it on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15460817595" title="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3933/15460817595_676a7bca38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sony A7R with an M42 Pentax Asahi lens" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
