<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Advent Calendar 2014 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2014/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-28T08:31:34+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar 2014 - The Rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/advent-calendar-2014-the-rules.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-28T11:06:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/advent-calendar-2014-the-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8230998731/" title="HiF Advent Calendar"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8350/8230998731_e265161b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HiF Advent Calendar Logo" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Welcome again to a new Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar! Like in the years before, a smooth foundation (so a good set of rules) makes running this a lot easier for everyone involved. Read them carefully and everything will be clear. </p>

<p>This years calendar will run 25 days (= 25 Doors), and behind each door you will find a fine piece of brand-new gear which should make your next outdoor adventure more fun and easy. Some information on the prizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>All prizes are sent directly from the company providing them. </li>
  <li>Sometimes it is possible that you can choose size, colour and other variables. Where this is the case, it will be mentioned in the text of the Door.</li>
  <li>This means garments can be either female or male, backpacks can be different torso sizes, shoes can be in different sizes, and meals can be vegetarian or with meat. Just the skis, those come as they are!</li>
</ul>

<p>So plenty of nice outdoor gear, and to enter a chance to win something you should check in each day here and enter the raffle. There are a couple of things to keep in mind, though:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You only can win once. If you don’t win one day, you still can try your luck the next day!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I am using a paid-for version of <a href="https://www.rafflecopter.com/">Rafflecopter</a> for the Give-Aways. With Rafflecopter you can get multiple entries by following someone on Twitter, Like a page on Facebook, Follow a Pinterest page or susbscribe to a Mailing List. This increases your chances to win, but is not mandatory.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Rafflecopter Widget is integrated with <a href="http://www.random.org/">Random.org</a> and it choses the winner. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Once you won, I contact you via the provided Email address and you have 24 hours to reply. If I don’t hear from you, I imagine you don’t want the item and will let Random.org chose a new winner.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Posts go online in the morning around nine-ish, and the raffles close at midnight - Finnish time. Rafflecopter then will show the name of the winner after I pushed that button, this keeps posts to a minimum.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It is open to everyone. As in from Afghanistan to Zambia, prices are send everywhere (unless noted otherwise).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can’t bribe me or anyone involved to win. You use the item(s) on your own responsibility. Use common sense.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That’s it, really. The Advent Calendar starts today, the 28th of November. Subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/105082905705272949032">Google+</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to stay up-to-date and don’t miss it!</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: All gear is sponsored. I try to not spend all time in front of a screen so relax if a post goes up a tad late or I don’t reply an email asap.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
