<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Advent Calendar 2014 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2014/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-30T13:46:02+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-28T12:34:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <em>“Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off”</em> is open.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15897268395" title="HiF Advent Calendar Kick-Off by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7543/15897268395_9aeafa3031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HiF Advent Calendar Kick-Off" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>And so the merry countdown till Christmas begins, and again we kick it off with a fully loaded Day Zero Advent Calendar Door. Lets take a look what’s all in there, shall we?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/">Unterwegs</a> provides a sweet <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/ta-0211-496163.html?farbe=kauri&amp;groesse=19%20Liter">Tatonka TA 0211 Daypack</a> which is all the rage amongst us outdoorsy Lumbersexuals. It’s large enough to carry our provisions and a spare plaid shirt in case we get the one we are wearing dirty when chopping wood. It’s durable enough to survive a week in the forest and stylish enough to go to a trendy Café in town.</p>

<p>In our Daypack there’s a <a href="http://marmot.com/products/details/compact-hauler">Compact Hauler</a> from <a href="http://www.marmot.eu">Marmot</a>, a small and useful toiletry bag. It holds all the important cosmetics we need to care for our beards and skin, like the <a href="http://mawaii-suncare.com">mawaii</a> AllWeatherProtection, <a href="http://mawaii-suncare.com/Products.html">DuoCare SPF30 (Face&amp;Lips)</a>, AfterSun 75ml and LipCare. These help us care for our skin in summer as winter, in -20°C as well as +30°C.</p>

<p>That we can walk with the safety of a wild cat on frozen sidewalks in town we have <a href="http://www.edelrid.de/">Edelrid</a> <a href="http://www.edelrid.de/en/Edelrid/Sports/Ice-Axes-Crampons/Spiderpick-icemint.html">Spiderpick</a> snow chains on our shoes. These give us the grip we need on slippery surfaces and frozen lakes alike, and are easy to attach to our shoes and take off again.</p>

<p>On our head we have the <a href="http://www.mammut.ch/">Mammut</a> <a href="http://www.mammut.ch/de/productDetail/109004380_v_5617_one_size/Alyeska-Beanie.html">Alyeska Beanie</a>, which looks like our grandma knitted it herself for us, but on the inside a cuddly microfleece lining adds even more warmth. </p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/">Mountain Laurel Designs</a> <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=37&amp;products_id=51">eVent Mitts</a> on our hands ensure we don’t get cold and wet fingers in the snow and wind, and pack so small they fit without problems into our daypack.</p>

<p><a href="http://princetontec.com/">Princeton Tec</a> brings since almost 40 years light into the dark, and with their <a href="http://princetontec.com/sync">SYNC</a> headlamp we can continue to chop wood in the forest even after the night has fallen. The Dualbeam mode will make the night look like day and helps us to find the way back to our cabin when all the food is chopped.</p>

<p>Further inside our pack we find the <a href="http://www.vaude.com/de-DE/Produkte/Outdoor-Zubehoer/Drybag-Cordura-Light-20l-orange.html">Drybag Cordura Light</a> from <a href="http://www.vaude.com/">Vaude</a>, a waterproof and durable dry sack which has taped seams and weighs just 100 g. </p>

<p>Inside the dry bag we pack our <a href="http://bigskyproducts.com/Big-Sky-DreamSleeper-Deluxe-inflatable-pillow.aspx">Big Sky DreamSleeper Deluxe inflatable pillow with pillow case</a> from the <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a>, for those afternoon power naps. A pillow is inherently more comfortable than a log to rest ones head on, and the Deluxe pillow ensure we can power nap in comfort.</p>

<p>Also in the dry bag we pack our <a href="http://www.whoopieslings.com">Whoopieslings.com</a> gear for our hammock. A pair of <a href="http://shop.whoopieslings.com/Whoopie-Slings-AWS.htm">Whoopieslings</a>, <a href="http://shop.whoopieslings.com/Tree-Huggers-TH.htm">Tree Huggers</a> and <a href="http://shop.whoopieslings.com/Toggles-Pair-TOG-WO.htm">Toggles</a> allows us to hang our hammock in the most convenient way possible.</p>

<p>So light and compact packs the <a href="http://www.traildesigns.com/stoves/caldera-keg-f-stove-system">Keg F Stove System</a> from <a href="http://www.traildesigns.com/">Trail Designs</a> that we also still fit it in our pack. With it we can easily heat up water for our afternoon coffee (black, no sugar!) or rehydrate meals when we’re for a long time out in the woods.</p>

<p>What now doesn’t fit into our pack anymore is our tenkara rod and flies for our after-work tenkara session. But that’s not a problem because we have a sweet <a href="http://www.zimmerbuilt.com/store/p20/Tenkara_Strap_Pack.html">Tenkara Strap Pack</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.zimmerbuilt.com/store/p39/Tenkara__QuickDraw.html">QuickDraw</a> combo from <a href="http://www.zimmerbuilt.com">ZimmerBuilt</a> to carry them with. The small Strap pack holds our small fly box, tenkara line, tippit and tools and the QuickDraw carries our rod and slides out of the way when we cast our fly to catch that trout for dinner.</p>

<h2 id="the-prizes">The Prizes</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15710705759" title="Tatonka TA 0211 Daypack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7468/15710705759_8fddfca730_b.jpg" width="783" height="1024" alt="Tatonka TA 0211 Daypack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15896741205" title="Marmot Compact Hauler by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7580/15896741205_e72bbdc27a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="808" alt="Marmot Compact Hauler" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15277092423" title="mawaii by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8629/15277092423_c1df819858_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="mawaii" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15896741195" title="Edelrid Spiderpick by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8571/15896741195_ee85c9c036_o.jpg" width="711" height="353" alt="Edelrid Spiderpick" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15274473474" title="Mammut Alyeska Beanie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15274473474_eeb2c13972_b.jpg" width="854" height="1024" alt="Mammut Alyeska Beanie" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15894743421" title="MLD Rainmitts by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8649/15894743421_036125f384_o.jpg" width="648" height="656" alt="MLD Rainmitts" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15894743001" title="Princeton Tec Sync by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7471/15894743001_0d45660d5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="537" alt="Princeton Tec Sync" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15894742511" title="VAUDE Drybag by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7468/15894742511_466dfe8dd8_b.jpg" width="421" height="1024" alt="VAUDE Drybag" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15709240378" title="Big Sky DreamSleeper Deluxe Pillow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8634/15709240378_444fbf1a68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Big Sky DreamSleeper Deluxe Pillow" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15896080742" title="Whoopieslings by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7474/15896080742_f613df4910_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Whoopieslings" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15709430200" title="Trail Designs Keg F by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8572/15709430200_affdc9bb82_o.jpg" width="857" height="582" alt="Trail Designs Keg F" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15710705269" title="Zimmerbuilt QuickDraw &amp; Tenkara Strap Pack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7470/15710705269_dd71ffa46d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Zimmerbuilt QuickDraw &amp; Tenkara Strap Pack" /></a></p>

<h2 id="enter">Enter!</h2>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd89528/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd89528" data-theme="classic" data-template="" id="rcwidget_bgnu4db1">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com//widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/advent-calendar-2014-the-rules.html">Read The Rules</a>. All prizes are send directly from the manufacturer. You can choose the size of the Spiderpick snow chains (shoes NOT included). Also the tenkara rod and line are NOT included in the ZimmerBuilt kit.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar 2014 - The Rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/advent-calendar-2014-the-rules.html"/>
    <updated>2014-11-28T11:06:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hendrikmorkel.github.com/2014/11/advent-calendar-2014-the-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8230998731/" title="HiF Advent Calendar"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8350/8230998731_e265161b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HiF Advent Calendar Logo" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Welcome again to a new Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar! Like in the years before, a smooth foundation (so a good set of rules) makes running this a lot easier for everyone involved. Read them carefully and everything will be clear. </p>

<p>This years calendar will run 25 days (= 25 Doors), and behind each door you will find a fine piece of brand-new gear which should make your next outdoor adventure more fun and easy. Some information on the prizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>All prizes are sent directly from the company providing them. </li>
  <li>Sometimes it is possible that you can choose size, colour and other variables. Where this is the case, it will be mentioned in the text of the Door.</li>
  <li>This means garments can be either female or male, backpacks can be different torso sizes, shoes can be in different sizes, and meals can be vegetarian or with meat. Just the skis, those come as they are!</li>
</ul>

<p>So plenty of nice outdoor gear, and to enter a chance to win something you should check in each day here and enter the raffle. There are a couple of things to keep in mind, though:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You only can win once. If you don’t win one day, you still can try your luck the next day!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I am using a paid-for version of <a href="https://www.rafflecopter.com/">Rafflecopter</a> for the Give-Aways. With Rafflecopter you can get multiple entries by following someone on Twitter, Like a page on Facebook, Follow a Pinterest page or susbscribe to a Mailing List. This increases your chances to win, but is not mandatory.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Rafflecopter Widget is integrated with <a href="http://www.random.org/">Random.org</a> and it choses the winner. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Once you won, I contact you via the provided Email address and you have 24 hours to reply. If I don’t hear from you, I imagine you don’t want the item and will let Random.org chose a new winner.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Posts go online in the morning around nine-ish, and the raffles close at midnight - Finnish time. Rafflecopter then will show the name of the winner after I pushed that button, this keeps posts to a minimum.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It is open to everyone. As in from Afghanistan to Zambia, prices are send everywhere (unless noted otherwise).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can’t bribe me or anyone involved to win. You use the item(s) on your own responsibility. Use common sense.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That’s it, really. The Advent Calendar starts today, the 28th of November. Subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/105082905705272949032">Google+</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to stay up-to-date and don’t miss it!</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: All gear is sponsored. I try to not spend all time in front of a screen so relax if a post goes up a tad late or I don’t reply an email asap.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
